<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 07:31:39 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>James Webb telescope : The most powerful space telescope</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/james-webb-telescope/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>JSWT</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>JSWT, Big bang</p></div></div><h4><strong style="letter-spacing: -0.0415625em;"><img alt="James Webb telescope" class="alignnone wp-image-627363" height="289" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst.jpg 1500w" width="512"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Much of the universe remains unknown. The James Webb telescope will hopefully provide a powerful window to help resolve some of the cosmos’s many mysteries.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/in-news-james-webb-space-telescope/"><strong>What is James Webb Space Telescope (JWST)? </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is a space telescope being jointly developed by NASA, the European Space Agency (ESA), and the Canadian Space Agency (CSA).</li>
<li>It has taken 30 years and $10bn to develop, and is being described as one of the grand scientific endeavors of the 21st Century.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Where it is placed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The James Webb Space Telescope will not be in orbit around the Earth, like the Hubble Space Telescope is – it will actually orbit the Sun, 1.5 million kilometres (1 million miles) away from the Earth at what is called the second Lagrange point or L2.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Mission</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It will be “a giant leap forward in quest to understand the Universe and our origins”, as it will examine every phase of cosmic history: from the Big Bang to the formation of galaxies, stars, and planets to the evolution of our own Solar System.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="james webb telescope " class="alignnone wp-image-627356" height="446" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 446px) 100vw, 446px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-768x770.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-897x900.jpg 897w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1.jpg 1021w" width="446"/>Special features of JWST</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Time machine in space: </strong>Powerful space telescopes, like JWST or the Hubble Telescope, are often called time machines because of their ability to view very faraway objects. The light coming from those objects, stars or galaxies, which is captured by these telescopes, began its journey millions of years earlier. Essentially, what these telescopes see are images of these stars or galaxies as they were millions of years ago. The more distant the planet or star, the farther back in time are the telescopes able to see.</li>
<li><strong>Farthest from Earth: </strong>James Webb telescope will also be positioned much deeper into space, about a million miles from Earth, at a spot known as L2. It is one of the five points, known as Lagrange’s points, in any revolving two-body system like Earth and Sun, where the gravitational forces of the two large bodies cancel each other out.</li>
<li><strong>Engineering marvel: </strong>JWST has one large mirror, with a diameter of 21 feet (the height of a typical two-storey building), that will capture the infra-red light coming in from the deep universe while facing away from the Sun.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the goal of this telescope?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The telescope will be able to see just about anything in the sky.</li>
<li>However, it has one overriding objective – to see the light coming from the very first stars to shine in the Universe.</li>
<li>These pioneer stars are thought to have switched on about 100-200 million years after the Big Bang, or a little over 13.5 billion years ago.</li>
<li>James Webb telescope will be picking out groupings of these stars.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="james webb telescope " class="alignnone wp-image-627357" height="291" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 516px) 100vw, 516px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC.jpg 1280w" width="516"/>Its significance</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is widely expected to unveil many secrets of the universe, particularly those related to the Formation of stars and galaxies in the early period the first few hundred million years after the Big Bang.</li>
<li>Some have called James Webb telescope  the “telescope that ate astronomy”.</li>
<li>It is said to look back in time to the Dark Ages of the universe.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The universe is vast and most of it is unknown. We hope that the James Webb telescope, over its lifetime would provide us with a powerful window to help resolve some of the many mysteries of the cosmos and make it a little bit more comprehensible.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What is James Webb telescope experiment? Do you think it shades light on dark matter? Explain.  </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/james-webb-telescope/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Construction and demolition waste should be managed properly</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/construction-and-demolition-waste/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>solid waste management</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Construction and demolition" class="alignnone wp-image-627621" height="352" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 986px) 100vw, 986px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.20510300_1598362635_0-300x107.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.20510300_1598362635_0-300x107.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.20510300_1598362635_0-768x275.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.20510300_1598362635_0.jpg 1024w" width="986"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Huge amounts of construction and demolition waste in a residential area is hazardous for human health and warrants immediate disposal.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Twin towers in Noida, Uttar Pradesh were demolished by controlled implosion. Their being located in a residential neighbourhood of Noida makes it even more essential to introduce interventions to mitigate pollution and waste, post-demolition.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is construction and demolition waste?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Construction and demolition wastes (CDW) are the status of building materials after the end life of buildings. CDW could be concrete, steel, wood products, asphalt shingles, and bricks from building.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/managing-indias-growing-waste/"><strong>What is waste management?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Waste management refers to the activities and actions required to manage waste from its start till its disposal. This includes collection, transport, treatment and disposal of waste together with monitoring and regulation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Construction and demolition" class="alignnone wp-image-627622" height="315" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 559px) 100vw, 559px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-1536x864.jpeg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-2048x1152.jpeg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-1200x675.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-1980x1113.jpeg 1980w" width="559"/>Why they should be managed properly?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Waste management and diligent planning becomes critical for regulation of humongous solid waste being generated every day. With growing urbanization and rise of smart cities on the offing the issue of solid waste management becomes even more imperative<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Data to remember </strong></h4>
<p><strong>62 million tons of waste is generated annually in the country at present.</strong></p>
<p><strong>India manages to recover and recycle only about 1 per cent of its construction and demolition (C&amp;D) waste, says new CSE analysis.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="Construction and demolition" class="alignnone wp-image-627623" height="322" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 578px) 100vw, 578px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Debris-1-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Debris-1-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Debris-1-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Debris-1.jpg 980w" width="578"/>What are the impacts of construction waste on the environment and human health?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Air: </strong>Disassembling and shredding of construction waste generate dust or large particulates into the surroundings and affects the respiratory health of waste management workers and others.</li>
<li><strong>Water: </strong>(Landfills are not properly designed to hold construction waste + Illegal dump sites + Improper recycling &amp; disposal of e-waste) = compounds leach into the ground = Groundwater gets toxified due to heavy metals from demolition waste.</li>
<li><strong>Soil: </strong>Soil is contaminated by direct contact with contaminants from construction waste or its by-products from recycling &amp; disposal + indirectly through irrigation. Soils become toxic when substances such as lead, mercury, cadmium, arsenic, and polychlorinated biphenyl’s (PCBs) are deposited in landfills. Contaminated soils have bad impacts on microbes and plants =&gt; the pollutants reach higher animals or humans through the food chain.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Some positive suggestions </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Need robust estimation and characterisation of C&amp;D waste to design systems for material recovery: </strong>Cities need comprehensive assessment and quantification of C&amp;D waste generation, to plan adequate infrastructure and systems for treatment and management.</li>
<li><strong>Need of documentation:</strong> Cities must create easily accessible databases of buildings and their physical and legal attributes. Construction/demolition permits need to be inventorised with associated waste management plans attached<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Preparing for waste management from new generation material: </strong>Expanded polystyrene insulation (EPS), Styrofoam, plastic spacers, bituminous material and asbestos embedded within new wall assemblies are a recycling challenge. This needs special attention.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure projects need to set up their own recycling facilities</strong>: DMRC has done so. Concrete can be easily recycled. Butt excavated waste is a challenge. Other infrastructure projects like highway and roadwork find recycling of bituminous material waste challenging. Globally, proactive prevention of waste is undertaken through modification of existing on site construction practices etc.</li>
<li><strong>Responsibility of the construction Industry</strong>: The current system provides no incentive to the construction agencies for managing their own waste via waste reduction and on-site reuse and recycling. The Rules have created a push by creating a legal requirement for waste management but the financial drivers are missing. This requires fiscal strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Environmental and material challenges associated with the Construction and Demolition waste problem need urgent and immediate attention nation-wide to recover material, protect environment, and for clean air.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. India manages to recover and recycle only about 1 per cent of its construction and demolition waste analyse the constraints in it. Also suggest some positive measures to address this challenge.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/construction-and-demolition-waste/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Places in news: Taiwan Strait</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-taiwan-strait-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Taiwan Strait</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>One China Policy</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627769" height="424" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 346px) 100vw, 346px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/taiwan-strait-245x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/taiwan-strait-245x300.jpg 245w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/taiwan-strait.jpg 607w" width="346"/></strong></p>
<p>India has for the first time referred to what it called “the militarization of the Taiwan Strait”, marking a rare instance of New Delhi appearing to comment on China’s actions towards Taiwan.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Two American warships have recently sailed very close to China through Taiwan Strait.</li>
<li>This has intimidated the China which is already fuming due to the visit of Nancy Pelosi.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Taiwan Strait</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Taiwan Strait is a 180-kilometer wide strait separating the island of Taiwan and continental China (and Asia of course).</li>
<li>The strait is part of the South China Sea and connects to the East China Sea to the north.</li>
<li>The narrowest part is 130 km wide.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues over Taiwan Strait</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Taiwan Strait is itself a subject of an international dispute over its political status.</li>
<li>China claims to enjoy sovereignty, sovereign rights and jurisdiction over the Taiwan Strait” and regards the waterway as “internal territorial waters” instead of being international waters.</li>
<li>This means that the Chinese government denies any foreign vessel having the freedom of navigation in the strait.</li>
<li>This position has drawn strong objections from the western World.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s change of stance</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has followed a “<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-china-taiwan-tension-a-flash-point-in-indo-pacific/">One China policy</a>” since its recognition of the PRC in 1949, and only maintains trade and cultural relations with Taiwan.</li>
<li>India routinely reiterated this policy until 2008 after which it stopped mentioning it in official statements.</li>
<li>This is a demand that China usually asks of most countries in official declarations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is India shifting its stance?</h4>
<ul>
<li>China often make provocative statements claiming Arunachal Pradesh.</li>
<li>It often moves to issue “stapled visas” to Indian citizens in Jammu and Kashmir and Arunachal.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-taiwan-strait-2/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Positive Indigenisation List (PIL)?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-positive-indigenisation-list-pil/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Positive Indigenisation List (PIL)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Defence indigenization</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627775" height="560" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL-768x768.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL-900x900.jpg 900w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL.jpg 1200w" width="560"/></p>
<p>In line with the effort to promote self-reliance in defence manufacturing, the Defence Minister has approved the third Positive Indigenisation List (PIL) of 780 strategically important line replacement units (LRU).</p>
<h4>What is a Positive Indigenisation List (PIL)?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The positive indigenisation list essentially means that the Armed Forces—Army, Navy, and Air Force—will only procure the listed items from domestic manufacturers.</li>
<li>The manufacturers could be private sector players or Defense Public Sector Undertakings (DPSUs).</li>
<li>This concept was rolled out in the Defence Acquisition Procedure (DAP) 2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>This third list is different from the three PILs announced for the armed forces.</li>
<li>This list is in continuation to the two PILs of LRUs, sub-systems, assemblies, sub-assemblies and components that were published in December 2021 and March 2022.</li>
<li>These lists contain 2,500 items which are already indigenised and 458 (351+107) items which will be indigenised within the given timelines.</li>
<li>Out of the 458 items, 167 items (163 from the first PIL, and four from the second PIL) have been indigenised, so far, it stated.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Other steps taken by the Centre to boost defence production</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Licensing relaxation:</strong> Measures announced to boost exports since 2014 include simplified defence industrial licensing, relaxation of export controls and grant of no-objection certificates.</li>
<li><strong>Lines of Credit:</strong> Specific incentives were introduced under the foreign trade policy and the Ministry of External Affairs has facilitated Lines of Credit for countries to import defence product.</li>
<li><strong>Policy boost:</strong> The Defence Ministry has also issued a draft Defence Production &amp; Export Promotion Policy 2020.</li>
<li><strong>Budgetary allocation:</strong> In addition, a percentage of the capital outlay of the defence budget has been reserved for procurement from domestic industry.</li>
<li><strong>Defence Industrial Corridors:</strong> The government has also announced 2 dedicated Corridors in the States of TN and UP to act as clusters of defence manufacturing that leverage existing infrastructure, and human capital.</li>
<li><strong>Long-term vision:</strong> The vision of the government is to achieve a turnover of $25 bn including export of $5 bn in Aerospace and Defence goods and services by 2025.</li>
<li><strong>Push for self-reliance:</strong> The govt has identified the Defence and Aerospace sector as a focus area for the ‘Aatmanirbhar Bharat’ or Self-Reliant India initiative.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues retarding defence indigenization</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Excess reliance on Public Sector:</strong> India has four companies (Indian ordnance factories, Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL), Bharat Electronics Limited (BEL) and Bharat Dynamics Limited (BDL)) among the top 100 biggest arms producers of the world.</li>
<li><strong>Policy delays:</strong> In the past few years, the government has approved over 200 defence acquisition worth Rs 4 trillion, but most are still in relatively early stages of processing.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of Critical Technologies:</strong> Poor design capability in critical technologies, inadequate investment in R&amp;D and the inability to manufacture major subsystems and components hamper the indigenous manufacturing.</li>
<li><strong>Long gestation:</strong> The creation of a manufacturing base is capital and technology-intensive and has a long gestation period. By that time newer technologies make products outdated.</li>
<li><strong>‘Unease’ in doing business:</strong> An issue related to stringent labour laws, compliance burden and lack of skills, affects the development of indigenous manufacturing in defence.</li>
<li><strong>Multiple jurisdictions:</strong> Overlapping jurisdiction of the Ministry of Defence and Ministry of Industrial Promotion impair India’s capability of defence manufacturing.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of quality:</strong> The higher indigenization in few cases is largely attributed to the low-end technology.</li>
<li><strong>FDI Policy:</strong> The earlier FDI limit of 49% was not enough to enthuse global manufacturing houses to set up bases in India.</li>
<li><strong>R&amp;D Lacunae:</strong> A lip service to technology funding by making token allocations is an adequate commentary on our lack of seriousness in the area of Research and Development.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of skills:</strong> There is a lack of engineering and research capability in our institutions. It again leads us back to the need for a stronger industry-academia interface.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reducing import dependence:</strong> India was the world’s second-largest arms importer from 2014-18, ceding the long-held tag as the largest importer to Saudi Arabia, says 2019 SIPRI report.</li>
<li><strong>Security Imperative:</strong> Indigenization in defence is critical to national security also. It keeps intact the technological expertise and encourages spin-off technologies and innovation that often stem from it.</li>
<li><strong>Economic boost:</strong> <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indigenisation-in-defence-technologies-manufacturing-will-ensure-indias-strategic-autonomy/">Indigenization in defence</a> can help create a large industry which also includes small manufacturers.</li>
<li><strong>Employment generation:</strong> Defence manufacturing will lead to the generation of satellite industries that in turn will pave the way for a generation of employment opportunities.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-positive-indigenisation-list-pil/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is a Full Court Meeting?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-full-court-meeting/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Full Court Meeting</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>Within hours of taking over, the new Chief Justice of India Uday Umesh Lalit called a meeting of the ‘full court’ where the judges discussed how to deal with issues relating to listing and backlog of cases.</p>
<h4>What is a Full Court Meeting?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A full court meeting literally means one which is attended by all the judges of the court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When is it held?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There are no written rules dealing with this.</li>
<li>As per convention, full-court meetings are called by the Chief Justice of India to discuss issues of importance to the judiciary.</li>
<li>The senior designations of practising advocates in the Supreme Court and high courts are also decided during the full court meetings.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the significance of a full court meeting?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The basic idea is to take everyone along.</li>
<li>Full court meetings are an ideal occasion to arrive at common solutions to deal with problems that beset the country’s legal system and to make any amends, if necessary, in the administrative practices of the court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How frequently is it held?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As a full court meeting is convened at the discretion of the Chief Justice of India, it does not follow any particular calendar.</li>
<li>Full court meetings have been held many times in the past.</li>
<li>In March 2020, it was convened to discuss demands by associations of lawyers to close the court till further notice following the Covid-10 outbreak.</li>
<li>Also, a full court meeting held on May 7, 1997 decided that “every Judge should make a declaration of all his/her assets in the form of real estate or investment” held in own name or in the name of spouse or any person dependent.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong><em>Do you know?</em></strong></h4>
<p><em>Justice Uday Umesh Lalit, sworn in as the 49th Chief Justice of India on Saturday, will be the sixth head of the Indian judiciary to have a tenure of less than 100 days. </em></p>
<p><em>Lalit will demit office on November 8 with a tenure of 74 days.</em></p>
<p><em>Justice Kamal Narain Singh, who was the CJI between November 25, 1991 and December 12, 1991, had a tenure of 18 days.</em></p>
<p><em>Justice S Rajendra Babu had a tenure of 30 days as the chief justice of India between May 2, 2004 and May 31, 2004.</em></p>
<p><em>Justice J C Shah had a tenure of 36 days when he was the CJI between December 17, 1970 and January 21, 1971.</em></p>
<p><em>Justice G B Patnaik had a 41-day tenure as the head of the Indian judiciary when he held the office of the CJI from November 8, 2002 to December 18, 2002.</em></p>
<p><em>Justice L M Sharma had a tenure of 86 days as the CJI when he was in office between November 18, 1992 and February 11, 1993.</em></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/justice-lalit-appointed-49th-cji/">Tap to read more about appointment of CJIs.</a></p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-full-court-meeting/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Fruit Fly: Novel method to study Nuclear Matrix</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nuclear Matrix</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627770" height="489" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 566px) 100vw, 566px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly.jpg 665w" width="566"/></p>
<p>Now, using a novel method, Indian researchers have established a way of studying the nuclear matrix of the fruit fly (Drosophila melanogaster) without removing the nucleus from the embryo.</p>
<h4>Nuclear Matrix of fruit flies</h4>
<ul>
<li>Every cell that makes up an organism contains a copy of its genome.</li>
<li>This genome is packaged in special ways with the help of a structure known as the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>The nuclear matrix gives an organisation and architecture to the nucleus.</li>
<li>A familiar figure, the nuclear matrix of fruit flies, for instance, has been studied for many years, mainly by isolating it in nuclei that have been taken out from fruit fly embryos.</li>
<li>This allows comparative study of nuclear matrix in different cells within the embryo, giving a boost for fruit fly genetics.</li>
<li>Two of the most recent papers on this work have been published in the journals Nucleus and Molecular and Cell Proteomics.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What exactly is Nuclear Matrix?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The nuclear matrix is like a scaffolding.</li>
<li>Using biochemical means, if the nucleus is taken out and treated with an enzyme that digests all the DNA.</li>
<li>It is then washed with a solution of high salt concentration so that viable DNA proteins or protein-protein interactions are removed.</li>
<li>What is then left is a fibrous meshwork of proteins called the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>This is like a building from which all movables have been sucked out, leaving only the beams, ceiling, and walls, plug points, etc.</li>
<li>Analogous to the building, the nuclear matrix creates the architecture in which the genome is packaged.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why study them?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Studying the nuclear matrix is, therefore, very important to get a better picture of how precisely development progresses every time a new individual is born.</li>
<li>We have 220 different types of cells in the body, but all contain identical genomes.</li>
<li>The same genome sequence is present in neurons, where it works for thinking; in the liver, the same sequence enacts metabolism; and in the intestine, it works to digest.</li>
<li>So, this information is packaged differently in different cell types.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Lifetime perks for former CJIs, SC Judges</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/lifetime-perks-for-former-cjis-sc-judges/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Perks and privileges to Judges</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627766" height="320" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 416px) 100vw, 416px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/judge-300x231.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/judge-300x231.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/judge.jpg 455w" width="416"/></p>
<p>The Centre amended the Supreme Court Judges Rules the second time in a week to provide chauffeurs (car driver) and domestic help for retired Chief Justices of India and Supreme Court judges for their entire lifetime.</p>
<h4>Perks for Retired CJs</h4>
<ul>
<li>Retired CJIs would also get secretarial assistants.</li>
<li>The staff would be paid the salary and allowances of regular employees of the Supreme Court.</li>
<li>The first series of amendments in the Rules on August 23 had allowed retired Chief Justices of India and Supreme Court judges chauffeurs, secretarial assistants and security cover only for a year.</li>
<li>There was no mention of “domestic help”, who would be an employee in the level of junior court assistant.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What else?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The judiciary had recently raised concerns about attacks on judges.</li>
<li>Hence the benefit of 24-hour security cover has been extended to five years for retired Chief Justices and three years for retired judges of the Supreme Court.</li>
<li>Besides, former CJIs and retired judges of the top court can get their monthly mobile phone and Internet bills reimbursed to the extent of ₹4,200.</li>
<li>A retired CJI is also entitled to a rent-free Type VII accommodation, other than the designated official residence, in New Delhi for six months immediately after retirement.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why such move?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The government is one of the biggest litigants in the Supreme Court.</li>
<li>There has been public debate on whether post-retirement benefits dangled by the government could influence the judicial work of serving judges.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/lifetime-perks-for-former-cjis-sc-judges/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia blocks agreement on Nuclear Non-proliferation Treaty (NPT)</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/russia-blocks-agreement-on-nuclear-non-proliferation-treaty/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nuclear Non-proliferation Treaty</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>Russia has blocked the agreement on the final document of a four-week review of the Nuclear Non-proliferation Treaty (NPT).</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The NPT review conference is supposed to be held every five years but was delayed because of the COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
<li>This marked the second failure of its 191 state parties to produce an outcome document.</li>
<li>The last review conference in 2015 ended without an agreement because of serious differences over establishing a Middle East zone free of weapons of mass destruction.</li>
</ul>
<h4>About Nuclear Non-proliferation Treaty (NPT)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Between 1965 and 1968, the treaty was negotiated by the Eighteen Nation Committee on Disarmament, a United Nations-sponsored organization based in Geneva, Switzerland.</li>
<li>Opened for signature in 1968, the treaty entered into force in 1970.</li>
<li>The NPT is an international treaty whose objective is</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>To prevent the spread of nuclear weapons and weapons technology</li>
<li>To promote cooperation in the peaceful uses of nuclear energy and</li>
<li>To further the goal of achieving nuclear disarmament and general and complete disarmament</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The treaty <strong><u>defines nuclear-weapon states</u></strong> as those that have built and tested a nuclear explosive device before 1 January 1967; these are the United States (1945), Russia (1949), the United Kingdom (1952), France (1960), and China (1964).</li>
</ul>
<h4>Non-members of the treaty</h4>
<ul>
<li>Four UN member states have never accepted the NPT, three of which possess or are thought to possess nuclear weapons: India, Israel, and Pakistan.</li>
<li>In addition, South Sudan, founded in 2011, has not joined.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues in Nuclear Disarmament</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Notion of Nuclear ‘Haves’ and ‘Have-Nots’:</strong> The proponents of disarmaments are themselves nuclear armed countries thus creating a nuclear monopoly.</li>
<li><strong>Concept of Peaceful Nuclear Explosion (PNE):</strong> conducted for non-military purposes such as mining.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why didn’t India join NPT?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India is one of the only five countries that either did not sign the NPT or signed but withdrew, thus becoming part of a list that includes Pakistan, Israel, North Korea, and South Sudan.</li>
<li>India always considered the NPT as discriminatory and had refused to sign it.</li>
<li>India maintains that they are selectively applicable to the non-nuclear powers and legitimised the monopoly of the five nuclear weapons powers.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s commitment for de-nuclearization</h4>
<p>India has always batted for a universal commitment and an agreed global and non-discriminatory multilateral framework.</p>
<ul>
<li>It has outlined a <strong>working paper on Nuclear Disarmament</strong> submitted to the UN General Assembly in 2006.</li>
<li>India participated in the <strong>Nuclear Security Summit</strong> process and has regularly participated in the International Conferences on Nuclear Security organised by the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA).</li>
<li>India is also a member of the <strong>Nuclear Security Contact Group</strong> (but has signed off the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (NPT)).</li>
<li>India has expressed its readiness to support the commencement of negotiations on a <strong>Fissile Material Cut-off Treaty</strong> (FMCT).</li>
<li>India couldn’t join the <strong>Comprehensive Nuclear-Test-Ban Treaty (CTBT)</strong> due to several concerns raised by India.</li>
<li>India has piloted an annual UNGA Resolution on “<strong>Measures to Prevent Terrorists from Acquiring Weapons of Mass Destruction</strong>” since 2002, which is adopted by consensus.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has actively supported and contributed to the strengthening of the global nuclear security architecture.</li>
<li>There is a need for the international community to pay closer attention to the illicit proliferation of networks of nuclear weapons, their delivery systems, components and relevant technologies.</li>
<li>India hopes that the international community will continue to work towards realising our collective aspiration for a nuclear weapon-free world.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/russia-blocks-agreement-on-nuclear-non-proliferation-treaty/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Revisiting the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-627767" height="188" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-768x481.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji.jpg 885w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has referred to a three-judge Bench a series of petitions seeking a judicial direction that political parties who make wild promises should also reveal in their poll manifestos where they will get the money to pay for them.</p>
<p>The reference is a shift from the court’s own stand in the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs Tamil Nadu judgment of 2013.</p>
<h4>Hefty promises: A no lesser corrupt practice</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the <strong><u>Balaji case judgment</u></strong>, a Division Bench of the Supreme Court had held that making promises in election manifestos <strong><u>do not amount to a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> under Section 123 of the Representation of People Act (RP).</li>
<li>However, the Supreme Court is now worried that <strong><u>freebies promised</u></strong> by political parties to win elections could <strong><u>bleed the public exchequer dry</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Court said that parties who form the government riding the wave created by their pre-poll promises of free gifts are bleeding the State finances dry.</li>
<li>Parties actually try to <strong><u>fulfil their outlandish promises using public money</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Supreme Court has therefore decided to revisit the Balaji verdict.</p>
<h4>What triggered the Balaji case?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The course of events started in 2006, during the run-up to the Tamil Nadu Assembly elections.</li>
<li>A party released its election manifesto announcing a scheme of free distribution of colour television sets (CTVs) to each and every household if voted to power.</li>
<li>The party swept to power in the polls and decided to implement its scheme and portioned off ₹750 crore from the budget for the project.</li>
<li>The government finally distributed 30,000 TV sets across the State.</li>
<li>In 2011, the rival party also announced its election manifesto with free gifts to “equalise” the gifts offered.</li>
<li>It promised grinders, mixies, electric fans, laptop computers, four gram gold thalis, a cheque of ₹50,000 for women’s marriage, green houses, 20 kg of rice to ration card holders and free cattle and sheep.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Balaji case</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji, a resident of Tamil Nadu, challenged the schemes introduced by the parties in the Madras High Court.</li>
<li>He said that the <strong><u>expenditure was incurred by the State from the exchequer</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This was “<strong><u>unauthorised, impermissible and ultra vires the constitutional mandates</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>High Court dismissed his case</u></strong>, following which he had moved the apex court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did the case play out?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji argued that <strong><u>the State cannot act</u></strong> in furtherance of “<strong><u>eccentric principles of socialistic philanthropy</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>He argued that the promises of <strong><u>free distribution of non-essential commodities</u></strong> in an election manifesto amounts to electoral bribe under Section 123 of the RP Act.</li>
<li>Money can be taken out of the Consolidated Fund of the State <strong><u>only for “public purposes”</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>distribution of goods to certain sections</u></strong> of people was <strong><u>violative of Article 14 of the Constitution</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Argument provided against the Balaji Case</h4>
<ul>
<li>In response, the State of Tamil Nadu countered that <strong><u>promises do not constitute corrupt practice. </u></strong></li>
<li>Political parties are not the State and ‘<strong><u>freebies’ is a nebulous term which has no legal status</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises implemented by the party after forming the government is an <strong><u>obligation under the Directives Principles of State Policy</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The State is only doing its duty to promote the <strong><u>welfare of its people</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises are <strong><u>implemented by framing various schemes/guidelines/eligibility</u></strong> criteria etc. as well as <strong><u>with the approval of the legislature. </u></strong></li>
<li>Thus, it <strong><u>cannot be construed as a waste of public money</u></strong> or be prohibited by any statute or scheme.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Outcome of the Judgement</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court’s judgment held that <strong><u>promises by a political party cannot constitute a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> on its part.</li>
<li>It would be <strong><u>“misleading” to generalize</u></strong> that all promises in the election manifesto would amount to corrupt practice.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>manifesto is a statement of the policy</u></strong> for a political party.</li>
<li>The question of implementing the manifesto arises only if the political party forms a government.</li>
<li>It is the promise of a future government and not of an individual candidate.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Scope for revisiting the judgment</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court agreed that <strong><u>freebies create an “uneven playing field”.</u></strong></li>
<li>It had asked the Election Commission of India to <strong><u>consult political parties</u></strong> and issue guidelines on the election manifesto and make it a <strong><u>part of the Model Code of Conduct</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the Court’s move to review the Balaji judgment significant?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In its order, the court foresees that “freebies may create a situation wherein the <strong><u>State governments cannot provide basic amenities due to lack of funds</u></strong> and the State is pushed towards imminent bankruptcy”.</li>
<li>The court said it wants a <strong><u>transparent debate</u></strong> before the three-judge Bench on whether an “enforceable” judicial order can stop political parties from promising and distributing ‘irrational freebies’.</li>
<li>The case is unique as the Supreme Court is exploring <strong><u>whether judicial parameters can be set on a purely political act of promising freebies.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Concerns around Aadhaar-Voter ID linkage</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/concerns-around-aadhaar-voter-id-linkage/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Aadhaar</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Data Privacy and Aadhaar</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627768" height="238" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 422px) 100vw, 422px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vid-adhaar-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vid-adhaar-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vid-adhaar-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vid-adhaar.jpg 849w" width="422"/></strong></p>
<p>Reports have surfaced online of instances where block level officers have asked individuals to link their Aadhaar with their Voter IDs, failing which their Voter IDs could be cancelled.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>This furore comes in the aftermath of the Election Commission’s (EC) campaign to promote the linkage of Voter ID and Aadhaar that began on August 1.</li>
<li>In the first ten days since its launch, the campaign saw almost 2.5 crore Aadhaar holders voluntarily submitting their details to the EC.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Aadhaar-Voter ID linkage: Why does the government want this?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The EC conducts regular exercises to maintain an <strong><u>updated and accurate record</u></strong> of the voter base.</li>
<li>A part of this exercise is to <strong><u>weed out duplication of voters</u></strong>.</li>
<li>There have been <strong><u>migrant workers</u></strong> who may have been registered more than once on the electoral rolls in different constituencies or for persons registered multiple times within the same constituency.</li>
<li>As per the government, linkage of Aadhaar with voter IDs will assist in ensuring that only one Voter ID is issued per citizen of India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Is the linking of Aadhaar with one’s Voter ID mandatory?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In December 2021, Parliament passed the <strong><u>Election Laws (Amendment) Act, 2021</u></strong> .</li>
<li>This was to <strong><u>amend the Representation of the People Act, 1950</u></strong> and Section 23(4) was inserted in the RP Act.</li>
<li>It states that the <strong><u>electoral registration officer</u></strong> <strong><em>may</em></strong> require voters to furnish their Aadhaar numbers to verify Authencity of voters list.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is it making headlines now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There has been the <strong><u>use of discretionary language</u></strong> throughout the amendments.</li>
<li>This has been <strong><u>accompanied by assurances that linkage is optional</u></strong> by both the government and the EC.</li>
<li>Alternative is provided to only who does not have an Aadhaar number.</li>
<li>To that extent, the <strong><u>limited element of choice</u></strong> that has been incorporated in the amendments seem to be negated or at the very least thrown into confusion.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why there is such proposal for linking?</h4>
<p>The preference to use Aadhaar for verification and authentication, both by the state and private sector, stems from few reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increase in UID-holders:</strong> First, at the end of 2021, 99.7% of the adult Indian population had an Aadhaar card.</li>
<li><strong>Most versatile document:</strong> This coverage exceeds that of any other officially valid document such as driver’s licence, ration cards, PAN cards etc. that are mostly applied for specific purposes.</li>
<li><strong>Reliable source of authentication:</strong> Since Aadhaar allows for biometric authentication, Aadhaar based authentication and verification is considered more reliable, quicker and cost efficient when compared to other IDs.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with mandatory linking: Puttaswamy judgment highlights</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Puttaswamy judgment:</strong> The above reasons do not suffice the mandating of Aadhaar except in limited circumstances as per the Puttaswamy judgment.</li>
<li><strong>Indispensability of the purpose:</strong> It needs to be considered whether such mandatory linkage of Aadhaar with Voter ID would pass the test of being “necessary and proportionate” to the purpose of de-duplication which is sought to be achieved.</li>
<li><strong>Constitutional ambiguity:</strong> In Puttaswamy, one of the questions that the Supreme Court explored was whether the mandatory linking of Aadhaar with bank accounts was constitutional or not.</li>
<li><strong>Against informational autonomy: </strong>It is the right to privacy which would allow a person to decide which official document they want to use for verification and authentication.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Other judicial observations: <u>Lal Babu Hussein (1995) Case</u></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court had held that the Right to vote cannot be disallowed by insisting only on four proofs of identity.</li>
<li>The voters are entitled to rely on any other proof of identity and obtain the right to vote.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the operational difficulties?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Aadhaar is not a citizenship proof:</strong> The preference to Aadhaar for the purposes of determining voters is puzzling as Aadhaar is only a proof of residence and not a proof of citizenship.</li>
<li><strong>Excluding non-citizens is not easy:</strong> Verifying voter identity against this will only help in tackling duplication but will not remove voters who are not citizens of India from the electoral rolls.</li>
<li><strong>Estimate of error rates in biometric based authentication:</strong> This certainly differs. As per the UIDAI in 2018, Aadhaar based biometric authentication had a 12% error rate.</li>
<li><strong>Disenfranchisement of existing voters:</strong> Errors have led to the disenfranchisement of around 30 lakh voters in AP and Telangana before the Supreme Court stalled the process of linkage.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Key concern: Right to Privacy</h4>
<ul>
<li>Some civil societies has highlighted that linking of the two databases of electoral rolls and Aadhaar could lead to the <strong><u>linkage of Aadhaar’s “demographic” information with voter ID information</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This could lead to violation of the right to privacy and <strong><u>surveillance measures by the state</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This would leave the EC with the option of verifying its information only through <strong><u>door-to-door checks</u></strong>.</li>
<li>There is a <strong><u>lack of enforceable data protection principles</u></strong> that regulate how authentication data will be used.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What lies ahead?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Even as the amendments have been made and the EC has launched a campaign for linkage, a writ petition has filed with the Supreme Court challenging the same.</li>
<li>It challenges the amendments as being violative of the right to privacy.</li>
<li>The Supreme Court has transferred the writ to the Delhi High Court.</li>
<li>In the meantime, it is important that the government clarifies through a correction in Form 6B that the linking is not mandatory.</li>
<li>The govt should expedite the enactment of a data protection legislation that allays concerns of unauthorized processing of personal data held by the government.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/concerns-around-aadhaar-voter-id-linkage/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Forest rights act failed to deliver justice to tribals</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/forest-rights-act/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Community forest rights</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Tribal welfare</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="forest right act" class="alignnone wp-image-627940" height="418" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 628px) 100vw, 628px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.18262600_1661773268_p38dlpix-local-woman-processing-mahua-seeds-in-kamtana-village-of-odisha-arabinda-mahapatra-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.18262600_1661773268_p38dlpix-local-woman-processing-mahua-seeds-in-kamtana-village-of-odisha-arabinda-mahapatra-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.18262600_1661773268_p38dlpix-local-woman-processing-mahua-seeds-in-kamtana-village-of-odisha-arabinda-mahapatra-768x513.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.18262600_1661773268_p38dlpix-local-woman-processing-mahua-seeds-in-kamtana-village-of-odisha-arabinda-mahapatra.jpg 1024w" width="628"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is a surge in demand by forest communities to not only access the resources of their habitat, but also to establish their ownership over forests as forest rights act in not meeting its objective.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Residents of 18 villages in <strong>Chhattisgarh’s Udanti Sitanadi Tiger Reserve</strong> blocked the busy National Highway 130C.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What tribal people say?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>“We need forest resources for survival. Being a tiger reserve, we already lead a life with many restrictions. There is no power supply, access to grazing lands is non-existent and we cannot undertake construction works,” says Arjun Nayak of Nagesh, one of the 18 villages in Gariaband district.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="forest right act" class="alignnone wp-image-627941" height="403" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 575px) 100vw, 575px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Odisha-forest-graphic-300x210.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Odisha-forest-graphic-300x210.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Odisha-forest-graphic-1024x716.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Odisha-forest-graphic-768x537.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Odisha-forest-graphic.jpg 1200w" width="575"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/evolution-of-forest-rights-in-india-from-1856-to-2006-in-depth-analysis-of-fra-its-issues/">What is forest rights act 2006?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Forest Rights Act (FRA), 2006 recognizes the rights of the forest dwelling tribal communities and other traditional forest dwellers to forest resources, on which these communities were dependent for a variety of needs, including livelihood, habitation and other socio-cultural needs.</li>
<li>It aimed to protect the marginalised socio-economic class of citizens and balance the right to environment with their right to life and livelihood.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="forest right act" class="alignnone wp-image-627942" height="410" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 557px) 100vw, 557px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tendu-768x566-1-300x221.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tendu-768x566-1-300x221.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tendu-768x566-1.jpg 768w" width="557"/>What are individual rights under FRA act?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Act encompasses Rights of Self-cultivation and Habitationwhich are usually regarded as Individual rights<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-community-forest-rights/"><strong>What are community forest rights under FRA act?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Community Rights as Grazing, Fishing and access to Water bodies in forests, Habitat Rights for PVTGs, Traditional Seasonal Resource access of Nomadic and Pastoral community, access to biodiversity, community right to intellectual property and traditional knowledge, recognition of traditional customary rights and right to protect, regenerate or conserve or manage any community forest resource for sustainable use.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Case study / Value addition </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Chargaon village, Dhamtari district, Chhattisgarh</strong></p>
<p>Migration has drastically reduced due to economic benefits after getting CFRR. Success in improving quality of tendu leaves with better management practices, increasing income.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="forest right act" class="alignnone wp-image-627943" height="798" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 354px) 100vw, 354px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.50357400_1661773367_31-133x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.50357400_1661773367_31-133x300.jpg 133w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.50357400_1661773367_31-454x1024.jpg 454w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.50357400_1661773367_31-399x900.jpg 399w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.50357400_1661773367_31.jpg 500w" width="354"/>Issues with Forest rights act</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Non responsive states</strong>: The forest rights claims of these tribes and forest-dwellers are mostly rejected by the States.</li>
<li><strong>Improper claims</strong>: Being poor and illiterate, living in remote areas, they do not know the appropriate procedure for filing claims.</li>
<li><strong>Low awareness</strong>: The gram sabhas, which initiate the verification of their claims, are low on awareness of how to deal with them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="forest right act" class="alignnone wp-image-627944" height="350" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/691848-updated-women-from-the-forest-village-of-dhamditola1500-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/691848-updated-women-from-the-forest-village-of-dhamditola1500-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/691848-updated-women-from-the-forest-village-of-dhamditola1500-1024x614.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/691848-updated-women-from-the-forest-village-of-dhamditola1500-768x461.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/691848-updated-women-from-the-forest-village-of-dhamditola1500-1200x720.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/691848-updated-women-from-the-forest-village-of-dhamditola1500.jpg 1500w" width="584"/>Why are forest rights important for tribals?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Justice</strong>: Aimed at undoing the “historic injustice” meted out to forest-dependent communities due to curtailment of their customary rights over forests, the FRA came into force in 2008.</li>
<li><strong>Livelihood</strong>: It is important as it recognises the community’s right to use, manage and conserve forest resources, and to legally hold forest land that these communities have used for cultivation and residence.</li>
<li><strong>Conservation</strong>: It also underlines the integral role that forest dwellers play in the sustainability of forests and in the conservation of biodiversity.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>Despite the contentious and debatable nature of this law, the importance and necessity of the FRA, 2006 can not be negated completely. The law assumes even more significant importance when the country is a developing economy and is full-fledged following the path of capitalism, thus making it even more substantial to provide a redressal mechanism for vulnerable and marginalised communities and groups, such as the <i>Adivasis </i>and the other similar tribes, from the necessary evil of development and infrastructural growth while also safeguarding their traditions, heritage and identity that forms an important part of the nation’s cultural diversity as well.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. There is a surge in demand by forest communities to not only access the resources of their habitat, but also to establish their ownership over forests. In this context analyse the issues with working of FRA 2006.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/forest-rights-act/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Strong nuclear diplomacy brings opportunities for India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nuclear-diplomacy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>credible minimum deterrence’</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Nuclear diplomacy and foreign policy</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="nuclear diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-627980" height="387" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 686px) 100vw, 686px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc.jpg 1920w" width="686"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The return of nuclear weapons on the global platform. After 1998, India premised its strategy on building ‘credible minimum deterrence’. The time has come to reflect on what is ‘credible’ and redefine what ‘minimum’ might be to strengthen nuclear diplomacy.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Definition of nuclear diplomacy</h4>
<ul>
<li>Nuclear diplomacy deals with prevention of nuclear war and peacetime proliferation. It also deals with the use of threat of nuclear warfare to achieve diplomatic goals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="nuclear diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-627983" height="370" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 656px) 100vw, 656px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/51236_nukeeeeee_1551964351734-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/51236_nukeeeeee_1551964351734-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/51236_nukeeeeee_1551964351734-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/51236_nukeeeeee_1551964351734.jpg 960w" width="656"/>Theme of article </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India, one of the world’s nuclear weapon powers, ought to be paying a lot more attention to the international nuclear discourse that is acquiring new dimensions and taking a fresh look at its own civilian and military nuclear programmes<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>Nuclear cooperation has brought a new dimension to India’s nuclear diplomacy in the 21<sup>st</sup> India’s status as a responsible nuclear power is predicated upon the civil relationships in the nuclear domain that it has established with major powers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-indias-doctrine-of-nuclear-no-first-use/"><strong>What is credible minimum deterrence?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Credible minimum deterrence is the principle on which India’s nuclear diplomacy is based. It underlines no first use (NFU) with an assured second strike capability and falls under minimal deterrence, as opposed to mutually assured destruction.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="nuclear diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-627981" height="592" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 592px) 100vw, 592px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-768x768.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-900x900.jpg 900w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-1200x1200.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview.jpg 1667w" width="592"/>Why do countries proliferate nuclear weapons?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Proliferation models centred on security concerns or dilemmas dominate nuclear literature.</li>
<li>Nuclear weapons provide an overwhelmingly destructive force that increases a state’s relative power in comparison to its neighbours.</li>
<li>It provides a powerful tool in an anarchic system where superpowers dominate other nation-states sovereignty.</li>
<li>Hence weaponizing helps establish a deterrence to prevent war.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why relook is needed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Possessing nuclear weapons can confer India increased leverage to conduct foreign policy in both regional and international contexts.</li>
<li>There are two ways in which the possession of nuclear weapons can affect a state’s conduct of foreign policy and diplomacy.</li>
<li>The first involves military and strategic signalling. This includes military-oriented functions of deterrence, coercion, and brinkmanship.</li>
<li>The second, deals with non-military affairs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It should be noted that India’s quest to be a “responsible nuclear state” has given it considerable diplomatic capital in the West.</li>
<li>It would be unfortunate for India to squander such gain owing to the lack of carefully considered foreign policy that leverages its nuclear status for its national interest.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s civil nuclear engagements with the global community have strengthened its position in the global civil nuclear order, there is a need for the country to push for greater engagements with more key suppliers and stakeholders to fulfill its military nuclear potential and assert its status as a responsible nuclear state.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. India has been a nuclear weapons state for 22 years. Has this affected India’s foreign policy in a direct manner? Express your views in context of the return of nuclear weapons on the global platform.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nuclear-diplomacy/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Fiscal prudence for strong financial health of states</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fiscal-prudence/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>FRBM act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Fiscal health of states</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Fiscal prudence" class="alignnone wp-image-628150" height="294" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 528px) 100vw, 528px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fiscal-budget-4801-2-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fiscal-budget-4801-2-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fiscal-budget-4801-2.jpg 480w" width="528"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Central government’s alarm has been on the mounting debt burden and the deteriorating fiscal situation in some States due to diversion in fiscal prudence.</li>
<li>As both the Union government and States are expected to work closely in a co-operative federal structure, frictions arising out of these exchanges might have repercussions on both resource sharing and expenditure prioritisation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is India’s fiscal federalism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fiscal federalism refers to the financial relations between the country’s federal government system and other units of government.</li>
<li>It refers to how federal, state, and local governments share funding and administrative responsibilities within our federal system.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Three issues in India’s fiscal federalism                    </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>First:</strong> are a set of issues related to Goods and Services Tax (GST) such as the rate structure, inclusion and exclusion of commodities, revenue sharing from GST and associated compensation.</li>
<li><strong>Second</strong>: State-level expenditure patterns especially related to the welfare schemes of States.</li>
<li><strong>Third</strong>: the conception and the implementation of central schemes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Fiscal prudence" class="alignnone wp-image-628151" height="328" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 589px) 100vw, 589px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/economy-2-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/economy-2-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/economy-2.jpg 759w" width="589"/>Meaning of fiscal prudence</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fiscal prudence is defined as the ability of a government to sustain smooth monetary operation and long-standing fiscal condition.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Where should state government spend the borrowed money?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Fundamental infrastructure</strong>: Ideally, governments should use borrowed money to invest in physical and social infrastructure that will generate higher growth, and thereby higher revenues in the future so that the debt pays for itself.</li>
<li><strong>Targeted expenditure only:</strong> On the other hand, if governments spend the loan money on populist giveaways that generate no additional revenue, the growing debt burden will eventually implode.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Fiscal prudence" class="alignnone wp-image-628152" height="265" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 513px) 100vw, 513px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cartoon_791_adf-1-300x155.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cartoon_791_adf-1-300x155.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cartoon_791_adf-1.jpg 620w" width="513"/>Why there is a need for Fiscal Council?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Institutionalizing fiscal practices:</strong> With a complex polity and manifold development challenges, India need institutional mechanisms for fiscal prudence.</li>
<li><strong>Transparency</strong>: An independent fiscal council can bring about much needed transparency and accountability in fiscal processes across the federal polity.</li>
<li><strong>Fiscal prudence</strong>: International experience suggests that a fiscal council improves the quality of debate on public finance, and that, in turn, helps build public opinion favourable to fiscal discipline.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/a-chance-to-support-growth-fiscal-consolidation/"><strong>What does fiscal consolidation mean?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fiscal consolidation is defined as concrete policies aimed at reducing government deficits and debt accumulation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why fiscal consolidation is needed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fiscal expansion financed through debt and the resultant debt accumulation have important impacts on the economy both in the short run as well as in the long run.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How to achieve fiscal consolidation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Better targeting of government subsidies and extending Direct Benefit Transfer scheme for more subsidies</li>
<li>Improved tax revenue realization For this, increasing efficiency of tax administration by reducing tax avoidance, eliminating tax evasion, enhancing tax compliance etc. are to be made.</li>
<li>Enhancing tax GDP ratio by widening the tax base and minimizing tax concessions and exemptions also improves tax revenues.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Suggestions</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Amend FRBM Act for complete disclosure</strong>: First, the FRBM Acts of the Centre as well as States need to be amended to enforce a more complete disclosure of the liabilities on their exchequers.</li>
<li><strong>Centre should impose conditionalities</strong>: Under the Constitution, States are required to take the Centre’s permission when they borrow. The Centre should not hesitate to impose conditionalities on wayward States when it accords such permission.</li>
<li><strong>Use of financial emergency provision</strong>: There is a provision in the Constitution of India which allows the President to declare a financial emergency in any State if s/he is satisfied that financial stability is threatened.</li>
<li><strong>Course correction by the Centre</strong>: The Centre itself has not been a beacon of virtue when it comes to fiscal responsibility and transparency. It should complete that task in order to command the moral authority to enforce good fiscal behaviour on the part of States.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fiscal correction at the State level is important. While there exists a need for raising additional resources at the sub-national levels, expenditure prioritisation has to be carried out diligently. The Centre, too, on its part needs to demonstrate commitment to fiscal discipline by sticking to announced fiscal glide path to ensure the sustainability of a frictionless cooperative federal structure.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Why Fiscal correction at the State level is important? Why fiscal consolidation is needed? Write in context frictionless cooperative fiscal federal structure</strong>.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fiscal-prudence/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Jurisprudence of Bail in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/jurisprudence/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>jurisprudence of bail</p></div></div><h4><strong>What is Bail?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bail is the conditional release of a defendant with the promise to appear in court when required.</li>
<li>The term also means the security that is deposited in order to secure the release of the accused.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Types of Bail in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Depending upon the sage of the criminal matter, there are commonly three types of bail in India:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Regular bail:</strong> A regular bail is generally granted to a person who has been arrested or is in police custody. A bail application can be filed for the regular bail under section 437 and 439 of CrPC.</li>
<li><strong>Interim bail:</strong> This type of bail is granted for a short period of time and it is granted before the hearing for the grant of regular bail or anticipatory bail.</li>
<li><strong>Anticipatory bail:</strong> Anticipatory bail is granted under section 438 of CrPC either by session court or High Court. An application for the grant of anticipatory bail can be filed by the person who discerns that he may be arrested by the police for a non-bailable offense.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Conditions for Grant of Bail in Bailable Offences</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Section 436 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, lays down that a person accused of a bailable offense under IPC can be granted bail if:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>There are sufficient reasons to believe that the accused has not committed the offence.</li>
<li>There is sufficient reason to conduct a further inquiry in the matter.</li>
<li>The person is not accused of any offence punishable with death, life imprisonment or imprisonment up to 10 years.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Conditions for Grant of Bail in Non-Bailable Offences</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Section 437 of Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 lays down that the accused does not have the right to apply for bail in non-bailable offences.</li>
<li>It is discretion of the court to grant bail in case of non-bailable offences if:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>The accused is a woman or a child, bail can be granted in a non-bailable offence.</li>
<li>There is a lack of evidence then bail in non-Bailable offenses can be granted.</li>
<li>There is a delay in lodging FIR by the complainant, bail may be granted.</li>
<li>The accused is gravely sick.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What is the recent ruling about?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court underlined that arrest is a draconian measure that needs to be used sparingly.</li>
<li>The ruling is essentially a reiteration of several crucial principles of criminal procedure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why bail needs reform?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Huge pendency of undertrials:</strong> Referring to the state of jails in the country, where over two-thirds lodged are undertrials,</li>
<li><strong>Indiscriminate</strong> <strong>arrests:</strong> Of this category of prisoners, majority may not even be required to be arrested despite registration of a cognizable offense, being charged with offenses punishable for seven years or less.</li>
<li><strong>Disadvantageous for some sections:</strong> They are not only poor and illiterate but also would include women. Thus, there is a culture of offense being inherited by many of them.</li>
<li><strong>Colonial legacy:</strong> Theoretically, the court also linked the idea of indiscriminate arrests to magistrates ignoring the rule of “bail, not jail” to a colonial mindset.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the law on bail?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>CrPC does not define the word bail</u></strong> but only categories <strong><u>offences under the Indian Penal Code as ‘bailable’ and ‘non-bailable’. </u></strong></li>
<li>The <strong><u>CrPC empowers magistrates to grant bail</u></strong> for bailable offences as a matter of right.</li>
<li>This would involve release on furnishing a <strong><u>bail bond, without or without security</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>And what is the UK law?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Bail Act of the United Kingdom, 1976, prescribes the procedure for granting bail.</li>
<li>A key feature is that one of the aims of the legislation is “<strong><u>reducing the size of the inmate population</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The law also has provisions for ensuring <strong><u>legal aid for defendants</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Act recognises a <strong><u>“general right” to be granted bail</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What has the Supreme Court held on reforms?</strong></h4>
<p>The court’s ruling is in the form of guidelines, and it also draws the line on certain procedural issues for the police and judiciary:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Separate law on Bail:</strong> The court underlined that the CrPC, despite amendments since Independence, largely retains its original structure as drafted by a colonial power over its subjects.</li>
<li><strong>Uniform exercise of discretionary powers:</strong> It also highlighted that magistrates do not necessarily</li>
<li><strong>Avoid indiscriminate arrests:</strong> The SC also directed all state governments and Union Territories to facilitate standing orders to comply with the orders and avoid indiscriminate arrests.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/jurisprudence/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Artemis 1 Mission?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-artemis-1-mission/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of artemis mission</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p>NASA’s Artemis 1 mission has sought unexpected delay due to fuel leakages issue.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the Artemis I Mission?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>NASA’s Artemis mission is touted as the next generation of lunar exploration, and is named after the twin sister of Apollo from Greek mythology.</li>
<li>Artemis is also the goddess of the moon.</li>
<li>Artemis I is the first of NASA’s deep space exploration systems.</li>
<li>It is an uncrewed space mission where the spacecraft will launch on SLS — the most powerful rocket in the world — and travel 2,80,000 miles from the earth for over four to six weeks during the course of the mission.</li>
<li>The Orion spacecraft is going to remain in space without docking to a space station, longer than any ship for astronauts has ever done before.</li>
<li>The SLS rocket has been designed for space missions beyond the low-earth orbit and can carry crew or cargo to the moon and beyond.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Key objectives of the mission</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>With the Artemis Mission, NASA aims to land humans on the moon by 2024, and it also plans to land the first woman and first person of colour on the moon.</li>
<li>With this mission, NASA aims to contribute to scientific discovery and economic benefits and inspire a new generation of explorers.</li>
<li>NASA will establish an Artemis Base Camp on the surface and a gateway in the lunar orbit to aid exploration by robots and astronauts.</li>
<li>The gateway is a critical component of NASA’s sustainable lunar operations and will serve as a multi-purpose outpost orbiting the moon.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other agencies involved</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Other space agencies are also involved in the Artemis programme.</li>
<li>The Canadian Space Agency has committed to providing advanced robotics for the gateway.</li>
<li>The European Space Agency will provide the International Habitat and the ESPRIT module, which will deliver additional communications capabilities among other things.</li>
<li>The Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency plans to contribute habitation components and logistics resupply.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-artemis-1-mission/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Pakistan’s Flip-Flop on Trade with India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pakistans-flip-flop-on-trade-with-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>india pakistan relation</p></div></div><p>Pakistan’s Finance Minister has stated that the government may consider importing vegetables and other edible items from India following the destruction of standing crops due to the massive floods in the region.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>This statement comes after three years when Islamabad downgraded trade ties with New Delhi over the abrogation of Article 370 in Kashmir in 2019.</li>
<li>The fundamentalist country sees ties with India as against the spirit of religion and betrayal to the so-called Kashmir cause.</li>
</ul>
<h4>A U-turn by Pakistan</h4>
<ul>
<li>Pakistan’s double U-turn on resuming trade with India highlights the <strong><u>internal differences</u></strong> within the country.</li>
<li>There are huge differences between business and political communities, and the emphasis on politics over economy and trade.</li>
<li>It also signifies Pakistan cabinet’s grandstanding, linking <strong><u>normalisation of ties with India</u></strong> to Jammu and Kashmir.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Pakistan has sought to import only three items from India, namely cotton, yarn and sugar.</li>
<li>It has no consensus on resuming bilateral trade completely.</li>
<li>This is based on Pakistan’s immediate economic needs and not designed as a political confidence-building measure to normalise relations with India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What changed Pakistan’s mind?</h4>
<p><strong>(1) Decline of Textile sector</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>For the textile and sugar industries in Pakistan, importing from India is imperative, practical and is the most economic.</li>
<li>Yarn, cotton cloth, knitwear, bedwear and readymade garments form the core of Pakistan’s textile basket in the export sector.</li>
<li>By February 2020, there was a steep decline in the textile sector due to disruptions in supply and domestic production.</li>
<li>This is definitely due to dumping of cheap Chinese goods.</li>
<li>When compared to the last fiscal year (2019-20), there has been a 30% decline (2020-21) in cotton production.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong><em>Do you know?</em></strong></p>
<p><em>Pakistan is the fifth-largest exporter of cotton globally, and the cotton-related products (raw and value-added) earn close to half of the country’s foreign exchange.</em></p></blockquote>
<p><strong>(2) Crisis in the sugar industry </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>When compared to cotton, the sugar industry’s problem stem from different issues — the availability for local consumption and the steep price increase.</li>
<li>The sugar industry has prioritised exports over local distribution.</li>
<li>Increased government subsidy and a few related administrative decisions resulted in the sugar industry attempting to make a considerable profit by exporting it.</li>
<li>As a result, importing sugar from India would be cheaper for the consumer market in Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<h4>In a nutshell</h4>
<ul>
<li>Clearly, the crises in cotton and sugar industries played a role in the ECC’s decision to import cotton, yarn and sugar from India.</li>
<li>It would not only be cheaper but also help Pakistan’s exports.</li>
<li>This is also imperative for Pakistan to earn foreign exchange.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why all these have made headlines these days?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Pakistan is closer to bankruptcy like any other Chinese vassal state.</li>
<li>The second takeaway from the two U-turns — is the supremacy of politics over trade and economy, even if the latter is beneficial to the importing country.</li>
<li>For the cabinet, the interests of its own business community and its export potential have become secondary.</li>
<li>However, Pakistan need not be singled out; this is a curse in South Asia, where politics play supreme over trade and economy.</li>
<li>The meagre percentage of intra-South Asian Association for Regional Cooperation (SAARC) trade and the success (or the failure) of SAARC engaging in bilateral or regional trade would underline the above.</li>
<li>Trade is unlikely to triumph over politics in South Asia; especially in India-Pakistan relations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Kashmir link</h4>
<ul>
<li>The third takeaway is the emphasis on Jammu and Kashmir by Pakistan to make any meaningful start in bilateral relations.</li>
<li>This goes against what it has been telling the rest of the world that India should begin dialogue with Pakistan.</li>
<li>Recently, both Pakistan’s PM and the Chief of Army Staff, Qamar Javed Bajwa, were on record stating the need to build peace in the region.</li>
<li>Bajwa even talked about “burying the past” and moving forward.</li>
<li>There were also reports that Pakistan agreeing to re-establish the ceasefire along the Line of Control (LoC) was a part of this new strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>The latest statement by Pakistan’s cabinet that unless India revokes the 2019 decision in Jammu and Kashmir, there would be no forward movement.</li>
<li>This position also hints at Pakistan’s precondition to engage with India.</li>
<li>Pakistan has been saying that the onus is on India to normalise the process.</li>
<li>Perhaps, it is New Delhi’s turn to tell Islamabad that it is willing, but without any preconditions, and start with trade.</li>
<li>It may even allow New Delhi to inform Pakistan’s stakeholders about who is willing to trade and who is reluctant.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pakistans-flip-flop-on-trade-with-india/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumerism should be replaced by minimalism</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/consumerism/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Minimalism as way of life</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Consumerism" class="alignnone wp-image-628237" height="317" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 564px) 100vw, 564px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-4-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-4-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-4-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-4-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-4.jpeg 1200w" width="564"/> </strong><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The COVID-19 pandemic brought shifts in consumer behaviour. The world witnessed a shrinkage of demand. But post-pandemic recovery and suppressed consumerism is now leading to ‘revenge shopping’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is consumerism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Consumerism is a social and economic order that encourages the acquisition of goods and services in ever-increasing amounts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is minimalism? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Minimalism is owning fewer possessions. It is intentionally living with only the things we really need those items that support our purpose. Removing the distraction of excess possessions to focus more on those things that matter most.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Consumerism" class="alignnone wp-image-628238" height="378" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 568px) 100vw, 568px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1_v7Cd5DWFYjk-ri5aQCBgWg-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1_v7Cd5DWFYjk-ri5aQCBgWg-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1_v7Cd5DWFYjk-ri5aQCBgWg-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1_v7Cd5DWFYjk-ri5aQCBgWg.jpeg 960w" width="568"/>What Is Revenge Shopping?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Revenge shopping occurs when a customer who previously could not get access to certain goods or services for a period of time suddenly has access. It can also occur when customers have been deprived of other events or happenings.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Consumerism" class="alignnone wp-image-628239" height="209" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 392px) 100vw, 392px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0_MFfVpt4oTb-3Pq1T-300x160.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0_MFfVpt4oTb-3Pq1T-300x160.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0_MFfVpt4oTb-3Pq1T-1024x547.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0_MFfVpt4oTb-3Pq1T-768x410.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0_MFfVpt4oTb-3Pq1T-1200x641.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0_MFfVpt4oTb-3Pq1T.jpg 1400w" width="392"/>The symptoms of excessive consumerism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>You buy more than you planned</strong>: if you set out with a plan of what you need to purchase but consistently come back with more than you anticipated, then you’re falling in the consumerist trap.</li>
<li><strong>You run out of storage space for your stuff</strong>: sometimes it can’t be helped if you live in a tight area or you’re disorganised. But suppose you’re in a reasonable situation and things you bring in don’t have an allocated home. In that case, you’re likely living excessively.</li>
<li><strong>You rely too much on return policies</strong>: returning an item is useful. Particularly if you need to test a product for the intended purpose, be it sizing for clothes or a tool for a building project. However, suppose you’re depending on returns for purchases. In that instance, you’re not sure you need it, or if you can’t afford it, then you’re probably suffering from too much consumerism.</li>
<li><strong>You routinely seek approval for your purchases</strong>: getting feedback on purchases can be reassuring, especially if you’re indecisive. Yet, there’s a difference between picking someone’s brain before buying and looking to justify your purchase after the fact. If you’re seeking post-acquisition approval, you probably don’t need the item.</li>
<li><strong>You mistakenly buy things you already have</strong>: not much to say here. If you’re getting things only to realise you already have it, then you’re probably deep in a consumerist cycle.</li>
<li><strong>You buy things on credit</strong>: if you’re strategic and disciplined, you can buy things on credit cards to acquire points and benefits. However, if you’re like the majority of us, then you’re vulnerable to buying things you can’t afford.</li>
<li><strong>You constantly go over your budget</strong>: sometimes, you miss-forecast how much you need to spend each month. But if you set a realistic budget and find that you’re still going over, then you’re probably consuming excessively.</li>
<li><strong>You regret your purchases</strong>: the most obvious sign that you have a shopping habit is you regret things you bought. Buyer’s remorse is an overwhelming feeling and one we want to avoid.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Consumerism" class="alignnone wp-image-628240" height="274" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 390px) 100vw, 390px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/consumerism-titlea-300x211.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/consumerism-titlea-300x211.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/consumerism-titlea.jpg 560w" width="390"/>Negatives of consumerism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Causes more pollution:</strong> Consumerism as a system can have devastating effects on the environment.</li>
<li><strong>A major contributor to resource depletion: </strong>The second main negative of consumerism is resource depletion.  Simply put, resource depletion refers to the idea that human beings are using up the resources on the earth as an ever increasing rate such that we will ‘deplete’ or completely use up some resources.</li>
<li><strong>Leads companies to develop low quality products: </strong>Modern companies practice a technique called ‘planned obsolescence’. In general, planned obsolescence is best understood as products that are designed to fail. Modern companies do this to encourage consumers to repurchase a product over and over again.</li>
<li><strong>Does not necessarily lead to increased happiness beyond a certain point:</strong> The main negative aspect of consumerism is that it does not necessarily lead to higher levels of happiness for people.</li>
<li><strong>Global inequality: </strong>The huge rise in resource consumption in wealthier countries has led to an ever widening gap between the rich and the poor. As the age old saying goes, “the rich get richer and the poor get poorer.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can we do?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Extend the lifespan of your things</strong>: Repairing your things is not only an effective way to reduce your consumption, but it’s also beneficial to the environment.</li>
<li><strong>Reframe shopping as a skill: </strong>When you focus on the role the thing you’re buying will play in the overall experience instead of the experience of shopping itself, you’ll be able to shift away from a consumerist mind-set.</li>
<li><strong>Do the deathbed test: </strong>Not to get too dark, but if you were hypothetically on your deathbed today, and you were reflecting on your life, what would be your fondest memories? The quality of our lives is generally measured by moments of “that was a good time”, not “that thing I had was awesome”.</li>
<li><strong>Borrow or rent instead of buy: </strong>A simple method for getting your consumerism under control is to rent or borrow items instead of buying them.</li>
<li><strong>Practice minimalism</strong>: What’s the ultimate alternative to consumerism? Minimalism. A minimalist is someone who naturally rejects consumerism and sees value in having fewer things over more things. Minimalism is a powerful philosophy that impacts how you view material things, your relationships, commitments, and digital inventory.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The M.K. Gandhi once said: “The Earth provides-enough to satisfy everyone’s needs but not any one’s greed<strong>.”</strong> We shall find that Gandhian call to curtailment of wants is relevant in the rapidly depleting natural resources, bio-diversity and eco-system and its contemporary relevance</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you understand by the term consumerism? Discuss importance of minimalism as there is rise in revenge shopping in post covid19 era.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/consumerism/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Economic cooperation with Sri Lanka for deeper engagement</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sri-lanka/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>hambantota, trinconmalee projects</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>indo srilanka bilateral relations</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Sri lanka" class="alignnone wp-image-628265" height="364" sizes="(max-width: 549px) 100vw, 549px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5a11cf34251744cc40cc58d5f9333e4c-300x199.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5a11cf34251744cc40cc58d5f9333e4c-300x199.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5a11cf34251744cc40cc58d5f9333e4c.jpg 750w" width="549"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The present economic crisis in Sri Lanka has pushed it closer to India for immediate relief.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Economic cooperation with Sri Lanka</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India is Sri Lanka’s third-largest export destination, after the US and UK.</li>
<li>More than 60% of Sri Lanka’s exports enjoy the benefits of the India-Sri Lanka Free Trade Agreement, which came into effect in March 2000.</li>
<li>Concessional financing of about $ 2 billion has been provided to Sri Lanka through various Indian government-supported Lines of Credit across sectors like railways, infrastructure and security.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-india-sri-lanka-relations/"><strong>How India has helped to boost Sri Lanka’s economy</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Grants</strong>: The overall commitment by GOI is to the tune of more than USD 3.5 billion. Demand-driven and people-centric nature of India’s development partnership with Sri Lanka have been the cornerstone of this relationship.</li>
<li><strong>The Indian Housing Project</strong>: India has so far committed to construct close to 62,500 houses in Sri Lanka, making it one of the largest projects undertaken by GoI abroad.</li>
<li><strong>Other Projects</strong>: India is also involved in projects for renovation of Palaly Airport, Kankesanthurai Harbor, construction of a Cultural Centre in Jaffna, interconnection of electricity grids between the two countries, construction of a 150-bed hospital in Dickoya and setting up a coal power plant in Sampur as a joint venture between National Thermal Power Corporation (NTPC) and Ceylon Electricity Board (CEB).</li>
<li><strong>Latest Development</strong>: India-SL agreed for joint development of Trincomalee Oil Tank farmed in 2022 after 35 years of wait.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="sri lanka" class="alignnone wp-image-628266" height="275" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 471px) 100vw, 471px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/30-A-protest-at-the-entrance-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/30-A-protest-at-the-entrance-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/30-A-protest-at-the-entrance.jpg 760w" width="471"/>Opportunities for India for deeper engagement</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dairy sector: </strong>Sri Lanka imports a considerable quantity of milk powder. On average, Colombo annually imports dairy products worth $315 million. . India can help Sri Lanka develop its dairy sector.</li>
<li><strong>Poultry sector:</strong> In this area, through its host of agricultural universities, India can share its knowledge on ways to increase both production and productivity.</li>
<li><strong>Energy sector:</strong> Considering how the problem on the energy front exploded into a major political crisis in Sri Lanka, India’s participation in energy projects will be desirable.</li>
<li><strong>Education sector:</strong> School education is another area where India’s presence could be more felt. India can expand its scheme of establishing smart classrooms and modern computer labs to cover all those institutions teaching children of hill country Tamils, the most underprivileged section in society.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="sri lanka" class="alignnone wp-image-628267" height="338" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 485px) 100vw, 485px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1658817828-22-300x209.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1658817828-22-300x209.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1658817828-22.jpg 650w" width="485"/>Challenges</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Possibility of greater economic collaboration</strong>: Whether this bonhomie can lead to greater economic collaboration between Sri Lanka and south India, not necessarily Tamil Nadu alone, given the historical baggage, is anybody’s guess.</li>
<li><strong>Baggage of history</strong>: Some sections of the Sinhalese still hold the view that India had been a threat to them and it can still be a threat to them.</li>
<li><strong>Modest investment in development</strong>: Despite India’s open willingness to take part in the development of Sri Lanka after the civil war, the scale of its involvement has been modest.</li>
<li><strong>Incomplete projects due to lack of political will</strong>: After the cancellation of the tripartite agreement, India was later provided with projects such as the West Container Terminal, the Trincomalee oil tank farm and a couple of renewable projects, there were several proposals that envisaged India’s participation but did not see the light of day.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Infrastructure development:</strong> Even now, there is enormous scope for collaboration between the two countries in the area of infrastructure development.</li>
<li><strong>Cross-border energy trade</strong>: The economic crisis has revived talk of linking Sri Lanka’s electricity grid with that of India.</li>
<li><strong>Facilitating people-to-people interaction</strong>: The apprehension in the minds of sections of the Sinhalese majority about India being a threat can be dispelled only by facilitating greater people-to-people interaction, including pilgrimages by monks and other sections of  society to places of Buddhist importance not only in north India but also in the south (Andhra Pradesh).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Given the history of bilateral ties, instances such as the Hambantota controversy are bound to arise. But what should not be glossed over is that a politically and economically stable Sri Lanka will be in India’s interest too.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question  </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. There is no such thing as charity in international politics. Critically analyse this statement showing how India can reap benefits of economic cooperation with Sri Lanka.</strong></p>
<p></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sri-lanka/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>PARAKH: A new regulator for ‘uniformity’ in all board exams</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/parakh-a-new-regulator-for-uniformity-in-all-board-exams/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PARAKH</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Harmonization of school education in India</p></div></div><p>The Centre is planning to draw up a benchmark framework ‘PARAKH’ to assess students at the secondary and higher secondary level to bring about “uniformity” across state and central boards.</p>
<h4>What is PARAKH?</h4>
<ul>
<li>PARAKH stands for Performance Assessment, Review and Analysis of Knowledge for Holistic Development.</li>
<li>The proposed regulator will act as a constituent unit of the NCERT.</li>
<li>It will also be tasked with holding periodic learning outcome tests like the National Achievement Survey (NAS) and State Achievement Surveys.</li>
<li>The benchmark assessment framework will seek to put an end to the emphasis on rote learning, as envisaged by the National Education Policy (NEP) 2020.</li>
<li>PARAKH, the proposed implementing agency, is also part of the NEP proposal.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Response form States</h4>
<ul>
<li>Most <strong><u>states endorsed the proposal</u></strong> to hold board exams twice a year, including one for helping students improve their scores.</li>
<li>States are also on board regarding a proposal to offer two types of papers on mathematics — a standard exam, and another to test higher level competency.</li>
<li>It will help reduce the fear of maths among students and encourage learning.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of PARAKH</h4>
<ul>
<li>PARAKH will help tackle the problem of students of some state boards being at a disadvantage during college admissions as compared to their peers in CBSE schools.</li>
<li>It will develop and implement “technical standards for the design, conduct, analysis and reporting” of tests at all levels of school education.</li>
<li>PARAKH will eventually become the national single-window source for all assessment related information and expertise, with a mandate to support learning assessment in all forms, both nationally and where applicable, internationally.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/parakh-a-new-regulator-for-uniformity-in-all-board-exams/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>NCRB releases ‘Crime in India’ Report</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ncrb-releases-crime-in-india-report/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NCRB</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Crime in India</p></div></div><p>A new edition of ‘Crime in India’, the annual report of the National Crime Records Bureau (NCRB), was released on August 29, for crime-related statistics in 2021.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>NCRB reports have been a valuable compilation of statistics over the years on offences ranging from crimes against women to economic and financial crimes.</li>
<li>It has provided honest and credible sets of crime related data in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Crime in India: Key highlights</h4>
<ul>
<li>Overall, 2021 saw a <strong><u>6 per cent decline in the number of crimes registered</u></strong>, as compared to 2020.</li>
<li>The crime rate per lakh population declined from 487.8 in 2020 to 445.9 in 2021.</li>
<li>However, crime statistics do not always tell the full story, and <strong><u>lower crimes reported in an area do not necessarily mean it is safe.</u></strong></li>
<li><strong><u>Crimes against women rose 15 per cent</u></strong> in India in 2021 and Delhi is the most unsafe metropolitan city.</li>
<li>Rajasthan reported the highest number of rape cases and Maharashtra topped the list when it comes to most suicides.</li>
<li>Around 1<strong><u>.73 lakh people died in traffic accidents</u></strong>. Uttar Pradesh saw the highest number of deaths (24,711) in traffic accidents.</li>
<li>Jammu and Kashmir registered the most <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/unlawful-activities-prevention-act-uapa/"><strong>Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act (UAPA)</strong></a> cases under the ‘special and local laws’ in 2021, as per NCRB data.</li>
<li>Of the total 814 cases under the UAPA in India, J&amp;K lodged 289 cases last year, followed by Manipur (157), Assam (95), Jharkhand (86) and Uttar Pradesh (83).</li>
<li><strong><u>Jharkhand and Maharashtra filed the highest cases of communal riots</u></strong> last year with 100 and 77 cases respectively.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who publishes the NCRB report?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The NCRB was established in January 1986 with the aim of establishing a body to compile and keep records of data on crime.</li>
<li>It functions under the Union Home Ministry.</li>
<li>Apart from publishing annual reports, its functions include “Collection, coordination and exchange of information on inter-state and international criminals to the respective states”.</li>
<li>NCRB also acts as a “<strong><u>national warehouse” for the fingerprint records</u></strong> of Indian and foreign criminals, and assists in locating interstate criminals through fingerprint search.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How does the NCRB collect information for its report?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The NCRB report contains data received from the 36 states and Union Territories across the country.</li>
<li>Similar data is furnished for 53 metropolitan cities, or those having a population of more than 10 lakh as per the 2011 census, by respective state-level crime records bureaus.</li>
<li>This information is entered by state/UT police at the police station/ district level, and is then validated further at the district level, then the state level, and finally by the NCRB.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with NCRB data</h4>
<ul>
<li>By its own admission, the NCRB says there are limitations to its data.</li>
<li>Since the publication caters to the ‘Principal Offence Rule’ for classification of crime, the actual count of each crime head may go <strong><u>under-reporting</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Principal Offence Rule states that in a case where multiple offences are registered, only the “most heinous crime”, carrying the most stringent punishment, is considered when counting.</li>
<li>For example, ‘<strong><u>Murder with Rape’ is accounted as ‘Murder’</u></strong>, leading to undercounting of the crime of rape.</li>
<li>Vacancies or a <strong><u>shortage of police officers</u></strong> at the local level may hinder the collection of data.</li>
<li>Also the data record the incidence of registered crime rather than of actual crime.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Antithesis to NCRB data</h4>
<ul>
<li>Reported <strong><u>crimes against women in Delhi rose significantly</u></strong> in the aftermath of the 2012 Nirbhaya Gangrape case.</li>
<li>This is not because the heinous crimes got trivialized.</li>
<li>It may have been a <strong><u>reflection of increased awareness about the need for registering crimes</u></strong>, both among those affected and the police, rather than an actual increase in the incidence of crime against women.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ncrb-releases-crime-in-india-report/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>