<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 09:09:35 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Universal basic income for complete social security</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/universal-basic-income/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>various schemes for vulnerable section</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>social security, universal basic income</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="universal basic income " class="alignnone wp-image-626175" height="386" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 685px) 100vw, 685px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/basic-income-2021-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/basic-income-2021-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/basic-income-2021-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/basic-income-2021.jpg 1024w" width="685"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>New evidence from two Kenyan counties shows that universal basic income  and other income supplements reduce hunger, illness, and risk exposure during crises.</li>
<li>Countries should consider building universal basic income that can be activated at short notice to help people weather unanticipated shocks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When the COVID-19 pandemic and the resulting recession pushed 120 million people worldwide into extreme poverty in 2020, many countries relied on social-protection measures to cushion the blow.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is social protection?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Social protection is concerned with preventing, managing, and overcoming situations that adversely affect people’s well-being.</li>
<li>Social protection programs that assist low-income families, insure against shocks, and break poverty traps offer a potential solution.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="universal basic income " class="alignnone wp-image-626176" height="401" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 711px) 100vw, 711px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/UBI-2-x433-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/UBI-2-x433-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/UBI-2-x433-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/UBI-2-x433.jpg 770w" width="711"/>Universal basic income meaning</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Universal basic income (UBI) is a model for providing all citizens of a country or other geographic area with a given sum of money, regardless of their income, resources or employment status.</li>
<li>The purpose of UBI is to prevent or reduce poverty and increase equality among citizens.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/universalisation-of-social-security-remains-an-unfulfilled-aspiration/"><strong>What is social security?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Social securityin India includes a variety of statutory insurances and social grant schemes bundled into a formerly complex and fragmented system run by the Indian government.</li>
<li>These are retirement, healthcare, disability, childcare, gratuity and provident fund and insurance programs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is insurance simple words?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An agreement by which a person pays a company and the company promises to pay money if the person becomes injured or dies or to pay for the value of property lost or damaged.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Constitutional mandate </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Directive Principles of State Policy, enshrined in Part IV of the Indian Constitution reflects that India is a welfare state.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Interesting fact </strong></p>
<p><strong>India operates the widest spectrum of social security schemes which cater to the largest number of people than any other country.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/op-ed-snap-ensure-a-minimum-income-for-all/"><strong>What are the benefits of Universal Basic Income?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Ending poverty: </strong>Advocates for UBI say that it could help bring everyone’s income above the poverty line.</li>
<li><strong>Discouraging low wages: </strong>UBI would give employees enough security to have bargaining power.</li>
<li><strong>Redistributing wealth: </strong>The economic growth of high-income countries is making the rich richer, but having very little effect on the working classes.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Case study / value addition </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Namibia</strong></p>
<p>Namibia had a basic income pilot program between 2008 and 2009. Every resident of Otjivero-Omitara was entitled to 100 Namibian dollars ($6.75) every month. The program was funded by donors from around the world.</p>
<p>Findings from the pilot program showed that cases of child malnutrition had dropped significantly while school enrollment went up. Also, social crimes such as theft had significantly dropped.</p></blockquote>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/op-ed-snapgood-jobs-not-universal-basic-income-are-needed-for-a-good-society/"><strong><img alt="universal basic income " class="alignnone wp-image-626177" height="470" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ubi1.jpeg" width="706"/>Negative implications of UBI</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Induce lethargy: </strong>UBI removes the incentive to work, adversely affecting the economy and leading to a labour and skills shortage.</li>
<li><strong>Inequity:</strong> Universal basic income would be just that: universal. That means that everyone, regardless of how poor, or rich, they were would get the same amount of money.</li>
<li><strong>Huge Cost</strong>: The cost of implementing UBI could be huge. In the United States it’s estimated to be about $3.9 trillion per year.</li>
<li><strong>Motivation to work</strong>: One concern is that UBI would incite millions of workers to stop working. If people aren’t working, there is less taxable income.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Some government initiatives </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>National Pension Scheme for Traders and Self Employed Persons.</li>
<li>Pradhan Mantri Suraksha Bima Yojana.</li>
<li>Employees’ State Insurance Scheme.</li>
<li>Minimum Wages for various employment roles.</li>
<li>National Pension System.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>One of the major criticisms of poverty alleviation programs is significant leakages. UBI is seen as a more efficient alternative. Though UBI has many advantages, there are many practical challenges too. The idea should be to save costs with better targeting. This will help create the necessary conditions for higher growth which will decisively lift people out of poverty.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. India operates the widest spectrum of social security schemes which cater to the largest number of people than any other country. Do you think they are enough? Discuss in context of rising demand for universal basic income and its pros and cons for ensuring social security.</strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/universal-basic-income/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Forest fire management for positive sustainable forest growth</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/forest-fire/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>National Action Plan on Forest Fires</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>environment conservation</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="forest fire" class="alignnone wp-image-626486" height="390" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 692px) 100vw, 692px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.49259600_1661422079_wildfire-in-california-2013-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.49259600_1661422079_wildfire-in-california-2013-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.49259600_1661422079_wildfire-in-california-2013-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.49259600_1661422079_wildfire-in-california-2013.jpg 1024w" width="692"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Forest fires are becoming more common and wildfires are destroying nearly twice as much tree cover globally as they did in 2001.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Climate change is driving more intense and widespread forest fire by fuelling more extreme heat and deepening drought, which dries out forests.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How to define <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-forest-fires-are-sometimes-a-good-thing/">forest fire</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A wildfire, forest fire, bushfire, wildland fire or rural fire is an unplanned, uncontrolled and unpredictable fire in an area of combustible vegetation starting in rural and urban areas.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What causes forest fires?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Human activities</strong>: Forest fires can be caused by a number of natural causes, but officials say many major fires in India are triggered mainly by human activities.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/subject/climate-change/"><strong>Climate change</strong></a>: Emerging studies link climate change to rising instances of fires globally, especially the massive fires of the Amazon forests in Brazil and in Australia in the last two years. Fires of longer duration, increasing intensity, higher frequency and highly inflammable nature are all being linked to climate change.</li>
<li><strong>Season</strong>: In India, wildfires are most commonly reported during March and April, when the ground has large quantities of dry wood, logs, dead leaves, stumps, dry grass and weeds that can make forests easily go up in flames if there is a trigger.</li>
<li><strong>Natural reasons:</strong> Under natural circumstances, extreme heat and dryness, friction created by rubbing of branches with each other also have been known to initiate fire.</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="forest fire " class="alignnone wp-image-626490" height="508" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 761px) 100vw, 761px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/main_1500-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/main_1500-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/main_1500-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/main_1500-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/main_1500-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/main_1500.jpg 1500w" width="761"/></p>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Key fact </strong></h4>
<p><strong>7.4 million acres of forest are getting burnt annually now an area roughly the size of Belgium.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>What factors make forest fires a concern?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-must-commit-to-net-zero-emissions/"><strong>Carbon emission</strong>:</a> They act as a sink, reservoir and source of carbon.</li>
<li><strong>Livelihood loss</strong>: In India, with 1.70 lakh villages in close proximity to forests (Census 2011), the livelihood of several crores of people is dependent on fuelwood, bamboo, fodder, and small timber.</li>
<li><strong>Destruction of animals’ habitat</strong>: Heat generated during the fire destroys animal habitats. Soil quality decreases with the alteration in their compositions.</li>
<li><strong>Soil degradation</strong>: Soil moisture and fertility, too, is affected. Thus forests can shrink in size. The trees that survive fire often remain stunted and growth is severely affected.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Measures to curb Forest fires</strong></h4>
<p><strong>1) National Action Plan on wild fires</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The MoEFCC has prepared a National Action Plan on wild fire in 2018 after several rounds of consultation with all states and UTs.</li>
<li>The objective of this plan is to minimize forest fires by informing, enabling and empowering forest fringe communities and incentivizing them to work in tandem with the State Forest Departments.</li>
<li>The plan also intends to substantially reduce the vulnerability of forests across diverse forest ecosystems in the country against fire hazards, enhance capabilities of forest personnel and institutions in fighting fires and swift recovery subsequent to fire incidents.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2) Forest Fire Prevention and Management scheme</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The MoEFCC provides wildfire prevention and management measures under the Centrally Sponsored Forest Fire Prevention and Management (FPM) scheme.</li>
<li>The FPM is the only centrally funded program specifically dedicated to assist the states in dealing with forest fires.</li>
<li>The FPM replaced the Intensification of Forest Management Scheme (IFMS) in 2017. By revamping the IFMS, the FPM has increased the amount dedicated for forest fire work.</li>
<li>Funds allocated under the FPM are according to the 90:10 ratio of central to state funding in the Northeast and Western Himalayan regions and 60:40 ratio for all other states.</li>
<li>Nodal officers for forest fire prevention and control have been appointed in each state.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="forest fire" class="alignnone wp-image-626491" height="539" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 539px) 100vw, 539px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-1-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-1-1.jpeg 225w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-1-1-150x150.jpeg 150w" width="539"/>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Awareness should be created among the villagers residing near the forests with respect to the long-term ill effects of forest fires.</li>
<li>Measures to prevent wildfires have to be taken before summer season when fires are prevalent.</li>
<li>Local people should be given skills to use online portals or mobile apps in order to monitor the forests for fires and inform forest authorities regarding the same.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Climate change is driving more intense and widespread forest fires by fueling more extreme heat and deepening drought. Why forest fires are cause of concern? Discuss our preparedness level for the same in the above context.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/forest-fire/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Manusmriti: the controversial ancient Sanskrit text</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/manusmriti-the-controversial-ancient-sanskrit-text/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Manusmriti</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Vice Chancellor of a renowned university recently criticized the Manusmriti, the ancient Sanskrit text, over its gender bias.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The VC said that the Manusmriti has categorised all women as shudras, which is extraordinarily regressive.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Manusmriti?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Mānavadharmaśāstra</u></strong>, also known as Manusmriti or the Laws of Manu, is a Sanskrit text belonging to the Dharmaśāstra literary tradition of Hinduism.</li>
<li>Composed sometime between the <strong><u>2nd century BCE and 3rd century CE</u></strong>, the Manusmriti is <strong><u>written in sloka verses</u></strong>, containing two non-rhyming lines of 16 syllabus each.</li>
<li>The text is attributed to the mythical figure of Manu, considered to be ancestor of the human race in Hinduism.</li>
<li>There has been considerable debate between scholars on the authorship of the text.</li>
<li>Many have argued that it was compiled by many Brahmin scholars over a period of time.</li>
<li>However, Indologist Patrick Olivelle argues that Manusmṛiti’s “unique and symmetrical structure,” means that it was composed by a “single gifted individual,” or by a “strong chairman of a committee” with the aid of others.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the text about?</h4>
<h4>(A) Social aspects</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Manusmriti is encyclopaedic in scope, covering subjects such as the <strong><u>social obligations and duties of the various castes</u></strong> and of individuals in different stages of life.</li>
<li>It seeks to <strong><u>govern the suitable social and sexual relations of men and women of different castes</u></strong>, on <strong><u>taxes</u></strong>, the <strong><u>rules for kingship</u></strong>, on <strong><u>maintaining marital harmony</u></strong> and the procedures for <strong><u>settling everyday disputes.</u></strong></li>
<li>At its core, the Manusmriti <strong><u>discusses life in the world, how it is lived in reality</u></strong>, as well as how it ought to be.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(B) Political aspects</h4>
<ul>
<li>They argue that the <strong><u>text is about dharma, which means duty, religion, law and practice</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It also discusses <strong><u>aspects of the Arthashashtra</u></strong>, such as issues relating to statecraft and legal procedures.</li>
<li>The aim of the text is to present a blueprint for a properly <strong><u>ordered society</u></strong> under the <strong><u>sovereignty of the king and the guidance of Brahmins.</u></strong></li>
<li>It was <strong><u>meant to be read by the priestly caste and Olivelle</u></strong> argues that it would likely have been part of the curriculum for young Brahmin scholars at colleges.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is its significance?</h4>
<ul>
<li>By the early centuries of the Common Era, Manu had become, and remained, the standard source of authority in the orthodox tradition for that centrepiece of Hinduism, varṇāśrama-dharma (social and religious duties tied to class and stage of life)”.</li>
<li>Indologists argue that it was a very significant text for Brahmin scholars — it attracted 9 commentaries by other writers of the tradition, and was cited by other ancient Indian texts far more frequently than other dharmaśāstra.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did colonists consider this text?</h4>
<ul>
<li>European Orientalists considered the Manusmṛiti to be of great historical and religious significance as well. It was the first Sanskrit text to be translated into a European language, by the British philologist Sir William Jones in 1794.</li>
<li>Subsequently, it was translated into French, German, Portuguese and Russian, before being included in Max Muller’s edited volume, Sacred Books of the East in 1886.</li>
<li>For colonial officials in British India, the translation of the book served a practical purpose.</li>
<li>In 1772, Governor-General Warren Hastings decided to implement laws of Hindus and Muslims that they believed to be “continued, unchanged from remotest antiquity.</li>
<li>For Hindus, the dharmasastras were to play a crucial role, as they were seen by the British as ‘laws,’ whether or not it was even used that way in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is it controversial?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ancient text has 4 major divisions: 1) Creation of the world. 2) Sources of dharma. 3) The dharma of the four social classes. 4) Law of karma, rebirth, and final liberation.</li>
<li>The third section is the longest and most important section.</li>
<li>The text is deeply concerned with maintaining the <strong><u>hierarchy of the four-fold varna system</u></strong> and the rules that each caste has to follow.</li>
<li>Then, the <strong><u>Brahmin is assumed to be the perfect representative of the human race</u></strong>.</li>
<li>While Shudras, who are relegated to the bottom of the order, are given the sole duty of serving the ‘upper’ castes.</li>
<li>Some verses also contain highly prejudicial sentiments against women on the basis of their birth.</li>
<li>There are many verses in the text that are considered highly controversial.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Dr. Ambedkar and Manusmriti</h4>
<ul>
<li>On December 25, 1927, Dr B R Ambedkar had famously burned the Manusmṛiti, which he saw as a source of gender and caste oppression.</li>
<li>However, he widely acknowledged that Manusmriti is <strong><u>NOT a religious decree</u></strong> but a social doctrine, manipulated since centuries to normalize oppression of the population.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/manusmriti-the-controversial-ancient-sanskrit-text/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>One Nation One Fertiliser (ONOF) Scheme</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/one-nation-one-fertiliser-onof-scheme/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>One Nation One Fertiliser (ONOF)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India's fertilizer subsidy</p></div></div><p>The Ministry of Chemicals and Fertilisers will implement One Nation One Fertiliser (ONOF) by introducing a Single Brand for Fertilisers and Logo under the fertiliser subsidy scheme named “Pradhanmantri Bhartiya Janurvarak Pariyojna” (PMBJP).</p>
<h4>One Nation One Fertiliser (ONOF)</h4>
<ul>
<li>The single brand name for UREA, DAP, MOP and NPK etc. would be BHARAT UREA, BHARAT DAP, BHARAT MOP and BHARAT NPK etc. respectively for all Fertiliser Companies, State Trading Entities (STEs) and Fertiliser Marketing Entities (FMEs).</li>
<li>Also a logo indicating Fertiliser subsidy scheme namely Pradhanmantri Bhartiya Janurvarak Pariyojna will be used on said fertiliser bags.</li>
<li>Under the scheme, companies are allowed to display their name, brand, logo and other relevant product information only on one-third space of their bags.</li>
<li>On the remaining two-thirds space, the “Bharat” brand and Pradhanmantri Bharatiya Jan Urvarak Pariyojana logo will have to be shown.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the government’s argument for introducing this scheme?</h4>
<p>The government’s logic for introducing a <strong><u>single ‘Bharat’ brand</u></strong> for all subsidised fertilisers being marketed by companies is as follows:</p>
<p><strong>(1) Subsidies normalization</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The maximum retail price of urea is currently fixed by the government, which compensates companies for the higher cost of manufacturing or imports incurred by them.</li>
<li>The MRPs of non-urea fertilisers are, on paper, decontrolled.</li>
<li>But companies cannot avail of subsidy if they sell at MRPs higher than that informally indicated by the government.</li>
<li>Simply put, there are some 26 fertilisers (inclusive of urea), on which government bears subsidy and also effectively decides the MRPs;</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Harmonizing markets</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Apart from subsidising and deciding at what price companies can sell, the government also decides where they can sell.</li>
<li>This is done through the Fertiliser (Movement) Control Order, 1973.</li>
<li>Under this, the department of fertilisers draws an agreed monthly supply plan on all subsidised fertilisers in consultation with manufacturers and importers.</li>
<li>This supply plan is issued before the 25th of each month for the following month, with the department also regularly monitoring movement to ensure fertiliser availability as per requirement, including remote areas.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Farmers welfare</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The government is spending vast sums of money on fertiliser subsidy (the bill is likely to cross Rs 200,000 crore in 2022-23).</li>
<li>By deciding where and at what price companies can sell, it would obviously want to take credit and send that message to farmers.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What can be the drawbacks of the scheme?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It may <strong><u>disincentivise fertiliser companies</u></strong> from undertaking marketing and brand promotion activities.</li>
<li>They will now be <strong><u>reduced to contract manufacturers</u></strong> and importers for the government. Any company’s strength ultimately is its brands and farmer trust built over decades.</li>
<li>Currently, in case of any bag or batch of fertilisers not meeting the required standards, the <strong><u>blame is put on the company</u>. </strong>But now, that may be passed on fully to the government.</li>
<li>Politically, the scheme might well boomerang rather than benefit the ruling party.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/one-nation-one-fertiliser-onof-scheme/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Labour Codes empower workers: PM</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/labour-codes-empower-workers-pm/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Labour codes</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>Addressing to the National Labour Conference, Prime Minister said that the Centre had taken initiatives to abolish laws from “the period of slavery” that reflected a slavery mentality through the Labour Codes.</p>
<h4>New Labour Codes</h4>
<p>The four codes likely to be implemented in FY23 are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Code on Wages</li>
<li>Industrial Relations Code</li>
<li>Social Security Code, and</li>
<li>Occupational Safety, Health and Working Conditions Code</li>
</ol>
<h4>Objectives of the Labour Code</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-new-labour-laws/">new labor codes</a> are aimed at facilitating ease of doing business in the country and seek to replace 29 cumbersome laws.</li>
<li>The objective is to encompass over 500 million organized and unorganized sector workers—90% of the workforce which has been outside labour laws.</li>
<li>The idea is to ensure that they receive wage security, social security and health security, gender equality in terms of remuneration, a minimum floor wage, make the lives of inter-state migrant workers easier.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the current status of the codes?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The central government has completed the process of finalizing the draft rules, state governments are in the process of drafting the same.</li>
<li>With labor being a concurrent subject, states are in the process of pre-publishing draft rules for these reforms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How many labour laws do Indian states have?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The simplification of 29 labour laws into the four labour codes is expected be a watershed moment for labour reforms.</li>
<li>India currently has a web of multiple labour legislations, over 40 central laws and 100 state laws involving labour.</li>
<li>The Second National Commission on Labour (2002) recommended simplification to bring about transparency and uniformity.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the major reforms in these codes?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Social security benefits:</strong> With organized sector workers being approximately 10% of the total workforce, the new codes may ensure that social security benefits are for all.</li>
<li><strong>Take-home salary:</strong> As per the proposed labour codes, total allowances such as house rent, leave, travel etc. are to be capped at 50% of the salary, while basic pay should account for the remaining 50%.</li>
<li><strong>Four days work:</strong> There could also be a permissible four-day work week of 12 hours per day.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How will it affect ease of doing business?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Labour productivity:</strong> It is likely to improve with both employees and employers developing a sense of being partners in wealth creation.</li>
<li><strong>Labour reform:</strong> A transparent environment in terms of workers’ compensation, clear definition of employee rights and employer duties.</li>
<li><strong>Compliance un-burdening:</strong> Simplified labour codes making compliance easier are likely to attract investments.</li>
<li><strong>Formalization of the economy:</strong> With more workers in the organized sector, leakage in terms of direct as well as indirect taxes may be plugged.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="JQsCoVPwp7"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-new-labour-laws/">[Burning Issue] New Labour Laws</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="JQsCoVPwp7" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-new-labour-laws/embed/#?secret=pEgHi1HIRf#?secret=JQsCoVPwp7" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Burning Issue] New Labour Laws” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/labour-codes-empower-workers-pm/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Robust Sport governance for national pride</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sport-governance/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>sports bodies</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>sport governance transparency</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="sport governance" class="alignnone wp-image-626497" height="377" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 669px) 100vw, 669px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543.jpg 1600w" width="669"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The judicial push for reforms in sport governance of various sporting bodies, football, hockey, table tennis and the Indian Olympic Association has understandably received mixed reactions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The national sports federation’s usual governance practices do not place either the sport or the athlete front and centre; that space is reserved for official egos, whims and political clout.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is sport governance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sport governance refers to the power a government has over institutions and allows their decisions to be made with due consideration to their influence, authority, and organizational structure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-mudda-aapka-sports-as-a-fundamental-right/">Sports in India</a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Physical activity is fundamental to human beings:</strong>  The report states that having a fundamental right to literacy would mean identifying the intrinsic value of physical activity to human living.</li>
<li><strong>Part of elementary education:</strong> It would mean not seeing physical activity as an end in itself, and the establishment of physical activity/ physical education as a core component of the education curriculum.</li>
<li><strong>Supportive to other FRs:</strong> A fundamental right to physical literacy would actualise and enhance the enjoyment of other fundamental rights. It would go a long way in enhancing the opportunities and freedom to express oneself.</li>
<li><strong>Enhancing life quality:</strong> A physically literate individual would have a more fulfilling life of higher quality than one who is not.  Physical literacy, as a building block, would go a long way in the promotion and realisation of the right to health and the right to education.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="sport governance " class="alignnone wp-image-626496" height="409" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 576px) 100vw, 576px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/93726271-300x213.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/93726271-300x213.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/93726271.jpg 600w" width="576"/>Issues with the Current Sports governance </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of check and balance</strong>: The biggest concern regarding these bodies so far has been a complete lack of checks and balances.</li>
<li><strong>Excessive autonomy</strong>: In the pretext of autonomy, they have been allowed to function in any manner.</li>
<li><strong>Less people centric approach</strong>: The federations have generally fallen short of public expressions and have failed to carry out their jobs. It has been largely attributed to the way they are governed.</li>
<li><strong>Accountability</strong>: The current sports model faces accountability issues such as that of having unlimited discretionary powers and also there is no transparency in the decision-making.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="sport governance" class="alignnone wp-image-626499" height="291" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-3.jpeg" width="343"/></strong></h4>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong>Sport governance in India is administered by </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Ministry of Youth Affairs and Sports (MYAS)</li>
<li>National Sports Federation (NSF)</li>
<li>Indian Olympic Association (IOA)</li>
<li>State Olympic Association (SOA)</li>
<li>Sports Authority of India (SAI)</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Positive Suggestions</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Legislation</strong>: There must be presence of powerful and defined sports legislation in India covering all the nuances of sports and giving no arbiter powers to any authority.</li>
<li><strong>Transparency</strong>-: To maintain transparency with expenditure and fund utilization, Information like a board of members, administrative officials, and remuneration information must be in public domain.</li>
<li><strong>Women Representation</strong>: It is very important to have sufficient women representation in sports as well as in the administrative bodies, and it is the responsibility of these admin bodies to ensure sufficient representation from women in the board too, to maintain the diversity within the board.</li>
<li><strong>Plans</strong>: There should be fix timelines disclosed which are to be adopted by sports bodies for the purpose of growth and development of sports in future, which is to be achieved in a given specific period of time. These kinds of timelines and plans would be motivational for players and bodies to. Goals to be targeted in future must be predecided, which can be well monitored and regulated by the authorities. Effective implementation would bring positive results in future.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-olympic-association-ioa/"><strong>Committees</strong>:</a> To set up specific committees for specific activities relating to sports activities, like for planning, financing, research and development purposes. These committees would look after the particular task, which would bring transparency in work and achieving the common objective.</li>
<li><strong>Rules and Regulations</strong>: like other fields, sports also have conflicts regarding disciplinary, administrative and management issues, to solve this issues governing bodies must set up a common judicial system (tribunal) to deal with sports-related conflicts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is a close association of sports with national pride and the kind of influence it has on the psyche of the nation, a role for the State is urgent in sports reforms.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. The national sports federation’s usual governance practices do not place either the sport or the athlete front and centre; that space is reserved for official egos what do you think on this ? Explain the term sport governance with some dynamic changes needed in it.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sport-governance/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Arth Ganga Model: New govt model for the River’s Sustainable Development</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/arth-ganga-model/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Arth Ganga Model</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Director General of the National Mission for Clean Ganga, spoke about the Arth Ganga Model during his virtual keynote address to the Stockholm World Water Week 2022.</p>
<h4>What is Arth Ganga Model?</h4>
<ul>
<li>PM Modi first introduced the concept during the first National Ganga Council meeting in Kanpur in 2019.</li>
<li>He urged for a shift from <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/quick-catch-up-on-the-namami-gange-program/">Namami Gange</a>, the Union Government’s flagship project to clean the Ganga, to the model of Arth Ganga.</li>
<li>The latter focuses on the sustainable development of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/drainage-system-part-4/">Ganga</a> and its surrounding areas, by focusing on economic activities related to the river.</li>
<li>At its core, the Arth Ganga model seeks to use economics to bridge people with the river.</li>
<li>It strives to contribute at least 3% of the GDP from the Ganga Basin itself.</li>
<li>The Arth Ganga project’s interventions are in accordance with India’s commitments towards the UN sustainable development goals.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Features</h4>
<p>Under Arth Ganga, the government is working on six verticals.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong><u>Zero Budget Natural Farming</u></strong> that includes chemical-free farming for 10 kms on either side of the river, generating “more income, per drop”, ‘Gobar Dhan’ for farmers,</li>
<li><strong><u>Monetization and Reuse of Sludge &amp;Wastewater</u></strong> that envisages reuse of treated water for irrigation; industrial purposes and revenue generation for ULBs,</li>
<li><strong><u>Livelihood Opportunities Generation</u></strong> such as ‘Ghat Mein Haat’, promotion of local products, Ayurveda, medicinal plants, capacity building of volunteers like Ganga Praharis,</li>
<li><strong><u>Public Participation</u></strong> to ensure increased synergies between stakeholders,</li>
<li><strong><u>Cultural Heritage &amp;Tourism</u></strong> that looks to introduce boat tourism through community jettis, promotion of yoga, adventure tourism etc. and Ganga Artis and</li>
<li><strong><u>Institutional Building</u></strong> by enhancing the local capacities for better decentralized water governance.</li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/arth-ganga-model/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Jharkhand CM may face disqualification</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cm-disqualification-office-of-profit/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Office of Profit</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>Jharkhand CM’s chair remains uncertain as the Election Commission (EC) is understood to have conveyed its decision in an office-of-profit complaint against him to the Governor.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Under Section 9A of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/prominent-features-of-the-representation-of-peoples-act/">Representation of the People Act, 1951</a>, the CM could face disqualification for entering into a government contract.</li>
<li>The Constitution of India does not define the Office of Profit. It has only mentioned it under Article 102 (1) and Article 191 (1).</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Office of Profit?</h4>
<ul>
<li>MPs and MLAs, as members of the legislature, hold the government accountable for its work.</li>
<li>The essence of disqualification is if legislators hold an ‘office of profit’ under the government, they might be susceptible to government influence, and may not discharge their constitutional mandate fairly.</li>
<li>The intent is that <strong><u>there should be no conflict between the duties and interests of an elected member.</u></strong></li>
<li>Hence, the office of profit law simply seeks to enforce a basic feature of the Constitution- the principle of separation of power between the legislature and the executive.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What governs the term?</h4>
<ul>
<li>At present, the <strong><u>Parliament (Prevention of Disqualification) Act, 1959</u></strong>, bars an MP, MLA or an MLC from holding any office of profit under the central or state government unless it is exempted.</li>
<li>However, <strong><u>it does not clearly define what constitutes an office of profit.</u></strong></li>
<li>Legislators can face disqualification for holding such positions, which bring them financial or other benefits.</li>
<li>Under the provisions of <strong><u>Article 102 (1)</u> and <u>Article 191 (1)</u></strong> of the Constitution, an MP or an MLA (or an MLC) is barred from holding any office of profit under the Central or State government.</li>
</ul>
<h4>An undefined term</h4>
<ul>
<li>The officials of the law ministry are of the view that defining an office of profit could lead to the filing of a number of cases with the Election Commission and the courts.</li>
<li>Also, once the definition is changed, one will also have to amend various provisions in the Constitution including Article 102 (1) (a) and Article 109 (1) (a) that deal with the office of profit.</li>
<li>It will have an overarching effect on all the other sections of the Constitution.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Factors constituting an ‘office of profit’</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 1959 law does not clearly define what constitutes an office of profit but the <strong><u>definition has evolved over the years with interpretations made in various court judgments.</u></strong></li>
<li>An office of profit has been interpreted to be a position that brings to the office-holder some financial gain, or advantage, or benefit. The amount of such profit is immaterial.</li>
<li>In 1964, the Supreme Court ruled that the test for determining whether a person holds an office of profit is the test of appointment.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the ‘test of appointment’?</h4>
<p>Several factors are considered in this determination including factors such as:</p>
<ol>
<li>whether the government is the appointing authority,</li>
<li>whether the government has the power to terminate the appointment,</li>
<li>whether the government determines the remuneration,</li>
<li>what is the source of remuneration, and</li>
<li>the power that comes with the position.</li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cm-disqualification-office-of-profit/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India, Bangladesh discuss River Water Sharing issues</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/river-water-sharing-issues/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Rivers mentioned</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India-Bangladesh Relations</p></div></div><p>India and Bangladesh discussed a wide range of River Water Sharing issues related to the major common rivers such as the Ganga, Teesta and several others during the 38th meeting of the Joint River Commission (JRC).</p>
<h4>Rivers between India and Bangladesh</h4>
<ul>
<li>Overall, India and Bangladesh have 54 transboundary rivers between them, all of which are part of the drainage system of the Ganga-Brahmaputra-Meghna (GBM) basin.</li>
<li>The Padma (the Ganga), the Jamuna (the Brahmaputra) and the Meghna (the Barak) and their tributaries are integral in maintaining food and water security in Bangladesh.</li>
<li>In most of these cases, Bangladesh is the lower riparian.</li>
<li>This causes concern in Bangladesh that India—being both the upper riparian and first to develop the water resources—can have far more disproportionate control over the rivers.</li>
<li>Compounded by the lack of transparent data regarding trans-boundary rivers, such concern can lead to a more serious conflict between the two otherwise friendly neighbours.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Genesis of the disputes</h4>
<ul>
<li>The issues between India and Bangladesh regarding water resource allotment can be traced to the time <strong><u>Bangladesh was still East Pakistan</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In <strong><u>1961</u></strong>, India began <strong><u>construction of the Farakka Barrage</u></strong>—which was to be operational by April 1975—to divert a portion of the dry-season flow and increase the navigability of Kolkata port.</li>
<li>When India began its preliminary planning for the project in 1950-51, <strong><u>Pakistan immediately expressed concerns</u></strong> over the potential effect of the project on East Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Moves for disputes resolution: Joint River Commission</h4>
<ul>
<li>Soon after the <strong><u>independence of Bangladesh in 1971</u></strong>, the <strong><u>Joint River Commission</u></strong> was formed between India and Bangladesh in 1972.</li>
<li>In a joint declaration issued on 16 May 1974, the PM of Bangladesh and India acknowledged the need for the flow augmentation of the Ganga in the lean season to meet the requirements of both countries.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Often in news: Teesta River Dispute</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Bangladesh government has been insistent on sealing the <strong><u>Teesta Waters Agreement</u></strong>, which has eluded settlement so far.</li>
<li>Teesta River is a 315 km long river that rises in the eastern Himalayas, flows through the Indian states of Sikkim and West Bengal through Bangladesh and enters the Bay of Bengal.</li>
<li>It is a tributary of the Brahmaputra (known as Jamuna in Bangladesh), flowing through India and Bangladesh.</li>
<li>It originates in the Himalayas near Chunthang, Sikkim and flows to the south through West Bengal before entering Bangladesh.</li>
<li>Originally, it continued southward to empty directly into the Padma River but around 1787 the river changed its course to flow eastward to join the Jamuna river.</li>
<li>The Teesta Barrage dam helps to provide irrigation for the plains between the upper Padma and the Jamuna.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the dispute about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The point of contention between India and Bangladesh is mainly the lean season flow in the Teesta draining into Bangladesh.</li>
<li>The river covers nearly the entire floodplains of Sikkim while draining 2,800 sq km of Bangladesh, governing the lives of hundreds of thousands of people.</li>
<li>For West Bengal, Teesta is equally important, considered the lifeline of half-a-dozen districts in North Bengal.</li>
<li>Bangladesh has sought an “equitable” distribution of Teesta waters from India, on the lines of the Ganga Water Treaty of 1996, but to no avail.</li>
<li>The failure to ink a deal had its fallout on the country’s politics, putting the ruling party of PM Sheikh Hasina in a spot.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>Q.The hydrological linkages between India and Bangladesh are a product of geography and a matter of shared history. Discuss this statement in line with the Teesta water-sharing dispute.</p></blockquote>
<h4>The deal</h4>
<ul>
<li>Following a half-hearted deal in 1983, when a nearly equal division of water was proposed, the countries hit a roadblock. The transient agreement could not be implemented.</li>
<li>Talks resumed after the Awami League returned to power in 2008 and the former Indian PM Manmohan Singh visited Dhaka in 2011.</li>
<li>In 2015, PM Modi’s visit to Dhaka generated more ebullient lines: deliberations were underway involving all the stakeholders to conclude the agreement as soon as possible.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues from the Indian side</h4>
<ul>
<li>It remains an unfinished project and one of the key stakeholders — West Bengal CM is yet to endorse the deal.</li>
<li>Her objection is connected to “global warming. Many of the glaciers on the Teesta basin have retreated.</li>
<li>The importance of the flow and the seasonal variation of this river is felt during the lean season (from October to April/May) as the average flow is about 500 million cubic metres (MCM) per month.</li>
<li>The CM opposed an arrangement in 2011, by which India would get 42.5% and Bangladesh 37.5% of the water during the lean season, and the plan was shelved.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why does this deal matters?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India and Bangladesh have resolved border problems through the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/land-boundary-agreement-lba-with-bangladesh/">Land Boundary Agreement of 2015</a>.</li>
<li>However, both nations have locked horns over the sharing of multiple rivers that define the borders and impact lives and livelihoods on both sides.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/river-water-sharing-issues/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Digital health holds promising future for India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/digital-health/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Digital health id</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>National digital health mission</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="digital health" class="alignnone wp-image-626507" height="362" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 724px) 100vw, 724px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/digital-health-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/digital-health-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/digital-health-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/digital-health.jpg 800w" width="724"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The covid-19 pandemic has presented a watershed moment, bringing the world’s healthcare systems to a halt, forcing us to rethink existing healthcare delivery models and embrace the digital health transformation of the sector.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Definition of digital health care</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Digital health is a discipline that includes digital care programs, technologies with health, healthcare, living, and society to enhance the efficiency of healthcare delivery and to make medicine more personalized and precise.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Digital Health: A Backgrounder</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The National Health Policy 2017 had envisaged creation of a digital health technology eco-system aiming at developing an integrated health information system.</li>
<li>A Digital Health ID was proposed to reduce the risk of preventable medical errors and significantly increase the quality of care.</li>
<li>It recognised the need to establish a specialised ecosystem, called the National Digital Health Mission (NDHM).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="digital health" class="alignnone wp-image-626513" height="585" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 605px) 100vw, 605px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ndhmc-300x290.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ndhmc-300x290.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ndhmc.jpg 595w" width="605"/>The National Digital Health Mission</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The NDHM is a digital health ecosystem under which every Indian citizen will now have unique health IDs, digitized health records with identifiers for doctors and health facilities.</li>
<li>The mission will significantly improve the efficiency, effectiveness, and transparency of health service delivery and will be a major step towards the achievement of the UN Sustainable Development Goal 3.8 of Universal Health Coverage, including financial risk protection.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Digital health is a discipline that includes digital care programs, technologies with health, healthcare, living, and society to enhance the efficiency of healthcare delivery and to make medicine more personalized and precise." class="alignnone wp-image-626523" height="418" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/dh.jpeg" width="628"/>Significance of digital health </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Prioritizing patients: </strong>Say, mortality from Covid-19 is significantly increased by comorbidities or the presence of other underlying conditions like hypertension or diabetes.With digital health records, doctors can prioritise patients based on their test results.</li>
<li><strong>Portability of health records: </strong>Portability of records fairly eases in a patient with the first hospital visit, or her/his most frequently visited hospital. If she/he wishes to change a healthcare provider for cost or quality reasons, she can access her health records without carrying pieces of paper prescriptions and test reports. People will able to access their lab reports, x-rays and prescriptions irrespective of where they were generated, and share them with doctors or family members — with consent.</li>
<li><strong>Easy facilitation: </strong>This initiative will allow patients to access healthcare facilities remotely through e-pharmacies, online appointments, teleconsultation, and other health benefits. Besides, as all the medical history of the patient is recorded in the Health ID card, it will help the doctor to understand the case better, and improved medication can be offered.</li>
<li><strong>Technology impetus in policymaking: </strong>Meanwhile, it is also not just individuals who could emerge beneficiaries of the scheme. With large swathes of data being made available, the government too can form policies based on geographical, demographical, and risk-factor based monitoring of health.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Critical point to remember </strong></h4>
<p><strong>In the case of lung cancer, only 18.5 % of patients survive five or more years once diagnosed. These are threats that data-led technology will help address.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/on-digital-health-id-proceed-with-caution/"><strong>Major privacy issues involved</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Informed Consent:</strong>The citizen’s consent is vital for all access. A beneficiary’s consent is vital to ensure that information is released.</li>
<li><strong>Data leakages issue:</strong>Personalised data collected at multiple levels are a “sitting gold mine” for insurance companies, international researchers, and pharma companies.</li>
<li><strong>Digital divide:</strong>Other experts add that lack of access to technology, poverty, and lack of understanding of the language in a vast and diverse country like India are problems that need to be looked into.</li>
<li><strong>Data Migration:</strong>The data migration and inter-State transfer are still faced with multiple errors and shortcomings in addition to concerns of data security.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other challenges</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Existing digitalization is yet incomplete:</strong>India has been unable to standardise the coverage and quality of the existing digital cards like One Nation One Ration card, PM-JAY card, Aadhaar card, etc., for accessibility of services and entitlements.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of healthcare facilities:</strong>The defence of data security by expressed informed consent doesn’t work in a country that is plagued by the acute shortage of healthcare professionals to inform the client fully.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of finance:</strong>With the minuscule spending of 1.3% of the GDP on the healthcare sector, India will be unable to ensure the quality and uniform access to healthcare that it hoped to bring about.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>With an enabling ecosystem, supported by effective policies for digital healthcare and increased innovation, the promise of digital solutions in healthcare is immense. It’s not long before precision healthcare becomes central to the health and well-being of every citizen.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. The covid-19 pandemic has presented a watershed moment, bringing the world’s healthcare systems to a halt, forcing us to rethink existing healthcare delivery models. In this context discuss challenges and opportunities of digital health ecosystem in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/digital-health/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Dams in news: Vishnugadh Project</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vishnugadh-project/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Vishnugadh Project</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>An independent panel of the World Bank is considering a plea by residents of some village to investigate environmental damage from the under-construction Vishnugad Pipalkoti Hydro Electric Project (VPHEP).</p>
<h4>Vishnugadh Project</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 444-MW VPHEP is being built by the Tehri Hydropower Development Corporation (THDC), a partially State-owned enterprise.</li>
<li>It is being constructed on <strong><u>Dhauliganga River</u></strong> in <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issues-chamoli-disaster/">Chamoli District</a> of Uttarakhand.</li>
<li>The project is primarily funded by the World Bank and was sanctioned in 2011. It is proposed to be completed in June 2023.</li>
<li>About 40% of the funds for the $792 million project (₹64,000 crore approx.) has already been disbursed.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Residents in their complaint have said muck dumping from the dam threatens the local Lakshmi Narayan Temple, which is deemed to be of historical and cultural importance.</li>
<li>They also complained about the limited availability of water, saying that 70 of the 92 households received water only for two hours daily.</li>
<li>Before the project construction, they had ready access to water.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vishnugadh-project/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Recovery of Ozone Layer achieves significant milestone</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/recovery-of-ozone-layer-achieves-significant-milestone/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ozone, Ozone Hole</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Ozone recovery</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-626760" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 278px) 100vw, 278px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ozone-hole-278x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ozone-hole-278x300.jpg 278w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ozone-hole.jpg 470w" width="278"/></p>
<p>The concentration of ozone-depleting substances in the atmosphere has reduced to reach a significant milestone this year.</p>
<h4>What is Ozone and Ozone Layer?</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-600996" height="1600" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1480px) 100vw, 1480px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/ozon.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/ozon.jpg 1480w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/ozon-278x300.jpg 278w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/ozon-947x1024.jpg 947w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/ozon-768x830.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/ozon-1421x1536.jpg 1421w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/ozon-1200x1297.jpg 1200w" width="1480"/></p>
<ul>
<li>An ozone molecule consists of three oxygen atoms instead of the usual two (the oxygen we breathe, O2, makes up 21% of the atmosphere).</li>
<li>It only exists in the atmosphere in trace quantities (less than 0.001%), but its effects are very important.</li>
<li>Ozone molecules are created by the interaction of ultra-violet (UV) radiation from the Sun with O2 molecules.</li>
<li>Because UV radiation is more intense at higher altitudes where the air is thinner, it is in the stratosphere where most of the ozone is produced, giving rise to what is called the ‘ozone layer’.</li>
<li>The ozone layer, containing over 90% of all atmospheric ozone, extends between about 10 and 40km altitude, peaking at about 25km in Stratosphere.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why need Ozone Layer?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ozone layer is very important for life on Earth because it has the property of absorbing the most damaging form of UV radiation, UV-B radiation which has a wavelength of between 280 and 315 nanometres.</li>
<li>As UV radiation is absorbed by ozone in the stratosphere, it heats up the surrounding air to produce the stratospheric temperature inversion.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Ozone Hole?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Each year for the past few decades during the Southern Hemisphere spring, chemical reactions involving chlorine and bromine cause ozone in the southern polar region to be destroyed rapidly and severely.</li>
<li>The Dobson Unit (DU) is the unit of measure for total ozone.</li>
<li>The chemicals involved ozone depletion are chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs for short), halons, and carbon tetrachloride.</li>
<li>They are used for a wide range of applications, including refrigeration, air conditioning, foam packaging, and making aerosol spray cans.</li>
<li>The ozone-depleted region is known as the “ozone hole”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Tropical Ozone Hole</h4>
<ul>
<li>According to the study, the ozone hole is located at altitudes of 10-25 km over the tropics.</li>
<li>This hole is about seven times larger than Antarctica, the study suggested.</li>
<li>It also appears across all seasons, unlike that of Antarctica, which is visible only in the spring.</li>
<li>The hole has become significant since the 1980s. But it was not discovered until this study.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What caused an ozone hole in the tropics?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Studies suggested another mechanism of ozone depletion: Cosmic rays.</li>
<li>Chlorofluorocarbon’s (CFC) role in depleting the ozone layer is well-documented.</li>
<li>The tropical stratosphere recorded a low temperature of 190-200 Kelvin (K).</li>
<li>This can explain why the tropical ozone hole is constantly formed over the seasons.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of the finding</h4>
<ul>
<li>The tropical ozone hole, which makes up 50 percent of Earth’s surface, could cause a global concern due to the risks associated with it.</li>
<li>It is likely to cause skin cancer, cataracts and other negative effects on the health and ecosystems in tropical regions.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this PYQ</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Q.Consider the following statements:</strong></p>
<p><strong>Chlorofluorocarbons, known as ozone-depleting substances are used:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>In the production of plastic foams</li>
<li>In the production of tubeless tyres</li>
<li>In cleaning certain electronic components</li>
<li>As pressurizing agents in aerosol cans</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Which of the statements given above is/are correct?</strong></p>
<p>(a) 1, 2 and 3 only</p>
<p>(b) 4 only</p>
<p>(c) 1, 3 and 4 only</p>
<p>(d) 1, 2, 3 and 4</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/recovery-of-ozone-layer-achieves-significant-milestone/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre raises alarm over Undemarcated Protected Forests in Chhattisgarh</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/alarm-over-undemarcated-protected-forests/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Undemarcated Protected Forests</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Union Ministry of Environment, Forest and Climate Change has objected to the transfer of thousands of hectares of land without following due process by Chhattisgarh from its Forest to the Revenue Department for setting up industries and for building road, rail, and other infrastructure.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Union Environment Ministry has warned that the land in question is “undemarcated protected forests”, which cannot be used for non-forest purposes without clearance under the Forest Conservation (FC) Act, 1980.</li>
</ul>
<h4>‘Types of Forests’ in Law</h4>
<ul>
<li>Broadly, state Forest Departments have jurisdiction over two types of forests notified under the Indian Forest (IF) Act, 1927:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Reserve Forests (RF):</strong> where no rights are allowed unless specified and</li>
<li><strong>Protected Forests (PF):</strong> where no rights are barred unless specified</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Certain forests, such as <strong><u>village or nagarpalika forests</u></strong>, are managed by state Revenue Departments.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>FC Act, 1980, applies to all kinds of forests</u></strong>, whether under the control of the Forest or the Revenue Department.</li>
<li>It requires <strong><u>statutory clearance before forests can be used</u></strong> for any non-forest purpose such as industry, mining, or construction.</li>
<li>In 1976, <strong><u>forests were included in List III (Concurrent List)</u></strong> under the Seventh Schedule of the Constitution.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Chhattisgarh case</h4>
<ul>
<li>The recorded forest area in Chhattisgarh covers 44.21% of its geography.</li>
<li>The state government says it is constrained by the limited availability of land, particularly in the tribal regions, for development works.</li>
<li>Therefore, in May 2021, it sought a field survey to identify non-forest land — parcels smaller than 10 hectares with less than 200 trees per hectare.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Orange, a grey area</h4>
<ul>
<li>It sought that the forests had been included by mistake in Orange Areas under the Forest Department.</li>
<li>This year, it announced that over 300 sq km of “Orange” area in the Bastar region had been handed over to the Revenue Department.</li>
<li>Under the zamindari system, villagers used local malguzari (livelihood concessions) forests for firewood, grazing, etc.</li>
<li>When zamindari was abolished in 1951, malguzari forests came under the Revenue Department.</li>
<li>In 1958, the government of undivided Madhya Pradesh notified all these areas as Protected Forest (PFs) under the Forest Department.</li>
<li>Through the 1960s, ground surveys and demarcations of these PFs continued — either to form blocks of suitable patches to be declared as Reserve Forests, or to denotify and return to the Revenue Department.</li>
<li>For this purpose, Madhya Pradesh amended the IF Act, 1927, in 1965 — when forests figured in the State List — to allow denotification of PFs.</li>
<li>The areas yet to be surveyed — undemarcated PFs — were marked in orange on the map.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Policy jam</h4>
<ul>
<li>Since 2003, a case has been pending in the Supreme Court on rationalising these orange areas that have remained a bone of contention between the two Departments.</li>
<li>The transfer of PFs to the Revenue Department continued until 1976, when reports of illicit felling in Revenue areas prompted Madhya Pradesh to seek a fresh survey to shift quality forest patches.</li>
<li>But before this survey could be undertaken, the new government that came to power in the state in 1978 switched the focus to settling encroachments.</li>
<li>The FC Act came in 1980, and required central clearance for non-forest use of forest land.</li>
<li>This led to a situation where the rights of lakhs of villagers, including those settled by the government through pattas, remained restricted.</li>
</ul>
<h4>After MP was split</h4>
<ul>
<li>Carved out of Madhya Pradesh in 2000, Chhattisgarh inherited its share of ‘orange’ areas.</li>
<li>Ranked second after Orissa in implementing the Forest Rights Act, 2006, the state has settled over 26,000 claims since 2019.</li>
<li>The logical next step, say officials who declined to be quoted, was to find land for the economic development of the tribal belt.</li>
<li>Chhattisgarh did not seek central clearance to transfer over 300 sq km to Revenue, they claim, because it did not have to.</li>
</ul>
<h4>New definition of forests</h4>
<ul>
<li>In December 1996, the SC defined ‘forest’ after its dictionary meaning, irrespective of the status of the land it stands on.</li>
<li>It also defined forestland as any land thus notified on any government record irrespective of what actually stands on that land.</li>
<li>To meet this broad definition, Madhya Pradesh in 1997 framed a “practical yardstick” — an area no smaller than 10 hectares with at least 200 trees per hectare — to identify forests in Revenue areas for handing over to the Forest Department.</li>
<li>These non-forest areas, they claim, are now being identified and returned to the Revenue.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with such Un-forestation</h4>
<ul>
<li>The nature of vegetation changes over time.</li>
<li>After so many years, a visual survey cannot determine if a particular piece of land did not meet the definition of forest.</li>
<li>Once brought under the Forest Department, whether mistakenly or otherwise, an area gets the status of forestland as per the 1996 SC order, and hence comes under the FC Act, 1980.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Options available for CG</h4>
<ul>
<li>Chhattisgarh, thanks to the 1965 amendment to the IF Act, can still denotify PFs unilaterally.</li>
<li>It may also vest management of any land with any department since the state owns all land within its boundaries.</li>
<li>But if the stated purpose is non-forest use — building industries and infrastructure — the state will anyway require central clearance under the FC Act, 1980.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What lies ahead?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Clearance for non-forest use of forestland under the FC Act requires giving back twice the area for compensatory afforestation (CA) from Revenue to Forest.</li>
<li>That would defeat the very purpose of the state government’s action.</li>
<li>However, conversion of Forest to Revenue land has been exempted from CA under exceptional circumstances in the past.</li>
<li>For example, when enclaves were moved out of forests, the SC allowed those to be resettled at the edge of the forests, in the absence of suitable Revenue land, as revenue villages.</li>
<li>It will be a stretch, though, for such considerations to apply to thousands of hectares meant for industries.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/alarm-over-undemarcated-protected-forests/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Green finance for green future</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/green-finance/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Network for Greening the Financial System</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>green future ,green finance</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="green finance " class="alignnone wp-image-626762" height="454" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 682px) 100vw, 682px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/d9e58a08ed54835e9a92fc788385f6cc247f2359-1657283519-41cf5979-1920x1280-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/d9e58a08ed54835e9a92fc788385f6cc247f2359-1657283519-41cf5979-1920x1280-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/d9e58a08ed54835e9a92fc788385f6cc247f2359-1657283519-41cf5979-1920x1280-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/d9e58a08ed54835e9a92fc788385f6cc247f2359-1657283519-41cf5979-1920x1280-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/d9e58a08ed54835e9a92fc788385f6cc247f2359-1657283519-41cf5979-1920x1280-1.jpg 1200w" width="682"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Inclusion of climate change and green finance in policy is crucial for a strong economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/the-term-green-finance-has-gained-a-lot-of-attention-in-the-past-few-years-with-the-increased-focus-on-greed-development-why-the-green-finance-is-an-ambiguous-tern-and-what-are-the/"><strong>What is green finance?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Green finance is a phenomenon that combines the world of finance and business with environment friendly behaviour. It may be led by financial incentives, a desire to preserve the planet, or a combination of both.</li>
<li>In addition to demonstrating proactive, environment friendly behaviour, such as promoting of any business or activity that could be damaging to the environment now or for future generations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Green finance instruments        </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dedicated fund: </strong>A “green super fund” could be established to jumpstart green investments by pooling together international and domestic capital.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/green-bonds-digital-currency-hold-promise/"><strong>Sovereign green bond (SGB): </strong></a>The sovereign green bond is a novel idea. It will be a part of the government’s borrowing programme. The gross borrowing programme of the government is pegged at Rs 14.95 lakh crore. The SGB (sovereign green bond) raised will be part of the aggregate borrowing programme and has to be used for projects which are ESG (environment, social and governance) compliant.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="green finance" class="alignnone wp-image-626764" height="355" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 612px) 100vw, 612px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Green-financing-01-300x174.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Green-financing-01-300x174.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Green-financing-01-768x446.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Green-financing-01.jpg 840w" width="612"/>Network for Greening the Financial System</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Network for Greening the Financial System is a network of 114 central banks and financial supervisors that aims to accelerate the scaling up of green finance and develop recommendations for central banks’ role for climate change.</li>
<li>The NGFS was created in 2017 and its secretariat is hosted by the Banque de France.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Purpose</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Network’s purpose is to help strengthening the global response required to meet the goals of the Paris agreement and to enhance the role of the financial system to manage risks and to mobilize capital for green and low carbon investments in the broader context of environmentally sustainable development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="green finance" class="alignnone wp-image-626765" height="279" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1395268786138-300x142.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1395268786138-300x142.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1395268786138.jpg 750w" width="590"/>Significance </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Green goals</strong>: Reaching net-zero emissions and other climate-related and environmental goals will require significant investments to enable decarbonisation and innovation across all sectors of the economy. Greening the financial system is key to making these investments happen.</li>
<li><strong>SDG goals: </strong>Green finance initiatives also aim to achieve the 2030 Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs), shifting the focus from creating value for shareholders (economic) to creating value for stakeholders (economic, environmental, and social).</li>
<li><strong>Green future: </strong>And as we begin to recover from the pandemic, green finance presents a huge opportunity to build back with a greener future, creating new businesses and jobs.</li>
<li><strong>Robust growth: </strong>Supports strong and green growth in all sectors of economy .</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The issues in mobilization and effective use of green finance are</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low incentives</strong>: The return on green finance is long term, low in monetary value &amp; many times intangible, so that the ability of the financial system to mobilize private green finance, especially in developed countries is difficult.</li>
<li><strong>Distribution challenge</strong>: Developing countries like India have challenges of development &amp; poverty alleviation, so allocation of resources towards meeting fundamental needs &amp; promoting the green projects which require heavy investment is a challenge.</li>
<li><strong>Skewed investment</strong>: In many countries, green finance &amp; much of the green projects are limited to the investment in renewable energy: India whose 60% of installed capacity is coal based, greening of coal technology is required which is mostly limited to private players in developed countries. It is subjected to IPR &amp; makes them cost prohibitory.</li>
<li><strong>High risk</strong>: Green bonds are perceived as new and attach higher risk and their tenure is also shorter. There is a need to reduce risks to makes them investment grade.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Our future depends on how we resolve our environmental challenges. Further, we are the world’s third-largest carbon emitter and will play a crucial role in getting the planet to a low-carbon trajectory. Simply put, we must urgently transform our economy to get to the green frontier.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. As the world copes with the repercussions of carbon emissions, there is growing pressure to achieve climate-compatible growth. In this context What do you understand by the term green finance? Discuss how it will help to achieve climate-compatible growth along with limitations of green finance.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/green-finance/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Government e-Marketplace (GeM) eyes procurement of ₹2 lakh crore</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/government-e-marketplace-gem-eyes-procurement-of-%e2%82%b92-lakh-crore/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Government e-Marketplace</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-626761" height="150" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gem-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gem-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gem-1024x512.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gem-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gem.jpg 1200w" width="300"/></p>
<p>Government e-Marketplace (GeM), a national procurement portal, is eyeing annual procurement worth ₹2 lakh crore during FY23. Such a huge amount it is!</p>
<h4>Government e-Marketplace</h4>
<ul>
<li>GeM is an online platform for public procurement in India by various Government Departments / Organizations / PSUs.</li>
<li>The initiative was launched on August 9, 2016 by the Ministry of Commerce and Industry with the objective to create an open and transparent procurement platform for government buyers.</li>
<li>It is owned by GeM SPV (Special Purpose Vehicle) which is a 100 per cent Government-owned, non-profit company under the Ministry of Commerce and Industries</li>
<li>GeM aims to enhance transparency, efficiency and speed in public procurement.</li>
<li>It provides the tools of e-bidding, reverse e-auction and demand aggregation to facilitate the government users achieve the best value for their money.</li>
<li>The purchases through GeM by Government users have been authorized and made mandatory by Ministry of Finance.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong><em>Note:</em></strong><em> The government has made it mandatory for sellers on the Government e-Marketplace (GeM) portal to clarify the country of origin of their goods when registering new products.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4>Advantages for Buyers</h4>
<ul>
<li>Offers rich listing of products for individual categories of Goods/Services</li>
<li>Makes available search, compare, select and buy facility</li>
<li>Enables buying Goods and Services online, as and when required.</li>
<li>Provides transparency and ease of buying</li>
<li>Ensures continuous vendor rating system</li>
<li>Up-to-date user-friendly dashboard for buying, monitoring supplies and payments</li>
<li>Provision of easy return policy</li>
</ul>
<h4>Advantages for Sellers</h4>
<ul>
<li>Direct access to all Government departments.</li>
<li>One-stop shop for marketing with minimal efforts</li>
<li>One-stop shop for bids / reverse auction on products / services</li>
<li>New Product Suggestion facility available to Sellers</li>
<li>Dynamic pricing: Price can be changed based on market conditions</li>
<li>Seller friendly dashboard for selling, and monitoring of supplies and payments</li>
<li>Consistent and uniform purchase procedures</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/government-e-marketplace-gem-eyes-procurement-of-%e2%82%b92-lakh-crore/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Nepal postponed Gorkhas’ recruitment under the Agnipath scheme?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-nepal-postponed-gorkha-recruitment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Gorkha regiment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Indian Army</p></div></div><p>Nepal has postponed the recruitment rallies which were to be held in that country to recruit Gorkha soldiers for the Indian Army under the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-mudda-aapka-agnipath-scheme/">Agnipath scheme</a>.</p>
<h4>Why has Nepal postponed Agnipath recruitment rallies?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Nepal is of the opinion that this new form of entry into the Indian military is not covered under the Tripartite Agreement signed between Nepal, Indian and UK governments in 1947, soon after Indian independence.</li>
<li>The government feels that the Agnipath scheme must be approved by it and for that political consultations with all parties in Nepal must take place.</li>
<li>This is move is visibly ‘inspired’ with inputs from China.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What was the Tripartite Agreement between India, Nepal and UK?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Soon after Indian Independence on August 15, 1947, an agreement was reached by the governments of India, Nepal and the UK <strong><u>regarding the future of the Gorkha soldiers</u></strong> who were serving in the Indian Army.</li>
<li>As per the terms of this agreement four regiments of Gorkha soldiers – 2nd, 6th, 7th and 10th – were transferred to the British Army while the rest – 1st, 3rd, 4th, 5th, 8th and 9th – remained with the Indian Army.</li>
<li>A new Gorkha Regiment, the 11th Gorkha Rifles, was raised by India soon after Independence.</li>
<li>The agreement also provides for the terms and conditions of the <strong><u>Nepal-domiciled Gorkha soldiers in the Indian Army</u></strong> and for their post-retirement benefits and pensions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of Gorkha Soldiers</h4>
<ul>
<li>Legend has it that Hitler’s very words were, “If I had Gurkhas, no army in the world could defeat me.”</li>
<li>An interesting historical aspect of Gorkha troops is that Pakistan, at the time of Independence, and China, soon after the 1962 war, had also requested Nepal for Gorkha soldiers.</li>
<li>However, this request was turned down by the Nepal government.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>largest body of Gorkha troops serves in the Indian Army</u></strong> while in the UK their presence has been reduced from four regiments to just two.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Can Nepalese Gorkhas in foreign Armies be called mercenaries?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Mercenaries are understood as fighters who take part in a conflict for financial gain and usually are not parties to that conflict.</li>
<li>As per the definition of the 1949 Geneva Convention, gives the officially agreed definition of a mercenary.</li>
<li>It says that <strong><u>soldiers serving in sovereign armies are not considered mercenaries</u></strong>, and Gorkha soldiers cannot be called mercenaries.</li>
<li>In addition, Gorkha soldiers from Nepal serve side-by-side with Gorkha soldiers who are born and brought up in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Have any changes been made in Gorkha unit recruitments over the years?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There have been attempts to reduce the dependence on Nepal for the Gorkha soldiers in the Indian Army,</li>
<li>To this effect, the composition has increasingly been attempted to be balanced between Indian and Nepal-domiciled troops.</li>
<li>Also, a pure Indian Gorkha battalion was raised in 2016.</li>
<li>This unit, 6th Battalion of the 1st Gorkha Rifles (6/1 GR), was raised in Subathu, in Himachal Pradesh.</li>
<li>Otherwise, the ratio of Nepalese-domiciled soldiers and Indian-domiciled soldiers in a Gorkha battalion ranges from 60:40 to 70:30, though this will change further in future.</li>
<li>A change was made in the recruitment rules for Gorkha Rifles recently when the Army decided that soldiers hailing from the Kumaon and Garhwal regions of Uttarakhand will also be eligible for serving in Gorkha Rifles.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the socio-economic impact on Nepal of Gorkha soldiers serving in the Indian Army?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A major economic and social impact is felt in Nepal due to the Nepal-domiciled Gorkha soldiers serving in the Indian Army and much of it has to do with the remittances that they send home.</li>
<li>Kathmandu receives a <strong><u>sustainable source of remittances from Gorkhas</u></strong> working in foreign armies.</li>
<li>This has significantly contributed to social modernization in the isolated villages, while the financial remittances spurred entrepreneurship development thereby contributing to regional development.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why induct Gorkha soldiers?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Gorkha soldiers are tough. Living in the hills of Nepal makes them <strong><u>strong and resilient</u></strong> and they can stand war, climate and terrain better than most.</li>
<li>No one can match their <strong><u>swift movement in the mountainous terrain</u></strong>.</li>
<li>They are <strong><u>cheerful in disposition</u></strong> and nothing disturbs their equanimity.</li>
<li>They are <strong><u>loyal to the core</u></strong> and fearless in battle.</li>
<li>All this makes them amongst the <strong><u>best soldiers in the world</u></strong> and they are much sought after.</li>
<li>Historically, they have <strong><u>deep rooted connection and affinity for India</u></strong> definitely due to cultural assimilations.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-nepal-postponed-gorkha-recruitment/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>INS Vikrant: All about India’s first indigenous aircraft carrier</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ins-vikrant-indias-first-indigenous-aircraft-carrier/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>INS Vikrant</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Indian navy modernization</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-626759" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 633px) 100vw, 633px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ins-vikrant-300x184.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ins-vikrant-300x184.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ins-vikrant-768x471.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ins-vikrant.jpg 887w" width="633"/></p>
<p>The nation’s first Indigenous Aircraft Carrier (IAC-1) , INS Vikrant is set to be commissioned on September 2, the Indian Navy has announced.</p>
<h4>About INS Vikrant</h4>
<ul>
<li>The name ‘INS Vikrant’ originally belonged to India’s much-loved first aircraft carrier, a source of immense national pride over several decades of service before it was decommissioned in 1997.</li>
<li>The original ‘Vikrant’, a Majestic-class 19,500-tonne warship, which was acquired from the UK in 1961, played a <strong><u>stellar role in the 1971 War with Pakistan</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The IAC-1 is 262 m long and 62 m wide ‘Vikrant’ displaces approximately 43,000 tonnes when fully loaded, and has a maximum designed speed of 28 knots (about 52 km/h) with an endurance of 7500 NM.</li>
<li>It has around 2,200 compartments designed for a crew of around 1,600, including specialised cabins to accommodate women officers and sailors.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is it important for India to have an aircraft carrier?</h4>
<ul>
<li>An aircraft carrier is one of the <strong><u>most potent marine assets</u></strong> for any nation.</li>
<li>It enhances a Navy’s capability to travel far from its home shores to carry out air <strong><u>domination operations</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Having an aircraft carrier as essential to be considered a “blue water” navy — that is, a navy that has the capacity to <strong><u>project a nation’s strength and power across the high seas</u></strong>.</li>
<li>An aircraft carrier generally <strong><u>leads as the capital ship of a carrier strike/ battle group</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is it a big deal that this warship has been Made in India?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Only five or six nations currently have the capability</u></strong> of manufacturing an aircraft carrier, and India has joined this prestigious club now.</li>
<li>India has <strong><u>demonstrated the capacity and self-reliance</u></strong> to build what is considered to be one of the most advanced and complex battleships in the world.</li>
<li>India has had aircraft carriers earlier too — but those were built either by the British or the Russians.</li>
<li>The ‘INS Vikramaditya’, which was commissioned in 2013 and which is currently the Navy’s only aircraft carrier, started out as the Soviet-Russian warship ‘Admiral Gorshkov’.</li>
<li>India’s two earlier carriers, the ‘INS Vikrant’ and the ‘INS Viraat’, were originally the British-built ‘HMS Hercules’ and ‘HMS Hermes’.</li>
<li>These two warships were commissioned into the Navy in 1961 and 1987 respectively.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What indigenous components does the new ‘Vikrant’ have?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The indigenous <strong><u>content of the project is approximately 76%</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The warship-grade <strong><u>steel was indigenised</u></strong> through Steel Authority of India Limited (SAIL) in collaboration with Defence Research &amp; Development Laboratory (DRDL).</li>
<li>It includes 23,000 tonnes of steel, 2,500 km of electric cables, 150 km of pipes, and 2,000 valves.</li>
<li>It also includes a wide range of finished products including rigid hull boats, galley equipment, air-conditioning and refrigeration plants, and steering gear.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What weapons and equipment will the new ‘Vikrant’ have?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The new warship can carry up to 34 aircraft, including both fighter jets and helicopters.</li>
<li>It will be capable of operating 30 aircraft including MiG-29K fighter jets, Kamov-31 Air Early Warning Helicopters, MH-60R Seahawk multi-role helicopters, as well as the Advanced Light Helicopters (ALH).</li>
<li>Using a novel aircraft-operation mode known as Short Take Off But Arrested Recovery (STOBAR), the IAC is equipped with a ski-jump for launching aircraft.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What else will be there on the new INS Vikrant?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The carrier is designed with a very high degree of automation for machinery operations, ship navigation and survivability.</li>
<li>The carrier is equipped with the latest state of the art equipment and systems.</li>
<li>It boasts a fully-fledged state of the art medical complex with the latest medical equipment facilities..</li>
</ul>
<h4>Now that India has shown the capability, will it build more carriers?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Since 2015, the Navy has been seeking approval to build a third aircraft carrier for the country, which, if approved, will become India’s second Indigenous Aircraft Carrier (IAC-2).</li>
<li>This proposed carrier, to be named ‘INS Vishal’, is intended to be a giant 65,000-tonne vessel, much bigger than both IAC-1 and the ‘INS Vikramaditya’.</li>
<li>The Navy has been trying to convince the government of the “operational necessity” of having a third carrier.</li>
<li>Also, it is argued that now that India has developed the capability to build such vessels, it should not be whittled away.</li>
<li>The expertise gained by the Navy and the country over the past 60 years in the art of maritime aviation should not be wasted either.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of the induction</h4>
<ul>
<li>Vikrant is the largest warship to have ever been built in India, and the <strong><u>first indigenously designed and built</u></strong> aircraft carrier for the Indian Navy.</li>
<li>It puts India in an <strong><u>elite club of nations</u></strong> that have the capability to design and build these giant, powerful warships.</li>
<li>The indigenisation efforts led to the <strong><u>development of ancillary industries</u></strong>, and generated employment opportunities for 2,000 CSL personnel and about 13,000 employees in ancillary industries.</li>
<li>This bolstered <strong><u>plough-back effect on the nation’s economy</u></strong>. That is, it pushed all money back that it consumed.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ins-vikrant-indias-first-indigenous-aircraft-carrier/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Three-judge bench to review SC Verdict on Poll Promises</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/three-judge-bench-to-review-sc-verdict-on-poll-promises/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Lofty poll promises and election freebies</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-626758" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 207px) 100vw, 207px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/freebie-207x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/freebie-207x300.jpg 207w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/freebie.jpg 239w" width="207"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has decided to reconsider a 2013 judgment on Poll Promises, which held that promises in the election manifesto do not constitute a “corrupt practice” under the law.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A Bench led by the CJI, Ramana, ordered a three-judge Bench to be set up to review the court’s earlier position.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Subramaniam Balaji Judgment: Invalidating certain Poll Promises</h4>
<ul>
<li>It was held that <strong><u>pre-poll promises made by political parties to entice voters do not fall within the ambit of Section 123 (corrupt practices) under the Representation of the People (RP) Act</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The judgment, delivered by a two-judge Bench, had observed that although the law is obvious that the promises in the election manifesto cannot be construed as ‘corrupt practice’ under Section 123 of RP Act.</li>
<li>The reality cannot be ruled out that distribution of freebies of any kind, undoubtedly, influences all people.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why revisit this judgment?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rationale of the freebie:</strong> Now the CJI has said the three-judge Bench should consider whether an enforceable order can be passed to stop political parties in power from promising and distributing “irrational freebies”.</li>
<li><strong>Freebie vs. Welfare schemes:</strong> He opined that such freebies are completely divorced from actual welfare schemes, using public money in order to merely “capture vote banks”.</li>
<li><strong>Prevent bankruptcy:</strong> Freebies may create a situation wherein the State government cannot provide basic amenities due to lack of funds and the State is pushed towards imminent bankruptcy.</li>
<li><strong>Expert review:</strong> The new Bench would also deliberate if an expert body can be formed to independently study and make recommendations against the distribution of largesse at the cost of the national economy and public welfare.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What amounts to Freebie?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The term Freebies is not new; rather it is a prevalent culture in Indian politics (in the name of socialism).</li>
<li>The political parties are always trying to outdo each other in luring the Indian voters with assorted freebies.</li>
<li>From free water to free smartphones the Indian politicians promise everything to attract prospective voters in favour.</li>
<li>This trend has gained more momentum in the recent times with the political parties being innovative in their offerings as the ‘traditional free water and electricity’ is no longer sufficient as election goodies.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Examples of freebies</h4>
<ol>
<li>Promise of Rs 15 lakh in our bank accounts</li>
<li>Free TV, Laptops</li>
<li>Free electricity</li>
<li>Loan waivers</li>
<li>Offering free public transport ride to all women in Delhi</li>
</ol>
<h4>Why are such policies popular among the public?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Failure of economic policies:</strong> The answer lies in the utter failure of our economic policies to create decent livelihood for a vast majority of Indians.</li>
<li><strong>Quest for decent livelihood:</strong> The already low income had to be reoriented towards spending a disproportionately higher amount on education and health, from which, the state increasingly withdrew.</li>
<li><strong>Prevailing unemployment:</strong>  Employment surveys have shown that employment growth initially slowed down from the 1990s, and then has turned negative over the past few years.</li>
<li><strong>Increased cost of living:</strong> Real income growth of the marginal sections has actually slowed down since 1991 reforms.</li>
<li><strong>Increased consumerism:</strong> The poor today also spend on things which appear to be luxuries; cellphones and data-packs are two such examples which are shown as signs of India’s increased affluence.</li>
<li><strong>Necessity:</strong> For migrant workers, the mobile phone helps them keep in touch with their families back home, or do a quick video-call to see how their infant is learning to sit up or crawl.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Can Freebies be compared with Welfare Politics?</h4>
<ul>
<li>These freebies are not bad. It is a part of social welfare.</li>
<li>Using freebies to lure voters is not good.</li>
<li>Voter’s greediness may lead to a problem in choosing a good leader.</li>
<li>When we don’t have a good leader then democracy will be a mockery.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Impact of such policies</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Never ending trail:</strong> The continuity of freebies is another major disadvantage as parties keep on coming up with lucrative offers to lure more number of votes to minimize the risk of losing in the elections.</li>
<li><strong>Burden on exchequer:</strong> People forget that such benefits are been given at the cost of exchequer and from the tax paid.</li>
<li><strong>Ultimate loss of poors:</strong> The politicians and middlemen wipe away the benefits and the poor have to suffer as they are deprived from their share of benefits which was to be achieved out of the money.</li>
<li><strong>Inflationary practice:</strong> Such distribution freebie commodity largely disrupts demand-supply dynamics.</li>
<li><strong>Lethargy in population:</strong> Freebies actually have the tendency to turn the nation’s population into: Lethargy and devoid of entrepreneurship.</li>
<li><strong>Money becomes only remedy:</strong> Everyone at the slightest sign of distress starts demanding some kind of freebies from the Govt.</li>
<li><strong>Popular politics:</strong> This is psychology driving sections of the population expecting and the government promptly responds with immediate monetary relief or compensation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What cannot be accounted to a freebie?</h4>
<ul>
<li>MGNREGA scheme (rural employment guarantee scheme)</li>
<li>Right to Education (RTE)</li>
<li>Food Security through fair price shops ( under National Food Security Act)</li>
<li>Prime Minister Kisan Samman Yojana (PM-KISAN)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Arguments in favour</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Social investment:</strong> Aid to the poor is seen as a wasteful expenditure. But low interest rates for corporates to get cheap loans or the ‘sop’ of cutting corporate taxes are never criticized.</li>
<li><strong>Socialistic policy:</strong> This attitude comes from decades of operating within the dominant discourse of market capitalism.</li>
<li><strong>Election manifesto:</strong> Proponents of such policies would argue that poll promises are essential for voters to know what the party would do if it comes to power and have the chance to weigh options.</li>
<li><strong>Welfare:</strong> Economists opine that as long as any State has the capacity and ability to finance freebies then its fine; if not then freebies are the burden on economy.</li>
<li><strong>Other wasteful expenditure:</strong> When the Centre gives incentives like free land to big companies and announce multi-year tax holidays, questions are not asked as to where the money will come from.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>There is nothing wrong in having a policy-led elaborate social security programme that seeks to help the poor get out of poverty.</li>
<li>But such a programme needs well thought out preparation and cannot be conjured up just before an election.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="kbw9dvC4Ms"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-election-freebies-politics-and-economy/">[Sansad TV] Mudda Aapla: Culture of Freebies</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="kbw9dvC4Ms" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-election-freebies-politics-and-economy/embed/#?secret=HC6BWj5Fkm#?secret=kbw9dvC4Ms" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Sansad TV] Mudda Aapla: Culture of Freebies” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/three-judge-bench-to-review-sc-verdict-on-poll-promises/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>This is right time to repeal AFSPA</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/afspa/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<h4><strong><img alt="AFSPA" class="alignnone wp-image-626789" height="451" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 541px) 100vw, 541px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA_Protests_Nagaland_16122021_PTI-300x250.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA_Protests_Nagaland_16122021_PTI-300x250.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA_Protests_Nagaland_16122021_PTI-1024x853.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA_Protests_Nagaland_16122021_PTI-768x640.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA_Protests_Nagaland_16122021_PTI-1080x900.jpg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA_Protests_Nagaland_16122021_PTI.jpg 1200w" width="541"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While AFSPA is repealed in 28 districts in Assam, 7 districts in Nagaland and 6 in Manipur, NSF president Kegwayhun Tep said that it should be repealed in all Northeastern states .</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/armed-forces-special-powers-act/"><strong>What is Armed Forces (Special Powers) Act, 1958? </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Armed Forces Special Powers Act, to put it simply, gives armed forces the power to maintain public order in “disturbed areas.”</li>
<li>AFSPA gives armed forces the authority use force or even open fire after giving due warning if they feel a person is in contravention of the law.</li>
<li>The Act further provides that if “reasonable suspicion exists”, the armed forces can also arrest a person without warrant; enter or search premises without a warrant; and ban the possession of firearms.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>AFSPA: A Backgrounder</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AFSPA, 1958 came into force in the context of insurgency in the North-eastern States decades ago.</li>
<li>It provides “special power” to the Armed Forces applies to the Army, the Air Force and the Central Paramilitary forces etc.</li>
<li>It has been long contested debate whether the “special powers” granted under AFSPA gives total immunity to the armed forces for any action taken by them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="AFSPA" class="alignnone wp-image-626785" height="316" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 637px) 100vw, 637px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA-300x149.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA-300x149.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA.jpg 524w" width="637"/>What are the Special Powers?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Power to use force</strong>: including opening fire, even to the extent of causing death if prohibitory orders banning assembly of five or more persons or carrying arms and weapons, etc are in force in the disturbed area;</li>
<li><strong>Power to destroy structures</strong>: used as hide-outs, training camps, or as a place from which attacks are or likely to be launched, etc;</li>
<li><strong>Power to arrest</strong>: without warrant and to use force for the purpose;</li>
<li><strong>Power to enter and search premises</strong>: without a warrant to make arrest or recovery of hostages, arms and ammunition and stolen property etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who can declare/notify such areas?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Central Government or the Governor of the State or administrator of the Union Territory can declare the whole or part of the State or Union Territory as a disturbed area.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="AFSPA" class="alignnone wp-image-626786" height="445" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 543px) 100vw, 543px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/afsrem-300x246.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/afsrem-300x246.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/afsrem.jpg 600w" width="543"/>Issues with AFSPA</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Power to kill: </strong>Section 4 of the Act granted officers the authority to “take any action” even to the extent to cause the death.</li>
<li><strong>Sexual Misconduct by Armed Forces</strong>: The issue of violation of human rights by actions of armed forces came under the consideration of the Committee on Amendments to Criminal Law (popularly known as Justice Verma Committee) set up in 2012. It observed that- in conflict zones, legal protection for women was neglected.</li>
<li><strong>Autocracy</strong>: The reality is that there is no evidence of any action being taken against any officer of the armed forces or paramilitary forces for their excesses.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Recommendations to repeal AFSPA</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Justice B.P. Jeevan Reddy Commission: </strong>The 2004 Committee headed by Justice B.P. Jeevan Reddy, the content of which has never officially been revealed by the Government, recommended that AFSPA be repealed.</li>
<li><strong>ARC II: </strong>The Administrative Reforms Commission in its 5th Report on ‘Public Order’ had also recommended that AFSPA be repealed.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/its-time-to-repeal-afspa/"><strong>Why AFSPA should be repealed?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Human right violations</strong>: The repeal of AFSPA is necessary not just for restoring constitutional sanity, but also as a way of acknowledging dark history of our conduct in Nagaland.</li>
<li><strong>Need for ensuring individual dignity</strong>: The political incorporation of Nagaland (and all other areas where this law applies) will be set back if the guarantees of individual dignity of the Indian Constitution are not extended.</li>
<li><strong>Not state of exception</strong>: We often describe AFSPA in terms of a “state of exception”. But this theoretical term is misleading. How can a law that has been in virtually continuous existence since 1958 be described as an “exception”.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of human empathy</strong>: At the heart of AFSPA is a profound mutilation of human empathy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To bring in lasting peace in the North East, the government needs to avoid the trap of watered-down peace accords. While the move to withdraw AFSPA is welcome, it needs to be gradually erased. For that, changes in the ground situation would be crucial. Mere smoke signals or drum-beating can never do the job.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Do you think AFSPA is license to kill? Critically examine the utility of AFSPA today.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/afspa/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Right to privacy after 5 years</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-privacy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>article 21</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>right to privacy</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="right to privacy" class="alignnone wp-image-626979" height="418" sizes="(max-width: 558px) 100vw, 558px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/data-privacy-example-1024x768-1-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/data-privacy-example-1024x768-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/data-privacy-example-1024x768-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/data-privacy-example-1024x768-1.jpg 1024w" width="558"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Data privacy breaches which result in the loss and theft of personal, sensitive data have not reduced in terms of measurable frequency or their impact.</li>
<li>It has been 5 years since the nine-judge Supreme Court bench delivered the judgment in the Puttaswamy case. It asserted that Indians have a constitutionally protected fundamental right to privacy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/right-to-privacy/#:~:text=Without%20a%20data%20protection%20law,to%20writ%20proceedings%20in%20India."><strong>Right to Privacy can be defined as</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>A right to be let alone;</li>
<li>The right of a person to be free from any unwarranted publicity;</li>
<li>The right to live without any unwarranted interference by the public in matters with which the public is not necessarily concerned.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="right to privacy" class="alignnone wp-image-626980" height="282" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/privacy-10x10-featured-300x197.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/privacy-10x10-featured-300x197.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/privacy-10x10-featured-1024x672.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/privacy-10x10-featured-768x504.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/privacy-10x10-featured-1200x788.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/privacy-10x10-featured.jpg 1280w" width="429"/>Definition of data </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Data is a collection of discrete values that convey information, describing quantity, quality, fact, statistics, other basic units of meaning, or simply sequences of symbols that may be further interpreted.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Data Protection?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Data protection refers to policies and procedures seeking to minimise intrusion into the privacy of an individual caused by collection and usage of their personal data.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is data privacy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Data privacy refers to controlling access to the data. Organizations must determine who has access to data. Understandably, a privacy breach can lead to <a href="https://www.techtarget.com/searchdatamanagement/feature/Top-3-data-privacy-challenges-and-how-to-address-them" rel="noopener" target="_blank">data security issues</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is data security?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Data security refers specifically to measures taken to protect the integrity of the data itself against manipulation and malware. It provides defense from internal and external threats.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why we need data protection?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increasing internet</strong> <strong>use:</strong> India currently has over 750 million Internet users, with the number only expected to increase in the future.</li>
<li><strong>Data breaches: </strong>At the same time, India has among the highest data breaches in the world. Without a data protection law in place, the data of millions of Indians continues to be at risk of being exploited, sold, and misused without their consent.</li>
<li><strong>Individual privacy</strong>: Data monetization may happen at cost of individual privacy. The most sought-after datasets are those that contain sensitive personal data of individuals, ex. medical history, financial data.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="right to privacy" class="alignnone wp-image-626983" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 407px) 100vw, 407px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pega-300x246.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pega-300x246.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pega.jpg 492w" width="407"/><br/>
Issues with the data breaches in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Violation of the right to privacy</strong>: The right to privacy was recognized as a fundamental right, included under the right to life and liberty by the Supreme Court of India in 2017.</li>
<li><strong>Absence of legal framework</strong>: Without a law in place to regulate data collection and to act as an oversight mechanism, valid concerns about privacy and other rights violations continue to arise.</li>
<li><strong>High Infrastructural Costs:</strong> Technologies like Artificial Intelligence and Big Data are costly to implement. The size of stored information is extremely large and requires huge network &amp; data storage facilities, which are currently not available in India.</li>
<li><strong>The concern of Data Leakage</strong>: In today’s world of cybercrime, it is important to put appropriate safeguards in place in order to ensure the integrity of the repository/database, so that it doesn’t leak out the information and is not privatized or monetized.</li>
<li><strong>Reliability &amp; Authenticity</strong>: As the data collected may be used in the court of law during the course of a criminal trial, the reliability and the admissibility of the data along with standards and procedures followed would be taken into consideration. Hence, the authenticity of the data is crucial.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Today, there is a relentless pace of digitisation that relies on gathering personal data in all spheres of our lives. All of this is done in a legal vacuum without any oversight or remedy. This underscores the urgent need for robust data protection law.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.  What do you understand by the term data privacy? Explain how data leakages threatens the sacred right to privacy?</strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-privacy/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>