<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 18:13:56 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Jurisprudence of Bail in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/jurisprudence/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>jurisprudence of bail</p></div></div><h4><strong>What is Bail?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bail is the conditional release of a defendant with the promise to appear in court when required.</li>
<li>The term also means the security that is deposited in order to secure the release of the accused.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Types of Bail in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Depending upon the sage of the criminal matter, there are commonly three types of bail in India:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Regular bail:</strong> A regular bail is generally granted to a person who has been arrested or is in police custody. A bail application can be filed for the regular bail under section 437 and 439 of CrPC.</li>
<li><strong>Interim bail:</strong> This type of bail is granted for a short period of time and it is granted before the hearing for the grant of regular bail or anticipatory bail.</li>
<li><strong>Anticipatory bail:</strong> Anticipatory bail is granted under section 438 of CrPC either by session court or High Court. An application for the grant of anticipatory bail can be filed by the person who discerns that he may be arrested by the police for a non-bailable offense.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Conditions for Grant of Bail in Bailable Offences</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Section 436 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, lays down that a person accused of a bailable offense under IPC can be granted bail if:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>There are sufficient reasons to believe that the accused has not committed the offence.</li>
<li>There is sufficient reason to conduct a further inquiry in the matter.</li>
<li>The person is not accused of any offence punishable with death, life imprisonment or imprisonment up to 10 years.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Conditions for Grant of Bail in Non-Bailable Offences</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Section 437 of Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 lays down that the accused does not have the right to apply for bail in non-bailable offences.</li>
<li>It is discretion of the court to grant bail in case of non-bailable offences if:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>The accused is a woman or a child, bail can be granted in a non-bailable offence.</li>
<li>There is a lack of evidence then bail in non-Bailable offenses can be granted.</li>
<li>There is a delay in lodging FIR by the complainant, bail may be granted.</li>
<li>The accused is gravely sick.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What is the recent ruling about?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court underlined that arrest is a draconian measure that needs to be used sparingly.</li>
<li>The ruling is essentially a reiteration of several crucial principles of criminal procedure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why bail needs reform?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Huge pendency of undertrials:</strong> Referring to the state of jails in the country, where over two-thirds lodged are undertrials,</li>
<li><strong>Indiscriminate</strong> <strong>arrests:</strong> Of this category of prisoners, majority may not even be required to be arrested despite registration of a cognizable offense, being charged with offenses punishable for seven years or less.</li>
<li><strong>Disadvantageous for some sections:</strong> They are not only poor and illiterate but also would include women. Thus, there is a culture of offense being inherited by many of them.</li>
<li><strong>Colonial legacy:</strong> Theoretically, the court also linked the idea of indiscriminate arrests to magistrates ignoring the rule of “bail, not jail” to a colonial mindset.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the law on bail?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>CrPC does not define the word bail</u></strong> but only categories <strong><u>offences under the Indian Penal Code as ‘bailable’ and ‘non-bailable’. </u></strong></li>
<li>The <strong><u>CrPC empowers magistrates to grant bail</u></strong> for bailable offences as a matter of right.</li>
<li>This would involve release on furnishing a <strong><u>bail bond, without or without security</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>And what is the UK law?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Bail Act of the United Kingdom, 1976, prescribes the procedure for granting bail.</li>
<li>A key feature is that one of the aims of the legislation is “<strong><u>reducing the size of the inmate population</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The law also has provisions for ensuring <strong><u>legal aid for defendants</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Act recognises a <strong><u>“general right” to be granted bail</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What has the Supreme Court held on reforms?</strong></h4>
<p>The court’s ruling is in the form of guidelines, and it also draws the line on certain procedural issues for the police and judiciary:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Separate law on Bail:</strong> The court underlined that the CrPC, despite amendments since Independence, largely retains its original structure as drafted by a colonial power over its subjects.</li>
<li><strong>Uniform exercise of discretionary powers:</strong> It also highlighted that magistrates do not necessarily</li>
<li><strong>Avoid indiscriminate arrests:</strong> The SC also directed all state governments and Union Territories to facilitate standing orders to comply with the orders and avoid indiscriminate arrests.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/jurisprudence/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Artemis 1 Mission?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-artemis-1-mission/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of artemis mission</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p>NASA’s Artemis 1 mission has sought unexpected delay due to fuel leakages issue.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the Artemis I Mission?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>NASA’s Artemis mission is touted as the next generation of lunar exploration, and is named after the twin sister of Apollo from Greek mythology.</li>
<li>Artemis is also the goddess of the moon.</li>
<li>Artemis I is the first of NASA’s deep space exploration systems.</li>
<li>It is an uncrewed space mission where the spacecraft will launch on SLS — the most powerful rocket in the world — and travel 2,80,000 miles from the earth for over four to six weeks during the course of the mission.</li>
<li>The Orion spacecraft is going to remain in space without docking to a space station, longer than any ship for astronauts has ever done before.</li>
<li>The SLS rocket has been designed for space missions beyond the low-earth orbit and can carry crew or cargo to the moon and beyond.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Key objectives of the mission</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>With the Artemis Mission, NASA aims to land humans on the moon by 2024, and it also plans to land the first woman and first person of colour on the moon.</li>
<li>With this mission, NASA aims to contribute to scientific discovery and economic benefits and inspire a new generation of explorers.</li>
<li>NASA will establish an Artemis Base Camp on the surface and a gateway in the lunar orbit to aid exploration by robots and astronauts.</li>
<li>The gateway is a critical component of NASA’s sustainable lunar operations and will serve as a multi-purpose outpost orbiting the moon.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other agencies involved</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Other space agencies are also involved in the Artemis programme.</li>
<li>The Canadian Space Agency has committed to providing advanced robotics for the gateway.</li>
<li>The European Space Agency will provide the International Habitat and the ESPRIT module, which will deliver additional communications capabilities among other things.</li>
<li>The Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency plans to contribute habitation components and logistics resupply.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-artemis-1-mission/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Pakistan’s Flip-Flop on Trade with India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pakistans-flip-flop-on-trade-with-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>india pakistan relation</p></div></div><p>Pakistan’s Finance Minister has stated that the government may consider importing vegetables and other edible items from India following the destruction of standing crops due to the massive floods in the region.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>This statement comes after three years when Islamabad downgraded trade ties with New Delhi over the abrogation of Article 370 in Kashmir in 2019.</li>
<li>The fundamentalist country sees ties with India as against the spirit of religion and betrayal to the so-called Kashmir cause.</li>
</ul>
<h4>A U-turn by Pakistan</h4>
<ul>
<li>Pakistan’s double U-turn on resuming trade with India highlights the <strong><u>internal differences</u></strong> within the country.</li>
<li>There are huge differences between business and political communities, and the emphasis on politics over economy and trade.</li>
<li>It also signifies Pakistan cabinet’s grandstanding, linking <strong><u>normalisation of ties with India</u></strong> to Jammu and Kashmir.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Pakistan has sought to import only three items from India, namely cotton, yarn and sugar.</li>
<li>It has no consensus on resuming bilateral trade completely.</li>
<li>This is based on Pakistan’s immediate economic needs and not designed as a political confidence-building measure to normalise relations with India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What changed Pakistan’s mind?</h4>
<p><strong>(1) Decline of Textile sector</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>For the textile and sugar industries in Pakistan, importing from India is imperative, practical and is the most economic.</li>
<li>Yarn, cotton cloth, knitwear, bedwear and readymade garments form the core of Pakistan’s textile basket in the export sector.</li>
<li>By February 2020, there was a steep decline in the textile sector due to disruptions in supply and domestic production.</li>
<li>This is definitely due to dumping of cheap Chinese goods.</li>
<li>When compared to the last fiscal year (2019-20), there has been a 30% decline (2020-21) in cotton production.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong><em>Do you know?</em></strong></p>
<p><em>Pakistan is the fifth-largest exporter of cotton globally, and the cotton-related products (raw and value-added) earn close to half of the country’s foreign exchange.</em></p></blockquote>
<p><strong>(2) Crisis in the sugar industry </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>When compared to cotton, the sugar industry’s problem stem from different issues — the availability for local consumption and the steep price increase.</li>
<li>The sugar industry has prioritised exports over local distribution.</li>
<li>Increased government subsidy and a few related administrative decisions resulted in the sugar industry attempting to make a considerable profit by exporting it.</li>
<li>As a result, importing sugar from India would be cheaper for the consumer market in Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<h4>In a nutshell</h4>
<ul>
<li>Clearly, the crises in cotton and sugar industries played a role in the ECC’s decision to import cotton, yarn and sugar from India.</li>
<li>It would not only be cheaper but also help Pakistan’s exports.</li>
<li>This is also imperative for Pakistan to earn foreign exchange.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why all these have made headlines these days?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Pakistan is closer to bankruptcy like any other Chinese vassal state.</li>
<li>The second takeaway from the two U-turns — is the supremacy of politics over trade and economy, even if the latter is beneficial to the importing country.</li>
<li>For the cabinet, the interests of its own business community and its export potential have become secondary.</li>
<li>However, Pakistan need not be singled out; this is a curse in South Asia, where politics play supreme over trade and economy.</li>
<li>The meagre percentage of intra-South Asian Association for Regional Cooperation (SAARC) trade and the success (or the failure) of SAARC engaging in bilateral or regional trade would underline the above.</li>
<li>Trade is unlikely to triumph over politics in South Asia; especially in India-Pakistan relations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Kashmir link</h4>
<ul>
<li>The third takeaway is the emphasis on Jammu and Kashmir by Pakistan to make any meaningful start in bilateral relations.</li>
<li>This goes against what it has been telling the rest of the world that India should begin dialogue with Pakistan.</li>
<li>Recently, both Pakistan’s PM and the Chief of Army Staff, Qamar Javed Bajwa, were on record stating the need to build peace in the region.</li>
<li>Bajwa even talked about “burying the past” and moving forward.</li>
<li>There were also reports that Pakistan agreeing to re-establish the ceasefire along the Line of Control (LoC) was a part of this new strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>The latest statement by Pakistan’s cabinet that unless India revokes the 2019 decision in Jammu and Kashmir, there would be no forward movement.</li>
<li>This position also hints at Pakistan’s precondition to engage with India.</li>
<li>Pakistan has been saying that the onus is on India to normalise the process.</li>
<li>Perhaps, it is New Delhi’s turn to tell Islamabad that it is willing, but without any preconditions, and start with trade.</li>
<li>It may even allow New Delhi to inform Pakistan’s stakeholders about who is willing to trade and who is reluctant.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pakistans-flip-flop-on-trade-with-india/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumerism should be replaced by minimalism</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/consumerism/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Minimalism as way of life</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Consumerism" class="alignnone wp-image-628237" height="317" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 564px) 100vw, 564px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-4-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-4-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-4-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-4-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-4.jpeg 1200w" width="564"/> </strong><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The COVID-19 pandemic brought shifts in consumer behaviour. The world witnessed a shrinkage of demand. But post-pandemic recovery and suppressed consumerism is now leading to ‘revenge shopping’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is consumerism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Consumerism is a social and economic order that encourages the acquisition of goods and services in ever-increasing amounts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is minimalism? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Minimalism is owning fewer possessions. It is intentionally living with only the things we really need those items that support our purpose. Removing the distraction of excess possessions to focus more on those things that matter most.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Consumerism" class="alignnone wp-image-628238" height="378" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 568px) 100vw, 568px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1_v7Cd5DWFYjk-ri5aQCBgWg-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1_v7Cd5DWFYjk-ri5aQCBgWg-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1_v7Cd5DWFYjk-ri5aQCBgWg-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1_v7Cd5DWFYjk-ri5aQCBgWg.jpeg 960w" width="568"/>What Is Revenge Shopping?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Revenge shopping occurs when a customer who previously could not get access to certain goods or services for a period of time suddenly has access. It can also occur when customers have been deprived of other events or happenings.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Consumerism" class="alignnone wp-image-628239" height="209" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 392px) 100vw, 392px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0_MFfVpt4oTb-3Pq1T-300x160.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0_MFfVpt4oTb-3Pq1T-300x160.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0_MFfVpt4oTb-3Pq1T-1024x547.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0_MFfVpt4oTb-3Pq1T-768x410.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0_MFfVpt4oTb-3Pq1T-1200x641.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0_MFfVpt4oTb-3Pq1T.jpg 1400w" width="392"/>The symptoms of excessive consumerism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>You buy more than you planned</strong>: if you set out with a plan of what you need to purchase but consistently come back with more than you anticipated, then you’re falling in the consumerist trap.</li>
<li><strong>You run out of storage space for your stuff</strong>: sometimes it can’t be helped if you live in a tight area or you’re disorganised. But suppose you’re in a reasonable situation and things you bring in don’t have an allocated home. In that case, you’re likely living excessively.</li>
<li><strong>You rely too much on return policies</strong>: returning an item is useful. Particularly if you need to test a product for the intended purpose, be it sizing for clothes or a tool for a building project. However, suppose you’re depending on returns for purchases. In that instance, you’re not sure you need it, or if you can’t afford it, then you’re probably suffering from too much consumerism.</li>
<li><strong>You routinely seek approval for your purchases</strong>: getting feedback on purchases can be reassuring, especially if you’re indecisive. Yet, there’s a difference between picking someone’s brain before buying and looking to justify your purchase after the fact. If you’re seeking post-acquisition approval, you probably don’t need the item.</li>
<li><strong>You mistakenly buy things you already have</strong>: not much to say here. If you’re getting things only to realise you already have it, then you’re probably deep in a consumerist cycle.</li>
<li><strong>You buy things on credit</strong>: if you’re strategic and disciplined, you can buy things on credit cards to acquire points and benefits. However, if you’re like the majority of us, then you’re vulnerable to buying things you can’t afford.</li>
<li><strong>You constantly go over your budget</strong>: sometimes, you miss-forecast how much you need to spend each month. But if you set a realistic budget and find that you’re still going over, then you’re probably consuming excessively.</li>
<li><strong>You regret your purchases</strong>: the most obvious sign that you have a shopping habit is you regret things you bought. Buyer’s remorse is an overwhelming feeling and one we want to avoid.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Consumerism" class="alignnone wp-image-628240" height="274" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 390px) 100vw, 390px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/consumerism-titlea-300x211.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/consumerism-titlea-300x211.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/consumerism-titlea.jpg 560w" width="390"/>Negatives of consumerism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Causes more pollution:</strong> Consumerism as a system can have devastating effects on the environment.</li>
<li><strong>A major contributor to resource depletion: </strong>The second main negative of consumerism is resource depletion.  Simply put, resource depletion refers to the idea that human beings are using up the resources on the earth as an ever increasing rate such that we will ‘deplete’ or completely use up some resources.</li>
<li><strong>Leads companies to develop low quality products: </strong>Modern companies practice a technique called ‘planned obsolescence’. In general, planned obsolescence is best understood as products that are designed to fail. Modern companies do this to encourage consumers to repurchase a product over and over again.</li>
<li><strong>Does not necessarily lead to increased happiness beyond a certain point:</strong> The main negative aspect of consumerism is that it does not necessarily lead to higher levels of happiness for people.</li>
<li><strong>Global inequality: </strong>The huge rise in resource consumption in wealthier countries has led to an ever widening gap between the rich and the poor. As the age old saying goes, “the rich get richer and the poor get poorer.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can we do?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Extend the lifespan of your things</strong>: Repairing your things is not only an effective way to reduce your consumption, but it’s also beneficial to the environment.</li>
<li><strong>Reframe shopping as a skill: </strong>When you focus on the role the thing you’re buying will play in the overall experience instead of the experience of shopping itself, you’ll be able to shift away from a consumerist mind-set.</li>
<li><strong>Do the deathbed test: </strong>Not to get too dark, but if you were hypothetically on your deathbed today, and you were reflecting on your life, what would be your fondest memories? The quality of our lives is generally measured by moments of “that was a good time”, not “that thing I had was awesome”.</li>
<li><strong>Borrow or rent instead of buy: </strong>A simple method for getting your consumerism under control is to rent or borrow items instead of buying them.</li>
<li><strong>Practice minimalism</strong>: What’s the ultimate alternative to consumerism? Minimalism. A minimalist is someone who naturally rejects consumerism and sees value in having fewer things over more things. Minimalism is a powerful philosophy that impacts how you view material things, your relationships, commitments, and digital inventory.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The M.K. Gandhi once said: “The Earth provides-enough to satisfy everyone’s needs but not any one’s greed<strong>.”</strong> We shall find that Gandhian call to curtailment of wants is relevant in the rapidly depleting natural resources, bio-diversity and eco-system and its contemporary relevance</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you understand by the term consumerism? Discuss importance of minimalism as there is rise in revenge shopping in post covid19 era.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/consumerism/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Economic cooperation with Sri Lanka for deeper engagement</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sri-lanka/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>hambantota, trinconmalee projects</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>indo srilanka bilateral relations</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Sri lanka" class="alignnone wp-image-628265" height="364" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 549px) 100vw, 549px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5a11cf34251744cc40cc58d5f9333e4c-300x199.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5a11cf34251744cc40cc58d5f9333e4c-300x199.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5a11cf34251744cc40cc58d5f9333e4c.jpg 750w" width="549"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The present economic crisis in Sri Lanka has pushed it closer to India for immediate relief.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Economic cooperation with Sri Lanka</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India is Sri Lanka’s third-largest export destination, after the US and UK.</li>
<li>More than 60% of Sri Lanka’s exports enjoy the benefits of the India-Sri Lanka Free Trade Agreement, which came into effect in March 2000.</li>
<li>Concessional financing of about $ 2 billion has been provided to Sri Lanka through various Indian government-supported Lines of Credit across sectors like railways, infrastructure and security.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-india-sri-lanka-relations/"><strong>How India has helped to boost Sri Lanka’s economy</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Grants</strong>: The overall commitment by GOI is to the tune of more than USD 3.5 billion. Demand-driven and people-centric nature of India’s development partnership with Sri Lanka have been the cornerstone of this relationship.</li>
<li><strong>The Indian Housing Project</strong>: India has so far committed to construct close to 62,500 houses in Sri Lanka, making it one of the largest projects undertaken by GoI abroad.</li>
<li><strong>Other Projects</strong>: India is also involved in projects for renovation of Palaly Airport, Kankesanthurai Harbor, construction of a Cultural Centre in Jaffna, interconnection of electricity grids between the two countries, construction of a 150-bed hospital in Dickoya and setting up a coal power plant in Sampur as a joint venture between National Thermal Power Corporation (NTPC) and Ceylon Electricity Board (CEB).</li>
<li><strong>Latest Development</strong>: India-SL agreed for joint development of Trincomalee Oil Tank farmed in 2022 after 35 years of wait.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="sri lanka" class="alignnone wp-image-628266" height="275" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 471px) 100vw, 471px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/30-A-protest-at-the-entrance-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/30-A-protest-at-the-entrance-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/30-A-protest-at-the-entrance.jpg 760w" width="471"/>Opportunities for India for deeper engagement</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dairy sector: </strong>Sri Lanka imports a considerable quantity of milk powder. On average, Colombo annually imports dairy products worth $315 million. . India can help Sri Lanka develop its dairy sector.</li>
<li><strong>Poultry sector:</strong> In this area, through its host of agricultural universities, India can share its knowledge on ways to increase both production and productivity.</li>
<li><strong>Energy sector:</strong> Considering how the problem on the energy front exploded into a major political crisis in Sri Lanka, India’s participation in energy projects will be desirable.</li>
<li><strong>Education sector:</strong> School education is another area where India’s presence could be more felt. India can expand its scheme of establishing smart classrooms and modern computer labs to cover all those institutions teaching children of hill country Tamils, the most underprivileged section in society.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="sri lanka" class="alignnone wp-image-628267" height="338" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 485px) 100vw, 485px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1658817828-22-300x209.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1658817828-22-300x209.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1658817828-22.jpg 650w" width="485"/>Challenges</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Possibility of greater economic collaboration</strong>: Whether this bonhomie can lead to greater economic collaboration between Sri Lanka and south India, not necessarily Tamil Nadu alone, given the historical baggage, is anybody’s guess.</li>
<li><strong>Baggage of history</strong>: Some sections of the Sinhalese still hold the view that India had been a threat to them and it can still be a threat to them.</li>
<li><strong>Modest investment in development</strong>: Despite India’s open willingness to take part in the development of Sri Lanka after the civil war, the scale of its involvement has been modest.</li>
<li><strong>Incomplete projects due to lack of political will</strong>: After the cancellation of the tripartite agreement, India was later provided with projects such as the West Container Terminal, the Trincomalee oil tank farm and a couple of renewable projects, there were several proposals that envisaged India’s participation but did not see the light of day.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Infrastructure development:</strong> Even now, there is enormous scope for collaboration between the two countries in the area of infrastructure development.</li>
<li><strong>Cross-border energy trade</strong>: The economic crisis has revived talk of linking Sri Lanka’s electricity grid with that of India.</li>
<li><strong>Facilitating people-to-people interaction</strong>: The apprehension in the minds of sections of the Sinhalese majority about India being a threat can be dispelled only by facilitating greater people-to-people interaction, including pilgrimages by monks and other sections of  society to places of Buddhist importance not only in north India but also in the south (Andhra Pradesh).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Given the history of bilateral ties, instances such as the Hambantota controversy are bound to arise. But what should not be glossed over is that a politically and economically stable Sri Lanka will be in India’s interest too.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question  </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. There is no such thing as charity in international politics. Critically analyse this statement showing how India can reap benefits of economic cooperation with Sri Lanka.</strong></p>
<p> </p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sri-lanka/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>PARAKH: A new regulator for ‘uniformity’ in all board exams</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/parakh-a-new-regulator-for-uniformity-in-all-board-exams/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PARAKH</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Harmonization of school education in India</p></div></div><p>The Centre is planning to draw up a benchmark framework ‘PARAKH’ to assess students at the secondary and higher secondary level to bring about “uniformity” across state and central boards.</p>
<h4>What is PARAKH?</h4>
<ul>
<li>PARAKH stands for Performance Assessment, Review and Analysis of Knowledge for Holistic Development.</li>
<li>The proposed regulator will act as a constituent unit of the NCERT.</li>
<li>It will also be tasked with holding periodic learning outcome tests like the National Achievement Survey (NAS) and State Achievement Surveys.</li>
<li>The benchmark assessment framework will seek to put an end to the emphasis on rote learning, as envisaged by the National Education Policy (NEP) 2020.</li>
<li>PARAKH, the proposed implementing agency, is also part of the NEP proposal.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Response form States</h4>
<ul>
<li>Most <strong><u>states endorsed the proposal</u></strong> to hold board exams twice a year, including one for helping students improve their scores.</li>
<li>States are also on board regarding a proposal to offer two types of papers on mathematics — a standard exam, and another to test higher level competency.</li>
<li>It will help reduce the fear of maths among students and encourage learning.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of PARAKH</h4>
<ul>
<li>PARAKH will help tackle the problem of students of some state boards being at a disadvantage during college admissions as compared to their peers in CBSE schools.</li>
<li>It will develop and implement “technical standards for the design, conduct, analysis and reporting” of tests at all levels of school education.</li>
<li>PARAKH will eventually become the national single-window source for all assessment related information and expertise, with a mandate to support learning assessment in all forms, both nationally and where applicable, internationally.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/parakh-a-new-regulator-for-uniformity-in-all-board-exams/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>NCRB releases ‘Crime in India’ Report</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ncrb-releases-crime-in-india-report/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NCRB</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Crime in India</p></div></div><p>A new edition of ‘Crime in India’, the annual report of the National Crime Records Bureau (NCRB), was released on August 29, for crime-related statistics in 2021.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>NCRB reports have been a valuable compilation of statistics over the years on offences ranging from crimes against women to economic and financial crimes.</li>
<li>It has provided honest and credible sets of crime related data in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Crime in India: Key highlights</h4>
<ul>
<li>Overall, 2021 saw a <strong><u>6 per cent decline in the number of crimes registered</u></strong>, as compared to 2020.</li>
<li>The crime rate per lakh population declined from 487.8 in 2020 to 445.9 in 2021.</li>
<li>However, crime statistics do not always tell the full story, and <strong><u>lower crimes reported in an area do not necessarily mean it is safe.</u></strong></li>
<li><strong><u>Crimes against women rose 15 per cent</u></strong> in India in 2021 and Delhi is the most unsafe metropolitan city.</li>
<li>Rajasthan reported the highest number of rape cases and Maharashtra topped the list when it comes to most suicides.</li>
<li>Around 1<strong><u>.73 lakh people died in traffic accidents</u></strong>. Uttar Pradesh saw the highest number of deaths (24,711) in traffic accidents.</li>
<li>Jammu and Kashmir registered the most <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/unlawful-activities-prevention-act-uapa/"><strong>Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act (UAPA)</strong></a> cases under the ‘special and local laws’ in 2021, as per NCRB data.</li>
<li>Of the total 814 cases under the UAPA in India, J&amp;K lodged 289 cases last year, followed by Manipur (157), Assam (95), Jharkhand (86) and Uttar Pradesh (83).</li>
<li><strong><u>Jharkhand and Maharashtra filed the highest cases of communal riots</u></strong> last year with 100 and 77 cases respectively.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who publishes the NCRB report?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The NCRB was established in January 1986 with the aim of establishing a body to compile and keep records of data on crime.</li>
<li>It functions under the Union Home Ministry.</li>
<li>Apart from publishing annual reports, its functions include “Collection, coordination and exchange of information on inter-state and international criminals to the respective states”.</li>
<li>NCRB also acts as a “<strong><u>national warehouse” for the fingerprint records</u></strong> of Indian and foreign criminals, and assists in locating interstate criminals through fingerprint search.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How does the NCRB collect information for its report?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The NCRB report contains data received from the 36 states and Union Territories across the country.</li>
<li>Similar data is furnished for 53 metropolitan cities, or those having a population of more than 10 lakh as per the 2011 census, by respective state-level crime records bureaus.</li>
<li>This information is entered by state/UT police at the police station/ district level, and is then validated further at the district level, then the state level, and finally by the NCRB.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with NCRB data</h4>
<ul>
<li>By its own admission, the NCRB says there are limitations to its data.</li>
<li>Since the publication caters to the ‘Principal Offence Rule’ for classification of crime, the actual count of each crime head may go <strong><u>under-reporting</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Principal Offence Rule states that in a case where multiple offences are registered, only the “most heinous crime”, carrying the most stringent punishment, is considered when counting.</li>
<li>For example, ‘<strong><u>Murder with Rape’ is accounted as ‘Murder’</u></strong>, leading to undercounting of the crime of rape.</li>
<li>Vacancies or a <strong><u>shortage of police officers</u></strong> at the local level may hinder the collection of data.</li>
<li>Also the data record the incidence of registered crime rather than of actual crime.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Antithesis to NCRB data</h4>
<ul>
<li>Reported <strong><u>crimes against women in Delhi rose significantly</u></strong> in the aftermath of the 2012 Nirbhaya Gangrape case.</li>
<li>This is not because the heinous crimes got trivialized.</li>
<li>It may have been a <strong><u>reflection of increased awareness about the need for registering crimes</u></strong>, both among those affected and the police, rather than an actual increase in the incidence of crime against women.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ncrb-releases-crime-in-india-report/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>One Nation One Fertiliser (ONOF) Scheme</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/one-nation-one-fertiliser-onof-scheme/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>One Nation One Fertiliser (ONOF)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India's fertilizer subsidy</p></div></div><p>The Ministry of Chemicals and Fertilisers will implement One Nation One Fertiliser (ONOF) by introducing a Single Brand for Fertilisers and Logo under the fertiliser subsidy scheme named “Pradhanmantri Bhartiya Janurvarak Pariyojna” (PMBJP).</p>
<h4>One Nation One Fertiliser (ONOF)</h4>
<ul>
<li>The single brand name for UREA, DAP, MOP and NPK etc. would be BHARAT UREA, BHARAT DAP, BHARAT MOP and BHARAT NPK etc. respectively for all Fertiliser Companies, State Trading Entities (STEs) and Fertiliser Marketing Entities (FMEs).</li>
<li>Also a logo indicating Fertiliser subsidy scheme namely Pradhanmantri Bhartiya Janurvarak Pariyojna will be used on said fertiliser bags.</li>
<li>Under the scheme, companies are allowed to display their name, brand, logo and other relevant product information only on one-third space of their bags.</li>
<li>On the remaining two-thirds space, the “Bharat” brand and Pradhanmantri Bharatiya Jan Urvarak Pariyojana logo will have to be shown.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the government’s argument for introducing this scheme?</h4>
<p>The government’s logic for introducing a <strong><u>single ‘Bharat’ brand</u></strong> for all subsidised fertilisers being marketed by companies is as follows:</p>
<p><strong>(1) Subsidies normalization</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The maximum retail price of urea is currently fixed by the government, which compensates companies for the higher cost of manufacturing or imports incurred by them.</li>
<li>The MRPs of non-urea fertilisers are, on paper, decontrolled.</li>
<li>But companies cannot avail of subsidy if they sell at MRPs higher than that informally indicated by the government.</li>
<li>Simply put, there are some 26 fertilisers (inclusive of urea), on which government bears subsidy and also effectively decides the MRPs;</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Harmonizing markets</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Apart from subsidising and deciding at what price companies can sell, the government also decides where they can sell.</li>
<li>This is done through the Fertiliser (Movement) Control Order, 1973.</li>
<li>Under this, the department of fertilisers draws an agreed monthly supply plan on all subsidised fertilisers in consultation with manufacturers and importers.</li>
<li>This supply plan is issued before the 25th of each month for the following month, with the department also regularly monitoring movement to ensure fertiliser availability as per requirement, including remote areas.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Farmers welfare</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The government is spending vast sums of money on fertiliser subsidy (the bill is likely to cross Rs 200,000 crore in 2022-23).</li>
<li>By deciding where and at what price companies can sell, it would obviously want to take credit and send that message to farmers.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What can be the drawbacks of the scheme?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It may <strong><u>disincentivise fertiliser companies</u></strong> from undertaking marketing and brand promotion activities.</li>
<li>They will now be <strong><u>reduced to contract manufacturers</u></strong> and importers for the government. Any company’s strength ultimately is its brands and farmer trust built over decades.</li>
<li>Currently, in case of any bag or batch of fertilisers not meeting the required standards, the <strong><u>blame is put on the company</u>. </strong>But now, that may be passed on fully to the government.</li>
<li>Politically, the scheme might well boomerang rather than benefit the ruling party.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/one-nation-one-fertiliser-onof-scheme/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>One factor that drags ease of doing business down</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ease-of-doing-business/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>EODB</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>EODB in India</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-628299" height="270" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 516px) 100vw, 516px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ease-of-doing-300x157.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ease-of-doing-300x157.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ease-of-doing.jpg 574w" width="516"/></p>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-ease-of-doing-business-in-india/">Ease of doing business in India</a> remains low, dragged down by the way contracts are enforced in the country. Recent reforms have improved the business climate somewhat, but there is a long way to go.</p>
<p><strong>What is the Ease of Doing Business index?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>It is an index designed by the World Bank to rank 190 economies.</li>
<li>A higher rank (closer to 1) means the country’s regulatory environment is favourable to business operations.</li>
<li>India was ranked 63rd in the overall index in 2020.</li>
<li>World Bank has now discontinued the Doing Business index.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Indicators used</h4>
<p>The ranking is calculated on the basis of indicators such as:</p>
<ol>
<li>Starting a Business</li>
<li>Dealing with Construction Permits</li>
<li>Getting Electricity</li>
<li>Registering Property</li>
<li>Getting Credit</li>
<li>Protecting Minority Investors, Paying Taxes</li>
<li>Trading across Borders</li>
<li>Enforcing Contracts and</li>
<li>Resolving Insolvency</li>
</ol>
<h4>How is ‘Enforcing Contracts’ measured?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2020, in the parameter of ‘Enforcing Contracts’, India was ranked 163rd, against 186th in 2015. The parameter considers time, cost and quality of the judicial process.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Time considers the number of days to resolve a commercial dispute in courts;</li>
<li>Cost measures the expenses of attorney, courts and enforcement as a percentage of claim value; and</li>
<li>Quality considers the use of best practices which can promote efficiency and quality i.e., court proceedings, case management, alternative dispute resolution and court automation.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Each of the three indicators have a 33.3% weightage.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How is India doing on this parameter now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>At 163rd position in 2020, the country continues to struggle, with the time taken to resolve a commercial dispute being approximately 1,445 days in the Doing Business Report 2020.</li>
<li>However, as of August 2022, law ministry data shows a marked improvement of close to 50% in days taken to resolve a dispute to 744 days in New Delhi and 626 days in Mumbai.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are some of the reforms undertaken?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Department of Justice, the nodal point for ‘Enforcing Contracts’ indicator along with the eCommittee of the Supreme Court, has undertaken a series of reforms.</li>
<li>Some of the steps include <strong><u>the establishment of dedicated commercial courts</u></strong> with monetary jurisdiction up to ₹3 lakh.</li>
<li>There also exists online case filing, e-payment of court fees, electronic case management, special courts for infrastructure project contracts, as well as automatic and random allocation of commercial cases thereby eliminating human intervention.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What further steps are required?</h4>
<ul>
<li>An <strong><u>efficient judiciary</u></strong> instils confidence in investors and signals the commercial viability of transactions.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>number of court hearings</u></strong> <strong><u>should be minimized</u></strong> too; often, lawyers have an incentive to stretch out the process.</li>
<li>The judicial system should encourage <strong><u>out-of-court settlements</u></strong> through the respective lawyers as practised in advanced countries.</li>
<li>It is equally important that the judiciary leaves matters relating to <strong><u>economic governance</u></strong> to governments.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ease-of-doing-business/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Challenging the Special Marriage Act, 1954</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/challenging-the-special-marriage-act-1954/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Special Marriage Act, 1954</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with inter-faith marriage</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has dismissed a writ petition challenging the Constitutional validity of certain provisions of the Special Marriage Act, 1954 under which couples seek refuge for inter-faith and inter-caste marriages.</p>
<h4>What is Special Marriage Act, 1954?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Special Marriage Act, 1954 (SMA) was enacted to facilitate the marriage of couples professing different faiths, and preferring a civil wedding.</li>
<li>However, some practical problems arise in registering such marriages.</li>
<li>The law’s features on prior public notice being given and objections for the safety and privacy of those intending to marry across religions.</li>
<li>To overcome this, many settle for marriage under the personal law of one of them, with the other opting for religious conversion.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What does the petition seek?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court dismissed a writ petition challenging the Constitutional validity of certain provisions of the SMA under which couples seek refuge for inter-faith and inter-caste marriages.</li>
<li>The writ petition has called these provisions <strong><u>violative of Article 21</u></strong>, which guarantees the right to privacy.</li>
<li>Under this act, the couples require to give a notice of 30 days before the date of marriage inviting objections from the public.</li>
<li>The provisions <strong><u>contravene Article 14</u></strong> on prohibition of discrimination on grounds of religion, race, caste and sex as well as <strong><u>Article 15</u></strong> on right to equality as these requirements are absent in personal laws.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What did the court say?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The SC Bench rejected the writ petition on the grounds that the petitioner was no longer an aggrieved party as she had already solemnised her marriage under SMA.</li>
<li>The petitioner’s lawyers said that they were now deliberating on an alternative approach to initiate this litigation such as through a public interest litigation involving other victims.</li>
<li>Another writ petition is admitted by the Supreme Court in 2020 and the government’s reply to is awaited.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the provisions that have been challenged?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Section 5 of the SMA requires couples getting married under it to give a <strong><u>notice to the Marriage Officer</u></strong> 30 days before the date of marriage.</li>
<li>Section 6 requires such a notice to be then entered into the Marriage Notice Book maintained by the Marriage Officer, which can be <strong><u>inspected by any person desirous</u></strong> of inspecting the same.</li>
<li>These notices have to be also <strong><u>affixed at a “conspicuous place”</u></strong> in the office of the Marriage Officer so that anyone can raise an objection to the marriage.</li>
<li>Section 7 provides the process for making an objection such as if either party has a living spouse, is incapable of <strong><u>giving consent due to “unsoundness of mind</u></strong>” or is suffering from mental disorder resulting in the person being unfit for marriage or procreation.</li>
<li>Section 8 specifies the <strong><u>inquiry procedure to be followed after an objection</u></strong> has been submitted.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why are these provisions contentious?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The provisions throw the <strong><u>personal information</u></strong> of the individuals <strong><u>open to public scrutiny</u></strong>. This may result into <strong><u>vigilantism</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This seriously damages one’s <strong><u>right to have control over her or his personal information</u></strong> and its accessibility.</li>
<li>By making the personal details of the couple accessible to everyone, the very <strong><u>right of the couple to be the decision makers of their marriage </u></strong>is being hampered by the state.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How do these provisions make couples vulnerable?</h4>
<ul>
<li>These public notices have been used by <strong><u>anti-social elements to harass couples</u></strong> getting married.</li>
<li>For many who often marry without their parent’s consent this <strong><u>can be life-threatening</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Many states <strong><u>publicly share the details</u></strong> of couples marrying under SMA on their websites.</li>
<li>Many also complain about the <strong><u>behaviour of the staff at the SDM’s office</u></strong> who often delete or delay applications and dissuade couples from marrying under SMA.</li>
<li>With as many as 11 States passing <strong><u><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/q-1-discuss-the-rationale-behind-anti-conversion-laws-in-india-also-state-the-concerns-that-have-been-raised-with-regard-to-these-laws-10-marks/">anti-conversion</a> (or so-called love-jihad) laws</u></strong>, parents and the State are now armed to <strong><u>punish and harass such couples.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/challenging-the-special-marriage-act-1954/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Farmer suicide needs to stop urgently</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/farmer-suicide/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>agrarian distress</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="farmer suicide" class="alignnone wp-image-628304" height="336" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/images.jpeg" width="479"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An agricultural labourer died by suicide every 2 hours in 2021: NCRB</li>
<li>The national catastrophe of farmer suicide since the 1990s, often by drinking pesticides is attributed to their inability to repay loans mostly taken from landlords and banks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>NCRB Stats on Farmers Suicide</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Some 5,563 agricultural labourers died by suicide in 2021, according to the latest report of the National Crime Records Bureau (NCRB). The number of suicides increased by nine per cent from 2020 and by around 29 per cent from 2019.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Causes of Farmers Suicide</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Non sustainable cropping</strong>: Most of the suicides have occurred in areas of cash crops like cotton and sugarcane, which is high input, high output gambling, not based on the principle of sustained and resilient high yield.</li>
<li><strong>Multiple causes</strong>: There is no consensus on what the main causes might be but studies show farmer suicide victims are motivated by more than one cause however the primer reasons being the inability to repay loans.</li>
<li><strong>Combined causes</strong>: Major causes reportedly are bankruptcy/indebtedness, problems in the families, crop failure, illness and alcohol/substance abuse.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="farmer suicide" class="alignnone wp-image-628306" height="288" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 493px) 100vw, 493px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.48113100_1661855599_34-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.48113100_1661855599_34-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.48113100_1661855599_34-768x449.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.48113100_1661855599_34.jpg 1024w" width="493"/>Faulty measures </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low penetration of irrigation</strong>: Irrigation reaches less than half of India’s overall farmland, a picture that has not changed much over the past decade, and more than 60% of our farmers are susceptible to rainfall anomalies.</li>
<li><strong>Dry land farming:</strong> Rain-fed farming yields are typically less than half those of irrigated farmland.</li>
<li><strong>High input cost</strong>: Though India has caught up with global levels of fertilizer use, this is neither efficient nor environmentally sustainable. Both add to the cost of cultivation.</li>
<li><strong>Slow R&amp;D</strong>: Research on high-yielding crops has plateaued after an initial burst during the Green Revolution and farmers have to resort to patented seeds to draw more out of their scanty acres.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="farmer suicide" class="alignnone wp-image-628307" height="275" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 495px) 100vw, 495px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/maharashtra-drought-latur-7-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/maharashtra-drought-latur-7-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/maharashtra-drought-latur-7.jpg 389w" width="495"/>7R’ model utility</strong></h4>
<p><strong>It looks at the prevention of farmer suicide</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Remunerative agriculture,</li>
<li>Resilience building,</li>
<li>Rational expenditure,</li>
<li>Reassurance through connectivity,</li>
<li>Righteous conduct,</li>
<li>Religious support and</li>
<li>Responsible reporting</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="farmer suicide" class="alignnone wp-image-628309" height="271" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 515px) 100vw, 515px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/natural-farming-hero-desktop-1-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/natural-farming-hero-desktop-1-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/natural-farming-hero-desktop-1.jpg 600w" width="515"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/op-ed-snap-removing-the-roots-of-farmers-distress/">Way Forward</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Information technology promises to improve weather forecasting, crop identification as well as damage control, soil health monitoring, and mapping of available water resources.</li>
<li>Improvements in marketing and logistics can significantly raise the share that cultivators get of the money people pay for their food.</li>
<li>The govt. is using technology to connect farmers to a nationwide e-market, but the states need to amend their antiquated farm produce marketing laws that have squeezed farmers’ earnings.</li>
<li>An old problem of price signals failing to adjust demand and supply may also need fixing.</li>
<li>For agricultural incomes to rise, reforms, rather than cash transfers, loan waivers and the like, are the way ahead.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Along with subsidies, increased farm profits, the focus should also be on resilience building and problem-solving skills of farming families.</li>
<li>In suicide-prone states, agricultural institutes and scientists should start distributing seeds of resilience, tolerance and contentment among farmers, suggested researchers.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Despite agricultural growth Indian farmers are committing suicides Discuss the causes and give dynamic way forward to address the issue. </strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/farmer-suicide/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Backsliding on climate action</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/backsliding-on-climate-action/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Paris agreement</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Climate change</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>Europe is staring at a recession and its appetite for climate action is waning.</p>
<h4>Developed countries moving away from commitment</h4>
<ul>
<li>Countries in Europe led by Germany, Austria and the Netherlands are cranking up their coal plants again.</li>
<li>Fossil fuels are making a comeback and countries are rejecting the European Union (EU)’s plan to reduce natural gas consumption by 15%. Dutch, Polish and other European farmers are protesting against emission cuts from agriculture.</li>
<li>In the U.S. too, the Senate and the Supreme Court have struck blows to climate action.</li>
<li>And in the U.S. too, prices of fuel started increasing last year, not just this year.</li>
<li>Fossil fuels are making a quiet comeback, since the strength of the U.S. is its oil and gas industry.</li>
<li>That is why we have just witnessed a ‘re-calibration’ of U.S. policy towards the Gulf.</li>
<li>Coal, oil and gas are not going anywhere in the developed world; they are, in fact, making a comeback.</li>
<li>The West had rushed to draw down on fossil fuels even before technology for renewables were in place.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Global peaking issue</h4>
<ul>
<li>Article 4 of the Paris Agreement defines ‘Global Peaking’ thus: “In order to achieve the long-term temperature goal set out in Article 2, Parties aim <strong>to reach global peaking</strong> of greenhouse gas emissions as soon as possible, recognizing that peaking will take longer for developing country Parties.”</li>
<li>The developed countries, given their historical emissions, will have to peak first.</li>
<li>That’s why the reference is to<strong> ‘global peaking’</strong> and not ‘individual peaking’.</li>
<li>From this, it logically follows that when developing country parties peak later than developed countries, they will also achieve net zero later than developed countries.</li>
<li>Consequently, it is the logical conclusion of the Article 4 of the Paris Agreement that when we consider net zero, we should only consider ‘global net zero’ and not ‘individual net zero’ for 2050.</li>
<li>The statement calls on developed countries to do a net negative on mitigation by 2050 rather than just “net zero”, if they are serious about fighting climate change.</li>
<li>In effect, the West needs to do a net minus and not just net zero.</li>
<li>Thanks to the efforts of India, the phrase used in the 2021 summit-level declarations at both G-20 and Quad is ‘global net zero’. We need to build on this understanding.</li>
<li>India stands as beacon of hope in renewables.</li>
<li>It is time for all developing countries, especially the small island developing states, to make sure that the developed world doesn’t backslide on its commitments on mitigation yet again.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward for developing countries</h4>
<ul>
<li>With countries of the developed world almost sure to renege on their 2030 Paris Agreement commitments, countries of the developing world must do everything to hold the countries of the developed world to their commitments.</li>
<li>The Western nations have already started reinterpreting the Paris Agreement and look to downgrade their commitments.</li>
<li>The concept of net zero is being cleverly misinterpreted.</li>
<li> To bring this to the attention of the Global South, India, China and eight other countries from Africa, Asia and Latin America made a cross-regional statement on ‘global net zero’ on June 7 at the UN on World Environment Day.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>COP 27 in Egypt gives us that opportunity to hold their feet to the fire. It is time for the developed world to make net minus pledges. If we don’t collectively push for it, we will be collectively pushed back.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/backsliding-on-climate-action/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Old age poverty is getting worse if not addressed soon</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/old-age-poverty/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>elderly welfare</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="old age poverty" class="alignnone wp-image-628688" height="343" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 515px) 100vw, 515px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ASwaminathan-old-Indian-woman-writing-on-paper-1-scaled-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ASwaminathan-old-Indian-woman-writing-on-paper-1-scaled-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ASwaminathan-old-Indian-woman-writing-on-paper-1-scaled-1-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ASwaminathan-old-Indian-woman-writing-on-paper-1-scaled-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ASwaminathan-old-Indian-woman-writing-on-paper-1-scaled-1-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ASwaminathan-old-Indian-woman-writing-on-paper-1-scaled-1-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ASwaminathan-old-Indian-woman-writing-on-paper-1-scaled-1-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ASwaminathan-old-Indian-woman-writing-on-paper-1-scaled-1-1980x1319.jpg 1980w" width="515"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s old age poverty will be big by 2050. Only 2% informal workers have invested in NPS.</li>
</ul>
<div aria-controls="exacc_WDwQY7CYD8uSseMPtuiLqA0_6" aria-expanded="true" aria-labelledby="exacc_WDwQY7CYD8uSseMPtuiLqA0_5" class="wWOJcd" role="button" tabindex="0">
<h4 aria-hidden="true" class="iDjcJe IX9Lgd wwB5gf" id="exacc_WDwQY7CYD8uSseMPtuiLqA0_5"><strong>What is the real definition of poverty?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Poverty is about not having enough money to meet basic needs including food, clothing and shelter. However, poverty is more, much more than just not having enough money.</li>
</ul>
</div>
<h4><strong>Why is age a cause of poverty?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The “oldest-old”, aged 80 years or over, are less able to work than younger older persons; are more likely to have spent their savings; and are most in need of age-appropriate health and long-term personal care services.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How age induces poverty in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has no legal provisions for income security of the elderly, making the impacts of ageing far harsher for those who are already economically vulnerable.</li>
<li>Deteriorating brain and muscle capacity are largely non-negotiable facts of life, limiting one’s ability to get a job or remain employed.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reasons for old age poverty</strong></h4>
<h4><strong><img alt="old age poverty" class="alignnone wp-image-628689" height="335" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 447px) 100vw, 447px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ph_5067_93066-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ph_5067_93066-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ph_5067_93066-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ph_5067_93066.jpg 1024w" width="447"/></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dependency:</strong> A large section of the senior population in India is still dependent on the joint family set up for their senior care and post-retirement needs, with financial planning for retirement taking a back seat.</li>
<li><strong>High population</strong>: An increase in the number of seniors in India will reduce the percentage of India’s human resource capital and its ability to drive economic growth.</li>
<li><strong>Low insurance penetration</strong>: This highlights the inadequacy and underscores the critical need to streamline retirement planning schemes and strengthen the pension programs in the country. There is a lacks of social security framework.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Data to remember</strong></p>
<p>People employed in the unorganised sector form around 90 per cent of India’s workforce.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>How to assure wellness and dignity to elders?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Income security in the form of monthly pensions either state-assured or employment-linked has been one of the most prevalent modes of assuring continued wellness and dignity against the life-shock of ageing.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="old age poverty" class="alignnone wp-image-628690" height="427" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 604px) 100vw, 604px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/3290ed_a69e41db5fd34b5089032c755f98e89b_mv2-300x212.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/3290ed_a69e41db5fd34b5089032c755f98e89b_mv2-300x212.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/3290ed_a69e41db5fd34b5089032c755f98e89b_mv2-768x543.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/3290ed_a69e41db5fd34b5089032c755f98e89b_mv2.jpg 1000w" width="604"/>Addressing the roadblock</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Universal pension program:</strong> Income security in later years stems from multiple sources such as pensions, insurances (medical and life), Investments. This provides an opportunity for India to create a universal pension program for its 1.3 billion people<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Financial incentives: </strong>There is a pressing need to promote and facilitate fiscal planning in the early years and supplement it with senior-friendly tax structures and integrated insurance products. Such measures can help provide multiple income options to seniors to help them embrace a lifestyle of their choice.</li>
<li><strong>Regulatory mechanism: </strong>A regulatory mechanism will set a viable base rate for the interest accrued on senior citizen deposits and ensure market dips don’t affect retirement income and senior-specific saving plans.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Case study</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Rwanda has achieved roughly 2 million voluntary micro-pension enrolments (30 per cent of its adult population) within three years by making digital account activation easy and simple for informal workers.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-proposes-to-hike-monthly-pensions-for-the-elderly-poor-disabled-and-widows/"><strong>Government intervention to improve elderly wellness </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>A strong and sustained political commitment,</li>
<li>A statutory pension sector regulator,</li>
<li>A well-designed and low-cost NPS product architecture,</li>
<li>Credible and well-regulated NPS intermediaries,</li>
<li>Securities market capable of delivering high returns,</li>
<li>Near-universal banking and mobile penetration,</li>
<li>The India Stack infrastructure with Aadhaar for easy eKYC, and UPI for secure digital payments.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The government, Pension Fund Regulatory and Development Authority (PFRDA) and the NPS industry now need to urgently put their heads together and address the obvious supply and demand side barriers. Every day is precious. After all, pension exclusion is akin to climate change. It needs immediate attention. By 2050, India’s problem of old age poverty will have become way too large, too late, too expensive and entirely irreversible<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>Nearly 400 million young, economically active Indians are slowly walking towards extreme old age poverty in this context how will you explain and analyse the term old age poverty? Suggest some dynamic measures to address this problem.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/old-age-poverty/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Edible coating to prolong shelf life of fruits and vegetables</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/edible-coating/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Dunaliella tertiolecta</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-628740" height="207" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 411px) 100vw, 411px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coating-300x151.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coating-300x151.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coating-768x387.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coating.jpg 896w" width="411"/></p>
<p>A team of researchers at the IIT — Guwahati has developed an edible coating using marine alga that coated on vegetables and fruits, substantially extends their shelf-life.</p>
<h4>Dunaliella tertiolecta: The Edible coating</h4>
<ul>
<li>The team used a mix of an extract of a marine microalga called Dunaliella tertiolecta and polysaccharides to produce it.</li>
<li>The microalga is known for its antioxidant properties and has various bioactive compounds such as carotenoids and proteins.</li>
<li>It is also used to produce algal oil, a non-animal source of omega-3 fatty acid and is considered a good source of biofuel.</li>
<li>After the oil is extracted, the residue is usually discarded.</li>
<li>The researchers used extracts from this residue in formulating their film, in combination with chitosan, which is a carbohydrate.</li>
<li>It also has antimicrobial and antifungal properties and can be made into an edible film.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Benefits of this Edible coating</h4>
<ul>
<li>The films displayed superior antioxidant activity, thermal stability, mechanical strength, total phenolic content and water vapour barrier property.</li>
<li>They also had excellent UV-Vis light-blocking properties.</li>
<li>The researchers also tested the biosafety of these coatings.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is it viable?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The new coatings can be mass-produced.</li>
<li>They are very stable to light, heat, and temperature up to 40C, edible, and can be safely eaten as part of the product formulation and do not add unfavourable properties to it.</li>
<li>They retain texture, colour, appearance, flavour and nutritional value.</li>
<li>The material can be either directly coated on the vegetables and fruits or made into a vegetable storage pouch.</li>
<li>In both cases, the shelf-life of the vegetables can be extended.</li>
<li>It is a simple dip coating technique with no significant cost added to the post-harvest processing.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Economic significance of Edible coating</h4>
<ul>
<li>According to the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/agri-research-role-of-icar/">Indian Council of Agricultural Research</a>, between 4.6 and 15.9 per cent of fruits and vegetables go waste post-harvest, partly due to poor storage conditions.</li>
<li>In fact, post-harvest loss in certain produce items like potato, onion, and tomato could even be as high as 19%, which results in high prices for this highly consumed commodity.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/edible-coating/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why are the fisherfolk protesting over Vizhinjam Port Project?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vizhinjam-port-project/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Vizhinjam Port Project</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Port-led development in India</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-628741" height="237" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vizhi-300x237.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vizhi-300x237.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vizhi.jpg 435w" width="300"/></p>
<p>Vizhinjam near Thiruvananthapuram, is on the boil due to the under-construction Vizhinjam Port Project, from both sea and land.</p>
<h4>Vizhinjam Port Project</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Vizhinjam International Transhipment Deep-water Multipurpose Seaport is an ambitious project taken up by Government of Kerala.</li>
<li>It is designed primarily to cater container transhipment besides multi-purpose and break bulk cargo.</li>
<li>The port is being currently developed in landlord model with a Public Private Partnership component on a design, build, finance, operate and transfer (“DBFOT”) basis.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why protests are erupted?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The protestors have been opposing the construction work by the Adani Vizhinjam Port Private Limited.</li>
<li>Adani group is developing the port on DBFOT basis.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What lies at the heart of the protest?</h4>
<ul>
<li>According to fisherfolk, the port work has aggravated the coastal erosion along the coast of Thiruvananthapuram.</li>
<li>A scientific study to assess the impact of the port work on the shoreline has to be conducted urgently by stopping the construction.</li>
<li>Further, around 300 families along the coastline were shifted to relief camps after their houses were destroyed due to high-intensity coastal erosion.</li>
<li>The protesters demand a <strong><u>comprehensive rehabilitation package</u></strong>, an <strong><u>assured minimum wage</u></strong> when the sea turns rough due to inclement weather and subsidised kerosene for boats.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why the Vizhinjam project is considered important?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The port is located on the southern tip of the Indian Peninsula, just 10 nautical miles from the major international sea route and east-west shipping axis.</li>
<li>It has a natural water depth of more than 20 m within a nautical mile from the coast.</li>
<li>The Vizhinjam port is likely to play a pivotal role in the maritime development of the country and Kerala.</li>
<li>The commissioning of the port is expected to leverage the growth of 17 minor ports in the State along with creating thousands of employment opportunities.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vizhinjam-port-project/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Bhang, Ganja, and criminality in the NDPS Act</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bhang-ganja-and-criminality-in-the-ndps-act/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NDPS Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with NDPS Act</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-500883" height="683" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 444px) 100vw, 444px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/ndps-195x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/ndps-195x300.jpg 195w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/ndps.jpg 658w" width="444"/></p>
<p>While granting bail to a man arrested on June 1 for possessing 29 kg of bhang and 400 g of ganja, Karnataka High Court recently observed that nowhere in the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (NDPS) Act is bhang referred to as a prohibited drink or prohibited drug.</p>
<h4>What is Bhang?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Bhang is the edible preparation made from the leaves of the cannabis plant, often incorporated into drinks such as thandai and lassi, along with various foods.</li>
<li>Bhang has been consumed in the Indian subcontinent for centuries, and is frequently consumed during the festivals of Holi and Mahashivratri.</li>
<li>Its widespread use caught the attention of Europeans, with Garcia da Orta, a Portuguese physician who arrived in Goa in the 16th century, noting that, “Bhang is so generally used and by such a number of people that there is no mystery about it”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Bhang and the law</h4>
<ul>
<li>Enacted in 1985, the NDPS Act is the main legislation that deals with drugs and their trafficking.</li>
<li>Various provisions of the Act punish production, manufacture, sale, possession, consumption, purchase, transport, and use of banned drugs, except for medical and scientific purposes.</li>
<li>The NDPS Act defines cannabis (hemp) as a narcotic drug based on the parts of the plant that come under its purview. The Act lists these parts as:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Charas: “The separated resin, in whatever form, whether crude or purified, obtained from the cannabis plant and also includes concentrated preparation and resin known as hashish oil or liquid hashish.”</li>
<li>Ganja: “The flowering or fruiting tops of the cannabis plant (excluding the seeds and leaves when not accompanied by the tops), by whatever name they be known or designated.”</li>
<li>“Any mixture, with or without any neutral material, of any of the above forms of cannabis or any drink prepared therefrom.”</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The Act, in its definition, excludes seeds and leaves “when not accompanied by the tops”.</li>
<li>Bhang, which is made with the leaves of the plant, is not mentioned in the NDPS Act.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Cannabis and criminal liability</h4>
<ul>
<li>Section 20 of the NDPS Act lays out the punishment for the production, manufacture, sale, purchase, import and inter-state export of cannabis, as defined in the Act.</li>
<li>The prescribed punishment is based on the amount of drugs seized.</li>
<li>Contravention that involves a small quantity (100 g of charas/hashish or 1 kg of ganja), will result in rigorous imprisonment for a term that may extend to one year and/or a fine which may extend to Rs 10,000.</li>
<li>For a commercial quantity (1 kg charas/ hashish or 20 kg ganja), rigorous imprisonment of not less than 10 years, which may extend to 20 years, including a fine that is not less than Rs 1,00,000 but may extend to Rs 2,00,000.</li>
<li>Where the contravention involves quantity less than commercial, but greater than small quantity, rigorous imprisonment up to 10 years is prescribed, along with a fine which may extend to Rs 1,00,000.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="DOEo1szZv6"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-substance-abuse-in-india/">[Burning Issue] Substance Abuse in India</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="DOEo1szZv6" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-substance-abuse-in-india/embed/#?secret=Qo8qjnOp3G#?secret=DOEo1szZv6" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Burning Issue] Substance Abuse in India” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bhang-ganja-and-criminality-in-the-ndps-act/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Alcohol Laws in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/alcohol-laws-in-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Alcohol laws</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The most ambitious Delhi’s Alcohol Policy 2021-22 which brought in big discounts for consumers was scrapped on July 31 amid allegations of corruption and irregularities in the drafting and implementation of the policy.</p>
<p>After scrapping the new policy, the Delhi government decided to bring back the ‘<strong><u>old excise regime</u></strong>’ that was in force before.</p>
<blockquote><p>Definitely! We shall not nit-pick the old vs. new policy. Let us generally understand how alcohol is regulated in India.</p></blockquote>
<h4>Alcohol laws of India: A backgrounder</h4>
<ul>
<li>The legal drinking age in India and the laws which regulate the sale and consumption of alcohol vary significantly from state to state.</li>
<li>In India, consumption of alcohol is prohibited in the states of Bihar, Gujarat, Nagaland and Mizoram.</li>
<li>There is partial ban on alcohol in some districts of Manipur.</li>
<li>All other Indian states permit alcohol consumption but fix a legal drinking age, which ranges at different ages per region.</li>
<li>In some states the legal drinking age can be different for different types of alcoholic beverage.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Regulation</h4>
<ul>
<li>Alcohol is a subject in the <strong><u>State List</u></strong> under the Seventh Schedule of the Constitution of India.</li>
<li>Therefore, the <strong><u>laws governing alcohol vary from state to state</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Liquor in India is generally sold at liquor stores, restaurants, hotels, bars, pubs, clubs and discos but not online.</li>
<li>Some states, like Kerala and Tamil Nadu, prohibit private parties from owning liquor stores making the state government the sole retailer of alcohol in those states.</li>
<li>In some states, liquor may be sold at groceries, departmental stores, banquet halls and/or farm houses.</li>
<li>Some tourist areas have special laws allowing the sale of alcohol on beaches and houseboats.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Drunk driving law</h4>
<ul>
<li>The blood alcohol content (BAC) legal limit is 0.03% or 0.03 mg alcohol in 100 ml blood.</li>
<li>On 1 March 2012, the Union Cabinet approved proposed changes to the Motor Vehicle Act.</li>
<li>Higher penalties were introduced, including fines from ₹2,000 to ₹10,000 and imprisonment from 6 months to 4 years.</li>
<li>Different penalties are assessed depending on the blood alcohol content at the time of the offence.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Dry days</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dry days are specific days when the sale of alcohol is not permitted.</li>
<li>Most of the Indian states observe these days on major national festivals/occasions such as Republic Day (26 January), Independence Day (15 August) and Gandhi Jayanti (2 October).</li>
<li>Dry days are also observed during elections in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Taxation on Alcohol</h4>
<ul>
<li>Most states levy either Value added Tax (VAT) or Excise duty or both.</li>
<li>Excise duty is a tax levied to discourage the consumption of a product.</li>
<li>It is calculated on a per-unit basis. Meaning, if you buy 1 litre of liquor, you pay a fixed excise duty of Rs 15.</li>
<li>Value-added Tax is charged in the proportion of the product. If a bottle costs Rs 100, and the state levies 10 percent VAT, the price rises to Rs 110.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Tax rates in States</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 29 states/UTs in India approach liquor taxation differently.</li>
<li>For instance, Gujarat has banned its citizens from consuming liquor since 1961.</li>
<li>But outsiders with special licenses can still buy.</li>
<li>Puducherry, on the other hand, earns most of its revenue from alcohol trading.</li>
<li>Bihar has prohibited alcohol consumption entirely, meaning the state’s revenue from liquor consumption is nil.</li>
<li>Its neighbour, Uttar Pradesh, earns the most excise duty on liquor.</li>
<li>The state does not levy VAT but a special duty on liquor, collecting funds for particular purposes.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Do you know?</strong></h4>
<p>Andhra Pradesh, Telangana, Kerala, Karnataka, and Tamil Nadu consume as much as 45 percent of the liquor sold in the country.</p>
<p>Nationally, Maharashtra charges the highest rate but draws only a portion of its revenue from its sales.</p></blockquote>
<h4>Why alcohol isn’t banned everywhere?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Taxes from alcohol sales roughly form a quarter of state revenues.</li>
<li>If this stream suddenly stops, states have to compulsorily cut some important spending.</li>
<li>Also, moderate alcohol consumption may provide some health benefits.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/alcohol-laws-in-india/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Heritage conservation is need of hour</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/heritage/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>ASI</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>heritage conservation</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="heritage " class="alignnone wp-image-628757" height="240" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 456px) 100vw, 456px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/A4564-Conservation-and-protection-of-heritage-monuments-in-India.-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/A4564-Conservation-and-protection-of-heritage-monuments-in-India.-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/A4564-Conservation-and-protection-of-heritage-monuments-in-India.-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/A4564-Conservation-and-protection-of-heritage-monuments-in-India.-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/A4564-Conservation-and-protection-of-heritage-monuments-in-India..jpg 1200w" width="456"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Despite all the public talk of the importance of conserving our national heritage, the budget of the ASI, the primary institutional guardian of monuments, in 2021-22 has been reduced by more than Rs 200 cr.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How do you define heritage?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Heritage is the full range of our inherited traditions, monuments, objects, and culture. Most important, it is the range of contemporary activities, meanings, and behaviours that we draw from them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Threats to Indian Heritage</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Theft:</strong> The incidents of thefts have been observed usually from unprotected monuments, ancient temples. The thefts cases have also been seen in the protected monuments and museums as well. It is due to negligence of security guards in museums, monuments etc.</li>
<li><strong>Smuggling</strong>: illicit traffic and smuggling in antiquities. Illicit traffic is motivated often by profit and sometimes by the demand for luxuries.</li>
<li><strong>Tourism:</strong> Unregulated tourism, tourist activities run by touts, private agents have affected the art heritage places. The Culture Ministry of India has reported that up to 24 Indian monuments have been declared “untraceable” or “missing” by the Archaeological Survey of India (ASI).</li>
<li><strong>Issues with security of museums</strong>: Most of the museums are poorly guarded due to shortage of manpower leading to theft of artifacts, fire accidents etc.</li>
<li><strong>Duplication</strong>: Fakes paintings and art forms leading to threat to livelihoods of artists.</li>
<li><strong>Poor Maintenance</strong>: The state of the wall paintings in Ajanta caves is continuously getting worse, which can be attributed to humidity as well as to a lack of care.</li>
<li><strong>Encroachment on monuments</strong>: Another miss from the ministry has been encroachments of monuments. Over 278 centrally protected monuments have been encroached upon or have illegal occupants, as per government data.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="heritage " class="alignnone wp-image-628759" height="285" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 411px) 100vw, 411px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-10-300x208.webp" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-10-300x208.webp 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-10.webp 630w" width="411"/>Why should we protect our heritage?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Evolution of human consciousness is a continuous process</strong>: History here serves as a laboratory and the past serves as a demarcation to understand the regional laws and social structures. This understanding helps in our progress towards an ideal society.</li>
<li><strong>Pride of country</strong>: The art heritage is the identity and pride of our country. It is duty of every citizen to protect, preserve and perpetuate the cultural richness.</li>
<li><strong>Tourism potential</strong>: for art monuments and museums is very high. Tourism generates revenue for the state as well as private artists due to the money-multiplier quality.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure development:</strong> takes place in and around the areas. Eg. Hampi despite being a small town has excellent infrastructure.</li>
<li><strong>Jobs:</strong> It creates jobs for a lot of people from art industry and tourism industry as well</li>
<li><strong>Sense of belonging</strong>: It creates a feeling of oneness and a sense of attachment by enhancing a sense of belonging to a culture or a region.</li>
<li><strong>Strengthen conviction</strong>: Every historical site has an important story to tell and these stories have inspired many people to strengthen their convictions and commitment to fight injustice and oppression.</li>
<li><strong>Soft power</strong>: Art and culture is also a part of soft power in world politics.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>About Archaeological Survey of India (ASI)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ASI is an attached office of the Ministry of Culture.</li>
<li>It was founded in 1861 by Alexander Cunningham who also became its first Director-General.</li>
<li>Under the provisions of the AMASR Act of 1958, the ASI administers more than 3650 ancient monuments, archaeological sites and remains of national importance.</li>
<li>These can include everything from temples, mosques, churches, tombs, and cemeteries to palaces, forts, step-wells, and rock-cut caves.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Initiatives by ASI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Museums: </strong>ASI’s museums are customarily located right next to the sites that their inventories are associated with “so that they may be studied amid their natural surroundings and not lose focus by being transported”. A dedicated Museums Branch maintains a total of 44 museums spread across the country.</li>
<li><strong>Publications by ASI: </strong>Epigraphia Indica, Ancient India, Indian Archaeology: A Review (Annually).</li>
<li><strong>Library</strong>: <strong>Central Archaeological Library </strong>in the <strong>National Archives building</strong> in Janpath, New Delhi.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues and Challenges ahead of ASI </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>To restore or not: </strong>Issue is that technically speaking- ruins are seldom “restored” in original state. This is because in absence of documentation- archaeologists are left to conjecture what buildings may have looked like when they were originally built.</li>
<li><strong>Personnel Management Issues: </strong>Higher Authorities of ASI are traditionally from IAS Cadre<strong>. </strong>In-house specialist must be promoted for better coordination b/w technical and managerial aspects of restoration</li>
<li><strong>Issues explored in CAG Report: </strong>92 monuments are untraceable with no database on artifacts<strong>. </strong>Poor Documentation of Protected Monuments/Artifacts<strong>. </strong>Paucity of funds (Eg- Red fort gardens lie unkempt).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is the duty of every citizen to value and preserve the rich heritage of our composite culture. Preservation and conservation of India’s rich cultural heritage and promotion of all forms of art and culture, both tangible and intangible, is essential and assumes a lot of importance.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong> Safeguarding the Indian heritage is the need of the moment.</strong> <strong>What are the challenges faced in safeguarding them? What steps would you suggest to protect them?</strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/heritage/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why has the Solomon Islands blocked foreign navy vessels?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/solomon-islands/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Solomon Islands</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Chinese expansion in Pacific</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-494199" height="431" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 451px) 100vw, 451px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-300x287.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-300x287.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-1024x980.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-768x735.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-1536x1471.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-1200x1149.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon.jpg 1600w" width="451"/>After refusing access to US and UK ships to its ports earlier this month, the Solomon Islands has now temporarily halted all naval visits.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The country’s move is a departure from the norm and is been seen as an attempt to appease China.</li>
<li>This raises concerns about China’s growing influence in the country and the region at large.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where is the Solomon Islands located?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Solomon Islands is a sovereign country consisting of six major islands and over 900 smaller islands in Oceania, to the east of Papua New Guinea and northwest of Vanuatu.</li>
<li>Its capital, Honiara, is located on the largest island, Guadalcanal.</li>
<li>It is part of the ethnically Melanesian group of islands in the Pacific and lies between Papua New Guinea and Vanuatu.</li>
<li>The country takes its name from the Solomon Islands archipelago, which is a collection of Melanesian islands that also includes the North Solomon Islands (a part of Papua New Guinea).</li>
<li>It excludes outlying islands, such as the Santa Cruz Islands and Rennell and Bellona.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Quick recap of its past</h4>
<ul>
<li>The islands, which were initially controlled by the British Empire during the colonial era, went through the hands of Germany and Japan.</li>
<li>It then went back to the UK after the Americans took over the islands from the Japanese during World War II.</li>
<li>The islands became independent in 1978 to become a constitutional monarchy under the British Crown, with a parliamentary system of government.</li>
<li>Nevertheless, its inability to manage domestic ethnic conflicts led to close security relations with Australia, which is the traditional first responder to any crisis in the South Pacific.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did China enter the picture?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Earlier this year, the Solomon Islands established a <strong><u>security agreement with China</u></strong>, saying it needed Beijing’s assistance with its domestic security situation.</li>
<li>But the <strong><u>announcement had rattled the west</u></strong>, esp. the US, Australia and others in the Indo-Pacific region.</li>
<li>The concerns were that the agreement could potentially lead to a <strong><u>Chinese military base on the island nation</u></strong> and a gain in power-projection capabilities.</li>
<li>At that time, following intense scrutiny, the Solomon Islands had <strong><u>denied</u></strong> that the agreement would allow China to establish a naval base.</li>
<li>The Island insisted that the agreement was only to <strong><u>assist the Solomon Islands with what he called “hard internal threats”.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the Solomon Islands’ stance?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The government has asked all partner countries with plans to conduct naval visits or patrols to put them on hold until a <strong><u>revised national mechanism</u></strong> is in place.</li>
<li>The revised national mechanism <strong><u>applied to all foreign vessels seeking access to the country’s ports</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The nation wanted to <strong><u>build up its</u></strong> <strong><u>own naval capacity</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It has some <strong><u>unfortunate experiences of foreign naval vessels entering its waters</u></strong> without any diplomatic clearance.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is behind China’s growing influence in the region?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There is no dispute that China has been rapidly increasing its presence and influence in the region for over three decades, particularly in the South Pacific.</li>
<li>Certainly Beijing views the Pacific Island region as an <strong><u>important component of its Belt and Road Initiative (BRI). </u></strong></li>
<li>Specifically, it sees the region as a critical air freight hub in its so-called <strong><u>Air Silk Road</u></strong>, which connects Asia with Central and South America.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Concerns of the West</h4>
<ul>
<li>The United States and its regional allies, such as Australia and New Zealand, are concerned that the China-Solomon Islands security pact allows Chinese naval vessels to replenish there.</li>
<li>That could open the <strong><u>door to a Chinese naval base</u></strong>, which would significantly extend China’s military reach in the South Pacific.”</li>
<li>It is likely that this security agreement between China and the Solomon Islands has been driven by, what the CFR calls, Beijing’s “<strong><u>sense of vulnerability</u></strong>” in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the rationale for the Solomon Islands’ increasing proximity to China?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Solomon Islands had cultivated strong ties with Taiwan, which ended with the emergence of the current government in Honiara.</li>
<li>In 2019, the regime change switched Taiwan for China.</li>
<li>This was supposedly after Beijing offered half a billion US dollars in financial aid, roughly five times what Taiwan spent on the islands in the past two decades.</li>
<li>It has been alleged by the pro-Taiwan Opposition that the incumbent government has been bribed by China.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is China interested in the Solomon Islands?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Isolating Taiwan:</strong> The Solomon Islands was one among the six Pacific island states which had official bilateral relations with Taiwan.</li>
<li><strong>Supporter in UN:</strong> The small Pacific island states act as potential vote banks for mobilising support for the great powers in international fora like the United Nations.</li>
<li><strong>Larger EEZ:</strong> These states have disproportionately large maritime Exclusive Economic Zones when compared to their small sizes.</li>
<li><strong>Natural resources:</strong> Solomon Islands, in particular, have significant reserves of timber and mineral resources, along with fisheries.</li>
<li><strong>Countering US:</strong> But more importantly, they are strategically located for China to insert itself between America’s military bases in the Pacific islands and Australia.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What does this mean for the established geopolitical configuration in the region?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Diminishing western influence:</strong> The Pacific islands, in the post-World War II scenario, were exclusively under the spheres of influence of the Western powers, in particular, the US, UK, France and Australia and New Zealand.</li>
<li><strong>Inserting into western hegemony:</strong> All of them have territorial possessions in the region, with the three nuclear powers among them having used the region as a nuclear weapons testing ground.</li>
<li><strong>Shifting of dependencies:</strong> The smaller island nations of the region are heavily dependent on them, especially Australia as it is a resident power.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Damage control by West</h4>
<ul>
<li>Australia has reacted with boosted finances, and by extending its current security mission till 2023 when the islands will host the Pacific Games.</li>
<li>The US has responded by considering reopening its embassy in Honiara after a long 29-year gap.</li>
<li>New Zealand has shed its typical restraint about China and has criticised it for attempting to militarise the Pacific islands.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/solomon-islands/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Electricity Amendment Bill 2022 – Addressing the transition and equity</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/electricity/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of the bill</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>electricity reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="electricity" class="alignnone wp-image-629013" height="343" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download.jpeg" width="558"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Concerns of states on some provisions of the new Electricity Bill are justified. But the legislation proposes welcome correctives to longstanding problems of the power sector.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Important provisions of the bill</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Payment security</strong>: The Bill provides that electricity will not be scheduled or despatched if adequate payment security is not provided by the discom.   The central government may prescribe rules regarding payment security.</li>
<li><strong>Contract enforcement</strong>: The Bill empowers the CERC and SERCs to adjudicate disputes related to the performance of contracts.  These refer to contracts related to the sale, purchase, or transmission of electricity.  Further, the Commissions will have powers of a Civil Court.</li>
<li><strong>Renewable purchase obligation</strong>: The Act empowers SERCs to specify renewable purchase obligations (RPO) for discoms.  RPO refers to the mandate to procure a certain percentage of electricity from renewable sources.  The Bill adds that RPO should not be below a minimum percentage prescribed by the central government.  Failure to meet RPO will be punishable with a penalty between 25 paise and 50 paise per kilowatt of the shortfall.</li>
<li><strong>Selection committee for SERCs</strong>: Under the Act, the Chairperson of the Central Electricity Authority or the Chairperson of the CERC is one of the members of the selection committee to recommend appointments to the SERCs.  Under the Bill, instead of this person, the central government will nominate a member to the selection committee.  The nominee should not be below the rank of Additional Secretary to the central government.</li>
<li><strong>Composition of Commissions and APTEL</strong>: The Bill increases the number of members (including the chairperson) in SERCs from three to four.  Further, at least one member in both the CERC and SERCs must be from law background.  Under the Act, Appellate Tribunal for Electricity (APTEL) consists of a chairperson and three other members.  The Bill instead provides that the APTEL will have three or more members, as may be prescribed by the central government.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>State apprehensions of the bill </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multi state license: </strong>The clause pertaining to applicants seeking a distribution licence in more than one state. It states that the Central Electricity Regulatory Commission (CERC), and not the SERC, will grant the licence. This is problematic because a SERC is likely to be more aware of the field-level conditions in a state than its central counterpart.</li>
<li><strong>Centre can bypass state: </strong>The Bill has a provision empowering the Centre to give directions directly to the SERCs. Till now, the CERC received instructions from the Centre and the SERCs were under the state. The new Bill enables the Centre to bypass state governments. It’s not surprising that this is a matter of concern for the states.</li>
<li><strong>Direct appointment by centre:</strong> The Bill states that the SERC chairperson will now be a nominee of the central government and will be an additional secretary-level official. This gives the impression that the Centre is trying to control the appointments to the SERCs<strong>. </strong></li>
</ul>
<div class="mceTemp"></div>
<p><img alt="electricity" class="alignnone wp-image-629016" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 481px) 100vw, 481px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy-300x208.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy-300x208.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy.jpg 650w" width="481"/></p>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/power-sector-reforms/"><strong>Why the bill is important? </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Compensation clause: </strong>The Bill states that if power purchase agreement PPAs are renegotiated, the affected party has to be compensated within 90 days from the date of submission of the petition.</li>
<li><strong>Uniformity in tariffs revision:</strong> New tariffs have to be made applicable from the beginning of the financial year. New tariffs often come into force in the middle of the financial year (due to delays in the issuing of orders by SERCs). This means that discoms do not earn their full revenues leading to cash flow problems.</li>
<li><strong>Easy tariff petition processing now:</strong> The Bill has proposed a reduction in the time for processing tariff petitions from 120 days to 90 days.</li>
<li><strong>Suo moto jurisdiction</strong>: Regulatory commissions have been given suo motu jurisdiction if tariff petitions are not filed within 30 days of the stipulated time. This too is a step in the right direction.</li>
<li><strong>More teeth to load dispatcher: </strong>the Bill proposes to give more teeth to the national load dispatcher. We need to strengthen the load dispatcher for the smooth functioning of the grid, especially with a huge renewable capacity where intermittency of generation is a major issue in the offing.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The rollout of the proposed amendments through a consensus-based approach would go a long way in overhauling the weakest link in the nation’s power supply chain.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Electricity Bill 2022 is a remedy worse than the disease afflicting India’s power sector. Critically analyse.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/electricity/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>