<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Sep 2022 14:08:38 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Bhang, Ganja, and criminality in the NDPS Act</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bhang-ganja-and-criminality-in-the-ndps-act/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NDPS Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with NDPS Act</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-500883" height="683" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 444px) 100vw, 444px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/ndps-195x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/ndps-195x300.jpg 195w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/ndps.jpg 658w" width="444"/></p>
<p>While granting bail to a man arrested on June 1 for possessing 29 kg of bhang and 400 g of ganja, Karnataka High Court recently observed that nowhere in the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (NDPS) Act is bhang referred to as a prohibited drink or prohibited drug.</p>
<h4>What is Bhang?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Bhang is the edible preparation made from the leaves of the cannabis plant, often incorporated into drinks such as thandai and lassi, along with various foods.</li>
<li>Bhang has been consumed in the Indian subcontinent for centuries, and is frequently consumed during the festivals of Holi and Mahashivratri.</li>
<li>Its widespread use caught the attention of Europeans, with Garcia da Orta, a Portuguese physician who arrived in Goa in the 16th century, noting that, “Bhang is so generally used and by such a number of people that there is no mystery about it”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Bhang and the law</h4>
<ul>
<li>Enacted in 1985, the NDPS Act is the main legislation that deals with drugs and their trafficking.</li>
<li>Various provisions of the Act punish production, manufacture, sale, possession, consumption, purchase, transport, and use of banned drugs, except for medical and scientific purposes.</li>
<li>The NDPS Act defines cannabis (hemp) as a narcotic drug based on the parts of the plant that come under its purview. The Act lists these parts as:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Charas: “The separated resin, in whatever form, whether crude or purified, obtained from the cannabis plant and also includes concentrated preparation and resin known as hashish oil or liquid hashish.”</li>
<li>Ganja: “The flowering or fruiting tops of the cannabis plant (excluding the seeds and leaves when not accompanied by the tops), by whatever name they be known or designated.”</li>
<li>“Any mixture, with or without any neutral material, of any of the above forms of cannabis or any drink prepared therefrom.”</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The Act, in its definition, excludes seeds and leaves “when not accompanied by the tops”.</li>
<li>Bhang, which is made with the leaves of the plant, is not mentioned in the NDPS Act.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Cannabis and criminal liability</h4>
<ul>
<li>Section 20 of the NDPS Act lays out the punishment for the production, manufacture, sale, purchase, import and inter-state export of cannabis, as defined in the Act.</li>
<li>The prescribed punishment is based on the amount of drugs seized.</li>
<li>Contravention that involves a small quantity (100 g of charas/hashish or 1 kg of ganja), will result in rigorous imprisonment for a term that may extend to one year and/or a fine which may extend to Rs 10,000.</li>
<li>For a commercial quantity (1 kg charas/ hashish or 20 kg ganja), rigorous imprisonment of not less than 10 years, which may extend to 20 years, including a fine that is not less than Rs 1,00,000 but may extend to Rs 2,00,000.</li>
<li>Where the contravention involves quantity less than commercial, but greater than small quantity, rigorous imprisonment up to 10 years is prescribed, along with a fine which may extend to Rs 1,00,000.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="DOEo1szZv6"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-substance-abuse-in-india/">[Burning Issue] Substance Abuse in India</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="DOEo1szZv6" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-substance-abuse-in-india/embed/#?secret=Qo8qjnOp3G#?secret=DOEo1szZv6" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Burning Issue] Substance Abuse in India” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bhang-ganja-and-criminality-in-the-ndps-act/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Alcohol Laws in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/alcohol-laws-in-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Alcohol laws</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The most ambitious Delhi’s Alcohol Policy 2021-22 which brought in big discounts for consumers was scrapped on July 31 amid allegations of corruption and irregularities in the drafting and implementation of the policy.</p>
<p>After scrapping the new policy, the Delhi government decided to bring back the ‘<strong><u>old excise regime</u></strong>’ that was in force before.</p>
<blockquote><p>Definitely! We shall not nit-pick the old vs. new policy. Let us generally understand how alcohol is regulated in India.</p></blockquote>
<h4>Alcohol laws of India: A backgrounder</h4>
<ul>
<li>The legal drinking age in India and the laws which regulate the sale and consumption of alcohol vary significantly from state to state.</li>
<li>In India, consumption of alcohol is prohibited in the states of Bihar, Gujarat, Nagaland and Mizoram.</li>
<li>There is partial ban on alcohol in some districts of Manipur.</li>
<li>All other Indian states permit alcohol consumption but fix a legal drinking age, which ranges at different ages per region.</li>
<li>In some states the legal drinking age can be different for different types of alcoholic beverage.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Regulation</h4>
<ul>
<li>Alcohol is a subject in the <strong><u>State List</u></strong> under the Seventh Schedule of the Constitution of India.</li>
<li>Therefore, the <strong><u>laws governing alcohol vary from state to state</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Liquor in India is generally sold at liquor stores, restaurants, hotels, bars, pubs, clubs and discos but not online.</li>
<li>Some states, like Kerala and Tamil Nadu, prohibit private parties from owning liquor stores making the state government the sole retailer of alcohol in those states.</li>
<li>In some states, liquor may be sold at groceries, departmental stores, banquet halls and/or farm houses.</li>
<li>Some tourist areas have special laws allowing the sale of alcohol on beaches and houseboats.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Drunk driving law</h4>
<ul>
<li>The blood alcohol content (BAC) legal limit is 0.03% or 0.03 mg alcohol in 100 ml blood.</li>
<li>On 1 March 2012, the Union Cabinet approved proposed changes to the Motor Vehicle Act.</li>
<li>Higher penalties were introduced, including fines from ₹2,000 to ₹10,000 and imprisonment from 6 months to 4 years.</li>
<li>Different penalties are assessed depending on the blood alcohol content at the time of the offence.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Dry days</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dry days are specific days when the sale of alcohol is not permitted.</li>
<li>Most of the Indian states observe these days on major national festivals/occasions such as Republic Day (26 January), Independence Day (15 August) and Gandhi Jayanti (2 October).</li>
<li>Dry days are also observed during elections in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Taxation on Alcohol</h4>
<ul>
<li>Most states levy either Value added Tax (VAT) or Excise duty or both.</li>
<li>Excise duty is a tax levied to discourage the consumption of a product.</li>
<li>It is calculated on a per-unit basis. Meaning, if you buy 1 litre of liquor, you pay a fixed excise duty of Rs 15.</li>
<li>Value-added Tax is charged in the proportion of the product. If a bottle costs Rs 100, and the state levies 10 percent VAT, the price rises to Rs 110.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Tax rates in States</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 29 states/UTs in India approach liquor taxation differently.</li>
<li>For instance, Gujarat has banned its citizens from consuming liquor since 1961.</li>
<li>But outsiders with special licenses can still buy.</li>
<li>Puducherry, on the other hand, earns most of its revenue from alcohol trading.</li>
<li>Bihar has prohibited alcohol consumption entirely, meaning the state’s revenue from liquor consumption is nil.</li>
<li>Its neighbour, Uttar Pradesh, earns the most excise duty on liquor.</li>
<li>The state does not levy VAT but a special duty on liquor, collecting funds for particular purposes.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Do you know?</strong></h4>
<p>Andhra Pradesh, Telangana, Kerala, Karnataka, and Tamil Nadu consume as much as 45 percent of the liquor sold in the country.</p>
<p>Nationally, Maharashtra charges the highest rate but draws only a portion of its revenue from its sales.</p></blockquote>
<h4>Why alcohol isn’t banned everywhere?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Taxes from alcohol sales roughly form a quarter of state revenues.</li>
<li>If this stream suddenly stops, states have to compulsorily cut some important spending.</li>
<li>Also, moderate alcohol consumption may provide some health benefits.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/alcohol-laws-in-india/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Heritage conservation is need of hour</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/heritage/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>ASI</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>heritage conservation</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="heritage " class="alignnone wp-image-628757" height="240" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 456px) 100vw, 456px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/A4564-Conservation-and-protection-of-heritage-monuments-in-India.-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/A4564-Conservation-and-protection-of-heritage-monuments-in-India.-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/A4564-Conservation-and-protection-of-heritage-monuments-in-India.-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/A4564-Conservation-and-protection-of-heritage-monuments-in-India.-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/A4564-Conservation-and-protection-of-heritage-monuments-in-India..jpg 1200w" width="456"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Despite all the public talk of the importance of conserving our national heritage, the budget of the ASI, the primary institutional guardian of monuments, in 2021-22 has been reduced by more than Rs 200 cr.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How do you define heritage?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Heritage is the full range of our inherited traditions, monuments, objects, and culture. Most important, it is the range of contemporary activities, meanings, and behaviours that we draw from them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Threats to Indian Heritage</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Theft:</strong> The incidents of thefts have been observed usually from unprotected monuments, ancient temples. The thefts cases have also been seen in the protected monuments and museums as well. It is due to negligence of security guards in museums, monuments etc.</li>
<li><strong>Smuggling</strong>: illicit traffic and smuggling in antiquities. Illicit traffic is motivated often by profit and sometimes by the demand for luxuries.</li>
<li><strong>Tourism:</strong> Unregulated tourism, tourist activities run by touts, private agents have affected the art heritage places. The Culture Ministry of India has reported that up to 24 Indian monuments have been declared “untraceable” or “missing” by the Archaeological Survey of India (ASI).</li>
<li><strong>Issues with security of museums</strong>: Most of the museums are poorly guarded due to shortage of manpower leading to theft of artifacts, fire accidents etc.</li>
<li><strong>Duplication</strong>: Fakes paintings and art forms leading to threat to livelihoods of artists.</li>
<li><strong>Poor Maintenance</strong>: The state of the wall paintings in Ajanta caves is continuously getting worse, which can be attributed to humidity as well as to a lack of care.</li>
<li><strong>Encroachment on monuments</strong>: Another miss from the ministry has been encroachments of monuments. Over 278 centrally protected monuments have been encroached upon or have illegal occupants, as per government data.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="heritage " class="alignnone wp-image-628759" height="285" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 411px) 100vw, 411px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-10-300x208.webp" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-10-300x208.webp 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-10.webp 630w" width="411"/>Why should we protect our heritage?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Evolution of human consciousness is a continuous process</strong>: History here serves as a laboratory and the past serves as a demarcation to understand the regional laws and social structures. This understanding helps in our progress towards an ideal society.</li>
<li><strong>Pride of country</strong>: The art heritage is the identity and pride of our country. It is duty of every citizen to protect, preserve and perpetuate the cultural richness.</li>
<li><strong>Tourism potential</strong>: for art monuments and museums is very high. Tourism generates revenue for the state as well as private artists due to the money-multiplier quality.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure development:</strong> takes place in and around the areas. Eg. Hampi despite being a small town has excellent infrastructure.</li>
<li><strong>Jobs:</strong> It creates jobs for a lot of people from art industry and tourism industry as well</li>
<li><strong>Sense of belonging</strong>: It creates a feeling of oneness and a sense of attachment by enhancing a sense of belonging to a culture or a region.</li>
<li><strong>Strengthen conviction</strong>: Every historical site has an important story to tell and these stories have inspired many people to strengthen their convictions and commitment to fight injustice and oppression.</li>
<li><strong>Soft power</strong>: Art and culture is also a part of soft power in world politics.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>About Archaeological Survey of India (ASI)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ASI is an attached office of the Ministry of Culture.</li>
<li>It was founded in 1861 by Alexander Cunningham who also became its first Director-General.</li>
<li>Under the provisions of the AMASR Act of 1958, the ASI administers more than 3650 ancient monuments, archaeological sites and remains of national importance.</li>
<li>These can include everything from temples, mosques, churches, tombs, and cemeteries to palaces, forts, step-wells, and rock-cut caves.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Initiatives by ASI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Museums: </strong>ASI’s museums are customarily located right next to the sites that their inventories are associated with “so that they may be studied amid their natural surroundings and not lose focus by being transported”. A dedicated Museums Branch maintains a total of 44 museums spread across the country.</li>
<li><strong>Publications by ASI: </strong>Epigraphia Indica, Ancient India, Indian Archaeology: A Review (Annually).</li>
<li><strong>Library</strong>: <strong>Central Archaeological Library </strong>in the <strong>National Archives building</strong> in Janpath, New Delhi.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues and Challenges ahead of ASI </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>To restore or not: </strong>Issue is that technically speaking- ruins are seldom “restored” in original state. This is because in absence of documentation- archaeologists are left to conjecture what buildings may have looked like when they were originally built.</li>
<li><strong>Personnel Management Issues: </strong>Higher Authorities of ASI are traditionally from IAS Cadre<strong>. </strong>In-house specialist must be promoted for better coordination b/w technical and managerial aspects of restoration</li>
<li><strong>Issues explored in CAG Report: </strong>92 monuments are untraceable with no database on artifacts<strong>. </strong>Poor Documentation of Protected Monuments/Artifacts<strong>. </strong>Paucity of funds (Eg- Red fort gardens lie unkempt).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is the duty of every citizen to value and preserve the rich heritage of our composite culture. Preservation and conservation of India’s rich cultural heritage and promotion of all forms of art and culture, both tangible and intangible, is essential and assumes a lot of importance.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong> Safeguarding the Indian heritage is the need of the moment.</strong> <strong>What are the challenges faced in safeguarding them? What steps would you suggest to protect them?</strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/heritage/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why has the Solomon Islands blocked foreign navy vessels?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/solomon-islands/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Solomon Islands</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Chinese expansion in Pacific</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-494199" height="431" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 451px) 100vw, 451px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-300x287.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-300x287.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-1024x980.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-768x735.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-1536x1471.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-1200x1149.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon.jpg 1600w" width="451"/>After refusing access to US and UK ships to its ports earlier this month, the Solomon Islands has now temporarily halted all naval visits.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The country’s move is a departure from the norm and is been seen as an attempt to appease China.</li>
<li>This raises concerns about China’s growing influence in the country and the region at large.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where is the Solomon Islands located?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Solomon Islands is a sovereign country consisting of six major islands and over 900 smaller islands in Oceania, to the east of Papua New Guinea and northwest of Vanuatu.</li>
<li>Its capital, Honiara, is located on the largest island, Guadalcanal.</li>
<li>It is part of the ethnically Melanesian group of islands in the Pacific and lies between Papua New Guinea and Vanuatu.</li>
<li>The country takes its name from the Solomon Islands archipelago, which is a collection of Melanesian islands that also includes the North Solomon Islands (a part of Papua New Guinea).</li>
<li>It excludes outlying islands, such as the Santa Cruz Islands and Rennell and Bellona.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Quick recap of its past</h4>
<ul>
<li>The islands, which were initially controlled by the British Empire during the colonial era, went through the hands of Germany and Japan.</li>
<li>It then went back to the UK after the Americans took over the islands from the Japanese during World War II.</li>
<li>The islands became independent in 1978 to become a constitutional monarchy under the British Crown, with a parliamentary system of government.</li>
<li>Nevertheless, its inability to manage domestic ethnic conflicts led to close security relations with Australia, which is the traditional first responder to any crisis in the South Pacific.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did China enter the picture?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Earlier this year, the Solomon Islands established a <strong><u>security agreement with China</u></strong>, saying it needed Beijing’s assistance with its domestic security situation.</li>
<li>But the <strong><u>announcement had rattled the west</u></strong>, esp. the US, Australia and others in the Indo-Pacific region.</li>
<li>The concerns were that the agreement could potentially lead to a <strong><u>Chinese military base on the island nation</u></strong> and a gain in power-projection capabilities.</li>
<li>At that time, following intense scrutiny, the Solomon Islands had <strong><u>denied</u></strong> that the agreement would allow China to establish a naval base.</li>
<li>The Island insisted that the agreement was only to <strong><u>assist the Solomon Islands with what he called “hard internal threats”.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the Solomon Islands’ stance?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The government has asked all partner countries with plans to conduct naval visits or patrols to put them on hold until a <strong><u>revised national mechanism</u></strong> is in place.</li>
<li>The revised national mechanism <strong><u>applied to all foreign vessels seeking access to the country’s ports</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The nation wanted to <strong><u>build up its</u></strong> <strong><u>own naval capacity</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It has some <strong><u>unfortunate experiences of foreign naval vessels entering its waters</u></strong> without any diplomatic clearance.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is behind China’s growing influence in the region?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There is no dispute that China has been rapidly increasing its presence and influence in the region for over three decades, particularly in the South Pacific.</li>
<li>Certainly Beijing views the Pacific Island region as an <strong><u>important component of its Belt and Road Initiative (BRI). </u></strong></li>
<li>Specifically, it sees the region as a critical air freight hub in its so-called <strong><u>Air Silk Road</u></strong>, which connects Asia with Central and South America.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Concerns of the West</h4>
<ul>
<li>The United States and its regional allies, such as Australia and New Zealand, are concerned that the China-Solomon Islands security pact allows Chinese naval vessels to replenish there.</li>
<li>That could open the <strong><u>door to a Chinese naval base</u></strong>, which would significantly extend China’s military reach in the South Pacific.”</li>
<li>It is likely that this security agreement between China and the Solomon Islands has been driven by, what the CFR calls, Beijing’s “<strong><u>sense of vulnerability</u></strong>” in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the rationale for the Solomon Islands’ increasing proximity to China?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Solomon Islands had cultivated strong ties with Taiwan, which ended with the emergence of the current government in Honiara.</li>
<li>In 2019, the regime change switched Taiwan for China.</li>
<li>This was supposedly after Beijing offered half a billion US dollars in financial aid, roughly five times what Taiwan spent on the islands in the past two decades.</li>
<li>It has been alleged by the pro-Taiwan Opposition that the incumbent government has been bribed by China.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is China interested in the Solomon Islands?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Isolating Taiwan:</strong> The Solomon Islands was one among the six Pacific island states which had official bilateral relations with Taiwan.</li>
<li><strong>Supporter in UN:</strong> The small Pacific island states act as potential vote banks for mobilising support for the great powers in international fora like the United Nations.</li>
<li><strong>Larger EEZ:</strong> These states have disproportionately large maritime Exclusive Economic Zones when compared to their small sizes.</li>
<li><strong>Natural resources:</strong> Solomon Islands, in particular, have significant reserves of timber and mineral resources, along with fisheries.</li>
<li><strong>Countering US:</strong> But more importantly, they are strategically located for China to insert itself between America’s military bases in the Pacific islands and Australia.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What does this mean for the established geopolitical configuration in the region?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Diminishing western influence:</strong> The Pacific islands, in the post-World War II scenario, were exclusively under the spheres of influence of the Western powers, in particular, the US, UK, France and Australia and New Zealand.</li>
<li><strong>Inserting into western hegemony:</strong> All of them have territorial possessions in the region, with the three nuclear powers among them having used the region as a nuclear weapons testing ground.</li>
<li><strong>Shifting of dependencies:</strong> The smaller island nations of the region are heavily dependent on them, especially Australia as it is a resident power.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Damage control by West</h4>
<ul>
<li>Australia has reacted with boosted finances, and by extending its current security mission till 2023 when the islands will host the Pacific Games.</li>
<li>The US has responded by considering reopening its embassy in Honiara after a long 29-year gap.</li>
<li>New Zealand has shed its typical restraint about China and has criticised it for attempting to militarise the Pacific islands.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/solomon-islands/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Electricity Amendment Bill 2022 – Addressing the transition and equity</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/electricity/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of the bill</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>electricity reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="electricity" class="alignnone wp-image-629013" height="343" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download.jpeg" width="558"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Concerns of states on some provisions of the new Electricity Bill are justified. But the legislation proposes welcome correctives to longstanding problems of the power sector.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Important provisions of the bill</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Payment security</strong>: The Bill provides that electricity will not be scheduled or despatched if adequate payment security is not provided by the discom.   The central government may prescribe rules regarding payment security.</li>
<li><strong>Contract enforcement</strong>: The Bill empowers the CERC and SERCs to adjudicate disputes related to the performance of contracts.  These refer to contracts related to the sale, purchase, or transmission of electricity.  Further, the Commissions will have powers of a Civil Court.</li>
<li><strong>Renewable purchase obligation</strong>: The Act empowers SERCs to specify renewable purchase obligations (RPO) for discoms.  RPO refers to the mandate to procure a certain percentage of electricity from renewable sources.  The Bill adds that RPO should not be below a minimum percentage prescribed by the central government.  Failure to meet RPO will be punishable with a penalty between 25 paise and 50 paise per kilowatt of the shortfall.</li>
<li><strong>Selection committee for SERCs</strong>: Under the Act, the Chairperson of the Central Electricity Authority or the Chairperson of the CERC is one of the members of the selection committee to recommend appointments to the SERCs.  Under the Bill, instead of this person, the central government will nominate a member to the selection committee.  The nominee should not be below the rank of Additional Secretary to the central government.</li>
<li><strong>Composition of Commissions and APTEL</strong>: The Bill increases the number of members (including the chairperson) in SERCs from three to four.  Further, at least one member in both the CERC and SERCs must be from law background.  Under the Act, Appellate Tribunal for Electricity (APTEL) consists of a chairperson and three other members.  The Bill instead provides that the APTEL will have three or more members, as may be prescribed by the central government.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>State apprehensions of the bill </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multi state license: </strong>The clause pertaining to applicants seeking a distribution licence in more than one state. It states that the Central Electricity Regulatory Commission (CERC), and not the SERC, will grant the licence. This is problematic because a SERC is likely to be more aware of the field-level conditions in a state than its central counterpart.</li>
<li><strong>Centre can bypass state: </strong>The Bill has a provision empowering the Centre to give directions directly to the SERCs. Till now, the CERC received instructions from the Centre and the SERCs were under the state. The new Bill enables the Centre to bypass state governments. It’s not surprising that this is a matter of concern for the states.</li>
<li><strong>Direct appointment by centre:</strong> The Bill states that the SERC chairperson will now be a nominee of the central government and will be an additional secretary-level official. This gives the impression that the Centre is trying to control the appointments to the SERCs<strong>. </strong></li>
</ul>
<div class="mceTemp"></div>
<p><img alt="electricity" class="alignnone wp-image-629016" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 481px) 100vw, 481px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy-300x208.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy-300x208.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy.jpg 650w" width="481"/></p>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/power-sector-reforms/"><strong>Why the bill is important? </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Compensation clause: </strong>The Bill states that if power purchase agreement PPAs are renegotiated, the affected party has to be compensated within 90 days from the date of submission of the petition.</li>
<li><strong>Uniformity in tariffs revision:</strong> New tariffs have to be made applicable from the beginning of the financial year. New tariffs often come into force in the middle of the financial year (due to delays in the issuing of orders by SERCs). This means that discoms do not earn their full revenues leading to cash flow problems.</li>
<li><strong>Easy tariff petition processing now:</strong> The Bill has proposed a reduction in the time for processing tariff petitions from 120 days to 90 days.</li>
<li><strong>Suo moto jurisdiction</strong>: Regulatory commissions have been given suo motu jurisdiction if tariff petitions are not filed within 30 days of the stipulated time. This too is a step in the right direction.</li>
<li><strong>More teeth to load dispatcher: </strong>the Bill proposes to give more teeth to the national load dispatcher. We need to strengthen the load dispatcher for the smooth functioning of the grid, especially with a huge renewable capacity where intermittency of generation is a major issue in the offing.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The rollout of the proposed amendments through a consensus-based approach would go a long way in overhauling the weakest link in the nation’s power supply chain.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Electricity Bill 2022 is a remedy worse than the disease afflicting India’s power sector. Critically analyse.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/electricity/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Cervavac: India’s first indigenously developed Vaccine for Cervical Cancer</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cervavac-vaccine-for-cervical-cancer/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Cervavac, Cervical cancer</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Menstrual hygiene and related diseases</p></div></div><p><img alt="Cervavax" class="alignnone wp-image-629407" height="271" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 465px) 100vw, 465px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cervavac-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cervavac-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cervavac.jpg 645w" width="465"/></p>
<p>Union Minister of Science and Technology has announced the scientific completion of Cervavac, India’s first indigenously developed quadrivalent human papillomavirus (qHPV) vaccine for the prevention of cervical cancer.</p>
<h4>What is Cervavac?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Cervavac was developed by the Pune-based Serum Institute of India in coordination with the Department of Biotechnology (DBT).</li>
<li>The project to develop the vaccine was implemented by the then secretary of the DBT, Dr. M K Bhan in 2011.</li>
<li>Since then, 30 meetings of scientific advisory groups and site visits conducted by DBT have helped review the scientific merit of the entire journey to develop the vaccine.</li>
<li>Cervavac received market authorisation approval from the Drug Controller General of India on July 12 this year.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is so unique about Cervavac?</h4>
<ul>
<li>HPV vaccines are given in two doses and data has shown that the antibodies that develop after both are administered can last up to six or seven years.</li>
<li>Unlike Covid vaccines, booster shots may not be required for the cervical cancer vaccine.</li>
<li>Until now, the HPV vaccines available in India were produced by foreign manufacturers at an approximate cost of Rs 2,000 to Rs 3,500 per dose.</li>
<li>Cervavac is likely to be significantly cheaper, slated to cost approximately Rs 200 to 400.</li>
<li>It has also demonstrated a robust antibody response that is nearly 1,000 times higher than the baseline against all targeted HPV types and in all dose and age groups.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of the vaccine</h4>
<ul>
<li>Despite being largely preventable, cervical cancer is the fourth most common cancer among women globally, according to the WHO.</li>
<li>In 2018, an estimated 57000 women were diagnosed with the disease and it accounted for 311,000 deaths across the world.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How common is cervical cancer in India?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India accounts for about a fifth of the global burden of cervical cancer, with 1.23 lakh cases and around 67,000 deaths per year.</li>
<li>Almost all cervical cancer cases are linked to certain strains of human papillomavirus (HPV), a common virus that is transmitted through sexual contact.</li>
<li>The body’s immune system usually gets rid of the HPV infection naturally within two years.</li>
<li>However, in a small percentage of people, the virus can linger over time and turn some normal cells into abnormal cells and then cancer.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How dangerous is cervical cancer?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Cervical cancer is preventable if detected early and managed effectively.</li>
<li>Screening and vaccination are two powerful tools that are available for preventing cervical cancer.</li>
<li>Still, there is little awareness among women about the prevention of this cancer and less than 10% of Indian women get screened.</li>
<li>All women aged 30-49 must get screened for cervical cancer even if they have no symptoms and get their adolescent daughters vaccinated with the HPV vaccine.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the challenges?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The biggest task will be in allocating adequate resources and manpower for vaccinating the massive demographic of adolescent girls aged between 9 and 15, to ensure that they are protected from HPV early.</li>
<li>There is a huge need for stepping up awareness about the disease and the vaccine in the community.</li>
<li>Unlike Covid and the vaccination programme, there is very little awareness about cervical cancer.</li>
<li>Overall awareness and screening are very low in the community and that is a concern.</li>
<li>Since this is a preventable disease and hence a huge awareness programme is required</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>School-based vaccination programmes might work effectively.</li>
<li>Currently, none exist and therefore planning will have to be done along those lines.</li>
<li>Those accessing public health programmes will get the vaccine free of cost at government-aided schools.</li>
<li>However concerted efforts will have to be made to ensure the involvement of private healthcare facilities and NGOs towards an effective rollout.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cervavac-vaccine-for-cervical-cancer/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Urban planning can change the future of cities to happy cities</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-planning/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Urbanization issues</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Urban planning" class="alignnone wp-image-629340" height="285" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 506px) 100vw, 506px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city.jpg 1280w" width="506"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the recent few years, the growth of the economy and urbanization have accelerated. Rapid unplanned urbanization has put extreme pressure on natural resources.</li>
<li>Unplanned urbanization, however, exerts great strain on our cities. In fact, the Covid-19 pandemic has revealed the dire need for the planning and management of our cities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does urban planning mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Urban planning, also known as regional planning, town planning, city planning is a technical and political process that is focused on the development and design of land use and the built environment, including air, water, and the infrastructure passing into and out of urban areas, such as transportation, communications, and distribution networks and their accessibility.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are ‘Happy Cities’?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A term that follows the Green City, Sustainable City, Liveable City, in the lingo of urban planning</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a smart city?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A smart city is one that uses information and communication technologies to enhance citizen engagement. It is a neo-vision which seeks to improve the delivery of services in urban areas. The following story maps out the steps being taken by India to explore this concept in practice.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Smart Cities Mission?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sustainable cities</strong>: The Smart Cities Mission aims at developing 100 cities, which were shortlisted, into self-sustainable urban settlements.</li>
<li><strong>Chronology</strong>: The mission was launched on June 25, 2015 and was projected as one aimed at transforming the process of urban development in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Comprehensive revamp</strong>: Among its strategic components is ‘area-based development’, which includes city improvement (retrofitting), city renewal (redevelopment) and city extension (Greenfield development), plus a pan-city initiative in which ‘smart solutions’ are applied covering larger parts of the city.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Fast Facts – Urbanization in India</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Most Urbanized States: Tamil Nadu 43.9%; Maharashtra 4%; Gujarat  37.4%</li>
<li>3 out of world’s 21 mega cities: Mumbai (19 mill); Delhi (15 mill); Kolkata (14 mill)</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Urban planning" class="alignnone wp-image-629341" height="216" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 514px) 100vw, 514px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84-300x126.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84-300x126.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84.jpg 450w" width="514"/>Urban planning challenges </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Planning</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Many urban governments lack a modern planning framework</li>
<li>The multiplicity of local bodies obstructs efficient planning and land use</li>
<li>Rigid master plans and restrictive zoning regulations limit the land available for building, constricting cities’ abilities to grow in accordance with changing needs<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Housing</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Building regulations that limit urban density – such as floor space indexes – reduce the number of houses available, thereby pushing up property prices</li>
<li>Outdated rent control regulations reduce the number of houses available on rent – a critical option for the poor</li>
<li>Policy, planning, and regulation deficiencies lead to a proliferation of slums</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Service delivery</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is a strong bias towards adding physical infrastructure rather than providing financially and environmentally sustainable services</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Infrastructure</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Most urban bodies do not generate the revenues needed to renew infrastructure, nor do they have the creditworthiness to access capital markets for funds</li>
<li>Urban transport planning needs to be more holistic – there is a focus on moving vehicles rather than meeting the needs of the large numbers of people who walk or ride bicycles in India’s towns and cities.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Environment:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The deteriorating urban environment is taking a toll on people’s health and productivity and diminishing their quality of life.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Urban planning" class="alignnone wp-image-629343" height="301" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 572px) 100vw, 572px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120.jpg 1200w" width="572"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-reforms-in-urban-planning-capacity-in-india/">Solution offered by NITI ayog committee report on urban planning</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Demystifying Planning and Involving Citizens: </strong>While it is important to maintain the master plans’ technical rigour, it is equally important to demystify them for enabling citizens’ participation at relevant stages. Therefore, the committee strongly recommends a ‘Citizen Outreach Campaign’ for demystifying urban planning.</li>
<li><strong>Steps for Enhancing the Role of Private Sector: </strong>The report recommends that concerted measures must be taken at multiple levels to strengthen the role of the private sector to improve the overall planning capacity in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Revision of Town and Country Planning Acts: </strong>Most States have enacted the Town and Country Planning acts, that enable them to prepare and notify master plans for implementation. However, many need to be reviewed and upgraded.</li>
<li><strong>Revision of Town and Country Planning Acts: </strong>Most States have enacted the Town and Country Planning Acts, that enable them to prepare and notify master plans for implementation. However, many need to be reviewed and upgraded.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Interesting fact </strong></p>
<p>India is home to 11% of the total global urban population.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Government initiatives</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Atal Mission for Rejuvenation and Urban Transformation (AMRUT);</li>
<li>Pradhan Mantri Awas Yojana (PMAY) – Housing for all (Urban),</li>
<li>Smart Cities Mission (SCM),</li>
<li>Swachh Bharat Mission (SBM),</li>
<li>Heritage City Development and Augmentation Yojana (HRIDAY);</li>
<li>Deen Dayal Antyodaya Yojana – National Urban Livelihoods Mission (DAY-NULM).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>What is now increasingly understood, is that urban planning and design can be a powerful contributor to the happiness of citizens. The structure and layout of our streets, the availability of green spaces, the possibility of using urban spaces freely, the inclusion of beauty in public space.</li>
<li>It is safe to assume that when there are avenues for a community to come together in a pleasant environment, which is accessible to everyone, it can only increase well-being.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>Can urban planning and design change Indian cities to be happy cities? Express your views by addressing the roadblocks in the same.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-planning/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Glass ceiling needs to be broken to unlock women potential</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/glass-ceiling/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Government schemes</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Gender issues</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="glass ceiling" class="alignnone wp-image-629351" height="337" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 598px) 100vw, 598px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/360x203-large-xl_image_16_9-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/360x203-large-xl_image_16_9-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/360x203-large-xl_image_16_9.jpg 360w" width="598"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to available UNESCO data on some selected countries, India is at the lowest position, having only 14% female researchers working in STEM areas highlighting the presence of glass ceiling.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is glass ceiling? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A glass ceiling is a metaphor used to represent an invisible barrier that prevents women from rising beyond a certain level in a hierarchy. The metaphor was first coined by feminists in reference to barriers in the careers of high-achieving women.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What Is a Gender-equal Society?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A society in which both women and men shall be given equal opportunities to participate voluntarily in activities in all fields as equal partners, and be able to enjoy political, economic, social and cultural benefits equally as well as to share responsibilities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How glass ceiling limits women progress?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Few opportunities</strong>: Due to deep-rooted biases, it is difficult for women to access many experiences and networks that are easily accessible to men.</li>
<li><strong>Social barriers and gender norms</strong>: Personal barriers include notions of compromise and sacrifice that are ingrained in women. This feeds into how women present themselves. External barriers and cultural cues reinforce how men and women “ought” to behave.</li>
<li><strong>Gender Inequity</strong>: Stereotypes related to gender brilliance or gender-based intrinsic aptitude generate inequity which remains unnoticed.</li>
<li><strong>Low self-confidence</strong>: Our socio-cultural constructs reflect absolute patriarchy causing even women to be sceptical about their abilities, to accept the roles set for them in the household.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="glass ceiling " class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-629352" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/depositphotos_327428002-stock-illustration-gender-inequality-in-employment-we-300x300.webp" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/depositphotos_327428002-stock-illustration-gender-inequality-in-employment-we-300x300.webp 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/depositphotos_327428002-stock-illustration-gender-inequality-in-employment-we-150x150.webp 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/depositphotos_327428002-stock-illustration-gender-inequality-in-employment-we.webp 600w" width="300"/>The gender gap in employment</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Around the world, finding a job is much tougher for women than it is for men. When women are employed, they tend to work in low-quality jobs in vulnerable conditions, and there is little improvement forecast in the near future.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="glass ceiling" class="alignnone wp-image-629355" height="261" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 386px) 100vw, 386px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ilustration-two-persons-at-different-high-300x203.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ilustration-two-persons-at-different-high-300x203.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ilustration-two-persons-at-different-high.jpeg 696w" width="386"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-why-are-there-more-men-than-women-in-the-field-of-stem/">What are STEM areas?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>STEM stands for science, technology, engineering and mathematics and refers to any subjects that fall under these four disciplines.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the drivers at policy and programme level to promote women in STEM in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Breaking myths and stereotypes around STEM is crucial to achieve the UN’s Sustainable Development Goal 5 (gender equality) which includes women’s use of enabling technology, including ICT as a means of achieving economic empowerment and greater agency and also many other STEM-related SDGs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="glass ceiling" class="alignnone wp-image-629353" height="267" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 456px) 100vw, 456px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/KIRAN-Women-Scientist-Scheme-B-300x176.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/KIRAN-Women-Scientist-Scheme-B-300x176.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/KIRAN-Women-Scientist-Scheme-B-768x450.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/KIRAN-Women-Scientist-Scheme-B.jpg 1000w" width="456"/>Government initiatives </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>GATI: </strong>It will be called GATI (Gender Advancement through Transforming Institutions). The DST is incorporating a system of grading institutes depending on the enrolment of women and the advancement of the careers of women faculty and scientists.</li>
<li><strong>CURIE</strong>: For infrastructure in women’s universities</li>
<li><strong>Vigyan Jyoti Scheme</strong>: Encourage girls in high school to pursue STEM</li>
<li><strong>The Athena Swan Charter: </strong>is a framework which is used across the globe to support and transform gender equality within higher education (HE) and research.</li>
<li><strong>KIRAN</strong>: (Knowledge Involvement in Research Advancement through nurturing) Scheme to encourage women Scientists</li>
<li><strong>Indo-US Fellowship:</strong> for Women in STEMM (STEM and Medicine)</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Gender equality or parity will happen only when there is a change in mind-set and institutions consider women as assets rather than simply a diversity rectification issue. Policies that help women advance in science and society globally are needed. The world cannot afford to miss out on what women have to offer.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you understand by the term glass ceiling? Discuss how it has hampered the women participation in high end research STEM jobs by citing some government initiatives to address this.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/glass-ceiling/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How India adopted its military flags and badges based on Lord Mountbatten’s suggestions?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/how-india-adopted-its-military-flags-and-badges-mountbattens/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Flags and defence insignia</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-629568" height="152" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/navy-300x152.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/navy-300x152.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/navy.jpg 621w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The new Naval Ensign (flag), which will be unveiled by PM in Kochi, has brought into focus the flags and ranks adopted by the Indian military after Independence.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Do you know?</strong></p>
<p>The octagonal shape with twin golden borders draws inspiration from the seal of the great Indian emperor, Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj, whose visionary maritime outlook established a credible naval fleet</p></blockquote>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Documents accessed from <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-national-archives-of-india/">National Archives of India</a> show that Lord Mountbatten, former Viceroy and Governor General of India, played a major role in suggesting new flags and rank badges.</li>
<li>This was when India was about to become a Republic on January 26, 1950.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When did India switch from British-era flags and ranks?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The switch from British-era flags and ranks took place when India became a Republic (26<sup>th</sup> Jan, 1950).</li>
<li>Prior to that the flags and badges of ranks of the military were of the British pattern.</li>
<li>The new, Indian pattern of flags of Army, Navy and Air Force, and also the Regimental Flags of the Army and badges of ranks of all three services were adopted on January 26, 1950.</li>
<li>The ‘Kings Commission’ granted to Indian military officers was also changed to ‘Indian Commission’ on the same date.</li>
<li>And at a subsequent date the King’s Colours of the various Regiments were laid to rest in Indian Military Academy (IMA), Dehradun.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When did Lord Mountbatten come into the picture?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The national archives have files, dated 1949, that include a detailed note from Lord Mountbatten regarding names, flags and ranks of the armed forces, and then PM Nehru’s letter to the then Defence Minister Baldev Singh regarding Mountbatten’s suggestions.</li>
<li>The note, archives reveal, was given to Nehru by Lord Mountbatten when the two met in London.</li>
<li>The note was forwarded from the PM’s office to the office of then Governor General C Rajagopalachari on May 24, 1949, stating that it is on the issue of ‘Names and Insignia of Indian Armed Forces’ after India becomes a Republic.</li>
<li>The letter also stated that the note should be placed before the Governor General.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What did Lord Mountbatten say in the note?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The note begins by saying that consequent to becoming a Republic the word ‘Royal’ shall be dropped from India’s Army, Navy and Air Force.</li>
<li>Mountbatten strongly recommended that no other word like ‘State’ of ‘Republican’ should replace the word ‘Royal’.</li>
<li>This was because it would have the effect of separating the forces of India psychologically from the other services in the Commonwealth.</li>
<li>He further suggested in the letter that the Crown should be replaced from the insignias and replaced by the “three lions of Ashoka”.</li>
<li>Regarding the Naval Ensign, he said that all Commonwealth navies fly the same flag which consists of a large white flag with a red-cross and Union Jack in the upper corner nearer the staff and is known as the ‘White Ensign’.</li>
<li>The new Ensign, the note suggested, should continue to have the red-cross but the Indian national flag should replace the Union Jack.</li>
<li>He suggested this to maintain commonality with the Commonwealth flags.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What changes did Mountbatten suggest for uniforms?</h4>
<ul>
<li>He strongly urged that existing uniforms should be changed as little as possible.</li>
<li>He added that the Crown worn on badges of ranks of Majors and above should be replaced by the “three lions of Ashoka”.</li>
<li>The Star of the Order of the Bath should be replaced by Star of India or another form of star.</li>
<li>He also suggested that the crossed sword and baton on the badges of ranks of Generals should be retained.</li>
<li>The former Viceroy advocated retaining the stripes of rank in Navy and Air Force saying these were internationally almost the same.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did the Indian government react to Mountbatten’s suggestions?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Nehru wrote to the then defence minister in September 1949 saying that he agreed with the suggestions made by the former Governor General that there should be as little change as possible.</li>
<li>The then PM particularly mentioned the changes suggested by Mountbatten for the Navy.</li>
<li>Then Governor General C Rajagopalachari also wrote back to Nehru in May 1949 itself agreeing to Mountbatten’s suggestions.</li>
<li>In the end, Mountbatten’s suggestions were virtually all accepted and implemented with effect from January 26, 1950.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/how-india-adopted-its-military-flags-and-badges-mountbattens/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Importance of Tibetan Democracy Day</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/importance-of-tibetan-democracy-day/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Tibetan Democracy Day</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India's asylum to Tibetans</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-629405" height="217" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 387px) 100vw, 387px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tibet-300x168.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tibet-300x168.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tibet-1024x573.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tibet-768x430.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tibet.jpg 1118w" width="387"/></p>
<p>A little more than six decades ago, Tibetan Democracy Day was marked with the inauguration of the Tibetan government-in-exile in Dharamshala on September 2.</p>
<h4>Tibetan Democracy Day</h4>
<ul>
<li>In February 1960, a little less than a year after he crossed over into India, the Fourteenth Dalai Lama outlined in Bodh Gaya, where The Buddha attained Enlightenment, a detailed program of democratic practice for exiled Tibetans.</li>
<li>According to the website of the Tibetan Parliament-in-Exile (TPiE), he advised them to set up an elected body with three exiled representatives each from the three provinces, and one each from the four religious schools of Tibetan Buddhism.</li>
<li>After elections were held, 13 elected representatives, called ‘Deputies’, were designated as the ‘Commission of Tibetan People’s Deputies’ (CTPD). They took oath on September 2, 1960.</li>
<li>Subsequently from 1975 onward, this date began to be formally observed as Tibetan Democracy Day.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Parliament-in-Exile</h4>
<ul>
<li>The TPiE is the highest legislative body of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-extends-relief-to-tibetan-committee-by-5-years/">Central Tibetan Administration (CTA).</a></li>
<li>It is described as one of the three pillars of Tibetan democratic governance — the others being the Judiciary and the Kashag, or Executive.</li>
<li>The website of the TPiE underlines the Dalai Lama’s commitment to the democratic principle — it quotes the Dalai Lama from the Foreword to the Constitution for Tibet, drafted in 1963:</li>
<li>The CTA is based in Dharamsala, Himachal Pradesh.</li>
<li>Elections are held every five years to elect Members of the TPiE, and their Sikyong (Prime Minister). The 16th TPiE was elected in 2016.</li>
<li>This was the second direct election after the Dalai Lama distanced himself from the political functioning of the TPiE in 2011.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Government-in-Exile</h4>
<ul>
<li>On March 10, 1963, the Dalai Lama promulgated the Constitution of the Tibetan Government-in-Exile (TGiE).</li>
<li>From 1991 onwards, TPiE became the legislative organ of the CTA, the Tibetan Supreme Justice Commission became the judicial organ, and the Kashag the executive organ.</li>
<li>The TGiE is not recognised officially by any country, including India.</li>
<li>However, many countries, including the US, deal directly with the Sikyong and other Tibetan leaders through various forums.</li>
<li>The TPiE says its democratically elected character helps it manage Tibetan affairs, and raise the Tibetan issue across the world.</li>
<li>The current Sikyong (known as Kalön Tripa until 2012) of the CTA is Lobsang Sangay, who has been the head of the Kashag or Cabinet (first as Kalön Tripa and then as Sikyong) since 2011.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is India’s official policy towards the CTA?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India considers the Dalai Lama as a revered religious leader and an honored guest, but it does not encourage political activities by Tibetans.</li>
<li>It does not recognize any separate government of Tibet functioning in India.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/importance-of-tibetan-democracy-day/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Abnormal’ La Nina conditions impacting India’s monsoon</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/abnormal-la-nina-conditions/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>El-Nino, La-Nina</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>ENSO impact on Indian Monsson</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-629410" height="359" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 549px) 100vw, 549px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/la-nina-300x196.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/la-nina-300x196.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/la-nina-1024x669.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/la-nina-768x502.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/la-nina.jpg 1038w" width="549"/></p>
<p>In what may be termed as an uncommon ocean phenomenon, the prevailing La Nina conditions over the equatorial Pacific Ocean have entered the third consecutive year.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The current <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/is-la-nina-a-fair-weather-friend-of-our-country/">La Nina</a> phase has been prevailing since September 2020.</li>
<li>Since the 1950s, La Nina lasting for more than two years has been recorded only on six instances (see graph below), data by the India Meteorological Department (IMD) stated.</li>
<li>It confirmed that India’s La Nina conditions are here to stay till the end of 2022.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is El Nino and La Nina?</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-356942" height="216" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 487px) 100vw, 487px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/enso-300x133.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/enso-300x133.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/enso.jpg 708w" width="487"/></p>
<ul>
<li>While El Nino (Spanish for ‘little boy’), the more common expression, is the abnormal surface warming observed along the eastern and central regions of the Pacific Ocean (the region between Peru and Papua New Guinea).</li>
<li>The La Nina (Spanish for ‘little girl’) is an abnormal cooling of these surface waters.</li>
<li>Together, the El Nino (Warm Phase) and La Nina (Cool Phase) phenomena are termed as El Nino Southern Oscillation (ENSO).</li>
<li>These are large-scale ocean phenomena that influence the global weather — winds, temperature and rainfall. They have the ability to trigger extreme weather events like droughts, floods, hot and cold conditions, globally.</li>
<li>Each cycle can last anywhere between 9 to 12 months, at times extendable to 18 months — and re-occur after every three to five years.</li>
<li>Meteorologists record the sea surface temperatures for four different regions, known as Nino regions, along this equatorial belt.</li>
<li>Depending on the temperatures, they forecast either as an El Nino, an ENSO neutral phase, or a La Nina.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why has La Nina conditions continued for 3 years?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is surprising that it has continued for the last three years. It may be good for India but not for some other countries.</li>
<li>Under <strong><u>climate change conditions</u></strong>, one must expect more such instances. Climate change could be a factor driving such anomalous conditions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with La Nina</h4>
<ul>
<li>La Nina years are infamous for <strong><u>frequent and intense hurricanes and cyclones</u></strong> in the Atlantic Ocean and the Bay of Bengal.</li>
<li>Chances of more cyclones are likely due to multiple aiding factors, including <strong><u>high relative moisture and relative low wind shear over the Bay of Bengal.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this PYQ:</strong></h4>
<p><strong> Q. La Nina is suspected to have caused recent floods in Australia. How is La Nina different from El Nino?</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>La Nina is characterized by unusually cold ocean temperature in equatorial Indian Ocean whereas El Nino is characterized by unusually warm ocean temperature in the equatorial Pacific Ocean.</li>
<li>El Nino has an adverse effect on south-west monsoon of India, but La Nina has no effect on monsoon climate.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Which of the statements given above is/are correct?</strong></p>
<p>(a) Only 1</p>
<p>(b) Only 2</p>
<p>(c) Both 1 and 2</p>
<p>(d) Neither 1 nor 2</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/abnormal-la-nina-conditions/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>UN accuses China of Uighur rights abuses</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/xinjiang-leak-puts-uighur-in-spotlight/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Uighurs</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Blatant human rights violations worldwide and lobbying against India</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-547953" height="400" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/uyghr.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/uyghr.jpg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/uyghr-300x200.jpg 300w" width="600"/></p>
<p>The UN accused China of serious human rights violations that may amount to “crimes against humanity” in a report examining a crackdown on Uighurs and other ethnic groups.</p>
<h4>What is the leak about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>After initially denying their existence, Beijing has claimed the facilities are vocational training schools, attended voluntarily and aimed at stamping out religious extremism.</li>
<li>But the leaked documents give an insight into how leaders saw the minority population as a security threat.</li>
<li>Photos appear to show officers restraining hooded and shackled inmates with batons, while other guards wearing camouflage stand by with firearms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who are the Uighurs?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There are about 12 million Uighurs, mostly Muslim, living in north-western China in the region of Xinjiang, officially known as the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region (XUAR).</li>
<li>The Uighurs speak their own language, similar to Turkish, and see themselves as culturally and ethnically close to Central Asian nations.</li>
<li>They make up less than half of the Xinjiang population.</li>
<li>In recent decades, there’s been a mass migration of Han Chinese (China’s ethnic majority) to Xinjiang, and the Uighurs feel their culture and livelihoods are under threat.</li>
<li>In the early 20th Century, the Uighurs briefly declared independence, but the region was brought under complete control of mainland China’s new Communist government in 1949.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where is Xinjiang?</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-395897" height="374" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 456px) 100vw, 456px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/xing.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/xing.jpg 456w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/xing-300x246.jpg 300w" width="456"/></p>
<ul>
<li>Xinjiang lies in the north-west of China and is the country’s biggest region.</li>
<li>Like Tibet, it is autonomous, meaning – in theory – it has some powers of self-governance. But in practice, both face major restrictions by the central government.</li>
<li>It is a mostly desert region, producing about a fifth of the world’s cotton.</li>
<li>It is also rich in oil and natural gas and because of its proximity to Central Asia and Europe is seen by Beijing as an important trade link.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this PYQ:</strong></h4>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Q.Very recently, in which of the following countries have lakhs of people either suffered from severe famine/acute malnutrition or died due to starvation caused by war/ethnic conflicts?</strong><br/>
(a) Angola and Zambia<br/>
(b) Morocco and Tunisia<br/>
(c) Venezuela and Colombia<br/>
(d) Yemen and South Sudan</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<h4>What was the build-up to the Uighur crackdown?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Anti-Han and separatist sentiment rose in Xinjiang from the 1990s, flaring into violence on occasion.</li>
<li>In 2009 some 200 people died in clashes in Xinjiang, which the Chinese blamed on Uighurs who want their own state.</li>
<li>Xinjiang is now covered by a pervasive network of surveillance, including police, checkpoints, and cameras that scan everything from number plates to individual faces.</li>
<li>According to Human Rights Watch, police are also using a mobile app to monitor peoples’ behaviour, such as how much electricity they are using and how often they use their front door.</li>
<li>Since 2017 when President Xi Jinping issued an order saying all religions in China should be Chinese in orientation, there have been further crackdowns.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Chinese narrative</h4>
<ul>
<li>China says the crackdown is necessary to prevent terrorism and root out Islamist extremism and the camps are an effective tool for re-educating inmates in its fight against terrorism.</li>
<li>It insists that Uighur militants are waging a violent campaign for an independent state by plotting bombings, sabotage and civic unrest.</li>
<li>China has dismissed claims it is trying to reduce the Uighur population through mass sterilizations as “baseless”, and says allegations of forced labor are “completely fabricated”.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/xinjiang-leak-puts-uighur-in-spotlight/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Effecting the Ban on Single-Use Plastics</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/effecting-the-ban-on-single-use-plastics/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Single use plastics</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Need for plastic waste management</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-629408" height="234" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 355px) 100vw, 355px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-300x198.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-300x198.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1024x675.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-768x506.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1536x1013.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1200x791.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1980x1306.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban.jpg 2000w" width="355"/></p>
<p>Since July 1, 2022, India has banned the manufacture, import, stocking, distribution, sale, and use of single-use plastics (SUP) items with low utility and high littering potential.</p>
<h4>What are single-use plastics?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Single-use plastics, often also referred to as <strong><u>disposable plastics</u></strong>, are commonly used for plastic packaging and include items intended to be <strong><u>used only once</u></strong> before they are thrown away or recycled.</li>
<li>These include, among other items, grocery bags, food packaging, bottles, straws, containers, cups and cutlery.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why are single-use plastics harmful?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The purpose of single-use plastics is to use them once or for a short period of time before disposing of them. Plastic waste has drastic impacts on the environment and human health.</li>
<li>There is a greater likelihood of single-use plastic products <strong><u>ending up in the sea</u></strong> than reusable ones.</li>
</ul>
<h4>SUP ban in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has taken resolute steps to mitigate pollution caused by littered single-use plastics.</li>
<li>A number of items are banned, including earbuds with plastic sticks, balloon sticks, plastic flags, candy sticks, ice cream sticks, polystyrene (thermocol) for decorations, plates, cups, glasses, cutlery such as forks, spoons, knives, straws etc.</li>
<li>India has also banned plastic or PVC banners less than 100 micron, stirrers, etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the impact on the environment?</h4>
<p><strong>[A] Solid Waste generation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The disposal of plastics is one of the least recognized and most highly problematic areas of plastic’s ecological impact.</li>
<li>Ironically, one of plastic’s most desirable traits: its <strong>durability and resistance to decomposition</strong>, is also the source of one of its greatest liabilities when it comes to the disposal of plastics.</li>
<li>A very small amount of total plastic production (less than 10%) is effectively recycled; the remaining plastic is sent to landfills.</li>
<li>It is destined to remain entombed.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>[B] Ecological Impact</strong></p>
<p><strong>(i) Groundwater and soil pollution</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Plastic is a material made to last forever, and due to the same chemical composition, plastic cannot biodegrade; it breaks down into smaller and smaller pieces.</li>
<li>When buried in a landfill, plastic lies untreated for years.</li>
<li>In the process, toxic chemicals from plastics drain out and seep into groundwater, flowing downstream into lakes and rivers.</li>
<li>The seeping of plastic also causes soil pollution and have now started resulting in presence of micro plastics in soil.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(ii) Water Pollution</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The increased presence of plastic on the ocean surface has resulted in more serious problems.</li>
<li>Since most of the plastic debris that reaches the ocean remains floating for years as it does not decompose quickly, it leads to the dropping of oxygen level in the water.</li>
<li>It has severely affected the survival of marine species.</li>
<li>When oceanic creatures and even birds consume plastic inadvertently, they choke on it which causes a steady decline in their population.</li>
<li>In addition to suffocation, ingestion, and other macro-particulate causes of death in larger birds, fish, and mammals.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>[C] Health Hazards</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Burning of plastic results into formation of a class of flame retardants called as Halogens.</li>
<li>Collectively, these harmful chemicals are known to cause the following severe health problems: cancer, neurological damage, endocrine disruption, birth defects and child developmental disorders etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Ban elsewhere</h4>
<ul>
<li>India is not the first country to ban single-use plastics.</li>
<li>Bangladesh became the first country to ban thin plastic bags in 2002; New Zealand banned plastic bags in July 2019.</li>
<li>China had issued a ban on plastic bags in 2020 with a phased implementation.</li>
<li>As of July 2019, 68 countries have plastic bag bans with varying degrees of enforcement.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the plastic waste management rules in India?</h4>
<ul>
<li>With effect from September 30, 2021 India has the Plastic Waste Management Amendment Rules, 2021.</li>
<li>It prohibited the manufacture, import, stocking, distribution, sale, and use of plastic carry bags whose thickness is less than 75 microns.</li>
<li>From December 31, 2022, plastic carry bags whose thickness is less than 120 microns will be banned.</li>
<li>It means that the ban does not cover all plastic bags; however, it requires the manufacturers to produce plastic bags thicker than 75 microns which was earlier 50 microns.</li>
<li>As per the notification, the standard shall be increased to 120 microns in December this year.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the role of the manufacturer?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In addition, the Ministry of Environment, Forests, and Climate Change notified the Plastic Waste Management Amendment Rules, 2022 on February 16, 2022.</li>
<li>Extended Producer Responsibility (EPR) is the responsibility of a producer for the environmentally sound management of the product until the end of its life.</li>
<li>The guidelines provide a framework to strengthen the circular economy of plastic packaging waste, promote the development of new alternatives to plastic packaging and provide the next steps for moving towards sustainable plastic packaging by businesses.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Various steps taken</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian government has taken steps to promote innovation and create an ecosystem for accelerated adoption and availability of alternatives across the country.</li>
<li>To ensure the effective enforcement of the ban, national and State-level control rooms will be established, as well as special enforcement teams for the purpose of checking the illegal sale and use of single-use plastics.</li>
<li>To prevent the movement of banned single-use plastic items between States and Union Territories, border checkpoints have been established.</li>
<li>In an effort to empower citizens to help curb the plastic menace, the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB) has launched a grievance redressal application.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the challenges?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ban will succeed only if all stakeholders participate enthusiastically and engage in effective engagement and concerted actions.</li>
<li>However, if we look back at our past, almost 25 Indian States previously banned plastic at the state level.</li>
<li>However, these bans had a very limited impact in reality because of the widespread use of these items.</li>
<li>Now the challenge is to see how the local level authorities will enforce the ban in accordance with the guidelines.</li>
<li>Banned items such as earbuds with plastic sticks, plastic sticks for balloons, etc., are non-branded items and it is difficult to find out who the manufacturer is and who is accountable.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>The consumer needs to be informed about the ban through advertisements, newspaper or TV commercials, or on social media.</li>
<li>In order to find sustainable alternatives, companies need to invest in research and development.</li>
<li>The solution to the plastic pollution problem is not the responsibility of the government alone, but of industries, brands, manufacturers and most importantly consumers.</li>
<li>Finding alternatives to plastic seems a little difficult, however, greener alternatives to plastic may be considered a sustainable option.</li>
<li>For example, compostable and bio-degradable plastic, etc., may be considered as an option.</li>
<li>While the total ban on the use of plastic sounds a great idea, its feasibility seems difficult at this hour, especially in the absence of workable alternatives.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/effecting-the-ban-on-single-use-plastics/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Civil servants should be allowed to express themselves positively</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/civil-servants/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>conduct rules 1964</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>bureaucracy and reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Civil servants" class="alignnone wp-image-629580" height="312" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 468px) 100vw, 468px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/life-at-LBSNAA-IMG-2-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/life-at-LBSNAA-IMG-2-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/life-at-LBSNAA-IMG-2-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/life-at-LBSNAA-IMG-2-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/life-at-LBSNAA-IMG-2-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/life-at-LBSNAA-IMG-2-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/life-at-LBSNAA-IMG-2.jpg 1600w" width="468"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Can civil servants express their views on law, governance?</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A senior IAS officer, Smita Sabharwal from Telangana, tweeted from her personal account in support of Ms. Bilkis Bano and questioned the Gujarat government’s decision, sparking off a row over whether she was in breach of the Central Civil Services (Conduct) Rules of 1964 and reviving the debate on the freedom of civil servants to express their personal views on matters of law and governance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who are civil servants?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In a modern democracy, a civil servant is an official in the service of the people and is recruited based on predetermined qualifications. Civil servants are bureaucrats who need to be familiar with the laws and regulations of the country and are expected to act in the best interests of the country and its citizens.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is their expected role?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>They are responsible for managing the resources given to them by the government and making use of them efficiently and effectively. A sound parliamentary system of government requires civil servants to maintain their integrity, fearlessness, and independence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Civil servants" class="alignnone wp-image-629581" height="326" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 437px) 100vw, 437px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ias_4-1571657168_1-300x224.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ias_4-1571657168_1-300x224.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ias_4-1571657168_1.jpg 670w" width="437"/>What are Central Civil Services (Conduct) Rules of 1964?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Conduct Rules lay down clear principles as to what the Government expects from its employees.</li>
<li>Conduct rules apply to both official and personal life of the government servant.</li>
<li>If an official violates conduct rules, he may face warning/disciplinary action/departmental proceedings.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is rule 9?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Rule 9 of the Rules of the Central Civil Services (Conduct) Rules states, “No Government servant shall… make any statement of fact or opinion… which has the effect of an adverse criticism of any current or recent policy or action of the Central Government or a State Government.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Civil servants" class="alignnone wp-image-629582" height="290" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 387px) 100vw, 387px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/DlxQhSLV4AAe75Q-300x225.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/DlxQhSLV4AAe75Q-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/DlxQhSLV4AAe75Q-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/DlxQhSLV4AAe75Q-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/DlxQhSLV4AAe75Q-1536x1152.jpeg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/DlxQhSLV4AAe75Q-2048x1536.jpeg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/DlxQhSLV4AAe75Q-1200x900.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/DlxQhSLV4AAe75Q-1980x1485.jpeg 1980w" width="387"/>What is freedom of expression?          </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The citizens of country have the fundamental right of free speech guaranteed to them under the Constitution, which is subject to reasonable restrictions in the interest of securing the state’s sovereignty, international relations, health, morality, etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What central conduct rules say?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When you undertake a government service, you subject yourself to certain disciplinary rules. That prevents a government servant from becoming a member of a political organisation, or any organisation of such a nature, or expressing herself freely with regard to anything that has to do with the governance of the country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How Indian rules are different than others?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>One of the most important functions of the civil service, as stated by the head of the Canadian Public Service, is to <strong>“speak truth to power.”</strong></li>
<li>Which is prohibited in Indian context because this rule is of the British era. There is no doubt that the British were very, very strict and didn’t want their officers to be talking about how bad the governance was. But in a democracy, the right to criticise the government is a fundamental right and nobody can muzzle that.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What judiciary said in Lipika Paul vs The State Of Tripura case</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As a Government servant the petitioner is not devoid of her right of free speech, a fundamental right which can be curtailed only by a valid law.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Crux of this judgement in simple words</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>She (the petitioner) was entitled to hold her own beliefs and express them in the manner she desired, subject to not crossing the borders laid down in the Conduct Rules which were applicable in Tripura.</li>
<li>A fundamental right cannot be curtailed except by a valid law made by a legislature<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why this judgement is important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It abrogated state from exploiting vague terms of the policy of government and government action to punish civil servants who criticize government of the day in any manner harsh or mild.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What Kerala high court said in 2018? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>One cannot be prevented from expressing his views merely because he/she is an government employee. In a democratic society, every institution is governed by democratic norms. Healthy criticism is a better way to govern a public institution.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why it is highly contextual here?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>This judgement indirectly protected constructive and just criticism by protecting fundamental rights of the civil servants.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Action of IAS officer can be justified?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Since she added the words ‘civil servant’ in her tweet is because the dharma of the civil servant is to uphold constitutional principles in letter and in spirit, and the rule of law.</li>
<li>In Bilkis Bano case, both the spirit of the Constitution and the rule of law were being subverted.</li>
<li>Hence her expression can be justified.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/civil-service-accountability-and-challenges-benefits-of-an-independent-permanent-and-impartial-civil-service/"><strong>Can we justify rule 9 here in this context?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>The rules don’t violate Article 19. It is a rule, it’s not the law. It’s not in the Constitution. Freedom of speech is given in the Constitution, but these are Conduct Rules and they are imposed because there has to be some discipline in an organisation for that organisation to function.</li>
<li>There is a process of decision-making. Right from below, the matter is examined, the pros and cons are taken up, the bureaucracy is given an opportunity to examine all the aspects, write their notes of objection or support, and finally it reaches the political executive. When a policy is decided, it has to be obeyed and complied with by the bureaucracy.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Anybody could challenge these rules as they are offending constitutional fundamental rights of civil servant; then the Supreme Court would be forced to come down and say either it is good, or it is bad, and give good reasons for that.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong> Right time has arrived to challenge conduct rules of civil servants as their freedom of expression is curtailed by these rules. Critically analyse.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/civil-servants/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Nord Stream Pipeline to remain shut</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nord-stream-pipeline-to-stay-shut/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nord Stream Pipelines</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economic impact of Russian invasion</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-597151" height="295" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 443px) 100vw, 443px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nord-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nord-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nord-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nord.jpg 770w" width="443"/></p>
<p>Russian has said that it can‘t resume the supply of natural gas through a key pipeline to Germany for now because of what it said was a need for urgent maintenance work.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There are growing concerns in European countries that Russia would shut down its gas supplies in retaliation against the current sanctions against Moscow.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Nord Stream 1?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is a system of offshore natural gas pipelines running under the Baltic Sea from Russia to Germany.</li>
<li>Nord Stream 1 is a 1,224 km underwater gas pipeline that runs from Vyborg in northwest Russia to Lubmin in northeastern Germany via the Baltic Sea.</li>
<li>Two further pipelines under construction running from Ust-Luga to Lubmin termed Nord Stream 2.</li>
<li>Majority owned by the Russian energy giant Gazprom, the pipeline is the primary route through which its gas enters Germany.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Worry for Europe</h4>
<ul>
<li>There have been growing concerns that there could be further restrictions to European gas supplies.</li>
<li>European countries rely on Russian energy for their cold winters.</li>
<li>But now they believe that Russia could weaponized their dependency as a response to their sanction due to the conflict in Ukraine.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are Europe’s alternative sources of energy?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As an alternative source for energy, European countries have increasingly turned towards the US, from whom they purchase liquified natural gas (LNG) that comes via ships.</li>
<li>Since ship-delivered gas ends up being far more expensive, there are also attempts to get non-Russian pipeline gas from Norway and Azerbaijan.</li>
<li>While EU countries were earlier seeking to phase out fossil fuels and emphasize renewable forms of energy, many are now returning to coal to deal with the energy crisis.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nord-stream-pipeline-to-stay-shut/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What causes Rainbow Clouds (Cloud Iridescence)?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-causes-rainbow-clouds-cloud-iridescence/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Cloud iridescence</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-630169" height="299" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 399px) 100vw, 399px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-1200x900.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-1980x1485.jpg 1980w" width="399"/></strong></p>
<p>Last week, pictures of an unusually-shaped rainbow cloud that appeared over China were widely shared on social media.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The cloud in question resembles a pileus cloud.</li>
<li>Such phenomenon of bright colours appearing on a cloud is called cloud iridescence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Pileus Cloud? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A pileus cloud is usually formed over a <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/water-in-the-atmosphere/"><strong>cumulus or cumulonimbus cloud</strong></a>.</li>
<li>It is formed when the base cloud pushes a moist current of air upwards and the water vapour from the current condenses to somewhat resemble wave-like crests, or umbrellas.</li>
<li>In popular western culture, it is called as an “accessory cloud” that is “rather like a cloud haircut”.</li>
<li>A pileus cloud is transient in nature and <strong><u>lasts barely for a few minutes</u></strong>, making it difficult, and at the same time, exciting, to spot.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is cloud iridescence? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cloud iridescence or Irisation is an optical phenomenon that mostly occurs in wave-like clouds, including pileus and Altocumulus lenticularis.</li>
<li>Iridescence in clouds means the appearance of colours on clouds, which can either be in the form of parallel bands like in a rainbow, or mingled in patches.</li>
<li>In ancient Greek mythology, Iris is the goddess of rainbow. “Irisation”, the phenomenon of rainbow-like colours in clouds, is derived from her name.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a photometeor? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Iridescence of clouds is a photometeor.</li>
<li>It is an optical phenomenon produced by the reflection, refraction, diffraction or interference of sunlight.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What causes cloud iridescence? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In pileus clouds, <strong><u>small water droplets or ice crystals</u></strong>, usually of a similar size, <strong><u>diffract the sunlight</u></strong> falling on them.</li>
<li>The thinness of the cloud ensures more exposure to sunlight for each water droplet or ice crystal.</li>
<li>To ensure its wave crest-like appearance, water droplets or ice crystals in these clouds are always moving – droplets form at one side of the cloud and evaporate from the other end – and hence these clouds remain small and thin since the droplets have no way of combining and growing in size.</li>
<li>In its International Cloud Atlas, the World Meteorological Organisation says that iridescence or Irisation is caused by diffraction within 10 degrees from the sun.</li>
<li>Beyond ten degrees and up till about 40 degrees, interference of light is the main cause of iridescence.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-causes-rainbow-clouds-cloud-iridescence/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India to host Quad officials’ meet</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-to-host-quad-officials-meet/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>QUAD</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>New Delhi will host an official-level meeting of the Quad grouping with the US, Japan and Australia next week, the first such “senior officers meeting” (SOM) to be held since the recent escalation of tensions over the Taiwan Strait.</p>
<h4>Quadrilateral Security Dialogue: A Backgrounder</h4>
<p>Quadrilateral Security Dialogue or the Quad is an informal strategic forum between the United States, Japan, India and Australia that is maintained by semi-regular summits, information exchanges and military drills between member countries.</p>
<ul>
<li>The US, Japan, India and Australia came together in the aftermath of the 2004 Indian Ocean tsunami to assist the devastated countries.</li>
<li>Later, officials of the four countries met in 2007 “to look at issues of common interest.” During an India visit, then Japanese PM Shinzo Abe unveiled the idea of “the Confluence of the Two Seas” that gave birth to the concept of the Indo-Pacific.</li>
<li>A decade later officials of the four countries met in the Philippines in 2017 to talk about an aggressively rising China.</li>
<li>In 2019, the foreign ministers of the Quad countries met in Washington for the first time.</li>
<li>In November, the Quad nations came together to participate in a two-phase joint military exercise, Malabar 2020, in the Bay of Bengal and in the Arabian Sea.</li>
</ul>
<p>Now it is increasingly viewed as ‘Asian NATO’.</p>
<h4>Focus on Indo-Pacific: For the China-wary world</h4>
<ul>
<li>The latest meeting of Quad comes at a time when all four countries have either trade or security disputes with China.</li>
<li>Despite not explicitly mentioning China, Quad has been openly supporting a “free and fair” Indo-Pacific which is seen as a clear message to Beijing that it needs to curb its assertive behaviour.</li>
<li>The optics were hard to miss when India, the US, Japan and Australia joined their navies for the mega Malabar military exercise late last year, an activity which raised alarm in Beijing.</li>
<li>This posturing by the Quad nations sent a strong signal to China.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(1) US vs China</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>USA had followed a policy to contain China’s increasing influence in East Asia. Therefore, USA sees the coalition as an opportunity to regain its influence in the Indo-Pacific region.</li>
<li>The US has described China, along with Russia, as a strategic rival in its National Security Strategy, National Defence Strategy and the Pentagon’s report on Indo-Pacific Strategy.</li>
<li>Both are navigating intense disagreements over trade and human rights in Tibet, Hong Kong and the western Xinjiang region, as well as the coronavirus pandemic and increasing Chinese assertiveness in the South China Sea.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Australia vs China</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Australia is concerned about China’s growing interest in its land, infrastructure and politics, and influence on its universities.</li>
<li>Ties have been on a downward spiral since 2018 when Australia, accusing China of meddling in its domestic affairs, passed a new law against foreign interference and espionage.</li>
<li>It also barred Huawei from building the country’s 5G mobile network, among the first countries to do so, citing national security.</li>
<li> The atmosphere worsened when  PM Scott Morrison’s government called for an international inquiry into the origins of the coronavirus that causes Covid-19.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Japan vs. China</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Tensions between Japan and China over the Senkaku/Diaoyu Islands dispute have recently increased.</li>
<li>China has relentlessly continued attempts to unilaterally change the status quo by coercion in the sea area around the Senkaku Islands.</li>
<li>The more salient indicator is the number of Chinese patrols inside the territorial sea of the islands, which Japan sees as an explicit violation of its territorial sovereignty.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) India vs. Quad</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India’s strained relations with China needs no explanation. The year long border dispute is the testimony.</li>
<li>The Quad summit is taking place in the backdrop of an ongoing military disengagement between India and China following their months-long border standoff in eastern Ladakh.</li>
<li>China is increasing its footprint in our neighborhood through its Belt and Road policy and political coercion following the debt trap are some of the increasing concerns other than economic imbalance.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Opportunities unveiled for India</h4>
<p>India’s engagement with the Quad goes back to China’s expanding footprint in South Asia and the Indian Ocean Region over the last few years. India can reap some benefits as discussed below:</p>
<p><strong> (1) Checkmating the Chinese</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The maritime sphere is wide open to India to undertake coalition building, rule sets, and other forms of strategic exploration than compared to land borders.</li>
<li>The maritime space is more important to China than engaging in land grab attempts in the Himalayas. A huge chunk of Chinese trade happens via the Indian oceanic routes that pass through maritime chokepoints.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Channelizing geo-politics</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is a growing great power interest in the maritime sphere, especially with the arrival of the concept of ‘Indo-Pacific’. For instance, many European countries have recently released their Indo-Pacific strategies.</li>
<li>The most recent was for France to send its warship in the international waters of the South China Sea.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Maritime domain for India</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Above is the backdrop against which one must see the progressive evolution of Exercise “Malabar”,</li>
<li>In the beginning, it was a bilateral event involving just the Indian and US navies. It became tri-lateral with the inclusion of Japan in 2015.</li>
<li>And now it has transformed into a four-cornered naval drill that will also include Australia.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Check on China’s India Ocean Ambitions</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Quad has a valuable role to play as a check on China’s Indian Ocean ambitions.</li>
<li>India must develop ingrained habits of interoperable cooperation with its Quad partners.</li>
<li>This interoperable cooperation could pre-emptively dissuade China from mounting a naval challenge in its backyard.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Eccentricity in South Asia</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>With India, located right at the centre of the Indo-Pacific geopolitical imagination can realize the vision of a ‘broader Asia’ that can extend its influence away from geographical boundaries.</li>
<li>Further, India with Quad countries can check the imperialist policies of China in the Indian Ocean region and ensure Security and growth for all in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with Quad</h4>
<p><strong>(1) Structural problems</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Quad has a core structural problem as its objective pivots around the U.S.</li>
<li>The Quad riles China as a hostile grouping, but hardly serves the security interests of its members.</li>
<li>Despite rhetoric relating to the promotion of a ‘rules-based’ world order, the Quad neither shares a strategic vision nor is it animated by a shared agenda.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> (2) Nature of alliance</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Alliances involve written commitments to come to the defence of the other against a third party.</li>
<li>Despite the potential for cooperation, the Quad remains a mechanism without a defined strategic mission.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Economic alliance not feasible</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Quad is neither a military alliance nor an economic partnership.</li>
<li>Its intention to counter China in the rare-earth sector is logical given the dominant role the country plays in supplying more than half of the world’s such key materials.</li>
<li>But, for a country like India, the lack of relevant technologies and talent pool could obstruct its progress in building up a supply chain from scratch.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> (4) Overt emphasis on Maritime domain</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The entire focus on the Indo-Pacific makes the Quad a maritime, rather than a land-based grouping, raising questions whether the cooperation extends to the Asia-Pacific and Eurasian regions.</li>
<li>India’s core concerns with China are primarily undemarcated borders and trade deficit.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> (5) Lack of existence of Indo-Pacific system</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There has never been Indo-Pacific system ever since the rise of the port-based kingdoms of Indochina in the first half of the second millennium.</li>
<li>There were two Asian systems — an Indian Ocean system and an East Asian system — with intricate sub-regional balances.</li>
<li>The effort by a U.S. to artificially manufacture to combine the Indo and the Pacific into a unitary system is unlikely to succeed.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Indian borders can go more vulnerable</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>A lesson for India is China’s long-held and strategic interest in parts of Jammu and Kashmir.</li>
<li>It is wrongly argued that it is Pakistan that is the issue in J&amp;K.</li>
<li>China undoubtedly is as big an issue but has quietly hidden behind Pakistan’s cover.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Challenges: China will retaliate</h4>
<p><strong>(1) China’s assertiveness</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>China claims that it has historical ownership over nearly the entire region of South China Sea, which gives it the right to manufacture islands.</li>
<li>However, the International Court of Arbitration rejected the claim in 2016.</li>
<li>Since then, the incidences of Chinese transgression has only increased making China more assertive for its interest.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Preying small nations</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The ASEAN countries have a well-knit relationship with China. So are other SAARC countries have fallen prey to Chinese debt traps.</li>
<li>The Regional Cooperation Economic Partnership (RCEP) is a recent example of China’s increasing influence over ASEAN nations to which Australia is even a forerunner.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Chinese monopoly</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Considering the economic might of China and the dependence of Quad nations like Japan and Australia on China, the Quad nations cannot afford to have strained relations with it in the long run.</li>
<li>India too, is still very heavily dependent on Chinese exports.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way Forward</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Need for a clearer vision:</strong> It is important for members of the Quad not to be reactive. It is also important to exhibit openness, and ensure that all talk of a ‘Free and Open Indo-Pacific’ is more than just a mere slogan.</li>
<li><strong>Consensus for a common objective:</strong> The Quad nations need to better explain the Indo-Pacific Vision in an overarching framework with the objective of advancing everyone’s economic and security interests.</li>
<li><strong>Setting an agenda:</strong> This will reassure the littoral States that the Quad will be a factor for regional benefit, and a far cry from Chinese allegations that it is some sort of a military alliance. Future meetings can be an opportunity to define the idea and chart a future path.</li>
<li><strong>Expanding Quad:</strong> India has many other partners in the Indo-Pacific; therefore India should pitch for countries like Indonesia, Singapore to be invited to join in the future. There is also a vital need to economically expand the Quad.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-to-host-quad-officials-meet/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Millet crop is the best solution for climate smart agriculture</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/millet/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>examples of nutri-cereals</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>climate resilient agriculture</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="millet" class="alignnone wp-image-629923" height="285" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 498px) 100vw, 498px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Millet02-300x172.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Millet02-300x172.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Millet02.jpg 680w" width="498"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Government push to coarse cereals as climate change affects wheat, paddy cultivation</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/important-food-crops-rice-wheat-maize-millets-pulses-geographical-conditions-producing-areas-important-varieties-horticulture-fruits-vegetables/"><strong>What are millets crops? </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Millets are a group of highly variable small-seeded grasses, widely grown around the world as cereal crops or grains for human food and as fodder.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Features Millet crops in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Big three</strong>: The three major millet crops currently growing in India are jowar (sorghum), bajra (pearl millet) and ragi (finger millet).</li>
<li><strong>Examples</strong>: India also grows a rich array of bio-genetically diverse and indigenous varieties of “small millets” like kodo, kutki, chenna and sanwa.</li>
<li><strong>Area of production</strong>: Major producers include Rajasthan, Andhra Pradesh, Telangana, Karnataka, Tamil Nadu, Maharashtra, Gujarat and Haryana.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="millet" class="alignnone wp-image-629924" height="351" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 100vw, 527px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/millet-farmer-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/millet-farmer-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/millet-farmer.jpg 640w" width="527"/>What are Advantages of millet cultivation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low input cost</strong>: cereals are good for the soil, have shorter cultivation cycles and require less cost-intensive cultivation.</li>
<li><strong>Climate resilience</strong>: These unique features make millets suited for and resilient to India’s varied agro-climatic conditions.</li>
<li><strong>Drought tolerance</strong>: cereals are not water or input-intensive, making them a sustainable strategy for addressing climate change and building resilient agri-food systems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="millet" class="alignnone wp-image-629925" height="309" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 464px) 100vw, 464px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1456304251-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1456304251-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1456304251.jpg 555w" width="464"/>Reduction in millet production</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Effects of Green Revolution</strong>: The Green Revolution succeeded in making India food sufficient, however, it also led to water-logging, soil erosion, groundwater depletion and the unsustainability of agriculture.</li>
<li><strong>Deficit mind-set</strong>: Current policies are still based on the “deficit” mind-set of the 1960s.</li>
<li><strong>Biased policies</strong>: The procurement, subsidies and water policies are biased towards rice and wheat.</li>
<li><strong>Skewed cropping pattern</strong>: Three crops (rice, wheat and sugarcane) corner 75 to 80 per cent of irrigated water.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of diversification</strong>: Diversification of cropping patterns towards cereals, pulses, oilseeds, horticulture is needed for more equal distribution of water, sustainable and climate-resilient agriculture.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to promote millets as nutri-cereals? </strong></h4>
<p><strong>1) Rebranding the cereals as nutri-cereals</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The first strategy from a consumption and trade point of view was to re-brand coarse cereals/millets as nutri-cereals.</li>
<li>As of 2018-19, millet production had been extended to over 112 districts across 14 states.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2) Incentive through hiking MSP</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Second, the government hiked the MSP of nutri-cereals, which came as a big price incentive for farmers.</li>
<li>From 2014-15 to 2020 MSPs for ragi has jumped by 113 per cent, by 72 per cent for bajra and by 71 per cent for jowar.</li>
<li>MSPs have been calculated so that the farmer is ensured at least a 50 per cent return on their cost of production.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>3) Providing steady markets through inclusion in PDS</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>To provide a steady market for the produce, the Modi government included millets in the public distribution system.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>4) Increasing area, production and yield</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Ministry of Agriculture &amp; Farmers’ Welfare is running a Rs 600-crore scheme to increase the area, production and yield of nutri-cereals.</li>
<li>With a goal to match the cultivation of nutri-cereals with local topography and natural resources, the government is encouraging farmers to align their local cropping patterns to India’s diverse 127 agro-climatic zones.</li>
<li>Provision of seed kits and inputs to farmers, building value chains through Farmer Producer Organisations and supporting the marketability of nutri-cereals are some of the key interventions that have been put in place.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>5) Intersection of agriculture and nutrition</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Ministry of Women and Child Development has been working at the intersection of agriculture and nutrition by -1) setting up nutri-gardens, 2) promoting research on the interlinkages between crop diversity and dietary diversity 3) running a behaviour change campaign to generate consumer demand for nutri-cereals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India should aim for a food systems transformation, which can be inclusive and sustainable, ensure growing farm incomes and nutrition security<strong>. </strong>As the government sets to achieve its agenda of a malnutrition-free India and doubling of farmers’ incomes, the promotion of the production and consumption of nutri-cereals seems to be a policy shift in the right direction.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Promotion of millet crops serves the dual purpose of securing health and supporting farmers. Elucidate.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/millet/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>MGNREGA roadblocks should be removed urgently</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mgnrega/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of the scheme</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>social security</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="MGNREGA" class="alignnone wp-image-629928" height="389" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 499px) 100vw, 499px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/MGNREGA_Logo-300x234.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/MGNREGA_Logo-300x234.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/MGNREGA_Logo-1024x799.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/MGNREGA_Logo-768x599.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/MGNREGA_Logo.jpg 1145w" width="499"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The delay in payment of wages has pushed MGNREGS workers in West Bengal to the brink. There are allegations of corruption against the State government, the Centre’s reluctance in releasing payments, and the plight of the workers caught in this tussle.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is MGNREGA?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The MGNREGA stands for Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act of 2005. This is labour law and social security measure that aims to guarantee the ‘Right to Work’. The act was first proposed in 1991 by P.V. Narasimha Rao.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Significant Features of the scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Fixed employment</strong>: MGNREGA is unique in not only ensuring at least 100 days of employment to the willing unskilled workers, but also in ensuring an enforceable commitment on the implementing machinery i.e., the State Governments, and providing a bargaining power to the labourers.</li>
<li><strong>Assured compensation</strong>: The failure of provision for employment within 15 days of the receipt of job application from a prospective household will result in the payment of unemployment allowance to the job seekers.</li>
<li><strong>Locality is ensured</strong>: Employment is to be provided within 5 km of an applicant’s residence, and minimum wages are to be paid.</li>
<li><strong>Legal backing:</strong> Thus, employment under MGNREGA is a legal entitlement.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/mgnrega-scheme/"><strong><img alt="MGNREGA" class="alignnone wp-image-629930" height="320" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 427px) 100vw, 427px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/NREGAintro-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/NREGAintro-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/NREGAintro.jpg 400w" width="427"/>What are the issues?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Non-purposive spending and corruptions: </strong>Many works sanctioned under MGNREGA often seem to be non-purposive. Quite often, they are politically motivated hotspots to create rampant corruption by dominant sections of the local population. Even social audits of such projects are locally manipulated.</li>
<li><strong>Workers penalized for administrative lapses: </strong>The ministry withholds wage payments for workers of states that do not meet administrative requirements within the stipulated time period (for instance, submission of the previous financial year’s audited fund statements, utilization certificates, bank reconciliation certificates etc). There is no logical or legal explanation for this bizarre arrangement. It is beyond any logic as to why workers would be penalized for administrative lapses.</li>
<li><strong>Genuine job cards being deleted: </strong>Genuine job cards are being randomly deleted as there is a huge administrative pressure to meet 100 per cent DBT implementation targets in MGNREGA. In states like Jharkhand, there are multiple examples where the districts had later requested to resume job cards after civil society interventions into the matter.</li>
<li><strong>Too much centralization weakening local governance: </strong>A real-time MIS-based implementation and a centralised payment system has further left the representatives of the Panchayati Raj Institutions with literally no role in implementation. It has become a burden as they hardly have any power to resolve issues or make payments.</li>
<li><strong>Local priorities being ignored: </strong>MGNREGA could be a tool to establish decentralized governance. But, with the administration almost dictating its implementation, it is literally a burden now for the people and especially for the local elected representatives. The Gram Sabhas and gram panchayats’ plans are never honoured. This is a blatant violation of the Act as well.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="MGNREGA" class="alignnone wp-image-629929" height="297" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 435px) 100vw, 435px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mgnrega_660_040319050732-300x205.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mgnrega_660_040319050732-300x205.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mgnrega_660_040319050732.jpg 660w" width="435"/>Lack of fund has negative implications </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Delayed payment</strong>: Due to this, payments for MGNREGA workers as well as material costs will be delayed, unless States dip into their own funds.</li>
<li><strong>Livelihood loss:</strong> MGNREGA data shows that 13% of households who demanded work under the scheme were not provided work.</li>
<li><strong>Halt of work</strong>: Many workers are simply turned away by officials when they demand work, without their demand being registered at all.</li>
<li><strong>Fall in demands</strong>: This has led to stop the generation of work. There is an artificial squeezing of demand.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done according to rural development committee?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Utilization of funds</strong>: A large amount of funds allocated for MGNREGA have remained un-utilised. For example, in 2010-11, 27.31% of the funds remained unutilised. The Committee recommends that the Department of Rural Development should analyse reasons for poor utilisation of funds and take steps to improve the same. In addition, it should initiate action against officers found guilty of misappropriating funds under MGNREGA.</li>
<li><strong>Context specific projects and convergence</strong>: Since states are at various stages of socio-economic development, they have varied requirements for development. Therefore, state governments should be allowed to undertake works that are pertinent to their context. There should be more emphasis on skilled and semi-skilled work under MGNREGA. In addition, the Committee recommends a greater emphasis on convergence with other schemes such as the National Rural Livelihoods Mission, National Rural Health Mission, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Regulation of job cards</strong>: Offences such as not recording employment related information in job cards and unlawful possession of job cards with elected PRI representatives and MGNREGA functionaries should be made punishable under the Act.</li>
<li><strong>Participation of people with disabilities</strong>: Special works (projects) must be identified for people with disabilities and special job cards must be issued and personnel must be employed to ensure their participation.</li>
<li><strong>Payment of unemployment allowance</strong>: Dated receipts for demanded work should be issued so that workers can claim unemployment allowance. Funds for unemployment allowance should be met by the central government.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Some innovation in MGNREGA can address the challenges </strong></h4>
<p><strong>1) Looping in the skilled worker</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>First, there is a suggestion to use it to meet the wage cost of their employment in small and medium enterprises (SMEs).</li>
<li>Accordingly, skilled migrant workers may be placed in SMEs and their wages would be charged to MGNREGA.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2) Including farm related works</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In the last few years, un-remunerative prices of several crops have been the root cause of widespread agrarian distress.</li>
<li>The suggestion is to allow farmers to employ MGNREGA workers in agricultural operations like land preparation, sowing, transplantation of paddy, plucking of cotton, intercultural operations and harvesting of crops etc. so as to reduce the cost of cultivation.</li>
<li>The idea is to pay part of the wages of labour in agricultural operations from MGNREGA.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>3) Increasing the number of Work Schemes</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Currently, there are only 2-3 work schemes (say PMAY) running per panchayat, which is leading to the crowding of workers at worksites.</li>
<li>To prevent this and to ensure that all willing households are able to access employment through NREGA, the number of schemes needs to be increased, and 6-8 schemes must be introduced in each village.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>4) Paying Workers Immediately</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Rural households urgently need cash-in-hand, and so the emerging demand is for immediate payment to workers. NREGA payments are frequently delayed by weeks or months.</li>
<li>Given the circumstances, such delays will be entirely counterproductive.</li>
<li>It is recommended that in remote areas, wage payments should be made in cash, and paid on the same day.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Government and NGOs must study the impact of MGNREGA in rural areas so as to ensure that this massive anti-poverty scheme is not getting diluted from its actual path.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Large scale social security programmes like MGNREGA are subjected to undergo several stumbling blocks in the times to come due to lack of fund. Analyse these roadblocks and give some innovative measures to tackle these roadblocks.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mgnrega/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Cybercrime needs immediate revamp in response</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cybercrime/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Indian evidence act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Cybersecurity</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="cybercrime" class="alignnone wp-image-629933" height="200" sizes="(max-width: 382px) 100vw, 382px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Cybersecurity-Awareness-Month-Types-of-Cybercrime-300x157.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Cybersecurity-Awareness-Month-Types-of-Cybercrime-300x157.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Cybersecurity-Awareness-Month-Types-of-Cybercrime-1024x536.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Cybersecurity-Awareness-Month-Types-of-Cybercrime-768x402.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Cybersecurity-Awareness-Month-Types-of-Cybercrime.jpg 1201w" width="382"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There has been a steady spike in cases of cybercrime in the last five years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/cyber-security/"><strong>What is a cybercrime?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cybercrime is any criminal activity that involves a computer, networked device or a network. While most cybercrimes are carried out in order to generate profit for the cybercriminals, some cybercrimes are carried out against computers or devices directly to damage or disable them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What data states?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India reported 52,974 cases of cybercrime in 2021, an increase of over 5 per cent from 2020 (50,035 cases) and over 15 per cent from 2019 (44,735 cases), according to latest government data.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>How many cyber criminals are caught in India?</strong></p>
<p>In 2020, over 18.4 thousand people were arrested on account of cyber-crimes across India.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Who is responsible for cyber security centre or state?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>With ‘police’ and ‘public order’ being in the State List, the primary obligation to check crime and create the necessary cyberinfrastructure lies with States.</li>
<li>At the same time, with the IT Act and major laws being central legislations, the central government is no less responsible to evolve uniform statutory procedures for the enforcement agencies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="cybercrime" class="alignnone wp-image-629935" height="302" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 482px) 100vw, 482px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/surge-1024x640-1-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/surge-1024x640-1-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/surge-1024x640-1-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/surge-1024x640-1-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/surge-1024x640-1.jpg 1024w" width="482"/>Status of cyber investigation</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is no separate procedural code for the investigation of cyber or computer-related offences.</li>
<li>As electronic evidence is entirely different in nature when compared with evidence of traditional crime, laying down standard and uniform procedures to deal with electronic evidence is essential.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are general guidelines for cyber investigation? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The broad ‘guidelines for the identification, collection, acquisition and preservation of digital evidence’ are given in the Indian Standard IS/ISO/ IEC 27037: 2012, issued by the Bureau of Indian Standards (BIS).</li>
<li>This document is fairly comprehensive and easy to comprehend for both the first responder (who could be an authorised and trained police officer of a police station) as well as the specialist (who has specialised knowledge, skills and the abilities to handle a wide range of technical issues).</li>
<li>The guidelines, if followed meticulously, may ensure that electronic evidence is neither tampered with nor subject to spoliation during investigation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="cybercrime" class="alignnone wp-image-629938" height="397" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 529px) 100vw, 529px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-logs-40-per-cent-annual-increase-in-cyber-crime-cases-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-logs-40-per-cent-annual-increase-in-cyber-crime-cases-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-logs-40-per-cent-annual-increase-in-cyber-crime-cases-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-logs-40-per-cent-annual-increase-in-cyber-crime-cases-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-logs-40-per-cent-annual-increase-in-cyber-crime-cases.jpg 1200w" width="529"/><br/>
What is the meaning of digital evidence or electronic evidence?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Digital evidence is information stored or transmitted in binary form that may be relied on in court. It can be found on a computer hard drive, a mobile phone, among other places. Digital evidence is commonly associated with electronic crime, or e-crime, such as child pornography or credit card fraud.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Arjun Khotkar vs Kailash Gorantyal Judgement </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Court held that a certificate under Section 65B(4) of the Indian Evidence (IE) Act was a mandatory pre-requisite for the admissibility of (secondary) electronic record if the original record could not be produced.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Indian evidence act?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian Evidence Act, originally passed in India by the Imperial Legislative Council in 1872, during the British Raj, contains a set of rules and allied issues governing admissibility of evidence in the Indian courts of law.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Judicial activism for cyber security</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A significant attempt has been made by the higher judiciary in this field also. As resolved in the Conference of the Chief Justices of the High Court in April 2016, a five judge committee was constituted in July 2018 to frame the draft rules which could serve as a model for the reception of digital evidence by courts.</li>
<li>The committee, after extensive deliberations with experts, the police and investigation agencies, finalised its report in November 2018, but the suggested Draft Rules for the Reception, Retrieval, Authentication and Preservation of Electronic Records are yet to be given a statutory force.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What needs to be done?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Upgrade cyber labs</strong>: The cyber forensic laboratories of States must be upgraded with the advent of new technologies.</li>
<li><strong>Digital rupee</strong>: Offences related to cryptocurrency remain under-reported as the capacity to solve such crimes remains limited. The central government has proposed launching a digital rupee using block-chain technology soon.</li>
<li><strong>Empowering states</strong>: State enforcement agencies need to be ready for new technologies. The Centre helps in upgrading the State laboratories by providing modernisation funds, though the corpus has gradually shrunk over the years.</li>
<li><strong>Need for localisation of data</strong>: Most cybercrimes are trans-national in nature with extra-territorial jurisdiction. The collection of evidence from foreign territories is not only a difficult but also a tardy process.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Centre and States must not only work in tandem and frame statutory guidelines to facilitate investigation of cybercrime but also need to commit sufficient funds to develop much-awaited and required cyber infrastructure.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains questio</strong><strong>n </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>With the increasing use of computers in society, cybercrime has become a major issue. Analyse the loopholes in cyber security regime of India by giving suggestions to rectify the same.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cybercrime/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>