<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 17:30:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>India and UNSC</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-quest-for-permanent-membership-of-unsc/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UN Security council</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>International Relations</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641313" height="506" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 843px) 100vw, 843px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5edc92b402a52-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5edc92b402a52-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5edc92b402a52.jpg 500w" width="843"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is greater support for India to be a permanent member of the UN Security Council and also a broad global consensus over the need to reform the Council, said External Affairs Minister S Jaishankar. India has once again renewed its bid for permanent membership of UNSC.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">What is UNSC?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The United Nations Security Council (UNSC) is one of the six principal organs of the United Nations (UN) and is charged with ensuring international peace and security, recommending the admission of new UN members to the General Assembly, and approving any changes to the UN Charter.</li>
<li>Its powers include establishing peacekeeping operations, enacting international sanctions, and authorizing military action. The UNSC is the only UN body with the authority to issue binding resolutions on member states.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641314" height="509" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 697px) 100vw, 697px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_11largeimg_1702223617-300x219.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_11largeimg_1702223617-300x219.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_11largeimg_1702223617.jpg 660w" width="697"/>What is the composition of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/g4-countries-call-for-unsc-reforms/">UNSC</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Presently there five permanent members (P-5) with veto and 10 non-permanent members without veto elected for tenure of 2 years.</li>
<li>India has been the non-permanent member multiple times. Presently India is serving its tenure that will end in December 2022.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641315" height="469" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 833px) 100vw, 833px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1658498206-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1658498206-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1658498206.jpg 715w" width="833"/>Who are P-5 members?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The victors of World War 2 – USA, RUSSIA, CHINA, UK, FRANCE.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the hurdles that India facing?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Elite club:</strong> Most exclusive club in international relations. All other clubs have been breached. Until a quarter century ago, the nuclear weapon club had five members, the same five as the P-5.India, Pakistan, North Korea and Israel have since joined the club. But UNSC is unbreachable till date.</li>
<li><strong>All are reluctant: </strong>The inescapable fact is that none of the P-5 wants the UNSC’s ranks to be increased. One or the other of them might make some noise about supporting one or more of the aspirants. Each is confident that someone among them will torpedo the enlargement of the club. Declarations of support for India’s candidature need to be taken with a fistful of salt.</li>
<li><strong>Veto issue: </strong>Former UN Secretary-General Kofi Annan bluntly told India not to expect to get the veto power. Though India has said it will not accept a seat without veto power.</li>
<li><strong>China-Pakistan axis: </strong>China, which has historically blocked India’s aspirations to become a permanent member of the UNSC. Beijing has an “all-weather ally” in Islamabad, another neighbour who also strongly opposes India’s candidature to the UNSC.</li>
<li><strong>Odd man out: </strong>Four out of the five permanent members of the United Nations Security Council have bilaterally expressed official affirmations of support for India’s candidature to a permanent seat in an expanded UN Security Council.</li>
<li><strong>Coffee club opposition: </strong>Members like Italy, South Korea, Canada, Spain, Mexico, Turkey, Argentina, Pakistan, and others, who have together formed the Uniting for Consensus (UfC) movement. Also known as the Coffee Club, the movement argues that bids for permanent seats by India, Japan, Germany, and Brazil (G4 countries) must not be considered without first reaching an international consensus regarding the form and size of the new Security council.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641318" height="310" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768.jpeg 770w" width="550"/>What are the Efforts taken by India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Text based negotiation: </strong>External affairs minister is canvassing for the country’s candidature, meeting his counterparts from several countries. He has repeated the call, made often in the past, for a text-based negotiation on what has been euphemistically referred to as the reform of the United Nations Security Council (UNSC), i.e., negotiation on a written document outlining the proposed reform instead of just holding forth verbally.</li>
<li><strong>Woking together with G-4: </strong>INDIA, JAPAN, GEMANY, BRAZIL works together to get permanent UNSC seat however these efforts are opposed by coffee club.</li>
<li><strong>Multilateral engagements: </strong>By expanding its footprint in multilateral organisations, India is gearing up to become a global rule-maker.</li>
<li>Distinguished group of experts suggested a few years ago that a new category of semi-permanent members should be created. Countries would be elected for a period of eight to 10 years and would be eligible for re-election. India ought to give serious consideration to this idea.</li>
<li><strong>With or without veto: </strong>According to former foreign secretary Chinmaya gharekhan, if by some miracle we are offered or manage to obtain permanent membership without veto, we must grab it. Even a permanent membership without veto will be tremendously helpful in protecting our interests.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Looking at the present geopolitical divide India’s dream of seat at the highest table is unlikely to get fulfilled in near future. India must analyse the utility of UNSC membership for securing its national interest. India should not give up anything in bargain against UNSC seat which harms its international interest.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. India’s quest for UNSC is like “Sisyphus carrying the boulder  just to see how it falls”. In this context Analyse the utility of Permanent seat at UNSC.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-quest-for-permanent-membership-of-unsc/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Urban planning can change the future of cities to happy cities</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-planning/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Urbanization issues</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Urban planning" class="alignnone wp-image-629340" height="285" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 506px) 100vw, 506px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city.jpg 1280w" width="506"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the recent few years, the growth of the economy and urbanization have accelerated. Rapid unplanned urbanization has put extreme pressure on natural resources.</li>
<li>Unplanned urbanization, however, exerts great strain on our cities. In fact, the Covid-19 pandemic has revealed the dire need for the planning and management of our cities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does urban planning mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Urban planning, also known as regional planning, town planning, city planning is a technical and political process that is focused on the development and design of land use and the built environment, including air, water, and the infrastructure passing into and out of urban areas, such as transportation, communications, and distribution networks and their accessibility.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are ‘Happy Cities’?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A term that follows the Green City, Sustainable City, Liveable City, in the lingo of urban planning</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a smart city?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A smart city is one that uses information and communication technologies to enhance citizen engagement. It is a neo-vision which seeks to improve the delivery of services in urban areas. The following story maps out the steps being taken by India to explore this concept in practice.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Smart Cities Mission?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sustainable cities</strong>: The Smart Cities Mission aims at developing 100 cities, which were shortlisted, into self-sustainable urban settlements.</li>
<li><strong>Chronology</strong>: The mission was launched on June 25, 2015 and was projected as one aimed at transforming the process of urban development in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Comprehensive revamp</strong>: Among its strategic components is ‘area-based development’, which includes city improvement (retrofitting), city renewal (redevelopment) and city extension (Greenfield development), plus a pan-city initiative in which ‘smart solutions’ are applied covering larger parts of the city.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Fast Facts – Urbanization in India</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Most Urbanized States: Tamil Nadu 43.9%; Maharashtra 4%; Gujarat  37.4%</li>
<li>3 out of world’s 21 mega cities: Mumbai (19 mill); Delhi (15 mill); Kolkata (14 mill)</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Urban planning" class="alignnone wp-image-629341" height="216" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 514px) 100vw, 514px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84-300x126.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84-300x126.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84.jpg 450w" width="514"/>Urban planning challenges </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Planning</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Many urban governments lack a modern planning framework</li>
<li>The multiplicity of local bodies obstructs efficient planning and land use</li>
<li>Rigid master plans and restrictive zoning regulations limit the land available for building, constricting cities’ abilities to grow in accordance with changing needs<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Housing</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Building regulations that limit urban density – such as floor space indexes – reduce the number of houses available, thereby pushing up property prices</li>
<li>Outdated rent control regulations reduce the number of houses available on rent – a critical option for the poor</li>
<li>Policy, planning, and regulation deficiencies lead to a proliferation of slums</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Service delivery</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is a strong bias towards adding physical infrastructure rather than providing financially and environmentally sustainable services</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Infrastructure</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Most urban bodies do not generate the revenues needed to renew infrastructure, nor do they have the creditworthiness to access capital markets for funds</li>
<li>Urban transport planning needs to be more holistic – there is a focus on moving vehicles rather than meeting the needs of the large numbers of people who walk or ride bicycles in India’s towns and cities.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Environment:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The deteriorating urban environment is taking a toll on people’s health and productivity and diminishing their quality of life.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Urban planning" class="alignnone wp-image-629343" height="301" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 572px) 100vw, 572px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120.jpg 1200w" width="572"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-reforms-in-urban-planning-capacity-in-india/">Solution offered by NITI ayog committee report on urban planning</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Demystifying Planning and Involving Citizens: </strong>While it is important to maintain the master plans’ technical rigour, it is equally important to demystify them for enabling citizens’ participation at relevant stages. Therefore, the committee strongly recommends a ‘Citizen Outreach Campaign’ for demystifying urban planning.</li>
<li><strong>Steps for Enhancing the Role of Private Sector: </strong>The report recommends that concerted measures must be taken at multiple levels to strengthen the role of the private sector to improve the overall planning capacity in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Revision of Town and Country Planning Acts: </strong>Most States have enacted the Town and Country Planning acts, that enable them to prepare and notify master plans for implementation. However, many need to be reviewed and upgraded.</li>
<li><strong>Revision of Town and Country Planning Acts: </strong>Most States have enacted the Town and Country Planning Acts, that enable them to prepare and notify master plans for implementation. However, many need to be reviewed and upgraded.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Interesting fact </strong></p>
<p>India is home to 11% of the total global urban population.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Government initiatives</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Atal Mission for Rejuvenation and Urban Transformation (AMRUT);</li>
<li>Pradhan Mantri Awas Yojana (PMAY) – Housing for all (Urban),</li>
<li>Smart Cities Mission (SCM),</li>
<li>Swachh Bharat Mission (SBM),</li>
<li>Heritage City Development and Augmentation Yojana (HRIDAY);</li>
<li>Deen Dayal Antyodaya Yojana – National Urban Livelihoods Mission (DAY-NULM).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>What is now increasingly understood, is that urban planning and design can be a powerful contributor to the happiness of citizens. The structure and layout of our streets, the availability of green spaces, the possibility of using urban spaces freely, the inclusion of beauty in public space.</li>
<li>It is safe to assume that when there are avenues for a community to come together in a pleasant environment, which is accessible to everyone, it can only increase well-being.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>Can urban planning and design change Indian cities to be happy cities? Express your views by addressing the roadblocks in the same.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-planning/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Advantage of Market Based Economic Dispatch</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/market-based-economic-dispatch-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economics,Energy,Infrastructure</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641126" height="316" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-3-1.jpg" width="565"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The game changing scheme is being proposed by the central government in power sector governance. The scheme under consideration is the market-based economic dispatch (MBED). When it comes to any drastic change in the power sector, a clash between the Centre and the states is inevitable.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Market Based Economic Dispatch (MBED)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Market Based Economic Dispatch (MBED) is new approach towards power distribution to help distribution companies save costs and transition to a new form of power market.</li>
<li>It is a shift to a centralised framework, marks a radical departure from the current decentralised, voluntary pool-based electricity market.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641122" height="291" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-1-2.jpg" width="508"/>What is the framework under MBED?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The cheapest power from across the country will be dispatched to meet the system wide demand. The architecture would also lead to a “Market clearing price”.</li>
<li>Sellers and buyers will place their bids for the day market, and an outcome of this will be the discovery of the market clearing price.</li>
<li>This process is expected to generate significant savings for consumers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Present system of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/assessment-of-discoms/">power Distribution?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Under the present regime, each distribution company (Discom) is bound by the power purchase agreements (PPAs) that it holds.</li>
<li>It can schedule power only from its own PPAs, starting from the cheapest PPA and then moving up; it cannot schedule power from the PPA of some other distribution company.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> <img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641124" height="365" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-2.jpg" width="488"/></strong><strong>What are the drawbacks of present system?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Financial Burdon:</strong></li>
<li>The Indian government responded to COVID-19’s economic shock with a stimulus package of Rs.20-lakh crore, out of which Rs.90,000 crore was earmarked for discoms (later upgraded to Rs.1,25,000 crore). While it was called a stimulus, it is really a loan, meant to be used by discoms to pay off generators.</li>
<li>Discoms owe one lakh crore rupees to generators, and without such an infusion the chain will collapse.</li>
<li><strong>States are defaulters:</strong></li>
<li>State governments are the biggest defaulters, responsible for an estimated a third of trade receivables, besides not paying subsidies in full or on time.</li>
<li>On an annual cash flow basis, the shortfall in subsidy payments appears very low, only about 1% but cumulative unpaid subsidies, with modest carrying costs, make discoms poorer by over Rs.70,000 crore just over the last 10 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641125" height="323" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-12-1.jpg" width="570"/>What will be the Advantages of MBED?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Centralized approach: </strong>The centralised dispatch will be done with the assistance of electricity exchanges. Each discom and each generator will place a bid in the day-ahead market of the electricity exchanges, which will indicate how much power is being demanded/ supplied at what price.</li>
<li><strong>Pan India market: </strong>These bids will enable the load dispatcher to construct a pan India demand and supply curve, the intersection of which will determine the market clearing price (MCP). All generators whose variable cost of generation is below the MCP will be asked to dispatch and all of them will receive the same MCP irrespective of what they had bid. Generators whose variable cost is higher than the MCP will sit idle.</li>
<li><strong>No loss to discom: </strong>The MBED is so devised that its operation will not affect the current finances of either the discoms or the generators for the following reasons.</li>
<li>First, the fixed cost of the generators will still be paid by the discoms outside the market as determined by the regulator.</li>
<li>Second, if the MCP comes out to be Rs 3 per unit, and if in the case of any PPA, the variable cost is Rs 2.75 per unit, then the generator will compensate the discom to the extent of Rs 0.25 per unit. Similarly, if the MCP so determined is Rs 2.50 per unit, then the discom will compensate the generator to the extent of Rs 0.25 per unit.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing efficiency: </strong>The logic is that by adopting MBED, only the relatively efficient plants will generate, without affecting the revenues of either the discoms or generators. Hence, the total cost of generation under the MBED system would be less.</li>
<li><strong>Less pollution: </strong>There would be less coal consumption and less carbon dioxide injected into the atmosphere.</li>
<li><strong>Easy integration with renewable: </strong>It would also mean less movement of coal leading to decongestion of railway tracks. Further, there would be enhanced renewable integration since the balancing area would shift from state to national level.</li>
<li><strong>Single market clearing price (MCP): </strong>Incidentally, since there are three electricity exchanges in operation today, there would be three different MCPs determined. What we need is a single MCP for which there will be an institution called the “market coupler”. It will be the job of the coupler to determine a national MCP based on what has arrived at the three different exchanges.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why states are opposing?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>High generation cost: </strong>The reason is the state-owned generators are relatively inefficient and may have to sit idle as their variable cost of generation is likely to be more than the MCP.</li>
<li><strong>Political backlash: </strong>Today, the states are operating their own generators to the hilt, even though they are inefficient, and drawing only the balance from the more efficient interstate generating stations. Keeping state generators idle has its own political implications and no state would be enamoured of this idea.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Power distribution companies (discom) are sinkhole of government finances. Every year budgetary support is needed to this loss-making companies , With due consultation, all states and union territories need to adopt and implement the MBED and save the resources for other development activities.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. </strong><strong>India has became the power surplus nation, however power distribution and financial unsustainability is still a nightmare for union and states. Elaborate.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/market-based-economic-dispatch-2/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian Railways powerful experiment on AC III tier economy class coaches</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ac-iii-tier-economy-class-coaches/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economics, Infrastructure,Transport</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="AC III tier economy class coaches" class="alignnone wp-image-641307" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 633px) 100vw, 633px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-300x171.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-300x171.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1024x583.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-768x437.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1536x874.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-2048x1166.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1200x683.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1980x1127.jpg 1980w" width="633"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian Railways’ experiment to introduce AC III tier economy class coaches has started to pay off. Since its introduction, in the last one year, these coaches have earned the Railways more than Rs.230 crore in revenue.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="AC III tier economy class" class="alignnone wp-image-641094" height="289" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-6.jpg" width="514"/>What is </strong><strong>AC III tier economy class coach?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AC 3 tier economy class in Indian Railways is a milestone concerning pocket-friendly traveling experience for common man.</li>
<li>With fare slightly more than sleeper class and lower than conventional AC class.</li>
<li>The objective of the railway is to move sleeper class passengers to a comfortable AC class with luxurious facilities. AC-3 tier comprises air-conditioned coaches with 64 sleeping berths.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>When it is introduced?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian Railway has introduced the first AC III tier Economy Class for North Central Railway Zone in 2021 to provide a convenient traveling experience to the passengers<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>As of now 7 trains are equipped with AC III tier economy class coaches are running on the tracks</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="AC III tier economy class coaches" class="alignnone wp-image-641308" height="377" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 669px) 100vw, 669px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038.jpg 1600w" width="669"/>Features of the AC </strong>III<strong> tier economy coach</strong><strong>:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pocket friendly</strong>: According to the Indian Railways, the fair in these coaches are cheaper than the normal AC three-tier coach. Fares in AC III tier economy are 6%-7% cheaper than the AC III tier class. The economy class has a capacity of 83 berths compared to 72 in the regular coach.</li>
<li><strong>Divyang friendly and modern designs: </strong>The coaches were specially designed for the convenience of the divyangs. Providing Improved and modular design of berths and ergonomically designed ladder for accessing the middle and upper berths etc.</li>
<li><strong>Modern features: </strong>In these, modern arrangements have been made for mobile phones and magazine holders, fire safety, personalised reading lights, AC vents, USB points, mobile charging points.</li>
<li><strong>Optimum Speed</strong>: These air-conditioned three-tier economy class coaches are capable of running at an optimum speed of 160 kilometers per hour.</li>
<li><strong>More Capacity:</strong> The economy class has a capacity of 83 berths compared to 72 in the regular coach.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the current status of AC </strong><strong>III tier class?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>AC- III tier, the favorite mode of train travel of people falling in the bottom rung of the middle class, is the only class that earns the Railways profit among all its passenger services.</li>
<li>The AC III tier is the only class of service which has generated consistent profits for the Railways. Between FY16 and FY20,</li>
<li>AC III tier coaches carried only 1% of the total passengers, but were responsible for 21% of the earnings from travelers. Such a low-passenger, high-revenue dichotomy was not seen in any other class.</li>
<li>It is not as expensive as the other AC classes and at the same time, its share in revenue has not been impacted by the relatively low pricing</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong style="letter-spacing: -0.0415625em;"><img alt="AC III tier economy class coaches" class="alignnone wp-image-641309" height="464" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 619px) 100vw, 619px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84998782-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84998782-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84998782.jpg 400w" width="619"/>Revenue of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vande-bharat-production-to-begin/">Indian railways</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The overall revenue of Indian Railways at the end of August 2022 was Rs 95,486.58 crore, showing an increase 38 per cent over the corresponding period of last year.</li>
<li>Goods revenue climbed by Rs 10,780.03 crore (or 20 per cent) to Rs 65,505.02 crore till August-end this year</li>
<li>The revenue from passenger traffic was Rs 25,276.54 crore, an increase of Rs 13,574.44 crore (116 per cent) year-on-year.</li>
<li>Passenger traffic also increased compared to last year in both the segments — reserved and unreserved</li>
<li>Railways’ total revenue during the entire last fiscal (2021-22) stood at Rs.1,91,278.29 crore.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the issues faced by Indian railways to increase its revenue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cross Subsidized: </strong>The cross-subsidiszation in respect of second class, ordinary class and suburban services has increased continuously in the past five years with subsidy on ordinary class being the maximum,</li>
<li><strong>Concessional fare</strong>: The revenue forgone in passenger earnings due to concessions to various categories of passengers (physically challenged persons, patients, senior citizens, Izzat monthly season tickets, press correspondents, sport persons and war widows among others) increased from Rs 1,994.83 crore in 2018-19 to Rs 2,058.61 crore in 2019-20.</li>
<li><strong>Low -Revenue dichotomy in Expensive class:</strong> A high-passenger, low-revenue dichotomy was seen in the inexpensive classes. For instance, over 90% passengers travelled by second class which accounted for only 37% of the earnings.</li>
<li><strong>Operational Los</strong><strong>s</strong>: Operational losses (in crore) incurred while operating various classes of service. For instance, in operating AC first class service, the Railways incurred a loss of 403 crore in FY20</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Adding more AC III tier economy class coaches is a step in the right direction as it has shown positive result in revenue generation for railways and it provides a travel with dignity to a common man. But If Indian railway has to benefit it have to work extensively on operational loss incurred out of low Revenue dichotomy in Expensive classes.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. Indian Railways is often referred to as the lifeline of the country but runs at a loss when it comes to running class-divided coaches. In this context discuss the utility of class divided coaches.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ac-iii-tier-economy-class-coaches/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Ranipur TR: 4th Tiger Reserve in UP</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ranipur-tr-4th-tiger-reserve-in-up/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ranipur Tiger Reserve</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="ranipur" class="alignnone wp-image-641605 size-full" height="939" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tiger-reserves.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tiger-reserves.jpg 780w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tiger-reserves-249x300.jpg 249w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tiger-reserves-768x925.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tiger-reserves-748x900.jpg 748w" width="780"/></p>
<p>The UP cabinet approved the notification of Ranipur Tiger Reserve under Section 38(v) of the Wild life (Protection) Act of 1972.</p>
<h4>About Ranipur WS</h4>
<ul>
<li>Ranipur WS, was founded in 1977, is one of the attractions of Chitrakoot district in Uttar Pradesh.</li>
<li>It is spread over 230 sq.km and is noted for its diverse wildlife, but is not very frequently visited by tourists because of the difficult access.</li>
<li>The Ranipur TR has tropical dry deciduous forests and is home to fauna such as tigers, leopards, sloth bears, spotted deer, sambhar, chinkara and a number of birds and reptiles, the statement added.</li>
<li>The Ranipur TR will be the fourth in UP, after Dudhwa, Pilibhit and Amangarh (buffer of Corbett Tiger Reserve).</li>
<li>It will also be the first in the state’s portion of the Bundelkhand region, which it shares with neighbouring Madhya Pradesh.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why make it a tiger reserve?</h4>
<ul>
<li>RWS has no tigers of its own.</li>
<li>But pugmarks of the animals are frequently seen there as tigers from nearby Panna frequent it.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ranipur-tr-4th-tiger-reserve-in-up/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Forex Reserves to dip by $23 billion by Dec</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/forex-reserves-to-dip-by-23-billion-by-dec/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Forex reserves, BoP</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>India’s depleted foreign exchange reserves are likely to drop further, falling to their lowest level in more than two years by end-2022.</p>
<h4><strong>Forex to dip<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In a battle that has so far failed to staunch the rupee’s fall to a record low against the greenback, the RBI has drawn down its foreign exchange reserves by close to $100 billion, to $545 billion.</li>
<li>Those reserves are forecast to fall another $23 billion to $523 billion by the end of this year.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Foreign Exchange (Forex) Reserve?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Foreign exchange reserves are important assets held by the central bank in foreign currencies as reserves.</li>
<li>They are commonly used to support the exchange rate and set monetary policy.</li>
<li>In India’s case, foreign reserves include Gold, Dollars, and the IMF’s quota for Special Drawing Rights.</li>
<li>Most of the reserves are usually held in US dollars, given the currency’s importance in the international financial and trading system.</li>
<li>Some central banks keep reserves in Euros, British pounds, Japanese yen, or Chinese yuan, in addition to their US dollar reserves.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>India’s forex reserves cover:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Foreign Currency Assets (FCAs)</li>
<li>Special Drawing Rights (SDRs)</li>
<li>Gold Reserves</li>
<li>Reserve position with the International Monetary Fund (IMF)</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Countries with the highest foreign reserves</strong></h4>
<p>Currently, China has the largest reserves followed by Japan and Switzerland. India has overtaken Russia to become the fourth largest country with foreign exchange reserves. (Data from August 2022)</p>
<ol>
<li>China – $3,349 Billion</li>
<li>Japan – $1,376 Billion</li>
<li>Switzerland – $1,074 Billion</li>
<li>India – $612.73 Billion</li>
<li>Russia – $597.40 Billion</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Why are these reserves so important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>All international transactions are settled in US dollars and, therefore, required to support India’s imports.</li>
<li>More importantly, they need to maintain support and confidence for central bank action, whether monetary policy action or any exchange rate intervention to support the domestic currency.</li>
<li>It also helps to limit any vulnerability due to sudden disturbances in foreign capital flows, which may arise during a crisis.</li>
<li>Holding liquid foreign currency provides a cushion against such effects and provides confidence that there will still be enough foreign exchange to help the country with crucial imports in case of external shocks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Initiatives taken by the government to increase forex</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To increase the foreign exchange reserves, the Government of India has taken many initiatives like AatmaNirbhar Bharat, in which India has to be made a self-reliant nation so that India does not have to import things that India can produce.</li>
<li>Other than AatmaNirbhar Bharat, the government has started schemes like Duty Exemption Scheme, Remission of Duty or Taxes on Export Product (RoDTEP), Nirvik (Niryat Rin Vikas Yojana) scheme, etc.</li>
<li>Apart from these schemes, India is one of the top countries that attracted the highest amount of Foreign Direct Investment, thereby improving India’s foreign exchange reserves.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/forex-reserves-to-dip-by-23-billion-by-dec/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre extends Free Ration Scheme PMGKAY for 3 months</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-extends-free-ration-scheme-pmgkay-for-3-months/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PMGKAY</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Schemes related to food security</p></div></div><p>The Union government has extended the Pradhan Mantri Garib Kalyan Anna Yojana (PMGKAY) for another three months from October 1.</p>
<h4><strong>What is PMGKAY?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>PMGKAY is a food security welfare scheme announced by the GoI in March 2020, during the COVID-19 pandemic in India.</li>
<li>The program is operated by the Department of Food and Public Distribution under the Ministry of Consumer Affairs, Food and Public Distribution.</li>
<li>The scale of this welfare scheme makes it the largest food security program in the world.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Targets of the scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To feed the <strong>poorest citizens of India</strong> by providing grain through the <strong>Public Distribution System</strong> to all the priority households (ration card holders and those identified by the Antyodaya Anna Yojana scheme).</li>
<li>PMGKAY provides <strong>5 kg of rice or wheat</strong> (according to regional dietary preferences) <strong>per person/month</strong> and <strong>1 kg of dal</strong> to each family holding a ration card.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>At what rate are food grains provided under the NFSA?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>NFSA beneficiaries are entitled to receive foodgrains at highly subsidised rates.</li>
<li>Under the food law, rice is provided at Rs 3 per kg, wheat at Rs 2 per kg, and coarse grains at Re 1 per kg.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why was such a scheme needed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The devastation by pandemic has increased manifold in the second wave resulting into localized restrictions and lockdowns from the States.</li>
<li>This resulted in massive jobs losses in urban areas since the largest employers being construction and hospitality sectors have been completely shut down.</li>
<li>The virus penetrated deeper in the countryside in rural areas halting almost every sources of livelihood.</li>
<li>These areas are such where 60% of the income was earned from non-pharm activities. This resulted in livelihood losses of large section of population.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Success of the scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It was the first step by the government when pandemic affected India.</li>
<li>The scheme reached its targeted population feeding almost 80Cr people.</li>
<li>It has proven to be more of a safety net to migrant people who had job and livelihood losses.</li>
<li>This has also ensured nutrition security to children of the migrant workers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Failures</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme has been affected by widespread corruption, leakages and failure to distribute grain to the intended recipients.</li>
<li>Several of the states above have claimed that the ineffective distribution has been caused by the beneficiaries, especially migrant workers, not being available to receive their rations.</li>
<li>Out of the 79.25 crore beneficiaries under the National Food Security Act (NFSA), only 55 crore have so far received their 5 kg.</li>
<li>However, almost 90% of beneficiaries have received their regular subsidized grain for the month, raising questions over why the free grain has reached fewer beneficiaries.</li>
<li>Many people were denied their share due to inability to access ration cards.</li>
<li>Livelihood losses led to decline in aggregate demand and resulted into lowest ever consumption expenditure by the people owing to scarcity of cash.</li>
<li>This in turn led to selling of the free grains obtained in the local markets for cash.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There should be an all-encompassing database for migrant workers and their family. This should accurately capture the data on migration.</li>
<li>The One Nation One Ration Card should be implemented in true spirit by all the states.</li>
<li>Along with food security, there should be a sustainable income support through schemes like MGNREGS accompanied by free vaccines in nearest future.</li>
<li>The leakages in PDS should be minimized through modernize PDS.</li>
<li>To avoid leakages, there should be food-token system.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-extends-free-ration-scheme-pmgkay-for-3-months/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>MHA bans PFI for five years under UAPA</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mha-bans-pfi-five-years-under-uapa/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UAPA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Terror financing and money laundering</p></div></div><p>The Union Home Ministry has declared the Popular Front of India (PFI) and its front organizations as an “unlawful association” under the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act (UAPA).</p>
<h4><strong>PFI under Unlawful (Activities) Prevention Act (UAPA)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The UAPA is aimed at effective prevention of unlawful activities associations in India.</li>
<li>Its main objective was to make powers available for dealing with activities directed against the integrity and sovereignty of India</li>
<li>It is an upgrade on the Terrorist and Disruptive Activities (Prevention) Act TADA, which was allowed to lapse in 1995 and the Prevention of Terrorism Act (POTA) was repealed in 2004.</li>
<li>It was originally passed in 1967 under the then Congress government led by former Prime Minister Indira Gandhi.</li>
<li>Till 2004, “unlawful” activities referred to actions related to secession and cession of territory. Following the 2004 amendment, “terrorist act” was added to the list of offences.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Unlawful Activities and Associations?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The UAPA lays down the definitions and rules for designating an organisation as an “unlawful association” if it is engaged in certain types of activities.</li>
<li>Under Section 3 of the UAPA Act, the government has powers to declare an association “unlawful”.</li>
<li>The government can then issue a notification designating such an organisation as a terrorist organisation, if it believes that the organisation is part of “terrorist activities.”</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(1) Unlawful Activites</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Under section 2(o) of the UAPA, an unlawful activity in relation to an individual or association means – Any action taken by such an individual or association (whether by committing an act or by words, either spoken or written, or by signs or by visible representation or otherwise), –</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Works for the <strong><u>Cession of a part of the territory of India</u></strong> or the secession of a part of the territory of India from the Union</li>
<li>Disclaims, questions, disrupts or is intended to <strong><u>Disrupt the sovereignty and territorial integrity of India</u></strong>; or</li>
<li>which causes or is intended to cause <strong><u>Disaffection against India</u></strong>;</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Related and ancillary acts, including financing, support or promotion of any such activities are also “unlawful activity”.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Unlawful Association</strong></p>
<p>The UAPA also defines an “Unlawful Association” under section 2(p) as meaning any association,–</p>
<ol>
<li>which has for its object any unlawful activity, or which <strong><u>encourages or aids persons to undertake any unlawful activity</u></strong>, or of which the members undertake such activity or</li>
<li>which <strong><u>encourages or aids persons to undertake any such activity</u></strong>, or of which the members undertake any such activity</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Reading the ban on PFI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At present, the MHA notification published has said that the PFI and its affiliated organisations are being notified as “Unlawful Associations” with immediate effect.</li>
<li>The charges against PFI are-</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Pursuing a secret agenda to radicalize a particular section of society</li>
<li>Working towards undermining the concept of democracy and</li>
<li>Showing sheer disrespect towards the constitutional authority and constitutional set up of the country</li>
<li>Gathering funds and ideological support from outside the country</li>
<li>Money laundering</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Immediate trigger for PFI’s ban</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PFI is accused of engaging in violent and barbaric acts.</li>
<li>Criminal violent acts carried out by PFI include chopping off the limb of a college professor, cold-blooded killings of persons associated with organisations espousing other faiths.</li>
<li>It has been allegedly involved in obtaining explosives to target prominent people and places and destruction of public property.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does the ‘ban’ mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The notification means that the membership of, support or financing to the PFI and the allied banned organizations, is now ILLEGAL.</li>
<li>Any person who is a member of these organisations can face arrest, and joining membership of these organisations is a criminal offence.</li>
<li>The government can also seize the properties, bank accounts and offices connected to these organisations.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mha-bans-pfi-five-years-under-uapa/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Is Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022 Flawless?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/draft-telecommunications-bill/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Right to Privacy</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Cyber security,Right to privacy,Technology</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641528" height="415" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 622px) 100vw, 622px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31.jpeg 1200w" width="622"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Keeping an eye on the telecommunication regulatory framework Supreme Court issued substantive legal reform on surveillance laws in India. Union government has published the Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022 to replace the Telegraph Act, 1885.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Over two decades ago, allegations of surveillance against politicians led to a CBI inquiry and report against V P Singh’s government. The allegations revealed that imaginary reasons were given for ordering phone tapping without authorization.</li>
<li>Last years, many publications reported that phones of several dozen Indian journalists, lawyers and human rights activists had been compromised using an invasive Israeli-developed malware called Pegasus.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641527" height="406" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58.jpeg 1024w" width="608"/>What is Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The draft Indian Telecommunication Bill, 2022 is an attempt by the Department of Telecommunications (DoT) to consolidate various legislations presently governing the telecommunication landscape in India.</li>
<li>The Bill seeks to replace three laws, the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885, the Indian Wireless Telegraphy Act, 1933 and the Telegraph Wires (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1950.</li>
<li>The new regulatory framework is to bring the law at par with technological advancements and remove obsolete provisions from the colonial era laws.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the current laws governing communication surveillance in India?</strong></h4>
<p>Communication surveillance in India takes place primarily under two laws:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Telegraph Act, 1885</strong>: It deals with interception of calls.</li>
<li><strong>Call interception:</strong>Under Section 5(2) of this law, the government can intercept calls only in certain situations.</li>
<li><strong>For sovereignty:</strong>They include the interests of the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the state, friendly relations with foreign states or public order, or for preventing incitement to the commission of an offense.</li>
<li><strong>Free speech restrictions:</strong>These are the same restrictions imposed on free speech under Article 19(2) of the Constitution.</li>
<li><strong>Exceptions for journalists:</strong>A provision in Section 5(2) states that even this lawful interception cannot take place against journalists.</li>
<li><strong>Information Technology Act, 2000: </strong>It was enacted to deal with surveillance of all electronic communication, following the Supreme Court’s intervention in 1996.</li>
<li><strong>Electronic surveillance:</strong>Section 69 of the IT Act and the IT (Procedure for Safeguards for Interception, Monitoring, and Decryption of Information) Rules, 2009 were enacted to further the legal framework for electronic surveillance.</li>
<li><strong>Data interception:</strong>Under the IT Act, all electronic transmission of data can be intercepted.</li>
<li>Section 69 of the IT Act adds another aspect that makes it broader — interception, monitoring, and decryption of digital information “for the investigation of an offense”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641524" height="631" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-278x300.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-278x300.jpeg 278w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-768x829.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-834x900.jpeg 834w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56.jpeg 949w" width="585"/>How the loopholes in the current system breaching the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-privacy/">Data Privacy?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>No comprehensive data Protection Law: </strong></li>
<li>No comprehensive data protection law leaving ambiguities over several laws.</li>
<li>A comprehensive data protection law to address the gaps in existing frameworks for surveillance is yet to enact.</li>
<li><strong>Unaccountable, opaque exercise of surveillance: </strong></li>
<li>The Telegraph Act contains broad and excessive powers of interception and surveillance of communications carried out through any telegraph.</li>
<li>The surveillance power is principally contained under Section 5(2), and has resulted in an unaccountable, opaque and unconstitutional exercise of surveillance that has led to accusations across the political spectrum.</li>
<li><strong>Less transparency:</strong></li>
<li>Ministry of Home Affairs refuses to disclose even aggregate data on the number of surveillance orders issued by it each year illegally gathered evidence is being sought to prosecute people.</li>
<li>For instance, the Bombay High Court about three years ago noted in a case that premier investigating agencies such as the CBI have used, interception orders (that) neither have sanction of law nor issued for legitimate aim.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641526" height="398" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 596px) 100vw, 596px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-1024x682.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-1200x800.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00.jpeg 1280w" width="596"/>Key features of</strong> <strong>the</strong> <strong>Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Broad Definitions: </strong></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>The Bill introduces a broad definition of ‘telecommunication services’.</li>
<li>It now includes internet-based services, in-flight and maritime connectivity, interpersonal communications services, machine to machine communication services, and over-the-top (OTT) based communication services that are made available to users by telecommunication</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>KYC and caller id requirements: </strong></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>The Bill requires licensed entities to ensure that they identify the persons to whom they provide telecommunication services.</li>
<li>The Bill places an obligation on telecommunication service providers to do this through a ‘verifiable mode’, as prescribed by the government.</li>
<li><strong>Licensing, registration, and authorization:</strong></li>
<li>Under the Bill, four types of permissions are identified – license, registration, authorization and assignment.</li>
<li>While the Bill does not differentiate between the four types of permissions, it clarifies that a license is only required for providing telecommunication services or operating telecommunication networks</li>
<li><strong>Wide ranging powers of Central Government: </strong></li>
<li>The Bill includes wide-ranging powers for the central and state governments in the event of a public emergency or in interest of public safety.</li>
<li>These powers include taking temporary possession of any telecommunication services, suspension of transmission in cases of public emergency, interception/detainment/disclosure of messages, suspension of communications, or otherwise transmit certain announcements for public safety and national security purposes.</li>
<li><strong>User protection and duties: </strong>User has been declared as an important policy objective of the Government. It places a duty on users to not furnish false information, suppress material information or impersonate others when proving identity to avail telecommunication services.</li>
<li><strong>Offences and penalties</strong>: Any offence under the Bill may be punished with a fine, imprisonment, suspension of telecommunication services or a combination of the above. For companies, the employees who were responsible for the conduct or the business relating to the offence at the time the offence was committed will be punished.</li>
<li><strong>Dispute resolution mechanism</strong>: The Bill provides for the right of appeal before the appellate authority. It also creates an enabling provision for the Central Government to set up an alternate dispute resolution mechanism such as arbitration, mediation or other processes of dispute resolution</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Concerns over the Draft Telecommunication bill, 2022?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Regulatory overlaps:</strong>The broad of the definition of ‘telecommunication services’ include OTT communication platforms such as WhatsApp, Telegram, Signal among others, may potentially lead to regulatory or jurisdictional overlaps.</li>
<li><strong>Unchecked use of State powers:</strong>The Bill gives broad powers to the central government in prescribed situations without any accompanying checks and balances. The Bill empowers the central and state government to intercept messages in the interest of public safety and emergency without the providing clearly defined guardrails for it.</li>
<li><strong>Undefined National security: </strong>The term, national security is left undefined and does not match constitutional precedent or text which instead uses the phrase,in the interests of the security of state</li>
<li><strong>Users Less choice in the privacy and security of their digital footprint:</strong></li>
<li>Power to prescribe standards under Clause 23, which may result in regulations as recently issued by the Computer Emergency Response Team (CERT-In) that have resulted in the closure of servers or services by leading, global VPN providers such as Proton and TunnelBear.</li>
<li>All of this practically means that users will have less choice in the privacy and security of their digital footprint, as these powers will lead to requirements to locally register and host data, and comply with requirements to identify users (KYC requirements).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There should be some reasonable basis or some tangible evidence to initiate or seek approval for interception by State authorities. Any digression from the ethical and legal parameters set by law would be tantamount to a deliberate invasion of citizens.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Any deviation from the moral and legal parameters set by the law would amount to a deliberate attack on citizens. In this context discuss the data privacy of citizens in the era of massive expansion of internet and mobile usage.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/draft-telecommunications-bill/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Transboundary Flood Disasters</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/transboundary-flood-disasters/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Transboundary Rivers</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Disaster Management</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Transboundary Flood Disasters" class="alignnone wp-image-641871 size-full" height="444" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 828px) 100vw, 828px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fld.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fld.jpg 828w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fld-300x161.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fld-768x412.jpg 768w" width="828"/></strong></h4>
<h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Pakistan experiencing devastation, with a spread of diseases and severe shortage of potable water after intense flooding. In June this year Assam experienced one of its worst floods in which it affected over 30 districts. Assam and Bihar frequently suffer from transboundary flood disasters.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-recurring-floods-in-india/">transboundary flood</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Floods that are originate in upper riparian state crosses the international boundary and also affects the lower riparian state. For example, river Brahmaputra causes flood both in China and India simultaneously.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Transboundary Flood Disasters" class="alignnone wp-image-641877 size-full" height="463" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.59.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.59.jpeg 800w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.59-300x174.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.59-768x444.jpeg 768w" width="800"/>How the transboundary floods are difficult to manage than <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/floods/">normal floods</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Flooding is still considered to be a natural phenomenon that cannot be entirely prevented. But it is compounded by the lack of transparency in the sharing of hydrological information and also information relating to activities (such as by one riparian state) that are transboundary in their effect (affecting other riparian states), thus serving as an obstacle in understanding the magnitude of flooding<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Transboundary Flood Disasters" class="alignnone wp-image-641552" height="370" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 654px) 100vw, 654px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1.jpeg 1085w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1-1024x579.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1-768x434.jpeg 768w" width="654"/>What is a riparian state?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A riparian state is state (or country) located alongside a river.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the International laws governing transboundary waters?</strong></h4>
<p>There are at two international treaties that governs the transboundary water</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>UNWC:</strong></li>
<li>United Nations Convention on the Law of the Non-Navigational Use of International Watercourses (UNWC) 1997.UNWC contains a direct reference to floods, which covers harmful conditions and the emergency situations.</li>
<li>Article 27 of the Convention says, Watercourse States shall individually and, where appropriate, jointly, take all appropriate measures to prevent or mitigate conditions that may be harmful to other watercourse States, whether resulting from natural causes or human conduct or desertification.</li>
<li><strong>Environmental Impact Assessment: </strong></li>
<li>The International Court of Justice (ICJ), in the Pulp Mills on the River Uruguay (Argentina vs Uruguay) case of 2010, upheld that conducting a transboundary environmental impact assessment (TEIA) of a planned measure or projects on the shared water course is part of customary international law.</li>
<li>In fact, the ICJ noted that the acting state must notify the affected party of the results of TEIA for assessment of its own damages that are likely to occur.</li>
<li><strong>UNECE: </strong>United Nations Economic Commission for Europe (UNECE) on the Protection and Use of Transboundary Watercourses and International Lakes 1992 (Water Convention).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Transboundary Flood Disasters" class="alignnone wp-image-641881" height="908" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 586px) 100vw, 586px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31.jpeg 720w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31-194x300.jpeg 194w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31-661x1024.jpeg 661w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31-581x900.jpeg 581w" width="586"/>How India manages transboundary flood?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Note:</strong>Neither India nor China are signatory to UNWC or UNCEC.</li>
<li><strong>River Brahmaputra:</strong> India has signed the memorandum of understanding (MoU) with China in 2013 with a view to sharing hydrological information during the flood season (June to September). The MoU does not allow India access to urbanisation and deforestation activities on the Chinese side of the river basin.</li>
<li><strong>Rivers Gandak and kosi</strong>: Floods are also a recurrent problem in the Kosi and Gandak river basins that are shared by India and Nepal.</li>
<li><strong>The India-Nepal Kosi agreement 1954: </strong>Agreement aimed at reducing devastating flooding in the river basin. The treaty-based joint bodies have also tried to refine the early warning systems for flood forecasting.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the suggestions?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Signing the treaty: </strong>Expert suggests, India by becoming a party to either the UNWC and the Water Convention could lay the groundwork for a bilateral treaty on the Brahmaputra but subject to the reservation that it should not insist on the insertion of a dispute settlement mechanism provision<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Information exchange: </strong>In contravention of procedural customary international law obligation, India considers data on transboundary rivers as classified information, which is one of the key challenges in developing cross-border flood warning systems. India needs to share the hydrological and river information for its own sake.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Climate change has accelerated the frequency and intensity of floods across the world. with Changing climate India should also change its strategy to protect its people, to preserve the soil and to save its resources from the scourge of floods.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Questions</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Climate change has created a more difficult challenge in flood management. In this context, what measures can be taken to deal with frequent transboundary floods in India. Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/transboundary-flood-disasters/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Stressed ecology of Bay of Bengal</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bay-of-bengal/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Location,BIMSTEC,Centre for Bay of Bengal Studies</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Foreign Policy,Regional Grouping</p></div></div><h4></h4>
<h4><strong><img alt="Bay of Bengal" class="alignnone wp-image-641718 size-large" height="487" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1024x487.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1024x487.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-300x143.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-768x365.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1536x731.jpeg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1200x571.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1980x942.jpeg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31.jpeg 2048w" width="1024"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At the fourth BIMSTEC summit, Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced the opening of the Centre for Bay of Bengal Studies (CBS) at Nalanda University. The launch of the CBS has once again demonstrated India’s commitment to advancing constructive agendas by forging connections and setting up platforms for all those with an interest in the of Bay of Benagl.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Bay of Bengal" class="alignnone wp-image-641724" height="547" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 545px) 100vw, 545px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-3-1.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-3-1.jpg 224w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-3-1-150x150.jpg 150w" width="545"/>Why <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/opportunity-to-propel-a-bay-of-bengal-dream/">Bay of Bengal</a> is so important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Commerce hub: </strong>The Bay has long been a major commerce hub for the Indian Ocean. It created a conduit between the East and the West in terms for trade and culture.</li>
<li><strong>Emerging arena of maritime warfare: </strong>An Indo-Pacific orientation and the realignment of global economic and military power towards Asia have had a considerable impact on the Bay region.</li>
<li><strong>Communication and Energy</strong>: The key sea lanes of communication in this area are lifelines for global economic security and are crucial to the energy security that powers the economies of many countries in the region.Further, non-traditional dangers including terrorism and climate change have become more prevalent.</li>
<li><strong>Under water resources: </strong>The Bay also provides an opportunity for greater regional cooperation in the environmentally friendly exploration of marine and energy resources. The Bay has a biodiverse marine environment.</li>
<li><strong>Fresh water resources: </strong>It receives the water from some of the world’s largest rivers. It is a partially enclosed sea that has given rise to several geological characteristics.</li>
<li><strong>Ecology: </strong>It is home to many rare and endangered marine species and mangroves, which are essential to the survival of the ecology and the fishing sector.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Bay of Bengal" class="alignnone wp-image-641722" height="422" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 632px) 100vw, 632px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S2352485520306678-gr1.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S2352485520306678-gr1.jpg 565w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S2352485520306678-gr1-300x200.jpg 300w" width="632"/>Why ecology in the region is under threat?</strong></h4>
<p>The region’s maritime environment has changed as are result of major powers expanding their economic and geopolitical influence.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Competition: </strong>Political and cultural engagement, together with economic competition, have taken on new dimensions. More crucially, the Bay’s ecosystem is going through an unprecedented crisis brought on by widespread environmental exploitation and geopolitical unrest.</li>
<li><strong>Resource exploitation</strong>: Species extinction is a result of careless exploitation of the maritime environment, which has severe consequences on biodiversity. Problems such as population growth, altered land use, excessive resource exploitation, salinity, sea level rise, and climate change are exerting significant strain on the Bay’s environment.</li>
<li><strong>Water pollution</strong>: Operational discharge from small and medium feeder ships, shipping collisions, unintentional oil spills, industrial waste, pollution, and the accumulation of non- biodegradable plastic litter are all contributing to the deterioration of the Bay.</li>
<li><strong>Declining ecology</strong>: A dead-zone has formed, and the mangrove trees that protect the shore from the fury of nature are under more threat than ever.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-641728" height="472" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S0959652620334545-fx1-e1664446288766.jpg" width="529"/>What could be the Solutions?</strong></h4>
<p>For a better knowledge of challenges, and strategies to overcome them for the sustainable development of the region, more focused and inter-disciplinary study is required on these issues.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Centre for Bay of Bengal studies: </strong>By founding the CBS, Nalanda University has already started its journey and given the nation a unique interdisciplinary research centre devoted to Bay focused teaching, research, and capacity building. Additionally, scholars from many countries and academic streams are already participating in CBS’s first certificate programme on the Bay.</li>
<li><strong>Inter-governmental cooperation: </strong>It is essential that nautical neighbours develop a partnership and cooperate because of the maritime domain’s interrelated and interdependent nature, transnational character, and cross-jurisdictional engagement of various governments and diverse organisations and enterprises.</li>
<li><strong>Maritime connectivity: </strong>A few concerns that need immediate attention include expanding cooperation in maritime safety and security, enhancing cooperation on maritime connectivity and the ease of maritime transit, and boosting investment possibilities in the maritime connectivity sector.</li>
<li><strong>Illegal activities: </strong>The latter subject involves addressing non-traditional threats and fostering group efforts to reduce illicit, unreported, and unregulated fishing.</li>
<li><strong>Data sharing: </strong>Standardising and harmonising data reporting.</li>
<li><strong>Balanced approach: </strong>Furthermore regional marine entities should strive to balance opportunities and goals on a national, regional, and international scale.</li>
<li><strong>Investment in R&amp;D: </strong>Littoral governments need to support and promote skill-building, research, and training.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Countries in the Bay of Bengal need to mobilise investments, manage maritime affairs more effectively. Alternative lifestyle should be explored. The cooperation of all member states, for information gathering, sharing and result oriented actions is crucial in protecting the ecology of Bay of Bengal.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Countries in the Indian subcontinent are developing rapidly, putting serious stress on the environment of the Bay of Bengal.Mention the challenges and suggest solutions.</strong></p></blockquote>
<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bay-of-bengal/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>All women have Right to Legal and Safe Abortion: Supreme Court</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-legal-and-safe-abortion/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>MRTP Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Abortion rights debate</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has held that all women, irrespective of their marital status, are entitled to safe and legal abortion till 24 weeks of pregnancy under the Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act.</p>
<h4><strong>A case for safe abortion<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A Bench led by Justice D.Y. Chandrachud was hearing the appeal of a woman who wanted to abort her 24-week pregnancy after her relationship failed and her partner left her.</li>
<li>The lower court had taken an “<strong><u>unduly restrictive view</u></strong>” that her plea for a safe abortion was not covered under the Medical Termination of Pregnancy Act.</li>
<li>This was since the pregnancy arose from a consensual relationship outside wedlock.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the last amendment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The court noted that an amendment to the Act in 2021 had <strong><u>substituted the term ‘husband’ with ‘partner’</u></strong>, a clear signal that the law covered unmarried women within its ambit.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reiterating the live-in recognition</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Chastising the lower court, the Bench said live-in relationships had already been recognised by the Supreme Court.</li>
<li>There were a significant number of people in social mainstream who see no wrong in engaging in pre-marital sex.</li>
<li>The law could not be used to quench “<strong><u>notions of social morality</u></strong>” and unduly interfere in their personal autonomy and bodily integrity.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>About Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Abortion in India has been a legal right under various circumstances for the last 50 years since the introduction of the<strong> <u>Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act in 1971</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Act was amended in 2003 to enable women’s access to safe and legal abortion services.</li>
<li>Abortion is covered 100% by the government’s public national health insurance funds, Ayushman Bharat and Employees’ State Insurance with the package rate for surgical abortion.</li>
</ul>
<p>The idea of terminating your pregnancy cannot originate by choice and is purely circumstantial. There are four situations under which a legal abortion is performed:</p>
<ol>
<li>If continuation of the pregnancy poses any <strong><u>risks to the life of the mother</u></strong> <strong>or <u>mental health</u></strong></li>
<li>If the <strong><u>foetus has any severe abnormalities</u></strong></li>
<li>If pregnancy occurred as a result of <strong><u>failure of contraception</u></strong> (but this is only applicable to married women)</li>
<li>If pregnancy is a result of <strong><u>sexual assault or rape</u></strong></li>
</ol>
<p>The pregnancy can be terminated upto 24 weeks of gestational age after the opinion of two registered medical practitioners under these conditions —</p>
<ul>
<li>If the woman is ​​either a survivor of sexual assault or rape or incest</li>
<li>If she is a minor</li>
<li>If her marital status has changed during the ongoing pregnancy (i.e. either widowhood or divorce)</li>
<li>If she has major physical disabilities or is mentally ill</li>
<li>On the grounds of foetal malformation incompatible with life or if the child is born, it would be seriously handicapped</li>
<li>If the woman is in humanitarian settings or disaster, or emergency situations as declared by the government</li>
</ul>
<p>These are the key changes that the Medical Termination of Pregnancy (Amendment) Act, 2021, has brought in:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong><u>The gestation limit for abortions has been raised from the earlier ceiling of 20 weeks to 24 weeks</u></strong>, but only for special categories of pregnant women such as rape or incest survivors. But this termination would need the approval of two registered doctors.</li>
<li><strong><u>All pregnancies up to 20 weeks require one doctor’s approval</u></strong>. The earlier law, the MTP Act 1971, required one doctor’s approval for pregnancies upto 12 weeks and two doctors’ for pregnancies between 12 and 20 weeks.</li>
<li><strong><u>Women can now terminate unwanted pregnancies caused by contraceptive failure</u></strong>, regardless of their marital status. Earlier the law specified that only a “married woman and her husband” could do this.</li>
<li><strong><u>There is also no upper gestation limit for abortion in case of foetal disability</u></strong> if so decided by a medical board of specialist doctors, which state governments and union territories’ administrations would set up.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Criticism of Abortion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Foetuses feel the pain:</strong> If the foetus is beyond 20 weeks of gestation, gynaecs assume that there will be pain caused to the foetus.</li>
<li><strong>Abortions cause psychological damage:</strong> Young adult women who undergo abortion may be at increased risk for subsequent depression.</li>
<li><strong>Abortions reduce the number of adoptable babies:</strong> Instead of having the option to abort, women should give their unwanted babies to people who cannot conceive. Single parenthood is also gaining popularity in the US.</li>
<li><strong>Cases of selective abortion:</strong> Such cases based on physical and genetic abnormalities (eugenic termination) is overt discrimination.</li>
<li><strong>Abortion as a form of contraception:</strong> It is immoral to kill an unborn child for convenience. Many women are using abortion as a contraceptive method.</li>
<li><strong>Morality put to question:</strong> If women become pregnant, they should accept the responsibility that comes with producing a child. People need to take responsibility for their actions and accept the consequences.</li>
<li><strong>Abortion promotes throwaway culture:</strong> The legalization of abortion sends a message that human life has little value and promotes the throwaway culture.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Arguments in favour for Abortion Rights</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Upholding individual conscience and decision-making:</strong>  The US Supreme Court has declared abortion to be a fundamental right guaranteed by the US Constitution.</li>
<li><strong>Reproductive choice empowers women:</strong> The choice over when and whether to have children is central to a woman’s independence and ability to determine her future.</li>
<li><strong>Foetal viability occurs post-birth:</strong>  Personhood begins after a foetus becomes “viable” (able to survive outside the womb) or after birth, not at conception. Abortion is the termination of a pregnancy, not a baby.</li>
<li><strong>No proof of foetal pain:</strong> Most neuroscientists believe that the cortex is necessary for pain perception. The cortex does not become functional until at least the 26th week of a foetus’ development.</li>
<li><strong>Preventing illegal abortions:</strong> Access to legal, professionally-performed abortions reduces maternal injury and death caused by unsafe, illegal abortions.</li>
<li><strong>Mother’s health:</strong> Modern abortion procedures are safe and do not cause lasting health issues such as cancer and infertility.</li>
<li><strong>Child’s health:</strong> Abortion gives pregnant women the option to choose not to bring fetuses with profound abnormalities to full term.</li>
<li><strong>Prevents women’s exclusion:</strong> Women who are denied abortions are more likely to become unemployed, to be on public welfare, to be below the poverty line, and to become victims of domestic violence.</li>
<li><strong>Reproductive choice protects women from financial disadvantage:</strong> Many women who choose abortion don’t have the financial resources to support a child.</li>
<li><strong>Justified means of population control:</strong> Many defends abortion as a way to curb overpopulation. Malnutrition, starvation, poverty, lack of medical and educational services, pollution, underdevelopment, and conflict over resources are all consequences of overpopulation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Hence it is now established that the right to abortion is a legal right of all women.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-legal-and-safe-abortion/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>UNESCO Lists 50 iconic Indian Textiles</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/unesco-iconic-indian-textiles/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Textiles mentioned in the newscard</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The UNESCO has released a list of 50 exclusive and iconic heritage textile crafts of the country.</p>
<h4>About the Report</h4>
<ul>
<li>The report is titled- Handmade for the 21st Century: Safeguarding Traditional Indian Textile.</li>
<li>It lists the histories and legends behind the textiles, describes the complicated and secret processes behind their making, mentions the causes for their dwindling popularity, and provides strategies for their preservation.</li>
<li>The publication, which aims to bridge this gap, brings together years of research on the 50 selected textiles.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Key heritage textiles mentioned in the list</h4>
<ul>
<li>Toda embroidery and Sungadi from Tamil Nadu</li>
<li>Himroo from Hyderabad</li>
<li>Bandha tie and dye from Sambalpur in Odisha</li>
<li>Khes from Panipat, Haryana</li>
<li>Chamba rumals from Himachal Pradesh</li>
<li>Thigma or wool tie and dye from Ladakh</li>
<li>Awadh Jamdani from Varanasi, UP</li>
<li>Ilkal and Lambadi or Banjara embroidery from Karnataka</li>
<li>Sikalnayakanpet Kalamkari from Thanjavur, TN</li>
<li>Kunbi weaves from Goa</li>
<li>Mashru weaves and Patola from Gujarat</li>
<li>Himroo from Maharashtra and</li>
<li>Garad-Koirial from West Bengal</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: UN Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization</h4>
<ul>
<li>The UNESCO is a specialised agency of the UN aimed at promoting world peace and security through international cooperation in education, arts, sciences and culture.</li>
<li>It has 193 member states and 12 associate members, as well as partners in the non-governmental, intergovernmental and private sector.</li>
<li>UNESCO was founded in 1945 as the successor to the League of Nations’s International Committee on Intellectual Cooperation.</li>
<li>It pursues this objective through five major program areas: education, natural sciences, social/human sciences, culture and communication/information.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/unesco-iconic-indian-textiles/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Behind the ‘world’s first CNG terminal’ at Bhavnagar, Gujarat</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/behind-the-worlds-first-cng-terminal/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CNG vs LPG</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="cng" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-641985" height="469" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 869px) 100vw, 869px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cng.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cng.jpg 869w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cng-300x162.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cng-768x414.jpg 768w" width="869"/></p>
<p>Prime Minister has laid the foundation stone for the “world’s first CNG (Compressed Natural Gas) terminal” at Bhavnagar in Gujarat.</p>
<h4>Bhavnagar CNG terminal</h4>
<ul>
<li>The idea got incepted during the January 2019 Vibrant Gujarat summit when a consortium of some stakeholder signed MoU with Gujarat Maritime Board (GMB) for development of the CNG terminal.</li>
<li>The port will be built under the BOOT (Build, Own, Operate and Transfer) policy of the state government.</li>
<li>The state-run GMB will continue to operate the berths on the south side of the port.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the Bhavnagar port important?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Bhavnagar port is in close vicinity to the Dholera Special Investment Region (SIR) and is expected to serve the industries that set up base in the region.</li>
<li>It is already connected to the northern hinterland through a railway line that extends to the existing berths at the port.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When is the CNG terminal expected to commence operations?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The construction is expected to commence in the first quarter of 2023 after GMB approves the Detailed Project Report.</li>
<li>It is expected to be made operational by 2026.</li>
<li>The proposed port terminal’s capacity is 4.65 Million Tonnes Per Annum (MTPA), of which the capacity of the CNG terminal will be 0.3 MTPA.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What makes the port unique?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The project will repair and redevelop the tidal lock gate system, which will be the fourth largest such system in the world.</li>
<li>Traditionally, because of the higher tidal range of approximately 10 meters, Bhavnagar creek attracts a significant amount of sediment in the form of silt.</li>
<li>This lock gate system has been set up so that a minimal amount of sediment enters the port basin during high tide, thus bringing down the cost of dredging inside the port substantially.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Natural gas vs. LPG</h4>
<ul>
<li>LPG, or liquefied petroleum gas, is a mixture of light hydrocarbons.</li>
<li>It consists of at least 90% of propane, with the balance made up of other gases including butane.</li>
<li>Natural gas, in contrast, is almost entirely made up of methane.</li>
<li>Compressed Natural Gas, or CNG, and Liquefied Natural Gas, or LNG, are the same substance.</li>
<li>CNG is received and stored in a vehicle’s tank in gaseous form.</li>
<li>To obtain LNG, natural gas is compressed and cooled to extremely low temperatures, at which point it turns to liquid.</li>
<li>LNG can then be shipped, stored, and used to fill the tanks of LNG vehicles.</li>
<li>Much of the global natural gas trade occurs in the form of LNG.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/behind-the-worlds-first-cng-terminal/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Vande Bharat Express 2.0</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vande-bharat-express-ii/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Vande Bharat Express</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="vande" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-641981" height="362" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vande.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vande.jpg 640w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vande-300x170.jpg 300w" width="640"/></strong></p>
<p>Prime Minister has inaugurated the new upgraded Vande Bharat Express.</p>
<h4><strong>Vande Bharat 2.0</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Vande Bharat Express is a semi-high-speed train designed, developed, and built by the Integral Coach Factory (ICF).</li>
<li>Presently there are only two Vande Bharat trains that are running — Delhi to Varanasi and Delhi to Katra.</li>
<li>The name may be the same, but this train, the third in the Vande Bharat series, is being dubbed ‘Vande Bharat 2.0’, because of certain upgrades.</li>
<li>PM had inaugurated the Vande Bharat when it was first launched in Delhi in 2019.</li>
<li>The new trainset costs around Rs 115 crore — Rs 15 crore more than the last version.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Key Features</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The current Vande Bharat trains have <strong><u>seating only in two classes</u></strong> — chair car and executive chair car. But Railways is planning to upgrade it.</li>
<li>The trains have fully <strong><u>sealed gangways for a dust-free environment</u></strong>, modular bio-vacuum toilets, rotating seats in Executive Class, personalized reading lights, automatic entry/exit doors with sliding footsteps, diffused LED lighting, mini pantry, and sensor-based interconnecting doors in each coach.</li>
<li>They are <strong><u>self-propelled trains</u></strong> that do not require an engine. This feature is called a <strong>distributed traction power system</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the major upgrades?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Ride comfort</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>For starters, this train reaches a top speed of 160 km per hour in 129 seconds, around 16 seconds faster than its predecessor.</li>
<li>This is because this train weighs around 392 tonnes, 38 tonnes lighter than the last one, and needs to run almost a km less to attain its top speed.</li>
<li>It also has a better riding index (lower the better) of 3.26 at 180 km per hour, from the earlier 3.87.</li>
<li>At a standard speed of 115 km per, its riding index is 3.26, better than 3.62 attained at the same speed by the earlier version.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em>Riding index is a global benchmark for rolling stock calculated during trials by measuring vertical/lateral acceleration. In layman’s terms, how comfortable and steady the passenger is while the train is in motion is roughly the idea behind a riding index.</em></p></blockquote>
<p><strong>(2) Safety features</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In terms of safety features, the new train comes fitted with the automatic anti-collision system Kavach, which the previous trains did not have.</li>
<li>Coaches have disaster lights and their battery backup is for three hours, increased from the last one’s one-hour battery backup.</li>
<li>The exterior has eight flatform-side cameras, up from four.</li>
<li>There is also passenger-guard communication facility in coaches, which comes with automatic voice recording feature.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Benefits of Vande Bharat Trains</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cuts Travel Time Drastically</li>
<li>Energy Efficient</li>
<li>Reduce Turnaround Time</li>
<li>Faster Acceleration and Deceleration among others.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has embarked on a mission to roll out 400 Vande Bharats.</li>
<li>By August 2023, the country is to introduce 72 more such trains, taking the total to 75.</li>
<li>The idea is that this third trainset will carry on with its commercial run and at the same time the Railway production units will keep producing more every month to reach the target.</li>
<li>In the works is the plan to introduce Vande Bharat with sleeper berths for overnight journeys.</li>
<li>Options to make these trainsets with an aluminum body is also being explored, for a lighter product.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vande-bharat-express-ii/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India ranks 40th in the Global Innovation Index of WIPO</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-ranks-40th-global-innovation-index/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>GII</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Innovation in India</p></div></div><p><img alt="innovation" class="alignnone wp-image-641982" height="315" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii-india.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii-india.jpg 843w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii-india-300x185.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii-india-768x473.jpg 768w" width="512"/></p>
<p>India climbed six notches to 40th position in the Global Innovation Index 2022 on account of improvement in several parameters. India was at 46th position in 2021 and at 81st rank in 2015.</p>
<h4><strong>Global Innovation Index</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Global Innovation Index (GII) is an annual ranking of countries by their capacity for, and success in, innovation.</li>
<li>It is published by Cornell University, INSEAD, and the World Intellectual Property Organization, in partnership with other organizations and institutions.</li>
<li>It is based on both subjective and objective data derived from several sources, including the International Telecommunication Union, the World Bank and the World Economic Forum.</li>
<li>The index was started in 2007 by INSEAD and World Business, a British magazine. It was created by Prof. Soumitra Dutta.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Components of GII</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="innovation" class="alignnone wp-image-641983" height="308" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 543px) 100vw, 543px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii.jpg 679w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii-300x170.jpg 300w" width="543"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The GII is computed by taking a simple average of the scores in two sub-indices, the Innovation Input Index and Innovation Output Index, which are composed of five and two pillars respectively</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Global scenario</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Switzerland, the US, Sweden, the United Kingdom and the Netherlands are the world’s most-innovative economies.</li>
<li>China is on the threshold of the top 10.</li>
<li>Other emerging economies are also showing consistently strong performance, including India and Turkey, both of which enter the top 40 for the first time.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-ranks-40th-global-innovation-index/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What are Small Savings Instruments (SSIs)?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/small-saving-instruments/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Small Savings Instruments (SSIs)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Centre has announced increases of 0.1-0.3 percentage points in interest rates payable on five small savings instruments (SSIs) marking the first increase in small savings rates since January 2019.</p>
<h4><strong>What are Small Savings Instruments (SSIs)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Small Savings Schemes or instruments are a set of savings instruments <strong><u>managed by the central government</u></strong> with an aim to encourage citizens to save regularly irrespective of their age.</li>
<li>They are popular as they provide <strong><u>returns higher than bank fixed deposits</u></strong>, <strong><u>sovereign guarantee</u></strong> and <strong><u>tax benefits</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How is it managed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Since 2016, the Finance Ministry has been <strong><u>reviewing the interest rates</u></strong> on small savings schemes on a <strong><u>quarterly basis</u></strong>.</li>
<li>All deposits received under various schemes are <strong><u>pooled in the National Small Savings Fund</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>money</u></strong> in the fund is <strong><u>used by the Centre </u></strong>to <strong><u>finance its fiscal deficit</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the different saving schemes?</strong></h4>
<p>The schemes can be grouped under three heads –</p>
<ol>
<li>Post office deposits</li>
<li>Savings certificates and</li>
<li>Social security schemes</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>(1) Post Office Deposits</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Under this we have the savings deposit, recurring deposit and time deposits with 1, 2, 3 and 5 year maturities and the monthly income account.</li>
<li>The savings account currently pays an interest of 4% per annum and can be opened individually or jointly with an initial investment of Rs 500.</li>
<li>The recurring deposit that pays 5.8% a year compounded quarterly matures after 60 months from the date of opening.</li>
<li>It allows investors to save on a monthly basis with a minimum deposit of Rs 100 per month.</li>
<li>Investments under the 5-year time deposit up to Rs 1.5 lakh further qualifies for benefit under section 80C of Income Tax Act.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Savings Certificates</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Under this, we have the National Savings Certificate and the Kisan Vikas Patra.</li>
<li>The National Savings Certificate pays interest at a rate of 6.8% per annum upon maturity after 5 years. The interest that is earned is reinvested into the scheme every year automatically.</li>
<li>The NSC also qualifies for tax saving under Section 80C of the income tax act.</li>
<li>The Kisan Vikas Patra, which is open to everyone, doubles your one-time investment at the end of 124 months signifying a return of 6.9% compounded annually.</li>
<li>The minimum investment amount is Rs 1000 while there is no upper limit.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Social security schemes</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In the third head of social security schemes, there is Public Provident Fund, Sukanya Samriddhi Account and Senior Citizens Savings Scheme.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong> Public Provident Fund</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The Public Provident Fund is a popular saving option for long term goals like retirement.</li>
<li>It pays 7.1% a year and qualifies for tax benefit under Section 80C of the Income Tax Act.</li>
<li>Upon maturity of the account after 15 years, it can be extended indefinitely in blocks of 5 years.</li>
<li>The accumulated amount and interest earned are exempt from tax at the time of withdrawal.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong> Sukanya Samriddhi Account </strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The Sukanya Samriddhi Account was <strong><u>launched in 2015 under the Beti Bachao Beti Padhao</u></strong> campaign exclusively for a girl child.</li>
<li>The account can be opened in the name of a girl child below the age of 10 years.</li>
<li>The scheme guarantees a return of 7.6% per annum and is eligible for tax benefit under Section 80C of the Income Tax Act.</li>
<li>The tenure of the deposit is 21 years from the date of opening of the account and a maximum of Rs 1.5 lakh can be invested in a year.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong> Senior Citizen Savings Account</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>And finally, the 5-year ​​Senior Citizen Savings Account can be opened by anyone who is over 60 years to age.</li>
<li>It carries an interest of 7.4% per annum payable quarterly and qualifies for Section 80C tax benefit.</li>
<li>These time-tested and safe modes of investments don’t offer quick returns, but are safer when compared to market-linked schemes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How are G-Secs and SSIs related?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>RBI had observed that the rise in yields on <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-government-securities-g-secs/">government securities</a> (G-Secs) had turned ‘the spread between the existing interest rates’ and formula-based rates ‘negative for most small saving schemes’.</li>
<li>Returns on SSIs are linked to market yields on G-Secs with a lag and are fixed on a quarterly basis.</li>
<li>The decision to raise rates on just five SSIs, will mean that returns for some of the schemes, such as the PPF, will be negative in the coming quarter in relation to the formula.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/small-saving-instruments/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Congenital Heart Disease</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/congenital-heart-disease/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Heart, and Heart Diseases</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Health</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Heart Disease" class="alignnone wp-image-641930" height="356" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 635px) 100vw, 635px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-10.00.15-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-10.00.15-1.jpeg 642w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-10.00.15-1-300x168.jpeg 300w" width="635"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Congenital Heart Disease (CHD), which the Centre for Disease Control and Prevention(CDC), Atlanta, U.S., acknowledges to be the most common congenital disorder, is responsible for 28% of all congenital birth defects, and accounts for 6%-10 % of all the infant deaths in India. 29 September is celebrated as world heart day.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-burden-of-heart-diseases/">Congenital Heart Disease (CHD)?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Congenital heart disease is a general term for a range of birth defects that affect the normal way the heart works. The term “congenital” means the condition is present from birth.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Heart Disease" class="alignnone wp-image-641931 size-large" height="947" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.55-1024x947.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.55-1024x947.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.55-300x278.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.55-768x710.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.55-973x900.jpeg 973w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.55.jpeg 1080w" width="1024"/>What is p</strong><strong>aediatric cardiac care?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Paediatric cardiologists diagnose, treat, and manage heart problems in children, including. “Congenital heart disease” (heart differences children are born with), such as holes between chambers of the heart, valve problems, and abnormal blood vessels</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Present situation of </strong><strong>Congenital <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-burden-of-heart-diseases/#:~:text=According%20to%20the%20Global%20Burden,a%20legacy%20of%20economic%20growth.">Heart Disease</a></strong> <strong>In India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is estimated that over 1,00,000 children keep getting added to the existing pool of children awaiting surgery.</li>
<li>According to the Paediatric Cardiac Society of India (PCSI), the prevalence of congenital cardiac anomalies is one in every 100 live births; or an estimated 2,00,000 children are born with CHD every year. Only 15,000 of them receive treatment.</li>
<li>At least 30% of infants who have complex defects require surgical intervention to survive their first birthday but only 2,500operations can be performed each year. A case in point is the premier All India Institute of Medical Sciences (AIIMS), where infants are waitlisted till 2026 for cardiac surgery.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Heart Disease" class="alignnone wp-image-641938 size-full" height="1280" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 733px) 100vw, 733px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.56.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.56.jpeg 733w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.56-172x300.jpeg 172w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.56-586x1024.jpeg 586w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.56-515x900.jpeg 515w" width="733"/>What are the Reasons behind this worrisome situation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of money: </strong>There has been more neglect and little improvement in child health care because creating a comprehensive paediatric cardiology care service is usually considered economically unviable — it is resource intensive and requires infrastructure investment that politicians and policy makers choose to evade.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure: </strong>There are 22 hospitals and less than 50 centres in India with infant and neonatal cardiac services.</li>
<li><strong>Uneven distribution: </strong>Geographically, these centres are not well distributed either. 2018 cardiology department report of AIIMS, highlighted how South India accounted for 70% of these centres; most centres are located in regions with a lower burden of CHD. For instance, Kerala has eight centres offering neonatal cardiac surgeries for an estimated 4.5 lakh annual childbirths. Populous Uttar Pradesh and Bihar, with an estimated annual childbirth of 48 and 27 lakh births per annum, respectively (Census of India, 2012), do not have a centre capable of performing neonatal cardiac surgery.</li>
<li><strong>Non-priority: </strong>A 2018 article by the Department of Cardiothoracic Cardiology, AIIMS, states, “paediatric cardiology is not a priority area in the face of competing demands for the resources</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the problems in treating</strong><strong> congenital Heart Disease?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Doctor population ratio: </strong>For 600 districts with a 1.4 billion population, there are only 250 paediatric cardiologists available. The doctor to patient ratio is an abysmal one for half-a-crore population. According to the Annals of Paediatric Cardiology journal, the United States had 2,966 paediatric cardiologists in 2019, ratio of one per 29,196population.</li>
<li><strong>Poverty: </strong>Poverty is another barrier before treatment. Transporting sick neonates from States with little or no cardiac care facilities to faraway centres for accurate diagnosis and treatment burdens parents financially.</li>
<li><strong>Medical devices: </strong>In addition, there is the non-availability of crucial equipment that is essential for diagnosis of heart diseases in the unborn. Accentuating the problem is the general lack of awareness about early symptoms of CHD among parents.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Heart Disease" class="alignnone wp-image-641940" height="439" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-09.58.50.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-09.58.50.jpeg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-09.58.50-300x217.jpeg 300w" width="608"/>What should be approach for the treatment of Congenital Heart Disease?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Timely treatment: </strong>Paediatricians say timely medical intervention can save 75% of these children and give them normal lives.</li>
<li><strong>National policy: </strong>The lack of a national policy for the treatment of cardiovascular diseases in children keeps a huge number outside the ambit of treatment.</li>
<li><strong>Echocardiography: </strong>The Child Heart Foundation, a non-governmental organisation working in Siliguri (WestBengal), Jalandhar (Punjab) and Delhi, with underprivileged children with CHD, has been flagging the need for fatal echocardiography.</li>
<li><strong>Hridayam</strong>: There are programmes worth emulating such as Kerala’s ‘Hridayam (for little hearts)’,aimed at early detection, management and support to children with CHD or the Tamilnadu Chief Minister’s Comprehensive Health Insurance Scheme offering free specialised surgeries.</li>
<li><strong>Ayushman Bharat: </strong>The National Health Protection Scheme (Ayushman Bharat), is expected to financially assist 10 crore poor families but has still to takeoff. So far, Maharashtra, Karnataka, Gujarat and Andhra Pradesh have apparently got going.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s performance in neo natal care is very regrettable. India can drastically reduce its infant mortality by investing in paediatric cardiac care. Sooner we realize this better will be the future of India.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Infant mortality India out of congenital Heart Disease is because of negligence and non-priority. Acknowledge the problems and suggest solutions.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/congenital-heart-disease/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Fixing Falling Indian Rupee</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/falling-indian-rupee/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>weakening of Rupee,appreciation and depreciation</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Indian Economics</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Falling Indian Rupee" class="alignnone wp-image-641941 size-full" height="752" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-1.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-1-300x188.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-1-1024x642.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-1-768x481.jpeg 768w" width="1200"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Last week, the rupee weakened against the dollar past the 81-mark to a record low. In recent months, the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) has been intervening in the FOREX market to smoothen the decline. Indian foreign exchange reserves have fallen by about $94billion in 12 months to about $545 billion until mid-September. Falling Indian Rupee poses huge challenge in the economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the major challenges before Indian Economy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Falling rupee</strong>: A fall in the rupee against the dollar in the FOREX market means that the Indian currency is weakening. This means that while importing from the United States or any country, India will have to pay more because the payment is done in dollars, i.e., less import cost more.</li>
<li><strong>Inflation: </strong>Since May this year, RBI has largely managed to control inflation. RBI managed inflation to keep it below 7.5 % but, looking at Ukraine situation, oil prices may shoot up again and there by inflation will rise.</li>
<li><strong>Growing CAD</strong>: India’s current account deficit (CAD) in April-June was at $23.9 billion, or 2.8 per cent of gross domestic product (GDP), much higher than the $13.4 billion, or 1.5 per cent of GDP, in January-March 2022. India has faced upward pressure on its import bill in 2022 because Russia’s invasion of Ukraine in late February led to a sharp rise in prices of commodities across the globe.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Falling of Rupee" class="alignnone wp-image-641951 size-large" height="576" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-1-1024x576.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-1-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-1-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-1-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-1.jpeg 1200w" width="1024"/>What is <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rbi-and-the-rupee-to-break-a-free-fall-or-not-to/">RBI’s role in managing falling Rupee ?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Use of foreign exchange reserve: </strong>The use of FOREX reserves is appropriate at this juncture. You build your reserves during good times and spend them during bad times. Right now, reserves are being spent in trying to curb currency volatility. RBI can’t defend the rupee at a particular level, because that would be swimming against the tide, which is not possible in this environment. But RBI can make it less volatile.</li>
<li><strong>Easy dollar supply: </strong>RBI has already undertaken measures such as easing provisions for remittances, allowing short-term foreign portfolio investments in government securities, etc. We can even think of a scheme similar to the one introduced in 2014to attract NRI investments<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Interest rate: </strong>Interest rates are being raised not only to control inflation, but also to address external imbalances. But let’s also look at past episodes of sharp depreciation of the currency which we have seen during the global financial crisis, during the taper tantrum. They tell us that the currency weakens very sharply during these episodes of global shocks, but it also corrects. If you plot it over a 15-20-year period, you will see that the overshooting of the currency typically gets corrected after the event is over. So, the aim now should only be to ensure that volatility is not too high, not to steer the currency in any direction.</li>
<li><strong>Managing the CAD</strong>: According to experts, RBI can finance the CAD with capital inflows, and prevent hot money outflow with the aid of interest rates, that could be an effective long-term solution. The focus should be on how we can stem capital that is flighty. Even during the tenure of Raghuram Rajan the CAD went up to 4%. But the moment hot money became flighty, panic set in. Till then, we were comfortably financing the CAD with capital flows.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Falling Indian Rupee" class="alignnone wp-image-641954 size-full" height="1179" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.54.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.54.jpeg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.54-275x300.jpeg 275w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.54-938x1024.jpeg 938w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.54-768x838.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.54-824x900.jpeg 824w" width="1080"/>What are the Notes of caution?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>On FOREX: </strong>There is also a limit to how much you can lean on the reserves. They can burn out pretty quickly if you are aggressive in your interventions<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>On rupee fall and CAD: </strong>RBI also needs to let the rupee depreciate in an orderly manner. Some, but not too much, depreciation will partly help the export sector, as global demand is the key influencer of exports, and currencies of our competitors are also weakening. So, the vulnerability that stems from high current account deficit (CAD) can get addressed to some extent.</li>
<li><strong>On interest rate: </strong>We have to focus on the real interest rate and economic growth, for public debt management. If the Real interest rate is going to be greater than Growth, then we are in an unsustainable situation. The only way to address these concerns such as fiscal consolidation, twin deficit crisis, given that the real rate of interest is negative, given the hawkish mode of the Fed, is to raise rates.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Falling Indian Rupee" class="alignnone wp-image-641955 size-large" height="1015" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1-1024x1015.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1-1024x1015.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1-300x298.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1-150x150.jpeg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1-768x762.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1-908x900.jpeg 908w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1.jpeg 1080w" width="1024"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>With rising external trade, India’s economy is integrating with world. Impact of global uncertainty on economy is natural outcome. Ukraine episode, slowing Europe and unclear USA is going give Indian policy maker a tough time in coming months.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Recent global events and future uncertainties pose challenges to microeconomic stability. Discuss what measures India can take to keep inflation low.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/falling-indian-rupee/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Competent Chief of Defence Staff</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/chief-of-defence-staff/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CDS</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Security, Role of CDS</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Chief of Defence Staff" class="alignnone wp-image-641953 size-full" height="1280" sizes="(max-width: 877px) 100vw, 877px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.52.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.52.jpeg 877w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.52-206x300.jpeg 206w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.52-702x1024.jpeg 702w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.52-768x1121.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.52-617x900.jpeg 617w" width="877"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Government on September 28, 2022, appointed former Eastern Army Commander Lt. General Anil Chauhan as the next Chief of Defence Staff (CDS). The appointment comes more than nine months after the post fell vacant following the death of General Bipin Rawat.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the role of the Office of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/back-in-news-chief-of-defence-staff-cds-2/">Chief of Defence Staff (CDS)?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Mandate is to bring convergence in the functioning of the Army, the Navy and the Air force and bolster the country’s overall military prowess.</li>
<li>The CDS is a high military office that oversees and coordinates the working of the three Services, and offers seamless tri-service views and single-point advice to the Executive.</li>
<li>On long-term it provides for defence planning and management, including manpower, equipment and strategy, and above all, “joint manship” in operations.</li>
<li>The role of the CDS becomes critical in times of conflict.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is the need of CDS?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tri-services coordination:</strong> The creation of the CDS will eventually lead to the formation of tri-service theatre commands intended to create vertical integration of the three forces.</li>
<li><strong>Single-point military advisory:</strong> The CDS will be a single-point military adviser to the government and synergise long term planning, procurements, training and logistics of the three Services.</li>
<li><strong>Efforts saving:</strong> This is expected to save money by avoiding duplication between the Services, at a time of shrinking capital expenditure within the defence budget.</li>
<li><strong>Military diplomacy:</strong> This is today supporting conventional diplomacy. That can’t be done by different Services.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Chief of Defence Staff" class="alignnone wp-image-641959 size-full" height="1280" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 853px) 100vw, 853px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56.jpeg 853w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-200x300.jpeg 200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-682x1024.jpeg 682w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-768x1152.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-600x900.jpeg 600w" width="853"/>All you need to know about the New Chief of Defence Staff (CDS):</strong> <strong>Lt. General Anil Chauhan</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Indian Army:</strong> Born on May 18, 1961, Lt. Gen. Chauhan was commissioned into the 11 Gorkha Rifles of the Indian Army in 1981.</li>
<li><strong>Alumnus of NDA and IMA:</strong> He is an alumnus of the National Defence Academy, Khadakwasla and Indian Military Academy, Dehradun.</li>
<li><strong>Career of 40 years:</strong> In a career spanning over nearly 40 years, Lt. Gen. Anil Chauhan had held several command, staff and instrumental appointments and had extensive experience in counter-insurgency operations in Jammu and Kashmir and North-East India.</li>
<li><strong>As Major General:</strong> In the rank of Major General, he had commanded an Infantry Division in Baramula sector in Jammu and Kashmir</li>
<li><strong>As Lt. General:</strong> As Lt. General, he commanded a Corps in the North East and subsequently became the Eastern Army Commander in September 2019 and held the charge until his retirement from service on May 31, 2021.</li>
<li><strong>As Military Advisor to the NSA</strong>: Lt. Gen. Chauhan took over as the Military Advisor in the National Security Council Secretariat (NSCS) from Lt. Gen. Vinod G. Khandare who stepped down from the post in October 2021</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Chief of Defence Staff" class="alignnone wp-image-641984 size-large" height="1024" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 932px) 100vw, 932px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-12.40.28-932x1024.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-12.40.28-932x1024.jpeg 932w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-12.40.28-273x300.jpeg 273w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-12.40.28-768x844.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-12.40.28-819x900.jpeg 819w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-12.40.28.jpeg 1165w" width="932"/>What are the challenges facing the new chief of Defence Staff?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Responsibility: </strong>In terms of prioritisation and building a bridge between a government in a hurry and an organisation that is resistant to change, shackled by tradition and plagued by continued turf battles that cannot be wished away.</li>
<li><strong>Enhancing operational capability:</strong> To build operational capability at a pace that will ensure that the military power asymmetry vis-à-vis China remains manageable.</li>
<li><strong>Integrated structure:</strong> The need to create fresh structures to support integrated training, planning and operations. India-specific requirements need to be addressed.</li>
<li><strong>Articulated strategy:</strong> The requirement is in the area of policy, doctrines and strategy. Policies and doctrines are easier to evolve under the cover of clearly articulated national and military strategies. Though the strategic establishment is divided on the pressing need for a National Security Strategy (NSS), the CDS has his task cut out to link the NSS with transformation and expedite its promulgation</li>
<li><strong>Maintaining balance:</strong> Balancing the need to retain the operational capability and the government’s push towards self-reliance in defence manufacturing. Considering that this push demands a paradigm shift in the thinking of India’s defence innovation and manufacturing ecosystem. One needs to look no further than the US, France and Israel to embrace this push. However, this again links to forcing the armed forces to step out of their comfort zone and develop diverse intellectual capital.</li>
<li><strong>Shedding infructuous colonial legacies:</strong> Shedding several infructuous colonial legacies and traditions and fostering a sense of pride in India’s martial traditions that go back to epics such as the Mahabharata and to the Maratha and Chola empires.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Chief of Defence Staff" class="alignnone wp-image-641960 size-full" height="538" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 970px) 100vw, 970px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.48.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.48.jpeg 970w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.48-300x166.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.48-768x426.jpeg 768w" width="970"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>CDS should not hesitate to speak truth to power. He should be unbiased while taking tough decisions and should consider national interest above all else. In a rapidly evolving geopolitical and global security environment, in which India faces challenges across the conflict spectrum, the CDS need to undertake this task.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.In a rapidly evolving geopolitical and global security environment, India faces challenges across the conflict spectrum. Discuss the role of CDS in the joint preparations of the three forces in this context.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/chief-of-defence-staff/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>