<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 07:27:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Rohini RH-200: ISRO eyeing 200th successful launch of Rohini RH-200</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rohini-rh-200-isro-eyeing-200th-successful-launch-of-rohini-rh-200/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Rohini</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="rohini" class="alignnone wp-image-640536 size-full" height="437" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 591px) 100vw, 591px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rohini-1.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rohini-1.jpg 591w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rohini-1-300x222.jpg 300w" width="591"/></p>
<p>In a few weeks’ time, the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO) hopes to achieve a remarkable feat — the 200th successful launch of the Rohini RH-200 sounding rocket in a row.</p>
<h4>Rohini RH-200</h4>
<ul>
<li>RH-200 is a two-stage rocket capable of climbing to a height of 70 km bearing scientific payloads.</li>
<li>The first and second stages of RH-200 are powered by solid motors. The ‘200’ in the name denotes the diameter of the rocket in mm.</li>
<li>Other operational Rohini variants are RH-300 Mk-II and RH-560 Mk-III.</li>
<li>For years, the RH-200 rocket had used a polyvinyl chloride (PVC)-based propellant.</li>
<li>The first RH-200 to use a new propellant based on hydroxyl-terminated Polybutadiene (HTPB) was successfully flown from the TERLS in September 2020.</li>
<li>The first and second stages of RH200 rocket are powered by solid motors.</li>
<li>Since inception of RH200 rocket, both solid stages are processed using polyvinyl chloride (PVC) based propellant.</li>
<li>As compared to PVC based propellants, HTPB based propellant is more energetic, higher mechanical &amp; interface properties and has less defects due to lower processing temperature.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What basically is a Sounding Rocket?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A sounding rocket is an instrument-carrying rocket designed to take measurements and perform scientific experiments during its sub-orbital flight.</li>
<li>The rockets are used to launch instruments from 48 to 145 km above the surface of the Earth, the altitude generally between weather balloons and satellites.</li>
<li>The maximum altitude for balloons is about 40 km and the minimum for satellites is approximately 121 km.</li>
</ul>
<h4>History of sounding rockets in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sounding rockets have an important place in the ISRO story.</li>
<li>The first sounding rocket to be launched from Thumba was the American Nike-Apache — on November 21, 1963.</li>
<li>After that, two-stage rockets imported from Russia (M-100) and France (Centaure) were flown. The ISRO launched its own version — Rohini RH-75 — in 1967.</li>
<li>The ISRO has launched more than 1,600 RH-200 rockets so far.</li>
<li>Currently, the RH200, RH300 MkII and RH560 Mk-III rockets are operational which were developed during the early phase of our journey in rocketry.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rohini-rh-200-isro-eyeing-200th-successful-launch-of-rohini-rh-200/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>In news: Attorney-General (A-G) of India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/attorney-general-a-g-of-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Attorney General</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>A senior and renowned advocate has declined the offer from the Union government to be the next Attorney-General (A-G) of India as the incumbent AGI is set to retire this week.</p>
<h4><strong>Attorney General of India (AGI)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AGI is the Indian government’s chief legal advisor and is a primary lawyer in the Supreme Court of India.</li>
<li>They can be said to be the advocate from the government’s side.</li>
<li>They are appointed by the President of India on the advice of Union Cabinet under Article 76(1) of the Constitution and holds office during the pleasure of the President.</li>
<li>They must be a person qualified to be appointed as a Judge of the Supreme Court ( i.e. a judge of some high court for five years or an advocate of some high court for ten years or an eminent jurist, in the opinion of the President and must be a citizen of India.).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Functions and duties</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AGI is necessary for advising the Government of India on legal matters referred to them.</li>
<li>They also perform other legal duties assigned to them by the President.</li>
<li>The AGI has the right of audience in all Courts in India as well as the right to participate in the proceedings of the Parliament, though not to vote.</li>
<li>The AGI appears on behalf of the Government of India in all cases (including suits, appeals and other proceedings) in the Supreme Court in which GoI is concerned.</li>
<li>They also represent the Government of India in any reference made by the President to the Supreme Court under Article 143 of the Constitution.</li>
<li>The AG is assisted by a Solicitor General and four Additional Solicitors General.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Powers of AG<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AG can accept briefs but cannot appear against the Government.</li>
<li>They cannot defend an accused in criminal proceedings and accept the directorship of a company without the permission of the Government.</li>
<li>The AG is to be consulted only in legal matters of real importance and only after the Ministry of Law has been consulted.</li>
<li>All references to the AG are made by the Law Ministry.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Limitations to his powers<br/>
</strong></h4>
<p>The AG:</p>
<ul>
<li>should not advise or hold a brief against the Government of India</li>
<li>should not defend accused persons in criminal cases without the permission of the government of India</li>
<li>should not accept appointment as a director in any company without the permission of the government</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Office of AG across the world<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Unlike the Attorney General of the United States, the AGI does not have any executive authority.</li>
<li>Those functions are performed by the Law Minister of India.</li>
<li>Also, the AG is not a government servant and is not debarred from private legal practice.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/attorney-general-a-g-of-india/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Asian Palm Oil Alliance (APOA) formed by 5 South Asian Countries</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/asian-palm-oil-alliance-apoa-formed-by-5-south-asian-countries/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Palm Oil, APOA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>Edible oil trade associations from five palm oil importing countries in South Asia – India, Pakistan, Sri Lanka, Bangladesh and Nepal – on Thursday announced the setting up of Asian Palm Oil Alliance (APOA).</p>
<h4><strong>What is Oil Palm?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Palm oil is an edible vegetable oil derived from the mesocarp of the fruit of the oil palms.</li>
<li>The oil is used in food manufacturing, in beauty products, and as biofuel.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is APOA?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Through APOA, the countries aim at safeguarding the economic and business interests of the palm oil consuming countries and will work towards increasing the consumption of palm oil in member countries.</li>
<li>The idea is to gain collecting bargaining power and make imports sustainable.</li>
<li>APOA held its first general body meeting on the side-lines of the Globoil Summit.</li>
<li>The industry associations of Asian palm oil importing countries, unlike their counterparts in Europe, are not involved in shaping the global discourse on sustainable palm oil in a collective way.</li>
<li>The alliance would work towards ensuring that palm oil is recognised as a high-quality, economical, and healthy vegetable oil and to change the negative image of palm oil.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why such move?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s annual imports of edible oil is around 13-14 million tonne (MT).</li>
<li>Around 8 MT of palm oil is imported from Indonesia and Malaysia, while other oils, such as soya and sunflower, come from Argentina, Brazil, Ukraine and Russia.</li>
<li>Asia accounts for around 40% of the global palm oil consumption while Europe accounts for 12% of palm oil trade.</li>
<li>Indonesia and Malaysia are the biggest palm oil exporters in the world.</li>
<li>India is the largest importer of palm oil in Asia, accounting for 15% of global imports, followed by China (9%), Pakistan (4%) and Bangladesh (2%).</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ:</h4>
<p><strong>Q.Among the agricultural commodities imported by India, which one of the following accounts for the highest imports in terms of value in the last five years?</strong></p>
<p>(a) Spices</p>
<p>(b) Fresh fruits</p>
<p>(c) Pulses</p>
<p>(d) Vegetable oils</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/asian-palm-oil-alliance-apoa-formed-by-5-south-asian-countries/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why India Inc. needs a neurodiverse workplace ?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/neurodiverse/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>human right of neuro-diverse people</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="neurodiverse" class="alignnone wp-image-640541" height="562" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 423px) 100vw, 423px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/neurodiversity-226x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/neurodiversity-226x300.jpg 226w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/neurodiversity.jpg 386w" width="423"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Discrimination in employment is a worldwide phenomenon. Gender, ethnic, racist discrimination are well known but discrimination towards neurodiverse persons are hardly debated in public forums. Despite having special abilities companies are not using their potentials.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/what-is-neurodiversity-202111232645#:~:text=The%20word%20neurodiversity%20refers%20to,as%20ADHD%20or%20learning%20disabilities." rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>What is </strong><strong>neurodiversity?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Harvard Health Publishing defines, neurodiversity as a notion that every person interacts and experiences their surroundings differently; there is no right way of thinking, learning, or/and behaving. These differences should not be construed as defects or disorders.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a neuro-diverse workplace?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Neurodiversity in the workplace refers to including people with neuro-divergent conditions such as attention-deﬁcit/hyperactivity disorder, autism spectrum disorders, dyslexia, dyspraxia, dyscalculia and Asperger’s Syndrome.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are those Conditions that make them different from normal humans?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Autism:</strong> A mental condition in which a person finds it difficult to communicate or form relationships with other people. Signs of autism include not responding to their name, avoiding eye contact, not smiling when you smile at them.</li>
<li><strong>Dyslexia:</strong> a difficulty that some people have with reading and spelling signs include confusion over letters that look similar and putting letters the wrong way round , confusing the order of letters in words, reading slowly or making errors when reading aloud</li>
<li><strong>Asperger’s syndrome:</strong> A developmental disorder related to autism and characterized by awkwardness in social interaction, pedantry in speech, and preoccupation with very narrow interests. Less severe symptoms than Autism syndrome.</li>
<li><strong>Dyscalculia:</strong> A brain disorder in which a wide range of difficulties with math, including weaknesses in understanding the meaning of numbers, and difficulty applying mathematical principles to solve problems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="neurodiverse" class="alignnone wp-image-640542" height="373" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 622px) 100vw, 622px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2869adc7-4764-4e36-8262-2e9c6a04820a-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2869adc7-4764-4e36-8262-2e9c6a04820a-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2869adc7-4764-4e36-8262-2e9c6a04820a.jpg 600w" width="622"/>How they can be naturally efficient and creative?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>More efficient: </strong>Studies have shown that teams with both neurodivergent and neurotypical members are far more efficient than teams that comprise neurotypical employees alone.</li>
<li><strong>Ability to focus: </strong>Neurodivergent individuals possess excellent attention to detail and an uncanny ability to focus on complex and repetitive tasks over a more extended period than their neurotypical peers.</li>
<li><strong>Ability to work at faster speed: </strong>A study by the University of Montreal found that in a test involving completing a visual pattern, people on the autism spectrum could finish their task 40% faster than those who were not on the spectrum.</li>
<li><strong>Robust spatial reasoning</strong>: People with dyslexia can think about objects in three dimensions and analyses such objects even with limited information.</li>
<li><strong>Out of box thinking</strong>: They have problem-solving capabilities which allow them to see multiple solutions to a problem. They are often out-of-the-box thinkers with average or above-average intelligence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Current Status of people living with neurodivergent conditions</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>People suffer with the Condition: </strong>According to a recent report, nearly 2 million people in India suffer from this neurological and developmental disorder and are therefore identified as autistic. Another study by Deloitte estimates that nearly 20% of the world is neurodiverse. In the U.S., it is estimated that 85% of people on the autism spectrum are unemployed compared with 4.2% of the overall population</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-discrimination-report/"><strong>Discrimination at employment</strong>:</a> Even with all the necessary skill sets and degrees, these persons are denied a job because they may react to situations differently from non-neurodiverse persons.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of awareness: </strong>Lack of awareness about neurodivergent conditions, and how the people with condition may react and lack of and accommodating environment. Hence, there is an urgency to create a work environment that welcomes neurodiverse individuals<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="neurodiverse" class="alignnone wp-image-640543" height="371" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 589px) 100vw, 589px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-300x189.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-300x189.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-1024x646.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-768x484.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-1536x969.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-1200x757.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic.jpg 1903w" width="589"/>Current work profile of companies and workplaces</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A 2019 McKinsey study revealed that companies with gender diversity were 25% more likely to have above-average profitability while those with ethnic diversity out-rival their competitors by 36%.</li>
<li>Another report titled ‘India’s Best Workplaces in Diversity, Equity &amp; Inclusion 2021’ states that diverse teams perform better, boost leadership integrity, heighten trust in the organization’s management and multiply revenue growth.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="neurodiverse" class="alignnone wp-image-640544" height="392" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960x0-300x201.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960x0-300x201.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960x0-768x514.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960x0.jpg 959w" width="585"/>Few Examples show that things are changing</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Competitive environment</strong>: Organisations embracing neurodiversity enjoy a competitive edge in several areas such as efficiency, creativity, and culture.</li>
<li><strong>Various MNC’s hiring program</strong>: Companies such as Deloitte, Microsoft, SAP, JPMorgan Chase, and E&amp;Y have introduced neurodiversity hiring programs.</li>
<li><strong>Indian company: </strong>Indian-origin companies Hatti Kaapi and Lemon Tree Hotels have also included a neurodiverse workforce.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to create more inclusive workplaces?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Creating neurodivergent friendly offices</strong>: .Many employees with neurodiversity may find the hustle and bustle of a traditional office disturbing. Therefore, neurodivergent friendly offices catering to the employees’ diverse sensory responses can help ensure that these employees are comfortable in office spaces.</li>
<li><strong>Openness:</strong> Creating the right environment is an ever-evolving exercise that requires openness and a will to change on the employer’s part. This flexibility can result in exceptional benefit with minimal or no additional costs.</li>
<li><strong>Wider Inclusivity</strong>: To ensure higher profitability and be respected as a responsible employer globally, companies need to widen their definition of inclusivity by providing higher participation of a neurodiverse workforce.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Organizations must not only remove barriers that obstruct the progress of such individuals but also create conducive conditions for them to achieve their true potential and providing proper infrastructure so that they can perform at their optimal levels.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. People with neurodiversity are discriminated not only socially but also economically, Comment. What measures could be taken to bridge this gap within the society?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/neurodiverse/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Soft power, the new race every country wants to win</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/soft-power/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>na</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Soft power</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="soft power" class="alignnone wp-image-640548" height="224" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/quote-the-image-of-a-country-is-not-just-about-economic-and-military-strength-the-soft-face-narendra-modi-130-43-87-300x126.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/quote-the-image-of-a-country-is-not-just-about-economic-and-military-strength-the-soft-face-narendra-modi-130-43-87-300x126.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/quote-the-image-of-a-country-is-not-just-about-economic-and-military-strength-the-soft-face-narendra-modi-130-43-87-768x323.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/quote-the-image-of-a-country-is-not-just-about-economic-and-military-strength-the-soft-face-narendra-modi-130-43-87.jpg 843w" width="533"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Increased interest, especially by smaller nations in the world, in investing more and doing well in elite sports in international sporting events boosts a nation’s chances of attaining soft power.</li>
<li>India’s medal tally at recent International sports events demonstrate the country’s soft power on the global stage and encourage working towards the status of a great “geopolitical actor”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.bridgeindia.org.uk/the-rise-of-india-as-a-global-soft-power/" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>What is soft power?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Origin:</strong>
<ul>
<li>As far back as the 4<sup>th</sup> century BC, Kautilya (chankyaniti) had propounded the concept of Saam(advice or cajole),daam(pay or bribe),dand(punish),bhed(exploit secrets) which acquired western touch and can be understood by Soft power, smart power, hard power, and sharp power respectively.</li>
<li>Joseph Nye introduced the concept of “soft power” in the late 1980s. For Nye, power is the ability to influence the behavior of others to get the outcomes you want.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Meaning:</strong></li>
<li>Soft power is the ability of a country to persuade others to do what it wants without force or coercion.</li>
<li>Soft power is the ability to influence the behavior of others to get the outcomes you want.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="soft power" class="alignnone wp-image-640547" height="327" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 491px) 100vw, 491px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749.jpg 1200w" width="491"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-yoga-indias-soft-power/">Why Soft power is so significant?</a></strong></h4>
<p>Use of ‘Soft Power’ includes the number of cultural missions such as language schools, Olympic Medals and the quality of a country’s overall growth. Soft power produces following things:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Familiarity</strong>: If people know more about your country, culture, sports, and its talents, businesses, and resources, then soft power is enhanced.</li>
<li><strong>Reputation</strong>: For a nation to be attractive and a role model for others, its overall reputation must be strong and positive.</li>
<li><strong>Influence</strong>: A direct measure of the perceived presence and impact that your country has in other countries</li>
<li><strong>Business/Innovation/Sports</strong>: The attractiveness of a country’s economic model, its digital engagement with the world, performance in sports etc.</li>
<li><strong>Government</strong>: Showcases the ability of country’s political leadership and what it delivers to its people in different arenas.</li>
<li><strong>Multi-Alignment:</strong> As a country rises up the ‘Soft Power’ list, more and more outside parties align themselves with the common goals of that country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why the Sports being used as a tool of soft power in modern international relations?</strong></h4>
<p>Sport can be used as tool of soft power both internationally and domestically.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>International platform</strong>: Sports provide a platform for countries to showcase their culture, values and tradition.</li>
<li><strong>Puts a Better image of a country</strong>: Sports as a tool to achieve social, political, and financial goals, and improve the image of the country<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>International exposure: </strong>The focus on culture and peaceful values in sports make it a useful tool for countries to use soft power to achieve international goals and improve their public diplomacy.</li>
<li><strong>Reducing differences</strong>: Sports provides a platform for trust-building; and reconciliation, integration and anti-racism.</li>
<li><strong>Learning from China’s Case</strong>:</li>
<li>Dongfeng Liu (International Professor of Sport Management) in his survey on China’s performance in the Olympics he found that a country’s Olympic achievement has a positive effect on its national soft power.</li>
<li>As china is a communist country and reputation about human rights is not good, so China uses its superiority in elite sports to build “people-to-people” relations with other countries. For example, athletes from African countries such as Madagascar are trained in swimming, badminton, table tennis, etc. in China, which helps Beijing create a positive impact on a wider population and result in better formal relations as well.</li>
<li>There is also China’s memorandum of understanding with countries such as Kenya so that Chinese runners can train with Kenyan athletes, as they are among the best in the world when it comes to long-distance running.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="soft power" class="alignnone wp-image-640550" height="512" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/80906-yutjpg-1554537206-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/80906-yutjpg-1554537206-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/80906-yutjpg-1554537206.jpg 640w" width="683"/>Introspection on India’s performance at recent International Sports events</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is being said that the golden period of Indian sports may have begun as at the Tokyo Olympics and then the Birmingham 2022 Commonwealth Games (CWG) are examples of a good performance.</li>
<li>India’s medal tally in the Tokyo Olympics Games — seven — was its most decorated Olympic Games in Indian history.</li>
<li>At the Commonwealth games (CWG) 2022, Indian athletes won 61 medals, including 22 gold.</li>
<li>India has one of the world’s poorest population-to-medal ratios when it comes to the Olympics.</li>
<li>Ensuring competent coaches, and having adequate funding and more sports academics still remain major issues even decades later</li>
<li>India spends only three paise per day per capita on sports. In contrast China spends 1 per day per capita.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to increase the country’s sporting performance and soft power</strong><strong>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Train Indian players overseas:</strong></li>
<li>India should concentrate on forging MoUs with nations that excel in specific sports and train Indian players overseas.</li>
<li>For example, Australia and the United Kingdom can assist us in swimming given their standing here.</li>
<li>When it comes to running, negotiating collaborative training agreements with African countries such as Kenya would be ideal.</li>
<li><strong>No Politics over assistance: </strong></li>
<li>There should be no politics in seeking or even offering assistance.</li>
<li>For example China has requested Indian assistance in improving cricket development in China (Chongqing city).</li>
<li><strong>Private Investment</strong>:</li>
<li>Private investment needs to be harnessed to develop infrastructure. The better a country performs in sporting events the greater a sports person’s interest in their sports atmosphere. This also creates a huge market for private players to invest in.</li>
<li>For example, leading corporate houses in India have already shown how their active participation and investment can improve sporting performance as a result of unique corporate sports programmes.</li>
<li><strong>Public –private partnership at grass root :</strong></li>
<li>The Government should also work on a public-private partnership (PPP) model to create basic sporting infrastructure.</li>
<li>As recommended by NITI Aayog, at the district level too so that talent can be captured at an early stage.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sports as a tool of soft power had always been a key element of leadership from the ancient times. Sports provide an international platform to develop an attitude of unity in a divided multi-polar modern world.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Sports provide an international platform to develop an attitude of unity and influence others in a divided multi-polar modern world. Discuss in this context that soft power is not an end but a means to an end.</strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/soft-power/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The future of India is linked to police reforms</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/police-reforms/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Police reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The future of India is linked to police reforms. If the country is to progress and emerge as a great power, there is no alternative to radical reforms in the police.</li>
<li>September 22, is observed as <a href="https://bprd.nic.in/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Police Reforms day</a> since the Supreme Court gave a landmark judgment on police reforms in 2006 on the same.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a term Police stands for?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Police is a constituted body of uniformed persons empowered by a state who are responsible for keeping law and order intact.</li>
<li>Their lawful powers include arrest and the use of force.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Role of Police?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Law enforcement</strong><strong>: </strong>The basic role of the police is to function as a law enforcement agency and render impartial service to law, without any heed to wishes, indications or desires expressed by the government which either come in conflict with or do not conform to the provisions contained in the constitution or laws.</li>
<li><strong>Service delivery</strong><strong>:</strong> The police should have duly recognised service-oriented role in providing relief to people in distress situations. They should be trained and equipped to perform the service oriented functions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Issues with police institution in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Colonial practice</strong>: The Police Act of 1861, which governs substantially the functioning of police even today, is a symbol of colonial rule.</li>
<li><strong>Cost of internal security on economic growth</strong>: Economic development depends on sound law and order and we can have good law and order only if we have professional police. According to the Institute for Economics and Peace, violence cost the country 7 per cent of its GDP in 2020.</li>
<li><strong>Infiltration of persons of questionable background at power:</strong> According to the Association of Democratic Reforms, the percentage of such people in Parliament has been showing a steady upward trend. It was 24 per cent in 2004, 30 per cent in 2009, 34 per cent in 2014 and 43 per cent in the last election held in 2019.This poses a challenge for police to take action against this segment of people and their supporters who have a shady background and who may one day devour the very system that has placed them in power.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of Internal security doctrine:</strong> Problems are tackled as per the perception of the ruling dispensation at any given point time and therefore police are not able to deal with the internal security challenges as effectively as they should.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of confidence of public in police:</strong> Most people believe police to be abusive and also believe that police personnel misuse their power in order to bring order to society. This is particularly true of the lower strata of society, who feel that there is one law for the poor and another for the rich and powerful as police under influence of political and financial clout.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing complexity of organized crimes</strong>: Organised crime has acquired international dimensions. Arms trafficking and drug trafficking do not observe any borders and Cybercrimes are increasing in geometrical progression.<strong> </strong></li>
<li><strong> Poor infrastructure and human resource: </strong>The police are not able to deliver partly because of poor infrastructure moreover there is a vacancy of more than 5,00,000 personnel.</li>
<li><strong>Poor housing conditions and long working hours:</strong> poor housing conditions and long working hours have an adverse impact on police performance.  According to the Status of Policing in India Report, 2019, an average policeman works for 14 hours a day and does not get any weekly off. This takes a heavy toll on his mental and physical health.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is meant by police reforms?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The aim of Police reforms is to enhance efficiency, capability, and adoptability according to the time and transforming culture, values and existing practice of police system.</li>
<li>As per the Indian Constitution Police comes under state list.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to improve <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/reforms-police-in-india-need/">efficiency of police in India</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Police sensitisation about their role in society: </strong>The sensitisation module should aim at bringing about attitudinal change in police — especially pertaining to gender and power relations and police behavior. It is necessary to increase public confidence in the police by upgrading levels of police service delivery as well as by investigating and acting in cases of police misconduct<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Increasing accountability</strong><strong>: </strong>Making them answerable to law and law alone and not to work under pressure of the political and financial clout.</li>
<li><strong>Develop infrastructure and fill vacancies:</strong> Overall, there is a vacancy of more than 5,00,000 personnel. These must be filled. There is huge scope for improvement in transport, communications and forensics as well</li>
<li><strong>Improving hosing conditions:</strong> The National Police Commission had recommended 100 per cent family accommodation for all non gazetted police personnel. The satisfaction level today is hardly 31.24 per cent.</li>
<li><strong> Reducing working hours:</strong> Long working hours have an adverse impact on police performance. We should have 12-hour shifts straightaway and gradually aim to achieve eight-hour shifts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A new role and new philosophy have to be defined for the police to not only make it a capable and effective body but also one accountable to the law of the land and to the people whom they serve.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. </strong><strong>If the country is to progress and emerge as a great power, there is no alternative to radical reforms in the police. Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/police-reforms/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>In news: Rotterdam Convention</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rotterdam-convention-chemicals-pic/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Rotterdam convention, PIC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>International trade of two new hazardous pesticides — Iprodione and Terbufos — has been recommended for “prior informed consent” (PIC) procedure under the Rotterdam convention.</p>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In India, the use of these chemicals was permitted by the 2015 Anupam Verma committee report. The country is among the largest exporters of Terbufos.</li>
<li>The chemicals are dangerous for humans and aquatic animals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Rotterdam Convention</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Rotterdam Convention is formally known as the Convention on the Prior Informed Consent Procedure for Certain Hazardous Chemicals and Pesticides in International Trade.</li>
<li>It is a multilateral treaty to promote shared responsibilities in relation to importation of hazardous chemicals.</li>
<li>The convention promotes open exchange of information and calls on exporters of hazardous chemicals to use proper labelling, include directions on safe handling, and inform purchasers of any known restrictions or bans.</li>
<li>Signatory nations can decide whether to allow or ban the importation of chemicals listed in the treaty, and exporting countries are obliged to make sure that producers within their jurisdiction comply.</li>
<li>India is a party to the convention, with 161 other parties.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Prior Informed Consent (PIC) procedure?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PIC procedure is a mechanism for formally obtaining and disseminating the decisions of importing parties on their willingness to receive future shipments of hazardous chemicals.</li>
<li>The PIC procedure is a mechanism for formally obtaining and disseminating the decisions of importing Parties as to whether they wish to receive future shipments of those chemicals listed in the Convention.</li>
<li>For each of the chemicals listed in Annex III and subject to the PIC procedure a decision guidance document (DGD) is prepared and sent to all Parties.</li>
<li>All Parties are required to take a decision as to whether or not they will allow future import of each of the chemicals in Annex III of the Convention.</li>
<li>These decisions are known as import responses.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Which are the new chemicals listed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Iprodione, a fungicide used on vines, fruits, trees and vegetables, has been classified as carcinogenic and toxic for reproduction.</li>
<li>Terbufos is a soil insecticide used commonly on sorghum, maize, beet and potatoes. It has also been found to pose risk to aquatic organisms due to its toxicity.</li>
<li>Both pesticides, which are used in agriculture, are known for their harmful impacts on human health and the environment.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rotterdam-convention-chemicals-pic/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre defers new Foreign Trade Policy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-defers-new-foreign-trade-policy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Foreign Trade Policy</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The government has extended the launch of new Foreign Trade Policy (FTP) (2022-27) by six more months and would continue with the existing one.</p>
<h4><strong>Why such delay in Foreign Trade Policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Geopolitical uncertainty:</strong> The geo-political situation is not suitable for long-term foreign trade policy, said Union Commerce Minister.</li>
<li><strong>Global recession:</strong> Currently, fears of a recession in major economies like the US and Europe have escalated a panic among investors.</li>
<li><strong>Decline in USD inflows:</strong> Foreign investors have begun to pull back their money from equities.</li>
<li><strong>Rupee depreciation:</strong> The US Dollar is at a 22-year high, while the Rupee hit a new all-time low of $81.6.</li>
<li><strong>Huge trade deficit:</strong> The trade deficit widened by more than 2-folds to $125.22 billion (April – August 2022) compared to $53.78 billion in the same period last year.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Foreign Trade Policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s Foreign Trade Policy (FTP) is a set of guidelines for goods and services imported and exported.</li>
<li>These are developed by the Directorate General of Foreign Trade (DGFT), the Ministry of Commerce and Industry’s regulating body for the promotion and facilitation of exports and imports.</li>
<li>FTPs are enforceable under the Foreign Trade Development and Regulation Act 1992.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is India’s Foreign Trade Policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In line with the ‘Make in India,’ ‘Digital India,’ ‘Skill India,’ ‘Startup India,’ and ‘Ease of Doing Business initiatives, the Foreign Trade Policy (2015-20) was launched on April 1, 2015.</li>
<li>It provides a framework for increasing exports of goods and services, creating jobs, and increasing value addition in the country.</li>
<li>The FTP statement outlines the market and product strategy as well as the steps needed to promote trade, expand infrastructure, and improve the entire trade ecosystem.</li>
<li>It aims to help India respond to external problems while staying on top of fast-changing international trading infrastructure and to make trade a major contributor to the country’s economic growth and development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues with FTP (2015-2020)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Acting on Washington’s protest, a WTO dispute settlement panel ruled in 2019 that India’s export <strong><u>subsidy measures are in violation of WTO norms</u></strong> and must be repealed.</li>
<li><strong><u>Tax incentives</u></strong> under the popular <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-rodtep-scheme/">Merchandise Exports from India Scheme (MEIS)</a> (now renamed as RODTEP Scheme)and Service Exports from India Scheme (SEIS) programmes were among them.</li>
<li>The panel found that because India’s per capita gross national product exceeds $1,000 per year, it may no longer grant subsidies based on export performance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>WTO-compliance:</strong> With incentives under MEIS and SEIS in the cloud, WTO-compliant tax benefits are a must.</li>
<li><strong>Access to credit:</strong> Credit availability has long been a need of exporters, particularly MSMEs.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure upgrade:</strong> China’s network of ports, motorways, and high-speed trains, which are among the greatest in the world, is one of the reasons it is a manufacturing and export powerhouse.</li>
<li><strong>Digitization and e-commerce boost:</strong> India requires innovative trading procedures as a result of Covid-19 breaking old supply channels.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-defers-new-foreign-trade-policy/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre’s push for NavIC System  </title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centres-push-for-navic-system/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NAVIC, IRNSS, GPS</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="navic" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-352595" height="595" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 641px) 100vw, 641px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/irnss.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/irnss.jpg 641w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/irnss-300x278.jpg 300w" width="641"/></p>
<p>The Union government is pushing tech giants to make smartphones compatible with its home-grown navigation system ‘NavIC’.</p>
<h4>What is NavIC?</h4>
<ul>
<li>NavIC, or Navigation with Indian Constellation, is an independent stand-alone navigation satellite system developed by the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO).</li>
<li>NavIC was originally approved in 2006 at a cost of $174 million.</li>
<li>It was expected to be completed by late 2011, but only became operational in 2018.</li>
<li>NavIC consists of <strong><u>eight satellites</u></strong> and <strong><u>covers the whole of India’s landmass and up to 1,500 km</u></strong> (930 miles) from its boundaries.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Note:</strong> The numbers of satellites in this constellation is disputed. It is given as 7 and 8 on different sources. Total Nine satellites were launched out of which the very first (IRNSS-1A) is partially failed because of some issue in its <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-entangled-atomic-clocks/">Atomic Clock</a>. Another and the last satellite had a launch failure. Hence the number 7/8.</p></blockquote>
<h4>Why is the Centre pushing for NavIC?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Currently, NavIC’s use is limited.</li>
<li>It is being used in public vehicle tracking in India.</li>
<li>It helps providing emergency warning alerts to fishermen venturing into the deep sea where there is no terrestrial network connectivity, and for tracking and providing information related to natural disasters.</li>
<li>Enabling it in smartphones is the next step India is pushing for.</li>
<li>India’s 2021 satellite navigation draft policy stated the government will work towards expanding the coverage from regional to global to ensure availability of NavIC signal in any part of the world.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How does NavIC compare?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The main difference is the serviceable area covered by these systems.</li>
<li>GPS caters to users across the globe and its satellites circle the earth twice a day, while NavIC is currently for use in India and adjacent areas.</li>
<li>Like GPS, there are three more navigation systems that have global coverage – Galileo from the European Union, Russia-owned GLONASS and China’s Beidou.</li>
<li>QZSS, operated by Japan, is another regional navigation system covering Asia-Oceania region, with a focus on Japan.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Strategic significance of NavIC</h4>
<ul>
<li>India says NavIC is conceived with the aim of <strong><u>removing dependence</u></strong> on foreign satellite systems for navigation service requirements, particularly for “strategic sectors.”</li>
<li>Relying on systems like GPS and GLONASS <strong><u>may not always be reliable</u></strong>, India says, as those are operated by the defence agencies of respective nations.</li>
<li>It is possible that <strong><u>civilian services can be degraded or denied</u></strong>.</li>
<li>NavIC is an indigenous positioning system that is under <strong><u>Indian control</u></strong>.</li>
<li>There is <strong><u>no risk of the service being withdrawn</u></strong> or denied in a given situation.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ:</h4>
<p><strong>Q. With reference to the Indian Regional Navigation Satellite System (IRNSS), consider the following statements:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li><strong>IRNSS has three Satellites in geostationary and four satellites the geosynchronous orbits.</strong></li>
<li><strong>IRNSS covers entire India and about 5500 sq. km beyond its borders.</strong></li>
<li><strong>India will have its own satellite navigation system with full global coverage by the middle of 2019.</strong></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Which of the statements given above is/are correct?</strong></p>
<p>(a) 1 only</p>
<p>(b) 1 and 2 only</p>
<p>(c) 2 and 3 only</p>
<p>(d) None</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Answer:</strong> (Post it here.)</p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centres-push-for-navic-system/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Here is how HDI has performed in last 3 decades</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hdi/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of report</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>human development</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="HDI" class="alignnone wp-image-636168" height="345" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 448px) 100vw, 448px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-300x231.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-300x231.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-1024x787.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-768x590.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-1171x900.jpg 1171w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant.jpg 1200w" width="448"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India, belonging to the medium HDI category, shows dimensional inequalities similar to or slightly below the average figures in the category, except in the case of education where it is high and closer to the low HDI countries. The inequalities in health and education are more than twice that of the very high and high HDI categories.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The bad news for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/human-development-report-by-undp/">India is that its global HDI rank has slipped</a> from 129 in 2019 to 131 in 2020 and to 132 in 2021-22.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the meaning of human development?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Human development is defined as the process of enlarging people’s freedoms and opportunities and improving their well-being. Human development is about the real freedom ordinary people have to decide who to be, what to do, and how to live.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is meant by Human Development Index?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The HDI is a summary measure of human development. The HDI is a summary composite measure of a country’s average achievements in three basic aspects of human development: health, knowledge and standard of living.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who publishes HDI?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Human Development Report (HDR) is an annual Human Development Index report published by the Human Development Report Office of the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="HDI" class="alignnone wp-image-636170" height="338" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3.jpg 960w" width="600"/>Dimensions of the Human Development Index</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Long and healthy life: </strong>The long and healthy life dimension is measured by life expectancy at birth. The life expectancy at birth is a statistical measure that an average individual is expected to live based on certain demographic factors such as the year of birth and current age.</li>
<li><strong>Education</strong>: This is a second dimension in the HDI. The indicators of education are the expected years of schooling and the mean years of schooling. According to the UN, the average maximum years of schooling is 18 years, while the mean maximum years of schooling is 15 years.</li>
<li><strong>Standard of living: </strong>The standard of living is usually measured by the gross national income (GNI) per capita. The GNI indicates the total domestic and foreign output created by the residents of a certain country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the 4 indicators of HDI?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Mean years of schooling</li>
<li>Expected years of schooling</li>
<li>Life expectancy at birth</li>
<li>Gross national income (GNI) per capita</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Which Countries Have the Highest HDI?</strong></p>
<p>In the latest HDI ranking, from 2022, Switzerland finished first with an HDI value of 0.962.</p></blockquote>
<p><img alt="HDI" class="wp-image-636173" height="339" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 509px) 100vw, 509px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook.jpg 1536w" width="509"/></p>
<h4><strong>Issues in HDI</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) An incomplete indicator</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Human development is incomplete without human freedom and that while the need for qualities judgement is clear; there is no simple quantitative measure available yet to capture the many aspects of human freedom.</li>
<li>HDI also does not specifically reflect quality of life factors, such as empowerment movements or overall feelings of security or happiness.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Limited idea of development</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The HDI is not reflecting the human development idea accurately.</li>
<li>It is an index restricted to the socio-economic sphere of life; the political and civil spheres are in the most part kept separate.</li>
<li>Hence there is a sub-estimation of inequality among countries, which means that this dimension is not being taken into consideration appropriately.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) A vague concept</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Concerning data quality and the exact construction of the index HDI is conceptually weak and empirically unsound.</li>
<li>This strong critic comes from the idea that both components of HDI are problematic. The GNP in developing countries suffers from incomplete coverage, measurement errors and biases.</li>
<li>The definition and measurement of literacy are different among countries and also, this data has not been available since 1970 in a significant number of countries.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Data quality issues</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The HDI, as a combination of only four relatively simple indicators, doesn’t only raise a questions what other indicators should be included, but also how to ensure quality and comparable input data.</li>
<li>It is logical that the UNDP try to collect their data from international organizations concentrating in collecting data in specific fields.</li>
<li>Quality and trustworthiness of those data is disputable, especially when we get the information from UN non-democratic members, as for example Cuba or China.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) A tool for mere comparison</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The concept of HDI was set up mainly for relative comparison of countries in one particular time.</li>
<li>HDI is much better when distinguishing between countries with low and middle human development, instead of countries at the top of the ranking.</li>
<li>Therefore, the original notion was not to set up an absolute ranking, but let’s quite free hands in comparison of the results.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Development has to be greener</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The human development approach has not adequately incorporated environmental conditions which may threaten long-term achievements on human development. The most pervasive failure was on environmental sustainability.</li>
<li>However, for the first time in 2020, the UNDP introduced a new metric to reflect the impact caused by each country’s per-capita carbon emissions and its material footprint.</li>
<li>This is Planetary Pressures-adjusted HDI or PHDI. It measured the amount of fossil fuels, metals and other resources used to make the goods and services it consumes.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(7) Wealth can never equate welfare</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Higher national wealth does not indicate welfare. GNI may not necessarily increase economic welfare; it depends on how it is spent.</li>
<li>For example, if a country spends more on military spending – this is reflected in higher GNI, but welfare could actually be lower.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Importance of HDI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multidimensionality</strong>: It is one of the few multidimensional indices as it includes indicators such as literacy rate, enrolment ratio, life expectancy rate, infant mortality rate, etc.</li>
<li><strong>True yardstick</strong>: It acts as a true yardstick to measure development in real sense.</li>
<li><strong>Helps in measuring a nation’s well-being:</strong> Unlike per capital income, which only indicates that a rise in per capital income implies economic development; HDI considers many other vital social indicators and helps in measuring a nation’s well-being.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Value addition line</strong></p>
<p><em>People are the real wealth of a nation. The basic objective of development should be to create an enabling environment for people to live long, healthy and creative lives. This may appear to be a simple truth.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To sum up, the introduction of the HDI three decades ago was an early attempt to address the shortcomings in conventional measures of wellbeing.</li>
<li>The HDI has continued to attract widespread attention and motivates the work of activists, scholars and political leaders around the world.</li>
<li>The HDI compels us to ask what matters more, the quantitative expansion of an economy, or the qualitative improvement in the capabilities of society.</li>
<li>Indeed the revival of interest in this subject at the highest levels of government is the need of the hour.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you understand by human development? Critically analyse the human development index given by UNDP.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hdi/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Karnataka brings law giving Quota for Locals</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/karnataka-brings-law-giving-quota-for-locals/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Quota for Locals</p></div></div><p>The Karnataka government recently tabled The Kannada Language Comprehensive Development Bill which gives preference to Kannadigas in government jobs and also provides for a reservation to locals in private jobs generated in the state.</p>
<h4><strong>What does the Karnataka legislation envisage?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Apart from ensuring job guarantee to Kannada speakers, the Bill pushes for the use of Kannada in institutes of higher learning and for sops to industries that employ locals.</li>
<li>Features highlighted in the Bill include reservation in higher, technical and professional education to those who studied in Kannada medium schools.</li>
<li>It seeks introduction of Kannada as essential language for seeking employment in the state government.</li>
<li>Also, industries will be entitled to concessions, tax rebates and deferment of taxes if they provide reservation for Kannadigas, as per the state’s industrial policy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Quota for Locals?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Ans.</strong> Constitutional provision for Equal Treatment</p>
<ul>
<li>Article 16 of the Constitution guarantees equal treatment under the law in matters of public employment. It prohibits the state from discriminating on grounds of place of birth or residence.</li>
<li>Article 16(2) states that “no citizen shall, on grounds only of religion, race, caste, sex, descent, place of birth, residence or any of them, be ineligible for, or discriminated against in respect of, any employment or office under the State”.</li>
<li>The provision is supplemented by the other clauses in the Constitution that guarantee equality.</li>
<li>However, Article 16(3) of the Constitution provides an exception by saying that Parliament may make a law “prescribing” a requirement of residence for jobs in a particular state.</li>
<li>This power vests solely in the Parliament, not state legislatures.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why does the Constitution prohibit reservation based on domicile?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When the Constitution came into force, India turned itself into one nation from a geographical unit of individual principalities and the idea of the universality of Indian citizenship took root.</li>
<li>India has single citizenship, and it gives citizens the liberty to move around freely in any part of the country.</li>
<li>Hence the requirement of a place of birth or residence cannot be qualification for granting public employment in any state.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>But are reservations not granted on other grounds such as caste?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Equality enshrined in the Constitution is not mathematical equality and does not mean all citizens will be treated alike without any distinction.</li>
<li>To this effect, the Constitution underlines two distinct aspects which together form the essence of equality law:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Non-discrimination among equals, and</li>
<li>Affirmative action to equalize the unequal</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Supreme Court rulings on quota for locals</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court has ruled against reservation based on place of birth or residence.</li>
<li>In 1984, ruling in Dr Pradeep Jain v Union of India, the issue of legislation for “sons of the soil” was discussed.</li>
<li>The court expressed an opinion that such policies would be unconstitutional but did not expressly rule on it as the case was on different aspects of the right to equality.</li>
<li>In a subsequent ruling in Sunanda Reddy v State of Andhra Pradesh (1995), the Supreme Court affirmed the observation in 1984 ruling to strike down a state government policy that gave 5% extra weightage to candidates.</li>
<li>In 2002, the Supreme Court invalidated appointment of government teachers in Rajasthan in which the state selection board gave preference to “applicants belonging to the district or the rural areas of the district concerned”.</li>
<li>In 2019, the Allahabad HC struck down a recruitment notification by the UP PSC which prescribed preference for women who are “original residents” of the UP alone.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why it is a bad idea?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Against Equality as well as meritocracy</strong>: It goes against the Constitution of India. In fact, it violates several fundamental rights, such as freedom to move anywhere, the right not to be discriminated on the basis of place of birth, the right to be treated equally before laws and the right to pursue one’s livelihood.</li>
<li><strong>Migration criteria not justified</strong>: The actual data on inter-State migration shows that inter-State migration is relatively low in India. Migration often bring skills, motivation, energy which may be in short supply or lacking locally.</li>
<li><strong>Free movement of labour</strong>: A more analytical aspect to highlight is that free movement of labour partly compensates for the uneven economic progress of different States. The idea also goes against the established fact that migration of labour is good for the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Un-ease of doing business</strong>: Local reservation in the private sector may not be the ideal solution to tackle the unemployment crisis. In fact, it can deter the corporate sector from investing in states that come up with such a rule.</li>
<li><strong>Scapegoating the private sector: </strong>What distinguishes the private sector from the public sector is the inherent competition and a hunger for improvement. In such a scenario, chief ministers should do well to engage with the private sector in a much more holistic manner, and not burden it with unfeasible rules.</li>
<li><strong>MSMEs to be hit harder: </strong>MSMEs could be the hardest hit. They do not have the necessary capital to relocate and many studies have shown that more than 50 per cent of employees are not residents of the state.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Arguments in favour of quota in private</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Avoiding encroachments:</strong> Often the privileged castes (or groups) use nefarious arguments to protect their interests.</li>
<li><strong>Foul argument of merit:</strong> Reservations once accepted in the constitutional framework are not a charity that is to be kept away from the ‘meritocracy’ of ‘private’ operations.</li>
<li><strong>Ensuring equal opportunity:</strong> Like all other constitutional guarantees, one may feel the necessity to get ensured of equal opportunity in all spaces.</li>
<li><strong>Preventing exclusion:</strong> Giving preference and quotas for socially and educationally deprived sections in the private space is, therefore, in keeping with this fundamental tenet.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The politics of identity and polarization on region/religious lines seems inadequate for the elections.</li>
<li>The philosophy and pragmatism of universal excellence through equality of opportunity for education and advancement across the nation is part of our founding faith and constitutional creed.</li>
<li>Clearly, this is not the appropriate domain of being “vocal for local”.</li>
<li>Although some reservations may still be necessary for the socio-political condition in India, reservation on the basis of domicile or residence within a State would be highly discriminatory.</li>
<li>It is more likely that such politically motivated steps would be overturned by the judiciary as has been done several times in the past.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/karnataka-brings-law-giving-quota-for-locals/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Process of sustainable tourism should be holistic and inclusive</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tourism-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Incredible India</p></div></div><p>“<em>To other Country, I may go as a tourist. But to India I come as a pilgrim</em>”, the words of Martin Luther King says a lot about India’s wisdom and tourism potential.</p>
<h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The three-day National Conference of State Tourism Minister was held at Dharamshala , a first of its kind meeting aimed  to discuss, debate and deliberate on modes and mechanisms to develop tourism in India .</li>
<li>The three-day National Conference concluded with the adoption of “Dharamshala Declaration” which affirms commitment toward developing “sustainable and responsible tourism” and positions India as a “global leader in the tourism sector by 2047”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism is travel for pleasure or business; also the theory and practice of touring, the business of attracting, accommodating, and entertaining tourists, and the business of operating tours.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Types of tourism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Domestic tourism</strong>: Refers to activities of a visitor within their country of residence and outside of their home (e.g. a Indian visiting other parts of India)</li>
<li><strong>Inbound tourism</strong>: Refers to the activities of a visitor from outside of country of residence (e.g. a Spaniard visiting Britain).</li>
<li><strong>Outbound tourism</strong>: Refers to the activities of a resident visitor outside of their country of residence (e.g. an Indian visiting an overseas country).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640662" height="327" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341.jpg 550w" width="580"/>What does sustainable tourism mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sustainable tourism is defined by the UN Environment Program and UN World Tourism Organization as “tourism that takes full account of its current and future economic, social and environmental impacts, addressing the needs of visitors, the industry, the environment and host communities.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the main importance of tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism boosts the revenue of the economy, creates thousands of jobs, develops the infrastructures of a country, and plants a sense of cultural exchange between foreigners and citizens.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640663" height="379" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 605px) 100vw, 605px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan.jpg 1024w" width="605"/>Why tourism is needed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism is not a fad. It is a compulsion driven by the urge to discover new places. Because we have this compulsion to venture into the unknown, we need each other. When humans travel, meet and exchange ideas, civilization flourishes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is “The Dharamshala Declaration” is all about?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Aim of the declaration: </strong>The Dharamshala Declaration aims to recognise India’s role in contributing towards global tourism as well as focusing on recovery by also promoting domestic tourism.</li>
<li><strong>Action plan:</strong> In the declaration, the Tourism Ministry has come up with a with a action plan to encourage more Indians to travel domestically and explore India’s natural, cultural, and spiritual beauty while simultaneously reaching the goal of an ‘Ek Bharat Shrestha Bharat’ (interaction and mutual understanding).</li>
<li><strong>Strategy: </strong>The Tourism Ministry has also been working with the Ministry of External Affairs to identify 20 Indian missions abroad with the highest tourist footfalls to India and build country-specific strategies to attract foreign tourists.</li>
<li><strong>Plan according to G-20: </strong>The Dharamshala Declaration affirms the plan to position India as a major tourism destination during its presidency of G-20 next year. India’s age-old dictum of ‘Atithi Devo Bhava’ will come to the fore as it welcomes delegates from the 20 countries/European Union.</li>
<li><strong>Necessary steps:</strong> The Ministry of Tourism also plans to work with other Ministries to bring in necessary interventions such as visa reforms, ease of travel, travel-friendly and improved immigration facilities at airports.</li>
<li><strong>National Tourism policy</strong><strong>:</strong> Drafted with a holistic vision and strategy to revive India’s tourism and targets to contribute USD 1 trillion to the GDP by 2047.<strong><br/>
</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640666" height="519" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 692px) 100vw, 692px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1200x900.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1980x1485.jpg 1980w" width="692"/>A draft on National <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gujarats-mice-tourism-policy/">Tourism Policy 2022</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Framework:</strong></li>
<li>Draft on National Tourism Policy 2022 aims at improving the framework conditions for tourism development in the country.</li>
<li>Supporting tourism industries, strengthening tourism support functions and developing tourism sub-sectors.</li>
<li>Impetus to digitalisation, innovation and technology through the National Digital Tourism Mission and skilling through the Tourism and Hospitality Sector Skill Mission.</li>
<li>The policy also gives a special impetus to private sector participation through public-private-partnerships (PPP)</li>
<li><strong>Guiding Principles</strong> :</li>
<li>Promoting sustainable, responsible and inclusive tourism in line with our civilisational ethos From Gautama to Gandhi, India has always spoken about the inherent need to live harmoniously with nature and within our means.</li>
<li>The National Green Tourism Mission aims at institutionalising green approach.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.incredibleindia.org/content/incredible-india-v2/en.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640665" height="375" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 666px) 100vw, 666px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-768x433.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism.jpg 1170w" width="666"/>Tourism Potential in India</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Employement generation:</strong> India has huge tourism potential. If capitalised properly it can emerge as one of the leading sectors to contribute to GDP and also has the potential to augment employment.</li>
<li><strong>The Pandemic cost and recovery: </strong>The pandemic has caused conspicuous losses for this sector but over the past few months, all the major tourism indices such as domestic air passenger traffic, hotel occupancy and tourist footfalls have shown signs of recovery and are going back to pre-pandemic levels.</li>
<li><strong>Short term estimate:</strong> By 2024, in short term the country is estimated to contribute USD 150 billion to the GDP from tourism, USD 30 billion in Foreign Exchange earnings and can get 15 million foreign tourist arrivals..</li>
<li><strong>Medium term by 2030:</strong> It is estimated to grow at seven to nine per cent Compound Annual Growth Rate in the coming decade. In the medium term, that is 2030, the tourism-related goals are USD 250 billion GDP contribution; 137 million jobs, 56 million foreign tourist arrivals and USD 56 billion in foreign exchange earnings.</li>
<li><strong>Visionary schemes</strong>: The visionary schemes like Swadesh Darshan or Dekho Apna Desh have the potential to increase tourism value while maintaining cultural integrity and ecological sustainability of the places.</li>
<li><strong>Dekho Apna Desh</strong>: Dekho apna desh rolled out in 2020 envisages encouraging domestic tourism, urging people to visit places in India. India is a land of rich cultural heritage.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>If the goal of positioning of India as one of the world’s best tourism destinations by 2047, there is need to integrate various schemes of different ministries. Need to involve various stakeholders, and local communities; necessary interventions at urban and rural level should be a priority.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Since the positive and negative outcomes of tourism depend on human factors, including the attitude and behavior of both tourists and hosts, in this context discuss India’s potential to become a global leader in tourism sector.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tourism-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>“Government of the people, by the people and for the people” for vibrant democracy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/democracy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Democratic credentials</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="democracy" class="alignnone wp-image-640675" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-300x199.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-300x199.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-1024x678.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-768x508.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-1536x1017.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-1200x794.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-1980x1311.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy.jpg 2000w" width="585"/>Context</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.g7germany.de/g7-en" rel="noopener" target="_blank">G7 nations and partner countries</a> including India recently signed “2022 Resilient democracies statement”-We, the Leaders of Germany, Argentina, Canada, France, India, Indonesia, Italy, Japan, Senegal, South Africa, the United Kingdom, the United States of America, and the European Union, affirm our commitment to strengthening the resilience of our democracies and to working towards equitable, inclusive and sustainable solutions to global challenges, including climate change and the COVID-19 pandemic, and reaffirm our commitment to the rules-based international order.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>How we define Democracy?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>“Government of the people, by the people and for the people” the words used by Abraham Lincoln in the year 1863 while talking about democracy<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Purpose of democracy</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Cornerstones of democracy include freedom of assembly, association, property rights, freedom of religion and speech, inclusiveness and equality, citizenship, consent of the governed, voting rights, freedom from unwarranted governmental deprivation of the right to life and liberty, and minority rights.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/highlights-of-the-democracy-report-2022/"><strong>Democracy Report 2022</strong></a></p>
<ul>
<li>The study, titled ‘Democracy Report 2022: Autocratisation Changing Nature?’ states that more than twice as many countries are undergoing Autocratisation as are witnessing democratization.</li>
<li>The conceptual scheme takes into account not only the electoral dimension (free and fair elections) but also the liberal principle that democracy must protect “individual and minority rights”</li>
<li>The V-Dem report classifies countries into four regime types based on their score in the Liberal Democratic Index (LDI): a)Liberal Democracy b)Electoral Democracy c)Electoral Autocracy and d)Closed Autocracy</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="democracy" class="alignnone wp-image-640676" height="383" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 676px) 100vw, 676px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/democracy-voting-1-300x170.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/democracy-voting-1-300x170.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/democracy-voting-1-768x435.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/democracy-voting-1.jpg 1000w" width="676"/>Where do the Reports and Indices put India?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Sweden based Sweden-based V-Dem Institute was harsher in its latest report on democracy. It said India had become an “electoral autocracy”</li>
<li>US-based non-profit Freedom House downgraded India from a free democracy to a “partially free democracy”.</li>
<li>India, described as a “flawed democracy”, slipped two places to 53rd position in the latest Democracy Index published by The Economist Intelligence Unit<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Status of Supporters of Democracy</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Decolonised African Countries: </strong></li>
<li>The number of African countries that have adopted democratic systems of government has grown since decolonisation, the collapse of communism and the ending of a number of civil wars.</li>
<li>Some countries, such as Ghana, are seen as resilient democracies, while for others the democratic transition is more fragile, after months of pro-democracy protests in 2019 in Sudan, a civilian-led transitional government is now paving the way for democracy after decades of military rule.</li>
<li><strong>India as example: </strong></li>
<li>India is the world’s largest democracy. India is staying as one unit despite having vast no of cultures, languages and religions. This is possible because of the democracy in India.</li>
<li>Minorities and disadvantaged sections are represented in parliament which enabled inclusive growth.</li>
<li>When India got independence, its economy was in shambles. Extreme poverty, unemployment, food insecurity were the major problems before Indian government. But India’s democratic constitution successfully balanced development and welfare of the country.</li>
<li>Now, India is one of the fastest growing economies in the world.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What critics arguing?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Democracy in crisis</strong>: Democracy is more in crisis than ever before, with the onset of centralisation of power, with a foreign policy defying public opinion, with the media centralised, and with corporate control of the economy tighter than ever.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing polarity: </strong>Threatening world order is emerging, which seeks to abrogate all individual rights and divide us along the extremist polarities that we thought had been neutralised.</li>
<li><strong>Global Crisis: </strong>We move into this new stage of conﬂict carrying the risk of a nuclear tragedy, further exacerbated by the collective buttressing of a global crisis of the novel coronavirus pandemic, uncontrollable ecological disasters, and food and water deﬁciency.</li>
<li><strong>Populism: </strong>Blatant fascist leanings of the so-called “democracies”, and escalating hunger and disease in Africa and other parts of the under-developed world give enough evidence that democracy faces serious issues of populism.</li>
<li><strong>Other global problems: </strong>Growing economic discrimination, overpopulation and environmental degradation, Misgivings about moral progress, about mutual understanding, exacerbate the dismal situation that faces humanity.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="democracy" class="alignnone wp-image-640677" height="301" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 602px) 100vw, 602px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-1024x512.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-1536x768.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-2048x1024.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-1200x600.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-1980x990.jpg 1980w" width="602"/>What can be done to strengthen the democracies further?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Strengthening public support:</strong> To protect freedom domestically and build support for a foreign policy that protects democratic rights and values abroad, it is essential to foster a stronger public understanding of democratic principles, especially among young people<strong>. </strong>civic education is necessary.</li>
<li><strong>Rule of law: </strong>In order to maintain trust in public institutions, the principles of legality, legal certainty and prohibition of arbitrariness of the executive powers, judicial independence, impartiality, and equality before the law need to be respected.</li>
<li><strong>Individual rights</strong><strong>: </strong>Democracy entails the right of individuals to participate in and influence the development of society, with free and fair elections at its core. Without an active turnout in elections and proper mechanisms for participation, the essence of democracy can be lost.</li>
<li><strong>Free speech: </strong>Free speech guard the freedom of expression and opinion, and affirmation of commitment to the very idea of democracy and a move towards opposing oppression and violence</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Democracy is always a work in progress. The key ingredients of democracy are effective and accountable institutions, and leadership. Institutions build resilience by embedding norms and standards and bridging periods of weak leadership.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Do you think Democracy is the best solution to tackle the growing fault lines between the communities? What makes India as the best example of Democracy to the world? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/democracy/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Carl-Gustaf M4 to be produced in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gustaf-m4-to-be-produced-in-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Carl-Gustaf M4</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="gustaf" class="alignnone wp-image-641101 size-full" height="853" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav.jpg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav-300x237.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav-1024x809.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav-768x607.jpg 768w" width="1080"/></p>
<p>Swedish defense major SAAB announced plans to manufacture its Carl-Gustaf M4 weapon system in India.</p>
<h4>What is the Carl-Gustaf M4?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Carl-Gustaf recoilless rifle is a man-portable, multi-role weapon system that allows dismounted soldiers to effectively deal with multiple challenges on the modern battlefield.</li>
<li>A proven performer in battle, the Carl-Gustaf M4 is said to be adaptable and flexible.</li>
<li>The Indian Army has been using the iconic Carl-Gustaf since 1976 and currently operates the Mk2 and Mk3 versions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Key features of Carl-Gustaf M4</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lightweight, robust, reliable, effective and easy to use</li>
<li>Tactical flexibility through a wide range of ammunition</li>
<li>Combat proven system</li>
<li>Ammunition: Anti-armour, anti-structure, anti-personnel, support</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In recent years, the Indian government has taken several steps to boost the defense manufacturing sector under the ‘Make in India’ and <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-self-reliance-in-defence/">‘Atmanirbhar Bharat’</a></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gustaf-m4-to-be-produced-in-india/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Jaldoot App to capture data on Groundwater Levels</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/jaldoot-app-to-capture-data-on-groundwater-levels/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Jaldoot App</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-641102" height="451" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 372px) 100vw, 372px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-248x300.jpg 248w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-845x1024.jpg 845w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-768x931.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-743x900.jpg 743w" width="372"/></p>
<p>With the rapidly declining water table threatening to push many regions into drought, the Union government on has launched a mobile application — Jaldoot.</p>
<h4>Jaldoot App</h4>
<ul>
<li>Jaldoot is jointly developed by the Rural Development and Panchayati Raj Ministries to monitor the groundwater levels across the country.</li>
<li>The App will enable Gram Rojgar Sahyak to measure the water level of well twice a year pre-monsoon and post-monsoon.</li>
<li>Jaldoots, that is, officers assigned to measure the water levels, should also upload the geo-tagged photographs through the app on every occasion of measurement.</li>
<li>This Mobile app will work in both online and offline mode.</li>
<li>So water level can be captured even without internet connectivity and captured date will be stored in mobile and when mobile comes in the connectivity area, data will synchronize with the central server.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Utility of the app</h4>
<ul>
<li>The despite promoting watershed development, afforestation, waterbody development and renovation, rainwater harvesting like initiatives, the ground water level in various parts of the country has depleted.</li>
<li>The regular data to be input by the Jaldoots would be integrated with the database of National Water Informatics Centre (NWIC), which can be utilised for analysis and display.</li>
<li>The app will facilitate in observing water tables across the country and the resulting data can be utilised for Gram Panchayat Development Plan and Mahatma Gandhi NREGA Plans.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/jaldoot-app-to-capture-data-on-groundwater-levels/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Places in news: Ram Setu</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-ram-setu/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ram Setu</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="ram setu" class="alignnone wp-image-641104 size-full" height="313" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 556px) 100vw, 556px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/setu.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/setu.jpg 556w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/setu-300x169.jpg 300w" width="556"/></p>
<p>A movie has once again generated buzz around the chain of shoals off the southeast coast of India that many believe is the Ram Setu or the bridge to Lanka mentioned in the Ramayana.</p>
<h4>The Ram Setu</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Ram Setu, also known as Adam’s Bridge, is a 48-km chain of limestone shoals between Rameswaram on India’s southeast coast and Mannar Island near Sri Lanka’s northwest coast.</li>
<li>The structure has significance in both Hindu and Muslim mythology – while Hindus believe this is the bridge (Setu) built by Lord Ram and his army to cross to Lanka and fight Ravan.</li>
<li>As per Islamic legend, Adam used this bridge to reach Adam’s Peak in Sri Lanka, where he stood on one foot for 1,000 years in repentance.</li>
</ul>
<p>Factual details of the bridge</p>
<ul>
<li>Scientists believe Ram Setu is a natural structure formed due to tectonic movements and sand getting trapped in corals.</li>
<li>However, over the years, evidence has been offered to claim that the bridge is man-made.</li>
<li>The bridge is not entirely natural, Hindu right wing outfits argue, which proves that it was indeed built by Lord Ram.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When was the structure came into highlights?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Ram Setu issue snowballed into a major controversy when the Sethusamudram Project, flagged off during the UPA I government.</li>
<li>The project aimed to reduce travel time between the eastern and western coasts of India, as ships would no longer have to circle Sri Lanka to travel between the Bay of Bengal and Arabian Sea.</li>
<li>The project was perceived as an attack on Hindu sentiments.</li>
<li>Various studies have been proposed on the Ram Setu, with the most recent being in 2021, when the government approved an underwater research project to ascertain its origins.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Ecological arguments against the project</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Sethusamudram project has been opposed on environmental grounds.</li>
<li>Some claims that it will harm marine life, and that dredging of the line of shoals will make India’s coast more vulnerable to tsunamis.</li>
<li>In March 2018, the Centre told the Supreme Court that the Ram Setu will not be affected in the execution of the Sethusamudram Shipping Canal project.</li>
</ul>
<h4>NASA images, and other proofs</h4>
<ul>
<li>Images of the Ram Setu clicked by NASA have been used over and over again to claim that this proves the existence of a man-made bridge.</li>
<li>NASA has repeatedly clarified that it does not agree with these claims.</li>
<li>Remote sensing images or photographs from orbit cannot provide direct information about the origin or age of a chain of islands.</li>
<li>It certainly cannot be determined whether humans were involved in producing any of the patterns seen.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-ram-setu/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Maharashtra Election Symbols Issue</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/maharashtra-election-symbols-issue/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Allocation of election symbols</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>In a blow to one faction, a Constitution Bench of the Supreme Court allowed the Election Commission (EC) to take a decision on the Maharashtra CM claim that his faction represents the “real” party.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Bench led by Justice D.Y. Chandrachud rejected the plea to stay the EC proceedings under the Election Symbols (Reservation and Allotment) Order of 1968.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A party has lost a large number of members in the rebellion that eventually caused the fall of the government in Maharashtra.</li>
<li>The rebel has claimed to be the only original leader of the party on the basis of the support of more than two-thirds of the party’s legislators in the Maharashtra Assembly.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Options for ECI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ECI in all likelihood can freeze the symbol so that neither of the two sides is able to use it until a final decision is made.</li>
<li>EC hearings are long and detailed, and may take at least six months.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>EC’s powers in Election Symbol Dispute</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The question of a split in a political party outside the legislature is dealt by Para 15 of the Symbols Order, 1968.</li>
<li>It states that the ECI may take into account all the available facts and circumstances and undertake a test of majority.</li>
<li>The decision of the ECI shall be binding on all such rival sections or groups emerged after the split.</li>
<li>This applies to disputes in recognised national and state parties.</li>
<li>For splits in registered but unrecognized parties, the EC usually advises the warring factions to resolve their differences internally or to approach the court.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How did the EC deal with such matters before the Symbols Order came into effect?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Before 1968, the EC issued notifications and executive orders under the Conduct of Election Rules, 1961.</li>
<li>The most high-profile split of a party before 1968 was that of the CPI in 1964.</li>
<li>A breakaway group approached the ECI in December 1964 urging it to recognise them as CPI(Marxist). They provided a list of MPs and MLAs of Andhra Pradesh, Kerala and West Bengal who supported them.</li>
<li>The ECI recognised the faction as CPI(M) after it found that the votes secured by the MPs and MLAs supporting the breakaway group added up to more than 4% in the 3 states.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the first case decided under Para 15 of the 1968 Order?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It was the first split in the Indian National Congress in 1969.</li>
<li>Indira Gandhi’s tensions with a rival group within the party came to a head with the death of President Dr Zakir Hussain on May 3, 1969.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Is there a way other than the test of majority to resolve a dispute over election symbols?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In almost all disputes decided by the EC so far, a clear majority of party delegates/office bearers, MPs and MLAs have supported one of the factions.</li>
<li>Whenever the EC could not test the strength of rival groups based on support within the party organisation (because of disputes regarding the list of office bearers), it fell back on testing the majority only among elected MPs and MLAs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What happens to the group that doesn’t get the parent party’s symbol?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The EC in 1997 did not recognise the new parties as either state or national parties.</li>
<li>It felt that merely having MPs and MLAs is not enough, as the elected representatives had fought and won polls on tickets of their parent (undivided) parties.</li>
<li>The EC introduced a new rule under which the splinter group of the party — other than the group that got the party symbol — had to register itself as a separate party.</li>
<li>It could lay claim to national or state party status only on the basis of its performance in the state or central elections after registration.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/maharashtra-election-symbols-issue/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why India has lashed out at the US over its F-16 package to Pakistan?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-india-has-lashed-out-at-the-us-over-its-f-16-package/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>F-16</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>US's double standards over Pakistan</p></div></div><p><img alt="f-16" class="alignnone wp-image-641100 size-full" height="447" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f-16.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f-16.jpg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f-16-300x224.jpg 300w" width="600"/></p>
<p>EAM S Jaishankar has lashed out at the US for its decision to provide Pakistan with a $450 million package for F-16 case fighter aircraft upgrade.</p>
<h4>F-16 and Pakistan</h4>
<ul>
<li>The F-16 is a single-engine multirole fighter aircraft originally developed by General Dynamics for the United States Air Force (USAF).</li>
<li>Designed as an air superiority day fighter, it evolved into a successful all-weather multirole aircraft.</li>
<li>The F-16 were inducted into Pakistan Air Force in 1983 during the Soviet-Afghan War.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Suspicion over US move</h4>
<ul>
<li>This is the first American military assistance package to Pakistan after the Trump Administration.</li>
<li>Mr Trump ended defence and security co-operation with Pakistan in 2018 after accusing it of giving only “lies and deceit” for the billions of dollars that the US had “foolishly” given it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What specific reasons has the Biden Administration given for its decision?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As per US version, the proposed sale does not include any new capabilities, weapons, or munitions.</li>
<li>The upgrade package aimed to retain interoperability with US and partner forces in ongoing counter-terrorism efforts and in preparation for future contingency operations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did US provide F-16 to the US?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has been concerned about the F-16s from the time the US first gave Pakistan F-16s as a reward for its assistance in the first Afghan war.</li>
<li>The US then had supplied weapons and money to Pakistan to unleash armies of jihadists against the Soviet Army.</li>
<li>When the US objective was achieved with the Soviet Union’s departure from Afghanistan, the US too resized its relations with Pakistan.</li>
<li>The Pressler Amendment, aimed against Pakistan’s nuclear ambitions, froze it out of military assistance.</li>
<li>A decade later, the Bush Administration not only approved the release of previously blocked F-16s, but also provided a refurbishment package, and sale of new F-16s.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s concerns</h4>
<ul>
<li>As pointed out by EAM, how the F-16s help in counter-terrorism remains unclear.</li>
<li>Jaishankar questioned the merits of the US-Pakistan partnership.</li>
<li>He said that the relations had “not served” either country (but created more troubles for India).</li>
<li>This move by the US will alter the basic military balance in the region.</li>
<li>The decision to provide military aid to Pakistan incensed India as the F-16 was used against Indian warplanes following the 2019 Balakot air strikes.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>Washington’s $450 million package has only resurrected old prejudices centred on the US not being a dependable ally for ever.</li>
<li>India needs to respond firmly and in no uncertain terms to the PAF’s F-16 upgrade programme to convey the message that India cannot be taken for granted.</li>
<li>India will have to effectively enhance the conventional combat capability of the IAF to continue to meet the challenge of a resurgent PAF.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-india-has-lashed-out-at-the-us-over-its-f-16-package/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India and UNSC</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-quest-for-permanent-membership-of-unsc/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UN Security council</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>International Relations</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="India and UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641078" height="275" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-5-300x165.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-5-300x165.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-5.jpg 303w" width="500"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is greater support for India to be a permanent member of the UN Security Council and also a broad global consensus over the need to reform the Council, said External Affairs Minister S Jaishankar. India has once again renewed its bid for permanent membership of UNSC.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">What is UNSC?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The United Nations Security Council (UNSC) is one of the six principal organs of the United Nations (UN) and is charged with ensuring international peace and security, recommending the admission of new UN members to the General Assembly, and approving any changes to the UN Charter.</li>
<li>Its powers include establishing peacekeeping operations, enacting international sanctions, and authorizing military action. The UNSC is the only UN body with the authority to issue binding resolutions on member states.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="India and UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641074" height="341" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-8.jpg" width="549"/>What is the composition of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/g4-countries-call-for-unsc-reforms/">UNSC</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Presently there five permanent members (P-5) with veto and 10 non-permanent members without veto elected for tenure of 2 years.</li>
<li>India has been the non-permanent member multiple times. Presently India is serving its tenure that will end in December 2022.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="India and UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641079" height="373" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-13.jpg" width="498"/>Who are P-5 members?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The victors of World War 2 – USA, RUSSIA, CHINA, UK, FRANCE.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the hurdles that India facing?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Elite club:</strong> Most exclusive club in international relations. All other clubs have been breached. Until a quarter century ago, the nuclear weapon club had five members, the same five as the P-5.India, Pakistan, North Korea and Israel have since joined the club. But UNSC is unbreachable till date.</li>
<li><strong>All are reluctant: </strong>The inescapable fact is that none of the P-5 wants the UNSC’s ranks to be increased. One or the other of them might make some noise about supporting one or more of the aspirants. Each is confident that someone among them will torpedo the enlargement of the club. Declarations of support for India’s candidature need to be taken with a fistful of salt.</li>
<li><strong>Veto issue: </strong>Former UN Secretary-General Kofi Annan bluntly told India not to expect to get the veto power. Though India has said it will not accept a seat without veto power.</li>
<li><strong>China-Pakistan axis: </strong>China, which has historically blocked India’s aspirations to become a permanent member of the UNSC. Beijing has an “all-weather ally” in Islamabad, another neighbour who also strongly opposes India’s candidature to the UNSC.</li>
<li><strong>Odd man out: </strong>Four out of the five permanent members of the United Nations Security Council have bilaterally expressed official affirmations of support for India’s candidature to a permanent seat in an expanded UN Security Council.</li>
<li><strong>Coffee club opposition: </strong>Members like Italy, South Korea, Canada, Spain, Mexico, Turkey, Argentina, Pakistan, and others, who have together formed the Uniting for Consensus (UfC) movement. Also known as the Coffee Club, the movement argues that bids for permanent seats by India, Japan, Germany, and Brazil (G4 countries) must not be considered without first reaching an international consensus regarding the form and size of the new Security council.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="India and UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641080" height="369" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-10.jpg" width="492"/>What are the Efforts taken by India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Text based negotiation: </strong>External affairs minister is canvassing for the country’s candidature, meeting his counterparts from several countries. He has repeated the call, made often in the past, for a text-based negotiation on what has been euphemistically referred to as the reform of the United Nations Security Council (UNSC), i.e., negotiation on a written document outlining the proposed reform instead of just holding forth verbally.</li>
<li><strong>Woking together with G-4: </strong>INDIA, JAPAN, GEMANY, BRAZIL works together to get permanent UNSC seat however these efforts are opposed by coffee club.</li>
<li><strong>Multilateral engagements: </strong>By expanding its footprint in multilateral organisations, India is gearing up to become a global rule-maker.</li>
<li>Distinguished group of experts suggested a few years ago that a new category of semi-permanent members should be created. Countries would be elected for a period of eight to 10 years and would be eligible for re-election. India ought to give serious consideration to this idea.</li>
<li><strong>With or without veto- </strong>According to former foreign secretary Chinmaya gharekhan, if by some miracle we are offered or manage to obtain permanent membership without veto, we must grab it. Even a permanent membership without veto will be tremendously helpful in protecting our interests.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Looking at the present geopolitical divide India’s dream of seat at the highest table is unlikely to get fulfilled in near future. India must analyse the utility of UNSC membership for securing its national interest. India should not give up anything in bargain against UNSC seat which harms its international interest.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Question</strong></h4>
<p><strong>India’s quest for UNSC is like “Sisyphus carrying the boulder  just to see how it falls”. In this context Analyse the utility of Permanent seat at UNSC.</strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-quest-for-permanent-membership-of-unsc/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Market Based Economic Dispatch</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/market-based-economic-dispatch-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economics,Energy,Infrastructure</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641126" height="316" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-3-1.jpg" width="565"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The game changing scheme is being proposed by the central government in power sector governance. The scheme under consideration is the market-based economic dispatch (MBED). When it comes to any drastic change in the power sector, a clash between the Centre and the states is inevitable.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Market Based Economic Dispatch (MBED)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Market Based Economic Dispatch (MBED) is new approach towards power distribution to help distribution companies save costs and transition to a new form of power market.</li>
<li>It is a shift to a centralised framework, marks a radical departure from the current decentralised, voluntary pool-based electricity market.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641122" height="291" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-1-2.jpg" width="508"/>What is the framework under MBED?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The cheapest power from across the country will be dispatched to meet the system wide demand. The architecture would also lead to a “Market clearing price”.</li>
<li>Sellers and buyers will place their bids for the day market, and an outcome of this will be the discovery of the market clearing price.</li>
<li>This process is expected to generate significant savings for consumers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Present system of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/assessment-of-discoms/">power Distribution?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Under the present regime, each distribution company (Discom) is bound by the power purchase agreements (PPAs) that it holds.</li>
<li>It can schedule power only from its own PPAs, starting from the cheapest PPA and then moving up; it cannot schedule power from the PPA of some other distribution company.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> <img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641124" height="365" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-2.jpg" width="488"/></strong><strong>What are the drawbacks of present system?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Financial Burdon:</strong></li>
<li>The Indian government responded to COVID-19’s economic shock with a stimulus package of Rs.20-lakh crore, out of which Rs.90,000 crore was earmarked for discoms (later upgraded to Rs.1,25,000 crore). While it was called a stimulus, it is really a loan, meant to be used by discoms to pay off generators.</li>
<li>Discoms owe one lakh crore rupees to generators, and without such an infusion the chain will collapse.</li>
<li><strong>States are defaulters:</strong></li>
<li>State governments are the biggest defaulters, responsible for an estimated a third of trade receivables, besides not paying subsidies in full or on time.</li>
<li>On an annual cash flow basis, the shortfall in subsidy payments appears very low, only about 1% but cumulative unpaid subsidies, with modest carrying costs, make discoms poorer by over Rs.70,000 crore just over the last 10 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641125" height="323" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-12-1.jpg" width="570"/>What will be the Advantages of MBED?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Centralized approach: </strong>The centralised dispatch will be done with the assistance of electricity exchanges. Each discom and each generator will place a bid in the day-ahead market of the electricity exchanges, which will indicate how much power is being demanded/ supplied at what price.</li>
<li><strong>Pan India market: </strong>These bids will enable the load dispatcher to construct a pan India demand and supply curve, the intersection of which will determine the market clearing price (MCP). All generators whose variable cost of generation is below the MCP will be asked to dispatch and all of them will receive the same MCP irrespective of what they had bid. Generators whose variable cost is higher than the MCP will sit idle.</li>
<li><strong>No loss to discom: </strong>The MBED is so devised that its operation will not affect the current finances of either the discoms or the generators for the following reasons.</li>
<li>First, the fixed cost of the generators will still be paid by the discoms outside the market as determined by the regulator.</li>
<li>Second, if the MCP comes out to be Rs 3 per unit, and if in the case of any PPA, the variable cost is Rs 2.75 per unit, then the generator will compensate the discom to the extent of Rs 0.25 per unit. Similarly, if the MCP so determined is Rs 2.50 per unit, then the discom will compensate the generator to the extent of Rs 0.25 per unit.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing efficiency: </strong>The logic is that by adopting MBED, only the relatively efficient plants will generate, without affecting the revenues of either the discoms or generators. Hence, the total cost of generation under the MBED system would be less.</li>
<li><strong>Less pollution: </strong>There would be less coal consumption and less carbon dioxide injected into the atmosphere.</li>
<li><strong>Easy integration with renewable: </strong>It would also mean less movement of coal leading to decongestion of railway tracks. Further, there would be enhanced renewable integration since the balancing area would shift from state to national level.</li>
<li><strong>Single market clearing price (MCP): </strong>Incidentally, since there are three electricity exchanges in operation today, there would be three different MCPs determined. What we need is a single MCP for which there will be an institution called the “market coupler”. It will be the job of the coupler to determine a national MCP based on what has arrived at the three different exchanges.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why states are opposing?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>High generation cost: </strong>The reason is the state-owned generators are relatively inefficient and may have to sit idle as their variable cost of generation is likely to be more than the MCP.</li>
<li><strong>Political backlash: </strong>Today, the states are operating their own generators to the hilt, even though they are inefficient, and drawing only the balance from the more efficient interstate generating stations. Keeping state generators idle has its own political implications and no state would be enamoured of this idea.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Power distribution companies (discom) are sinkhole of government finances. Every year budgetary support is needed to this loss-making companies , With due consultation, all states and union territories need to adopt and implement the MBED and save the resources for other development activities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Question</strong></h4>
<p><strong> </strong><strong>India has became the power surplus nation, however power distribution and financial unsustainability is still a nightmare for union and states. Elaborate.</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/market-based-economic-dispatch-2/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>