<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 18:24:54 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Food security and Climate change:The Interlink</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/food-security/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PDS,Subsidies</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Climate change and Food security</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Food security" class="alignnone wp-image-643267 size-full" height="1280" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 755px) 100vw, 755px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12.jpeg 755w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-177x300.jpeg 177w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-604x1024.jpeg 604w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-531x900.jpeg 531w" width="755"/>C</strong><strong>ontext</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In pursuance of the earlier announcement of additional food security under PMGKAY, the Union Cabinet has approved the extension for the Pradhan Mantri Garib Kalyan Anna Yojana (PMGKAY-Phase VII) for a further period of 3 months from October to December 2022.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Climate Change?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>United Nations defines Climate change as long-term shifts in temperatures and weather patterns. These shifts may be natural, such as through variations in the solar cycle. But since the 1800s, human activities have been the main driver of climate change, primarily due to burning fossil fuels like coal, oil and gas</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/how-indias-food-systems-must-respond-to-the-climate-crisis/">food security?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO)defines food security as , when all people, at all times, have physical and economic access to sufficient, safe and nutritious food to meet their dietary needs and food preferences for an active and healthy life.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Food security" class="alignnone wp-image-643272 size-full" height="663" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 663px) 100vw, 663px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.08.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.08.jpeg 663w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.08-300x300.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.08-150x150.jpeg 150w" width="663"/></strong><strong>Pradhan Mantri Garib Kalyan Anna Yojana?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Pradhan Mantri Garib Kalyan Anna Yojana (PM-GKAY) is a scheme as part of Atmanirbhar Bharat to supply free food grains to migrants and poor.</li>
<li>Phase-I and Phase-II of this scheme was operational from April to June, 2020 and July to November, 2020 respectively.</li>
<li>The PMGKAY scheme for Phase VI from April-September, 2022 would entail an estimated additional food subsidy of Rs. Rs. 80,000 Crore.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How food security and climate change are interlinked?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Extreme events: </strong>India is going to have extreme events such as heatwaves, droughts, floods, etc of increasing intensity and frequency.</li>
<li><strong>Rising GHGs emission</strong>: We may keep blaming developed economies and ask for climate justice, yet we will have to act fast and boldly to correct our own policies that increase GHG emissions and aggravate the situation.</li>
<li><strong>Subsidies: </strong>Power provided at next-to-nothing prices, free water and highly subsidised fertilisers especially urea are some of the policies that are damaging the natural environment.</li>
<li><strong>Food ecosystem: </strong>Food security is one of the leading concerns associated with climate change. Climate change affects food security in complex ways. It impacts crops, livestock, forestry, fisheries and aquaculture, and can cause grave social and economic consequences in the form of reduced incomes, eroded livelihoods, trade disruption and adverse health impacts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Food security" class="alignnone wp-image-643276 size-large" height="699" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.09-1-1024x699.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.09-1-1024x699.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.09-1-300x205.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.09-1-768x524.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.09-1.jpeg 1200w" width="1024"/>Why food security is a matter of concern?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Fiscal deficit</strong>: The fiscal deficit of the Centre may go higher than provisioned in the Budget for FY23. The finance ministry not supporting the extension of this free food beyond September was, economically, a rational recommendation. More so as Covid-19 is behind us and the economy is back to its normal level of activity.</li>
<li><strong>Depleting stocks: </strong>The PMGKAY was announced in April 2020 in the wake of the pandemic’s first wave. At that time, it was perhaps necessary to support all those who lost their jobs. But doubling free rations depleted the bulging stocks of grains. Now with wheat procurement having plummeted, there is a concern about whether stocks are enough to curb inflationary expectations in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Less harvest: </strong>To replenish wheat stocks in FCI godowns, the government will have to raise the minimum support price (MSP) of wheat quite substantially. For rice, the current stocks are ample, but given the monsoon vagaries, the forthcoming rice harvest is estimated to be about 7 million tonnes less.</li>
<li><strong>Rising MSP</strong>: PMGKAY will be difficult to extend beyond December without putting an undue burden on MSPs and the fiscal deficit.</li>
<li><strong>Other reasons</strong>:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Inflation: </strong>Even though the RBI has raised the repo rate by 50 basis points, the probability of inflation, as measured by the consumer price index (CPI), remaining higher than the central bank’s tolerance band is increasing by the day.</li>
<li><strong>Depreciating Rupee: </strong>The RBI has already spent more than $80 billion to support the rupee, and there are limits to which it can go. And, if RBI tries to hold the rupee artificially high, it will adversely hit Indian exports, widening the current account deficit and putting further pressure on the rupee. The best that RBI can and should do is to avoid a sudden and abrupt fall in the rupee, but also let it find its natural level given what is happening globally, especially in the currency markets.</li>
<li><strong>Long haul: </strong>The risks of higher inflation from the falling rupee remain and are likely to continue for at least one year, if not more.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong><img alt="Food security" class="alignnone wp-image-643277 size-large" height="1024" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.04-1024x1024.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.04-1024x1024.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.04-300x300.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.04-150x150.jpeg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.04-768x768.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.04-900x900.jpeg 900w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-11.05.04.jpeg 1080w" width="1024"/>What can we do?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increasing foreign exchange reserves: </strong>Government have to have innovative policies to promote exports and attract more foreign direct investment (FDI).</li>
<li><strong>Fixing Issue price: </strong>fix the issue prices of PDS supplies at half the MSP and limit the PDS coverage to 30 per cent of the bottom population.</li>
<li><strong>On rupee fall: </strong>The best that RBI can and should do is to avoid a sudden and abrupt fall in the rupee, but also let it find its natural level given what is happening globally, especially in the currency markets.</li>
<li><strong>Use of technology: </strong>If we have to tame food inflation, we will have to invest more in climate-smart agriculture, in precision farming, with high productivity and less damage to natural resources.</li>
<li><strong>Right ecosystem: </strong>Science and technologies can, of course, help us, but they cannot be scaled in a perverse policy ecosystem.</li>
<li><strong>Adoption of sustainable agricultural practices: </strong>India needs to step up public investment in development and dissemination of crop varieties which are more tolerant of temperature and precipitation fluctuations and are more water and nutrient efficient.</li>
<li><strong>Management of water resources: </strong>A four pronged strategy is recommended for the water sector; Increase irrigation efficiency, Promote micro irrigation in water-deficient areas, Better water resource infrastructure planning, Restoration of water bodies in rural areas, Stronger emphasis on public health.</li>
<li><strong>Long-term relief measures in the event of natural disasters: </strong>A recent report by NITI Aayog suggests that the government should transfer a minimum specified sum of cash to affected farmers and landless workers as an instant relief. For richer farmers who may want insurance above this relief, the report recommends a separate commercially viable crop insurance programme.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>So far India has done well to tame the food inflation as compared to other developed and developing economies. Present policy of RBI burning the FOREX and government increasing the deficit is unsustainable in long run. Food security needs to be insured by climate resilient policies for long term sustenance.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Climate change is a growing concern that threatens sustainable development in addition to food security and inflation. Discuss</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/food-security/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Natural Gas: The energy future of India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/natural-gas/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Natural gas</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Clean energy</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Natural Gas" class="alignnone wp-image-643331 size-full" height="640" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-13.01.05.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-13.01.05.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-13.01.05-300x150.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-13.01.05-1024x512.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-13.01.05-768x384.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-13.01.05-1200x600.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The announcement at the end of August by the ministry of petroleum that they had constituted a committee, headed by energy expert Kirit Parikh, to review the domestic natural gas pricing regime.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Prime Minister Narendra Modi wants to raise the share of gas in India’s energy mix to 15% by 2030 from 6.2%, helping it progress towards meeting a 2070 net zero carbon-emission goal.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Natural Gas?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Natural gas is a fossil fuel source consisting primarily of methane. It is the cleanest fossil fuels among the available fossil fuels.</li>
<li>It is used as a feedstock in the manufacture of fertilizers, plastics and other commercially important organic chemicals as well as used as a fuel for electricity generation, heating purpose in industrial and commercial units.</li>
<li>Natural gas is also used for cooking in domestic households and a transportation fuel for vehicles.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> <img alt="Natural Gas" class="alignnone wp-image-643320 size-large" height="768" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.05.17-1-1024x768.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.05.17-1-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.05.17-1-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.05.17-1-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.05.17-1-1200x900.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.05.17-1.jpeg 1280w" width="1024"/>Why Natural gas is Important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Energy Efficient:</strong>Natural gas produces more energy than any of the fossil fuels in terms of calorific value.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cleaner fuel:</strong> Natural gas is a superior fuel as compared with coal and other liquid fuels being an environment-friendly, safer and cheaper fuel.</li>
<li><strong>Economy of use:</strong> Natural Gas (as CNG) is much cheaper compared with petrol or Diesel.</li>
<li><strong>Emission commitments:</strong> India made a commitment to COP-21 Paris Convention in December 2015 that by 2030, it would reduce carbon emission by 33%-35% of 2005 levels.</li>
<li><strong>Diverse applications:</strong> Natural gas can be used as domestic kitchen fuel, fuel for the transport sector as well as a fuel for fertilizer industries and commercial units.</li>
<li><strong>Supply chain convenience: </strong>Natural Gas is supplied through pipelines just like we get water from the tap. There is no need to store cylinders in the kitchen and thus save space.</li>
<li><strong>Pacing up the progress line:</strong> On the global front,switching to natural gas is bringing commendable results.The latest report released by IEA shows that the electricity produced by natural gas worldwide was more than that of coal for the first time ever.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Natural gas scenario in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Domestic Gas Sources: </strong>The domestic gas in the country is being supplied from the oil &amp; gas fields located at western and southeastern areas viz. Hazira basin, Mumbai offshore &amp; KG basin as well as North East Region (Assam &amp; Tripura).</li>
<li><strong>Import of Liquefied Natural Gas (LNG): </strong>In order to meet the gas demand, LNG is imported through the Open General License (OGL) in the country.  At present, India is having six operational LNG regasification terminals at Dahej, Kochi, Mundra, Ennore etc.</li>
<li><strong>Gas Pipelines :</strong></li>
<li>Gas Pipeline infrastructure is an economical and safe mode of transporting natural gas by connecting gas sources to gas-consuming markets.</li>
<li>An interconnected National Gas Grid has been envisaged to ensure the adequate availability and equitable distribution of natural gas in all parts of the country.</li>
<li><strong>Pricing:</strong></li>
<li>To incentivise gas producers and boost local output, since 2014 India has linked local gas prices to a formula tied to global benchmarks, including Henry Hub, Alberta gas, NBP and Russian gas.</li>
<li>In 2016, the country began fixing the ceiling prices of gas produced from ultra-deep water and challenging fields and allowed marketing freedom to the operators of these fields.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Natural as" class="alignnone wp-image-643421 size-full" height="783" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 803px) 100vw, 803px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/DLiQJ9bUEAA08QH-1-e1664784639814.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/DLiQJ9bUEAA08QH-1-e1664784639814.jpg 803w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/DLiQJ9bUEAA08QH-1-e1664784639814-300x293.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/DLiQJ9bUEAA08QH-1-e1664784639814-768x749.jpg 768w" width="803"/>Statistics of<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/natural-gas-grid-ngg/"> Natural gas in India</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Current consumption: </strong>India’s natural gas consumption is expected to grow by eight per cent year-on-year to around 34,949 million standard cubic meters (MSCM) in the current calendar year aided by expanding infrastructure, strong GDP growth projections, and supportive government policy.</li>
<li><strong>2021 Consumption</strong>: In the 2021 calendar year (CY), the country’s natural gas demand stood at 32,360 MSCM. The share of domestic gas and imported RLNG was about 48% &amp; 52% respectively. The City Gas Distribution (CGD) accounts for the largest consumption of natural gas followed by fertilizers, power and other industrial sectors</li>
<li><strong>High prices: </strong>The state-set local gas prices and ceiling rates are at a record high and are expected to rise further due to a surge in global gas prices triggered by the Ukraine-Russia conflict.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Kirit Parikh Committee</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Objective:</strong> Ensuring fair prices to end consumers, and to suggest a market oriented, transparent and reliable pricing regime for India’s long term vision for ensuring a gas based economy.</li>
<li><strong>Members:</strong> The committee,headed by energy expert Kirit Parikh, will include members from the fertiliser ministry, as well as gas producers and buyers.Four of the six members are from the public sector.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Natural Gas" class="alignnone wp-image-643401 size-large" height="767" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-13.10.59-1024x767.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-13.10.59-1024x767.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-13.10.59-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-13.10.59-768x575.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-13.10.59-1200x899.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-13.10.59.jpeg 1280w" width="1024"/>What are the problems facing India’s natural gas reserves?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Harsh topography: </strong>IHS CERA has estimated India has undiscovered gas resources of approximately 64 TCF The bulk of this is, however, in harsh topography and complex geology. These reserves are difficult to locate.</li>
<li><strong>Distant from the market:</strong>Even if located,they are difficult to bring to market on economically viable terms. This is because the cost of creating the development and production infrastructure is massive.</li>
<li><strong>Heavy Budget: </strong>The reality is India is a high-risk exploration play. There are inherent geologic, technical, and economic obstacles to achieving commercial success.</li>
<li><strong>Administered Pricing</strong>: Constraint of administered pricing petroleum companies have reduced their exploration budgets under pressure to shift away from fossil fuels.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pricing freedom:</strong> It should clear up the existing complexity and, other than for producers of gas from nomination blocks, permit all producers of gas to determine prices through arms length,direct and transparent negotiations with different consumer segments.</li>
<li><strong>Subsidies:</strong> There are no liquefaction facilities for the export of LNG in India. Subsidies may have to be provided but if so,they should be given directly by the government,through the exchequer. The gas producers must not be asked to bear that brunt.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the wake of the Ukraine crisis, the international energy market has undergone a profound transformation.India has made impressive progress towards clean energy. It has,however, a long way to go before it can fully wean itself off fossil fuels.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>It is evident that clean energy transitions are underway and it’s also a signal that we have the opportunity to meaningfully move the needle on emissions through more ambitious policies and investments in natural gas regime. Comment</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/natural-gas/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Satellite Broadband Services in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/satellite-broadband-in-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Satellite broadband</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="satellite broadband" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-643393" height="464" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 464px) 100vw, 464px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/broadband.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/broadband.jpg 464w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/broadband-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/broadband-150x150.jpg 150w" width="464"/></p>
<p>The race for providing satellite broadband connectivity in India is heating up as companies like Jio, Oneweb, Hughes and Tata-backed Nelco are preparing to provide these services.</p>
<h4><strong>Recent developments on satellite broadband<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Earlier last month, Hughes Communications India (HCI), a satellite internet service provider launched India’s first high throughput satellite (HTS) broadband service powered by ISRO satellites.</li>
<li>It used Ku-band capacity from ISRO GSAT-11 and GSAT-29 satellites with Hughes JUPITER Platform ground technology to deliver high-speed broadband.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Satellite Broadband Service?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Broadband essentially means a wide bandwidth, high-capacity data transmission technique, using a broad range of frequencies.</li>
<li>In the case of a satellite broadband service, broadband services are delivered directly via satellites instead of optical fibre or mobile networks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How is it different from existing broadband services?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Transmission of data over space</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The main difference is that aggregation of all the data generated and transmitted by users accessing the internet happens in the sky or space that is in the satellite.</li>
<li>In contrast to this, if we take a look at cellular networks, aggregation happens on the ground, in the base stations through optical fibre, cable, etc.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Access to the services</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Another key difference is that to access satellite services, we will need a dish antenna just like we do in the case of TV services, so a normal mobile handset cannot directly access satellite broadband.</li>
<li>For a user to access satellite broadband a clear line of sight to the satellite is needed.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Advantages offered </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Speed:</strong> The main advantage of satellite services is that you can provide high-speed internet services in remote areas, where terrestrial networks cannot be set up.</li>
<li><strong>Eliminating terrain shortcomings:</strong> For instance in the middle of the ocean, in rugged unreachable terrain such as the Himalayas — even as remote as on top of Mt. Everest, satellite broadband will work.</li>
<li><strong>Curbing the divide:</strong> In a country with a wide range of geographies such as India, 20-25 per cent of the Indian population resides in areas where it is extremely hard for terrestrial operators to install internet facilities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Present scope in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Currently, VSAT operators offer satellite broadband services at a very limited capacity in India in a few remote locations.</li>
<li>The utilisation of satellite services for broadband services is restricted to minimal applications — such as disaster management, defence, scientific locations, etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How India (undoubtedly, the ISRO) has geared up for adapting to this?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>ISRO’s high throughput GEO (Geostationary Equatorial Orbit) satellites – GSAT-11 and GSAT-29 a few years ago, can beam high-speed internet up to 300 gigabytes per second.</li>
<li>Apart, many global players look to provide satellite broadband services in India by deploying low earth orbit (LEO) satellites.</li>
<li>They are launching a constellation of satellites very close to the earth’s surface in order to reduce the latency of satellite broadband.</li>
<li>Presently, Elon Musk’s Starlink, Sunil Bharti Mittal-backed OneWeb and the Canadian satellite major Telesat are eyeing the Indian market.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>When will these services be available in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>If things go as planned and the players get the necessary regulatory clearance, these services could become operational in India as soon as next year.</li>
<li>OneWeb wants to provide backhaul services to telcos by mid-next year, while Starlink wants to provide direct broadband services by December 2022, aiming at 2 lakh terminals.</li>
<li>Telesat, on the other hand, is eyeing an India launch by 2024.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How much will it cost?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The provision of direct broadband services through satellites will be pricey.</li>
<li>According to a user guide for India, provided by Starlink, the first-year cost of a Starlink terminal will be ₹1,58,000 after which it will cost around ₹1,15,000 every year.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Has it been rolled out in other parts of the world?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Starlink is operational in 14 countries, with 1 lakh terminals shipped to North America and Europe.</li>
<li>Starlink and OneWeb are still launching satellites that will be a part of their LEO constellation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the major hurdles?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Latency:</strong> Additionally, satellite Internet latency can be a significant problem. This can be a matter of only a second or two, but a delay on that scale can seriously affect real-time applications like video chats.</li>
<li><strong>Spatial hurdles:</strong> Users might not be able to connect to a satellite at all if they are located under heavy foliage or surrounded by other obstructions.</li>
<li><strong>Limited bandwidth:</strong> Satellite data transfer provides very slow Internet speeds and limited satellite bandwidth because of the distances the signals have to travel and all the potential obstacles in between.</li>
<li><strong>Connection times:</strong> This can also be impacted by your surroundings, the length of your message, and the status and availability of the satellite network.</li>
<li><strong>High input cost:</strong> This along with the complex equipment like satellite dishes being used to avail these services makes the service expensive.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Perspective analysis: Why is India itself lagging in this race?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Globally, companies are striving to build and deploy “mega-constellations” of hundreds or thousands of satellites for this.</li>
<li>Despite India’s impressive achievements in the space sector, growth has been at snail’s pace.</li>
<li>Satellite broadband services in India remains primarily for the B2B sector with a market size of roughly $100 million.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reason’s for India’s slow pace</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Upgrade issues:</strong> The Indian networks are still using conventional satellites despite the proliferation of high throughput satellites world-over.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of domestic industries:</strong> There is a lack of domestic participation for building space infrastructure despite ‘Make in India’ mission.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An urgent re-look at deregulation and privatization is required.</li>
<li>Advanced space-faring nations have privatized most of these blocks in the value chain.</li>
<li>There is a need for building systems to help nurture the industry and create an extensive ecosystem to generate a ‘Space 2.0’ in India.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/satellite-broadband-in-india/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Progress of the Jal Jeevan Mission</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/progress-jal-jeevan-mission/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Jal Jeevan Mission</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p>Around 62% of rural households in India had fully functional tap water connections under the Jal Jeevan Mission.</p>
<h4><strong>Jal Jeevan Mission</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Jal Jeevan Mission, a central government initiative under the Ministry of Jal Shakti, aims to ensure access of piped water for every household in India.</li>
<li>The mission’s goal is to provide to all households in rural India safe and adequate water through individual household tap connections by 2024.</li>
<li>The Har Ghar Nal Se Jal programme was announced by FM in Budget 2019-20 speech.</li>
<li>This programme forms a crucial part of the Jal Jeevan Mission.</li>
<li>It is a central sector scheme with the Centre funding 50% of the cost with States and UTs, except for UT without a legislature, and 90% for NE and Himalayan states.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Note:</strong> A fully functional tap water connection is defined as a household getting at least 55 litres of per capita per day of potable water all through the year.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Components of the mission</strong></h4>
<p>The following key components are supported under JJM-</p>
<ul>
<li>Development of in-village piped water supply infrastructure to provide tap water connection to every rural household</li>
<li>Bulk water transfer, treatment plants and distribution network to cater to every rural household</li>
<li>Technological interventions for removal of contaminants where water quality is an issue</li>
<li>Retrofitting of completed and ongoing schemes</li>
<li>Greywater management</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Progress of the scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tamil Nadu, Himachal Pradesh, Goa, and Puducherry reported more than 80% of households with fully functional connections.</li>
<li>However, less than half the households in Rajasthan, Kerala, Manipur, Tripura, Maharashtra, Madhya Pradesh, Mizoram and Sikkim had such connection.</li>
<li>Close to three-fourths of households received water all seven days a week and 8% just once a week.</li>
<li>On average, households got water for three hours every day, and 80% reported that their daily requirements of water were being met by the tap connections.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/progress-jal-jeevan-mission/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Light Combat Helicopter (LCH) Prachand inducted into IAF</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/light-combat-helicopter-lch/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>LCH Prachanda</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="lch" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-643735" height="519" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 956px) 100vw, 956px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/lch.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/lch.jpg 956w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/lch-300x163.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/lch-768x417.jpg 768w" width="956"/></p>
<p>The indigenous Light Combat Helicopter LCH-Prachand was formally inducted into the Indian Air Force (IAF).</p>
<h4>LCH- Prachand</h4>
<ul>
<li>The LCH has been designed as a twin-engine, dedicated combat helicopter of 5.8-ton class, thus categorized as light.</li>
<li>It features a narrow fuselage and tandem — one behind the other — configuration for pilot and co-pilot. The co-pilot is also the Weapon Systems Operator (WSO).</li>
<li>While LCH inherits many features of the ALH-Dhruv, it mainly differs in tandem cockpit configuration, making it sleeker.</li>
<li>It also has many more state-of-art systems that make it a dedicated attack helicopter.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Features, the significance of LCH</h4>
<ul>
<li>LCH has the maximum take-off weight of 5.8 tonnes, a maximum speed of 268 kilometers per hour, range of 550 kilometers.</li>
<li>It has endurance of over three hours and service ceiling the maximum density altitude to which it can fly — of 6.5 kilometres.</li>
<li>LCH is powered by two French-origin Shakti engines manufactured by the HAL.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Combat capabilities</h4>
<ul>
<li>The helicopter uses radar-absorbing material to lower radar signature and has a significantly crash-proof structure and landing gear.</li>
<li>A pressurised cabin offers protection from nuclear, biological and chemical (NBC) contingencies.</li>
<li>With these features, the LCH has the capabilities of combat roles such as destruction of enemy air defence, counter-insurgency warfare, combat search and rescue, anti-tank, and counter surface force operations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why need indigenous LCH?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It was during the 1999 Kargil war that the need was first felt for a homegrown lightweight assault helicopter that could hold precision strikes in all Indian battlefield scenarios.</li>
<li>This meant a craft that could operate in very hot deserts and also in very cold high altitudes, in counter-insurgency scenarios to full-scale battle conditions.</li>
<li>India has been operating sub 3 ton category French-origin legacy helicopters, Chetak and Cheetah, made in India by the HAL.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/light-combat-helicopter-lch/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Medicine Nobel for Work on Human Evolution</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/medicine-nobel-for-work-on-human-evolution/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nobel Prize, Neanderthal, Hominins, Denisovians</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-643737" height="829" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 483px) 100vw, 483px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-prize-for-medicine.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-prize-for-medicine.jpg 483w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-prize-for-medicine-175x300.jpg 175w" width="483"/></p>
<p>Swedish scientist Svante Paabo won the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/nobel-prizes/">Nobel Prize</a> in medicine for his discoveries on human evolution that provided key insights into our immune system and what makes us unique compared with our extinct ancestors.</p>
<h4><strong>Svante Paabo: His work, explained</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Svante Paabo’s seminal discoveries provide the basis for exploring what makes us uniquely human.</li>
<li>Hominins refer to the now-extinct species of apes that are believed to be related to modern humans, as well as modern humans themselves.</li>
<li>Paabo found that <strong><u>gene transfer had occurred</u></strong> <strong><u>from these now extinct Hominins to Homo sapiens</u></strong> following the migration out of Africa <strong><u>around 70,000 years ago</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This ancient flow of genes to present-day humans has physiological relevance today, for example affecting how our immune system reacts to infections.</li>
<li>Paabo established an entirely new scientific discipline, called <strong><u>paleogenomics</u></strong> that focuses on studying the DNA and genetic information of extinct hominins through reconstruction.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the relation between evolution and biology?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Paabo’s discoveries have established a unique resource, which is utilized extensively by the scientific community to better understand human evolution and migration.</li>
<li>We now understand that archaic gene sequences from our extinct relatives influence the physiology of present-day humans.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How did Paabo establish the linkage?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Paabo extracted DNA from bone specimens from extinct hominins, from Neanderthal remains in the Denisova caves of Germany.</li>
<li>The bone contained exceptionally well-preserved DNA, which his team sequenced.</li>
<li>It was found that this DNA sequence was unique when compared to all known sequences from Neanderthals and present-day humans.</li>
<li>Comparisons with sequences from contemporary humans from different parts of the world showed that gene flow, or mixing of genetic information among a species, had also occurred between Denisova and Homo sapiens – the species of modern-day humans.</li>
<li>This relationship was first seen in populations in Melanesia (near Australia) and other parts of South East Asia, where individuals carry up to 6% Denisova DNA.</li>
<li>The Denisovan version of the gene EPAS1 confers an advantage for survival at high altitudes and is common among present-day Tibetans.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the challenges in carrying out such research?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There are extreme technical challenges because with time DNA becomes chemically modified and degrades into short fragments.</li>
<li>The main issue is that only trace amounts of DNA are left after thousands of years, and exposure to the natural environment leads to contamination with DNA.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4><strong>Back2Basics: Neanderthal Man </strong></h4>
<p><img alt="neanderthal" class="alignnone wp-image-643736" height="821" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 408px) 100vw, 408px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/neanderthal.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/neanderthal.jpg 476w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/neanderthal-149x300.jpg 149w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/neanderthal-447x900.jpg 447w" width="408"/></p>
<ul>
<li>Neanderthals were humans like us, but they were a distinct species called Homo Neanderthalensis.</li>
<li>Together with an Asian people known as Denisovans, Neanderthals are our closest ancient human relatives. Scientific evidence suggests our two species shared a common ancestor.</li>
<li>Current evidence from both fossils and DNA suggests that Neanderthal and modern human lineages separated at least 500,000 years ago. Some genetic calibrations place their divergence at about 650,000 years ago.</li>
<li>The best-known Neanderthals lived between about 130,000 and 40,000 years ago, after which all physical evidence of them vanishes.</li>
<li>They evolved in Europe and Asia while modern humans – our species, <em>Homo sapiens</em> – were evolving in Africa.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/medicine-nobel-for-work-on-human-evolution/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Purchasing Managers Index (PMI)?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pmi-purchasing-managers-index/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Manufacturing Purchasing Managers’ Index (PMI)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India's manufacturing sector slowdown</p></div></div><p>India’s manufacturing sector experienced its slowest expansion in September since June, the S&amp;P Global India Manufacturing Purchasing Managers’ Index (PMI) indicated, with the index easing to 55.1 from August’s 56.2.</p>
<h4><strong>PMI improves<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A PMI reading above 50 indicates an increase in firms’ activity levels, and September marked the 15th straight month of growth in manufacturing activity.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Purchasing Managers’ Index (PMI)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>PMI is an indicator of business activity — <strong><u>both in the manufacturing </u></strong><u>and<strong> services sectors</strong></u>.</li>
<li>It is a survey-based measure that asks the respondents about changes in their perception of some key business variables from the month before.</li>
<li>It is calculated separately for the manufacturing and services sectors and then a composite index is constructed.</li>
<li>The PMI is compiled by IHS Markit based on responses to questionnaires sent to purchasing managers in a panel of around 400 manufacturers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How is the PMI derived?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PMI is derived from a series of qualitative questions.</li>
<li>Executives from a reasonably big sample, running into hundreds of firms, are asked whether key indicators such as output, new orders, business expectations and employment were stronger than the month before and are asked to rate them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does one read the PMI?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A figure above 50 denotes expansion in business activity. Anything below 50 denotes contraction.</li>
<li>Higher the difference from this mid-point greater the expansion or contraction. The rate of expansion can also be judged by comparing the PMI with that of the previous month data.</li>
<li>If the figure is higher than the previous month’s then the economy is expanding at a faster rate.</li>
<li>If it is lower than the previous month then it is growing at a lower rate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are its implications for the economy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PMI is usually released at the start of the month, much before most of the official data on industrial output, manufacturing and GDP growth becomes available.</li>
<li>It is, therefore, considered a good leading indicator of economic activity.</li>
<li>Economists consider the manufacturing growth measured by the PMI as a good indicator of industrial output, for which official statistics are released later.</li>
<li>Central banks of many countries also use the index to help make decisions on interest rates.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pmi-purchasing-managers-index/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Live-streaming of Court: Definitely A Great Move</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/live-streaming-of-court/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Live streaming of courts proceedings</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Court" class="alignnone wp-image-643641 size-full" height="360" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.51-2.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.51-2.jpeg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.51-2-300x100.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.51-2-1024x341.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.51-2-768x256.jpeg 768w" width="1080"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>On September 27, the Supreme Court enabled the live streaming of the hearing of cases.</li>
<li>A full court of all Supreme Court judges under the leadership of Chief Justice U U Lalit took the unanimous decision to live-stream constitutional bench proceedings. Justice Chandrachud, the Chairperson of the Supreme Court’s E-committee and the driving force behind the live streaming initiative, began the hearing in his courtroom by announcing,”We are virtual”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Court’s original decision by the bench of the then Chief Justice Dipak Misra, Justice A M Khanwilkar and Justice D Y Chandrachud on September 27, 2018, allowing the live telecast of important proceedings paved the way for this outcome. They had held that the live-streaming of court proceedings is in the public interest.</li>
<li>Their vision had the full support of Chief Justices M V Ramana and U U Lalit.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is live-streaming technology?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At its core, streaming content is meant to help people attend events, expos, and experiences they cannot attend in person.</li>
<li>Live streaming technology is how videos are streamed over the internet, live, in real-time, as they are being recorded.</li>
<li>Live streaming technology is the internet’s response to live television broadcasts, with the most popular being news shows and sports.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Live-streaming of the court?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Live streaming of court is that its proceedings that the people can watch on their mobiles and computers.All courtrooms function under camera glare.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Court" class="alignnone wp-image-643650 size-full" height="577" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 985px) 100vw, 985px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.51-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.51-1.jpeg 985w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.51-1-300x176.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.51-1-768x450.jpeg 768w" width="985"/>Why </strong><strong><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/live-streaming-of-sc-proceedings/">Live-streaming of court</a> is so important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Instilling Faith in the Judiciary: </strong>Enabling the ordinary people of the country to view, without any barrier, the workings of the highest court of the land will go a long way in instilling faith in the judiciary.</li>
<li><strong>Empowering the masses: </strong>It will enable the legal system to deliver on its promise of empowering the masses.Important step toward developing an informed citizenry.</li>
<li><strong>Respect to Rule of Law: </strong>The decision will enable people to understand the importance of the rule of law.It will help people appreciate that the judiciary is firm in protecting the rights of the impoverished, historically marginalised and disempowered sections of society. Potential to build a culture of respect for the rule of law.</li>
<li><strong>Living up the expectation of Constitution: </strong>Live-Streaming of Court proceedings is manifested in public interest. Public interest has always been preserved through the Constitution article 19 and 21.</li>
<li><strong>More transparency: </strong>It will encourage the principle of open court and reduce dependence on second-hand views. It will effectuate the public’s right to know. This would inspire confidence in the functioning of the judiciary as an institution and help maintain the respect that it deserved as a co-equal organ of the state.</li>
<li><strong>Raise the quality and standards of the legal profession:</strong> Lawyers will be better prepared to appear before the court and they will be mindful of not making irresponsible remarks. An inclusive approach to public scrutiny could nudge and enable lawyers to take the justice delivery mechanisms more seriously than they may have in the past.</li>
<li><strong>Level playing field:</strong> It also creates a level playing ground for the younger members of the legal profession as their preparedness and intellectual prowess will be apparent to all.</li>
<li><strong>Academic help:</strong> Watching courtroom proceedings,actual arguments by lawyers and searching questions by judges  could inspire law students to take up this relatively neglected field.Law faculty members and legal researchers will be motivated to work on new areas of scholarship and research relating to the functioning of the judiciary and legal profession.</li>
<li><strong>Easy accessibility reducing the obstacle of distance: </strong>With live-streaming, the litigants will no longer have to come to Delhi to witness proceedings of their case which would be just a click away.</li>
<li><strong>Strengthening Democracy:</strong> Transparency and accessibility of the process of justice delivery will strengthen the country’s democracy</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Court" class="alignnone wp-image-643654 size-full" height="397" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 772px) 100vw, 772px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.50.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.50.jpeg 772w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.50-300x154.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.02.50-768x395.jpeg 768w" width="772"/>What are the Concerns around live-streaming of court?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Contempt of court:</strong> Video clips of proceedings from Indian courts are already on YouTube and other social media platforms with sensational titles and little context, such as “HIGH COURT super angry on army officer”.</li>
<li><strong>Disinformation and sensationalism:</strong> There are fears that irresponsible or motivated use of content could spread disinformation among the public.</li>
<li><strong>Unnecessary activism:</strong> With the advent of social media, every citizen became a potential journalist. Study shows that justices behave like politicians when given free television time, they act to maximize their individual exposure</li>
<li><strong>Internet connectivity: </strong>Internet connectivity issues and the need for a well-equipped space where lawyers can conduct their cases are some of the major problems requiring attention.</li>
<li><strong>Awareness and training:</strong> Judges, court staff and lawyers are not well-versed with digital technology and its benefits. The need of the hour is for them to be made aware of these and receive adequate training.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Court" class="alignnone wp-image-643657 size-large" height="654" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.24.04-1024x654.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.24.04-1024x654.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.24.04-300x191.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.24.04-768x490.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.24.04-1200x766.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-08.24.04.jpeg 1280w" width="1024"/>Which countries live-stream their court hearing</strong>?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Internationally,constitutional court proceedings are recorded in some form or the other.</li>
<li><strong>United States</strong>: The Supreme Court of the United States streams its hearings in audio format at the end of each week.The US top court publishes hearings on its website and Oyez of all cases. Oyez is a multimedia judicial archive of the Supreme Court of the United States’ proceedings.</li>
<li><strong>Brazil</strong>: The Supreme Federal Court of Brazil live streams hearings of all cases in video format on television.</li>
<li><strong>UK</strong>: The UK Supreme Court live streams hearings of all cases in video format on its website.</li>
<li><strong>Canada</strong>: The Canadian Supreme Court also live streams hearings of all its cases in video format on its website.</li>
<li><strong>Australia</strong>: The Australian Supreme Court streams hearings of its full-court cases on its website with a delay of about a day. Meanwhile, the High Court of Australia (HCA) does not live-stream its proceedings.</li>
<li><strong>China</strong>: In China,court proceedings are live-streamed from trial courts up to the Supreme People’s Court of China.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The chief justices (past and present) and the judges of the Supreme Court deserve to be congratulated for enabling a path-breaking and democratic decision that allows the people of India to be able to watch the live proceedings of the Constitutional Bench.The distinguished jurist, Oliver Holmes,famously observed,“The great thing in the world is not so much where we stand, as in what direction we are moving.” The judges of the Supreme Court of India have ensured that we are indeed moving in the right direction.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Adoption of technology will radically change the field of law and transform the judiciary. What will be the role of courts, judges, politicians,media and citizens of the country regarding live streaming of court proceedings. Discuss</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> <a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/live-streaming-of-court/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Has Ayushman Bharat lived up to its potential?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/has-ayushman-bharat-lived-up-its-potential/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ayushman Bharat</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Success of India's health policies</p></div></div><p><img alt="ayushman bharat" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-643733" height="430" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 803px) 100vw, 803px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/abnhm.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/abnhm.jpg 803w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/abnhm-300x161.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/abnhm-768x411.jpg 768w" width="803"/></p>
<p>India has completed four years of Ayushman Bharat Pradhan Mantri-Jan Arogya Yojana (AB-PMJAY), the world’s largest public health insurance programme.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Ayushman Bharat?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Ayushman Bharat is National Health Protection Scheme, which will cover over 10 crore poor and vulnerable families (approximately 50 crore beneficiaries) providing coverage upto 5 lakh rupees per family per year for secondary and tertiary care hospitalization.</li>
<li>It was launched in September 2018 by the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare.</li>
<li>It is a centrally sponsored scheme and is jointly funded by both the union government and the states.</li>
<li>It has subsumed the on-going centrally sponsored schemes – Rashtriya Swasthya Bima Yojana (RSBY) and the Senior Citizen Health Insurance Scheme (SCHIS).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Features of the scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It will have a defined benefit <strong><u>cover of Rs. 5 lakh</u></strong> per family per year.</li>
<li>Benefits of the scheme are <strong><u>portable across the country</u></strong> and a beneficiary covered under the scheme will be allowed to take cashless benefits from any public/private empanelled hospitals across the country.</li>
<li>It will be an <strong><u>entitlement based scheme</u></strong> with entitlement decided on the basis of deprivation criteria in the SECC database.</li>
<li>The beneficiaries can avail benefits in both <strong><u>public and empanelled private facilities</u></strong>.</li>
<li>To control costs, the payments for <strong><u>treatment will be done on package rate</u></strong> (to be defined by the Government in advance) basis.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>India’s health expenditure post Ayushman Bharat</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Ans.</strong> India’s public healthcare spending is still among the lowest in the world.</p>
<ul>
<li>Total health expenditure declined to 3.2% of GDP in 2018-19 from 3.3% in 2017-18, while the government’s health expenditure (centre and state) as a percentage of GDP fell from 1.35% to 1.28% in the same period.</li>
<li>National health estimates showed the Centre’s share decreasing to 34.3% in 2018-19 from 40.8% in the previous year, while that of states rose from 59.2% to 65.7%.</li>
<li>Out-of-pocket spending as a percentage of total health expenditure declined to 48.2% in 2018-19, though it is significantly higher than the world average of 18.1% in 2019</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What about health insurance penetration?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Ans.</strong> Retail health insurance covers a meagre 3.2% of the country’s population.</p>
<ul>
<li>With a population of 1.36 billion, India is the world’s second most populous country, and is expected to surpass China soon.</li>
<li>Launched in 2018 to provide universal health coverage, AB-PMJAY, takes care of the bottom 50% of the population of approximately 700 million individuals.</li>
<li>The top 20% of the population is covered through social and private health insurance.</li>
<li>Therefore, about 30% of the population, or about 400 million, is “the missing middle”— they don’t have any financial protection for health emergencies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is sound healthcare important for the economy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Covid-19 exposed the economic consequences of poor healthcare. Higher out-of-pocket healthcare spending hits savings and consumption.</li>
<li>In the work space, poor health impacts physical and mental abilities, increase turnover and lead to lower productivity.</li>
<li>Data shows that 7% of India’s population is pushed into poverty every year due to healthcare costs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Healthcare management and disease prevention should be the focus, along with an all-encompassing healthcare system, including OPD.</li>
<li>The government also needs to pay attention on healthcare cover for “the missing middle” population.</li>
<li>As a pilot, states may allow the authority already implementing the AB-PMJAY scheme in the state to cover the missing middle.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/has-ayushman-bharat-lived-up-its-potential/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The Mediation Bill,2021: Needs And Concerns</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mediation-bill-2021/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Mediation Bill</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Scope of Mediation Bill</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Mediation" class="alignnone wp-image-643679 size-full" height="450" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 809px) 100vw, 809px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.17.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.17.jpeg 809w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.17-300x167.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.17-768x427.jpeg 768w" width="809"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Mediation Bill, 2021 was introduced in the Rajya Sabha on December20, 2021,with the Parliamentary Standing Committee being tasked with a review of the Bill. The committee’s report to the Rajya Sabha was submitted on July 13, 2022. In its report, the Committee recommends substantial changes to the Mediation Bill, aimed at institutionalising mediation and establishing the Mediation Council of India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is mean by mediation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Mediation: </strong>Mediation is a process wherein the parties meet with a mutually selected impartial and neutral person who assists them in the negotiation of their differences.</li>
<li><strong>Brings Parties Together</strong>: Parties can save and sometimes rebuild their relationship like during a family dispute or commercial dispute.</li>
<li><strong>Very Convenient: </strong>The parties can control the time, location, and duration of the proceedings to large extent. Scheduling isn’t subject to the convenience of courts</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Mediation" class="alignnone wp-image-643681 size-large" height="682" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.16-1024x682.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.16-1024x682.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.16-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.16-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.16-1200x800.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.16.jpeg 1280w" width="1024"/>Why does India need mediation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>No separate law</strong>: While there is no standalone legislation for mediation in India, there are several statutes containing mediation provisions,such as the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908,the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996,the Companies Act, 2013, the Commercial Courts Act, 2015, and the Consumer Protection Act, 2019.</li>
<li><strong>Supreme Court mandate</strong>: The Mediation and Conciliation Project Committee of the Supreme Court of India describes mediation as a tried and tested alternative for conflict resolution.</li>
<li><strong>Being an international signatory: </strong>As India is a signatory to the Singapore Convention on Mediation (formally the United Nations Convention on International Settlement Agreements Resulting from Mediation), it is appropriate to enact a law governing domestic and international mediation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/parliamentary-committee-opposes-mediation-bill/">Key features of the Mediation bill</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Promote mediation</strong>: The Bill aims to promote, encourage, and facilitate mediation, especially institutional mediation, to resolve disputes, commercial and otherwise.</li>
<li><strong>Mandatory Mediation</strong>: The Bill further proposes mandatory mediation before litigation. At the same time, it safeguards the rights of litigants to approach competent adjudicatory forums/courts for urgent relief.</li>
<li><strong>Confidentiality</strong>: The mediation process will be confidential and immunity is provided against its disclosure in certain cases.</li>
<li><strong>Legally binding</strong>: The outcome of the mediation process in the form of a Mediation Settlement Agreement (MSA) will be legally enforceable and can be registered with the State district or taluk legal authorities within 90days to ensure authenticated records of the settlement.</li>
<li><strong>Mediation Council of India</strong>: The Bill establishes the Mediation Council of India and also provides for community mediation.</li>
<li><strong>Services of Mediator: </strong>If the parties agree, they may appoint any person as a mediator. If not, they may apply to a mediation service provider to appoint a person from its panel of mediators.</li>
<li><strong>Disputes where no mediation required: </strong>The Bill lists disputes that are not fit for mediation (such as those involving criminal prosecution, or affecting the rights of third parties). The central government may amend this list.</li>
<li><strong>Time bound process: </strong>The mediation process must be completed within 180 days, which may be extended by another 180 days by the parties.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Mediation" class="alignnone wp-image-643682 size-full" height="634" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.19.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.19.jpeg 960w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.19-300x198.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.19-768x507.jpeg 768w" width="960"/>What are the Concerns over the bill?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Mandatory provision: </strong>According to the Bill, pre-litigation mediation is mandatory for both parties before filing any suit or proceeding in a court,whether or not there is a mediation agreement between them.</li>
<li><strong>Monetary punishment: </strong>Parties who fail to attend pre-litigation mediation without a reasonable reason may incur a cost. However,as per Article 21 of the Constitution,access to justice is constitutional right which cannot be fettered or restricted. Mediation should just be voluntary and making it otherwise would amount to denial of justice.</li>
<li><strong>Clause 26: </strong>According to Clause26 of the Bill, court annexed mediation, including pre-litigation mediation, will be conducted in accordance with the directions or rules framed by the Supreme Court or High Courts. However, the Committee objected to this. It stated that Clause26 went against the spirit of the Constitution.In countries that follow the Common Law system, it is a healthy tradition that inthe absence of statutes, apex court judgments and decisions carry the same weight. The moment a law is passed however, it becomes the guiding force rather than the instructions or judgments given by the courts. Therefore, Clause 26 is unconstitutional.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of international enforceability: </strong>Bill considers international mediation to be domestic when it is conducted in India with the settlement being recognised as a judgment or decree ofa court. The Singapore Convention does not apply to settlements that already have the status of judgments or decrees. As a result, conducting cross border mediation in India will exclude the tremendous benefits of worldwide enforceability.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Mediation" class="alignnone wp-image-643683 size-large" height="682" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.19-1-1024x682.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.19-1-1024x682.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.19-1-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.19-1-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.19-1-1200x800.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-09.34.19-1.jpeg 1280w" width="1024"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In order to enable a faster resolution of disputes,the Bill should be implemented after discussion with stakeholders and resolve the issues in an amicable manner. It’s a good opportunity for India to become an international mediation hub for easy business transactions.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Address the key concerns in the mediation bill 2021 and how India can become the centre of international dispute resolutions.Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mediation-bill-2021/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Free Breakfast Scheme,Healthy Children: Healthy Nation</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/free-breakfast-scheme/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Various Schemes</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Malnutrition, under-nutrition and micro-nutrition.</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Free breakfast scheme" class="alignnone wp-image-643702 size-full" height="688" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1032px) 100vw, 1032px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.55-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.55-1.jpeg 1032w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.55-1-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.55-1-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.55-1-768x512.jpeg 768w" width="1032"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Under the free breakfast scheme of Tamil Nadu Government, children in government schools from Class I to Class V will get nutritious breakfast provided in their schools every morning. The scheme is aimed at encouraging more children to continue to come to school and help prevent dropouts in primary level.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>CM’s Breakfast Scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme covers around 1.14 lakh students in 1,545 schools which include 417 municipal corporation schools, 163 municipality schools and 728 taluk and village panchayat-level schools.</li>
<li>The inauguration of the scheme marks an important milestone in the State’s history of providing free meals to school students.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the approach for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tamil-nadus-breakfast-scheme-in-schools/">breakfast scheme?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Morning Breakfast</strong>: Under the morning breakfast scheme, every student is to be provided a cooked meal of 150-500 grams breakfast with sambar with vegetables. With a budget outlay of Rs33.5 crore in the initial phase, the new scheme caters to 1,14,095 primary school students from1,545 government schools.</li>
<li><strong>Micronutrients deficiency</strong>: School administration will serve hot breakfasts to schoolchildren by 8:30 am before their classes begin. Students will be served upma, kichadi or Pongal from Monday to Friday, while rava kesari or semiya kesari will be added to the menu on Fridays.The local millets available in the area will also be part of the menu for at least two days a week.</li>
<li><strong>Aim of the scheme</strong>: The scheme mainly aims to help students attend school hunger free and improve their nutritional status.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Free breakfast scheme" class="alignnone wp-image-643704 size-large" height="567" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.09.08-1024x567.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.09.08-1024x567.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.09.08-300x166.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.09.08-768x425.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.09.08.jpeg 1047w" width="1024"/>What do the Critics of the scheme argue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Freebies: </strong>The scheme stands at the confluence of three socio-political developments: a fierce but murky political debate on freebies<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Mid-day meal scheme: </strong>There was no need to supplement the existing mid-day meal scheme. But going by the content of the scheme, it seems unlikely that it will bring any substantial or sustained improvements in the above mentioned aspects of nutrition, especially since T.N. is already doing well in this regard.</li>
<li><strong>Populism</strong>: This is just a populist scheme by state government for vote bank politics.</li>
<li><strong>Questionable outcomes</strong>: Though the scheme has the potential to ensure that children attend classes hunger free, reliable and representative data on what proportion of them attend school without having breakfast regularly is scarce. Though the State acknowledges that students tend to skip breakfast because of the school timing and their financial situation, it is important to identify which among these is the significant contributor. The present approach does not distinguish between the two.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">What the Defenders of the scheme argue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Positive outcomes</strong>: Studies from other countries suggest that free breakfast schemes might help increase educational outcomes through a likely increase in school attendance and improved concentration on studies.</li>
<li><strong>On freebies</strong>: The freebie debate strategically deploys fiscal burden as a potent tool to possibly constrain States from discharging this responsibility.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Free breakfast scheme" class="alignnone wp-image-643710 size-large" height="569" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.55-1024x569.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.55-1024x569.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.55-300x167.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.55-768x427.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.55.jpeg 1200w" width="1024"/>Why feeding children in school is important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Welfare state</strong>: The States have a responsibility to promote welfare and minimise inequalities in income as well as in facilities and opportunities among individuals and groups (Article38).</li>
<li><strong>Global Food Security Index</strong>: The welfare responsibility of the States remains undiminished, especially since India is ranked 71out of 113 countries on the Global Food Security Index.</li>
<li><strong>Global Hunger Index</strong>: India ranked 101 out of 116countries on the Global Hunger Index.</li>
<li><strong>Human development index</strong>: 132 out of 191 countries on the Human Development Index. India’s mean years of schooling stood at just 6.7 years in 2020-21.</li>
<li><strong>Inequality: </strong>Additionally, India has among the highest levels of inequality in education. This responds closely with the rising wealth inequality, as brought out by the recent Credit Suisse report.</li>
<li><strong>Stunting and wasting: </strong>Malnourishment in children (stunting, wasting and underweight) under 5 years has reduced as per National family health survey-5 (2019-21) from 38.4% to 35.5%, 21.0% to 19.3% and 35.8% to 32.1% respectively as compared to NHFS-4 (2015-16). However present scenario is not good as compare to other developing nations in south Asia.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Free breakfast scheme" class="alignnone wp-image-643706 size-full" height="350" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.51.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.51.jpeg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-04-at-11.03.51-300x175.jpeg 300w" width="600"/>What are the different Existing Scheme?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Midday Meal Scheme</strong>: The Midday meal is a school meal programme in India designed to better the nutritional standing of school-age children nationwide.</li>
<li>The programme supplies free lunches on working days for children in primary and upper primary classes in government, government aided, local body, Education Guarantee Scheme, and alternate innovative education centres, Madrasa supported under Sarva Shiksha Abhiyan, and National Child Labour Project schools run by the ministry of labour.</li>
<li>Serving 120 million children in over 1.27 million schools and Education Guarantee Scheme centres, the Midday Meal Scheme is the largest of its kind in the world.</li>
<li><strong>PM-POSHAN:</strong> The name of the scheme has been changed to PM-POSHAN (Pradhan Mantri Poshan Shakti Nirman) Scheme, in September 2021, by MoE (Ministry of Education), which is nodal ministry for the scheme.</li>
<li>The Central Government also announced that an additional 24 lakh students receiving pre-primary education at government &amp; government-aided schools would also be included under the scheme by 2022.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s spending in human development enhancing welfare schemes has been very dismal. There is an urgent need for implementing innovative and effective welfare schemes to address the disruptions caused by the pandemic in the education and nutrition sectors and strengthen these sectors.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Malnutrition, under-nutrition and micro-nutrition requires a different approach. Distinguish and suggest the existing policy gaps to address them.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/free-breakfast-scheme/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>International Day of Non-Violence event at UN</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/international-day-of-non-violence-event-at-un/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>International Day of Non-Violence</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="International" class="alignnone wp-image-644275 size-full" height="418" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 733px) 100vw, 733px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/gandhi.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/gandhi.jpg 733w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/gandhi-300x171.jpg 300w" width="733"/></p>
<p>The International Day of Non-Violence event, held at the UN headquarters in New York, saw a life-size hologram of Gandhi displayed.</p>
<h4>International Day of Non-Violence</h4>
<ul>
<li>Every year, since 2007, the day is observed on October 2, the birth anniversary of Mahatma Gandhi.</li>
<li>Iranian Nobel Laureate Shirin Ebadi, in January 2004, first proposed the idea of dedicating a day to non-violence, around the world.</li>
<li>In 2007, the UN General Assembly (UNGA) passed a resolution to commemorate October 2 as the International Day of Non-Violence, with the core objective to “disseminate the message of non-violence, including through education and public awareness.”</li>
</ul>
<h4>What does the term “non-violence” stand for?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The UN defines the term as a rejection of the use of physical violence in order to achieve social or political change.</li>
<li>The UNGA resolution reaffirms the universal relevance of the principle of non-violence and establishes a desire to secure a culture of peace, tolerance, understanding and non-violence.</li>
<li>The theory emphasises that the power of rulers depends on the consent of the populations, and non-violence therefore seeks to undermine such power through withdrawal of the consent and cooperation of the populace.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/international-day-of-non-violence-event-at-un/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Ponniyin Selvan and the Cholas</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ponniyin-selvan-1-chola/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ponniyin Selvan</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>In all the buzz around the Tamil film Ponniyin Selvan: 1 or PS1, a fictional period drama, a point of focus has been the Chola dynasty that the film is based on.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A notable actor has spoke about the progressiveness of the Chola era.</li>
<li>He mentioned the architectural marvels and temples, the social setup of the time, and how cities were named after women.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Behind the name- PS1</h4>
<ul>
<li>The fictional account of the Chola kingdom appeared in a weekly journal in the early 1950s and garnered popularity.</li>
<li>These were later compiled into a novel called ‘Ponniyin Selvan’, which became the inspiration for the movie, whose second part is due for release in 2023.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who were the Cholas?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Chola kingdom stretched across present-day Tamil Nadu, Kerala, and parts of Andhra Pradesh and Karnataka around <strong><u>9th to 12th century AD</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The dynasty was <strong><u>founded by the king Vijaylaya</u></strong>, described as a “feudatory” of the Pallavas.</li>
<li>Despite being a relatively minor player in the region among giants, Vijaylaya laid the foundation for a dynasty that would rule a major part of southern India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Might of the Cholas</h4>
<p><strong>(1) Defense</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>One of the biggest achievements of the Chola dynasty was its naval power, allowing them to go as far as Malaysia and the Sumatra islands of Indonesia in their conquests.</li>
<li>The domination was such that the Bay of Bengal was converted into a “Chola lake” for some time.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Economy</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>While the extent of this domination is disputed, the Cholas had strong ties with merchant groups and this allowed them to undertake impressive naval expeditions.</li>
<li>In general, even merchant guilds, which had close ties to the court, had to hire their own guards because roads could be dangerous.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Culture</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Another feature is how the practice of building grand temples, common to the dynasties of the region around this time, was ramped up in an unprecedented way by the Cholas, according to Kanisetti.</li>
<li>The grand Brihadeeswara temple of Thanjavur, built by the Cholas, was the largest building in India in that period.</li>
<li>Additionally, artworks and sculptures were commissioned by Chola kings and queens, including the famous bronze Nataraja idols.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Women under the Cholas</h4>
<ul>
<li>The role of women in the royal family is being brought to focus given their impact on public life.</li>
<li>But that is not to suggest that ordinary women wielded equal power as men.</li>
<li>The royal women’s proximity to male power was valued, rather than women in general.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Local annexations</h4>
<ul>
<li>When the Chola King Rajadhiraja came to power in 1044, he was able to “subdue” Pandyan and Kerala kings, and presumably to celebrate these victories performed the Ashvamedha sacrifice.</li>
<li>The Chola rulers sacked and plundered Chalukyan cities including Kalyani and massacred the people, including Brahmans and children.</li>
<li>They destroyed Anuradhapura, the ancient capital of the rulers of Sri Lanka.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ponniyin-selvan-1-chola/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Abortion Right extends to the Cisgenders: SC</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/abortion-right-extends-to-the-cisgender-sc/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Cisgenders</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Abortion rights debate</p></div></div><p>In a significant judgment, the Supreme Court said it was unconstitutional to distinguish between married and unmarried women while <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-legal-and-safe-abortion/">allowing abortion</a> when the foetus is between 20-24 weeks.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Going a step further, the court said the term ‘woman’ in the judgment included persons other than cisgender women.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is cisgender?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The term cisgender is used to define people whose gender identity and expression match the identity assigned to them at birth.</li>
<li>When a child is born, it is assigned a gender identity based on its physical characteristics.</li>
<li>Many believe that gender is a social construct, and growing up, the child may or may not confirm to the birth identity.</li>
<li>For transgender people, their sense of gender identity does not match the one assigned to them at birth.</li>
<li>Thus, a cisgender woman is a person who was assigned female at birth and continues to identify as a woman.</li>
<li>On the other hand, a child assigned female at birth can feel it identifies more authentically as a man as it grows up.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Use of gender-inclusive vocabularies in official documents</h4>
<ul>
<li>Before India’s Supreme Court used ‘cisgender’ in the context of reproductive rights, last year in June, the US government had replaced the word ‘mothers’ with ‘birthing people’.</li>
<li>Those who advocate the use of ‘birthing people’ say it is not just women who give birth.</li>
<li>Transmen — a person assigned the female gender at birth but who identifies as a man – and genderqueer people – who identify as neither man nor woman – also give birth.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why the word cisgender is important?</h4>
<ul>
<li>If there are ‘transgender’ people, there should be a word for those who are not.</li>
<li>Giving a label to only one section of the population, especially when that is in the minority, implies that the others are default, ‘normal’, and only that section needs to be labelled.</li>
<li>Having distinct words for transgender and cisgender people denotes that both are equally valid, neutral experiences, with neither being an aberration.</li>
<li>Also, cis and trans are not the only gender identifiers in use.</li>
<li>There are many other terms, such as gender-queer, gender fluid and gender variant.</li>
<li>Some also choose not to use the traditionally gender-tied pronouns of he/she/her/his, and go for they/them.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Criticism of the term</h4>
<ul>
<li>Some people, including those working on trans rights, feel terms like ‘cisgender’ belong in the realm of gender theory alone.</li>
<li>They feel that their usage can be counterproductive – people are less likely to grasp a message if they have to look up the individual words that make up the message.</li>
<li>Others feel that ‘cisgender’ as a counter to ‘transgender’ is restrictive – reinforcing a binary of genders that many choose to reject.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/abortion-right-extends-to-the-cisgender-sc/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>District formation in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/district-formation-in-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>District formation</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>This newscard is an excerpt from the original article published in the <a href="https://www.downtoearth.org.in/blog/governance/district-formation-in-indian-states-is-a-tricky-decision-85287" rel="noopener" target="_blank">DownToEarth</a>.</p>
<h4><strong>What are Districts?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s districts are local administrative units inherited from the British Raj.</li>
<li>They generally form the tier of local government immediately below that of India’s subnational states and territories.</li>
<li>A district is headed by a Deputy Commissioner/ Collector, who is responsible for the overall administration and the maintenance of law and order.</li>
<li>The district collector may belong to IAS (Indian Administrative Service).</li>
<li>Districts are most frequently further sub-divided into smaller administrative units, called either tehsils or talukas or mandals, depending on the region.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How are new districts carved?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The power to create new districts or alter or abolish existing districts rests with the State governments.</li>
<li>This can either be done through an executive order or by passing a law in the State Assembly.</li>
<li>Many States prefer the executive route by simply issuing a notification in the official gazette.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Does the Central government have a role to play here?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Centre has no role to play in the alteration of districts or creation of new ones. States are free to decide.</li>
<li>The Home Ministry comes into the picture when a State wants to change the name of a district or a railway station.</li>
<li>The State government’s request is sent to other departments and agencies such as the Ministry of Earth Sciences, Intelligence Bureau, Department of Posts, Geographical Survey of India Sciences and the Railway Ministry seeking clearance.</li>
<li>A no-objection certificate may be issued after examining their replies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why create districts?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A district enjoys multiple benefits in terms of endowments from the government for local administration and development.</li>
<li>The formation of districts leads to the development of infrastructure, including transportation, telecommunication, water, sanitation, health, education and power facilities.</li>
<li>A good infrastructure attracts potential investors and investments.</li>
<li>New businesses and industries emerge and existing ones expand.</li>
<li>This generates employment opportunities for the citizens in and around the district.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The question that arises is what limits a state to declare each place a district.</li>
<li>The answer lies in the cost associated with the formation of a district.</li>
<li>A district requires installing administrative offices and deploying officers and public servants.</li>
<li>This adds to the burden on the government exchequer.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is also essential to consult the local people who are the end beneficiaries of the decision to understand their aspirations and win their confidence.</li>
<li>This will potentially mitigate the issues and conflicts between people and government and thereby satisfy the people’s needs at large, which is essential for inclusive growth of state and nation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In sum, any political change regarding the formation of a district in a state comes with its own advantages and challenges.</li>
<li>Thus, the government and policymakers must mull over the decision and perform a cost-benefit analysis before district formation.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/district-formation-in-india/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Home Ministry designates 10 individuals as Terrorists</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/home-ministry-designates-terrorists/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UAPA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Terror designation in India</p></div></div><p>A total of 10 members of Hizbul Mujahideen (HM), Lashkar-e-Taiba (LeT) and other proscribed outfits have been designated as terrorists by the Union Ministry of Home Affairs (MHA) under the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act (UAPA).</p>
<h4><strong>What is Unlawful (Activities) Prevention Act (UAPA)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The UAPA is aimed at effective prevention of unlawful activities associations in India.</li>
<li>Its main objective was to make powers available for dealing with activities directed against the integrity and sovereignty of India</li>
<li>It is an upgrade on the Terrorist and Disruptive Activities (Prevention) Act TADA, which was allowed to lapse in 1995 and the Prevention of Terrorism Act (POTA) was repealed in 2004.</li>
<li>It was originally passed in 1967 under the then Congress government led by former Prime Minister Indira Gandhi.</li>
<li>Till 2004, “unlawful” activities referred to actions related to secession and cession of territory. Following the 2004 amendment, “terrorist act” was added to the list of offences.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Designation of Terrorists</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Centre had amended UAPA, 1967, in August 2019 to include the provision of designating an individual as a terrorist.</li>
<li>Before this amendment, only organisations could be designated as terrorist outfits.</li>
<li>Section 15 of the UAPA defines a “terrorist act” as any act committed with intent to threaten or likely to threaten the unity, integrity, security, economic security, or sovereignty of India or with intent to strike terror or likely to strike terror in the people or any section of the people in India or in any foreign country.</li>
<li>The original Act dealt with “unlawful” acts related to secession; anti-terror provisions were introduced in 2004.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who makes such designation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The UAPA (after 2019 amendment)seeks to empower the central government to designate an individual a “terrorist” if they are found committing, preparing for, promoting, or involved in an act of terror.</li>
<li>A similar provision already exists in Part 4 and 6 of the legislation for organizations that can be designated as a “terrorist organisations”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How individuals are declared terrorists?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The central government may designate an individual as a terrorist through a notification in the official gazette, and add his name to the schedule supplemented to the UAPA Bill.</li>
<li>The government is not required to give an individual an opportunity to be heard before such a designation.</li>
<li>At present, in line with the legal presumption of an individual being innocent until proven guilty, an individual who is convicted in a terror case is legally referred to as a terrorist.</li>
<li>While those suspected of being involved in terrorist activities are referred to as terror accused.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What happens when an individual is declared a terrorist?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The designation of an individual as a global terrorist by the United Nations is associated with sanctions including travel bans, freezing of assets and an embargo against procuring arms.</li>
<li>The UAPA, however, does not provide any such detail.</li>
<li>It also does not require the filing of cases or arresting individuals while designating them as terrorists.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Removing the terrorist tag</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The UAPA gives the central government the power to remove a name from the schedule when an individual makes an application.</li>
<li>The procedure for such an application and the process of decision-making will is decided by the central government.</li>
<li>If an application filed by an individual declared a terrorist is rejected by the government, the UAPA gives him the right to seek a review within one month after the application is rejected.</li>
<li>The central government will set up the review committee consisting of a chairperson (a retired or sitting judge of a High Court) and three other members.</li>
<li>The review committee is empowered to order the government to delete the name of the individual from the schedule that lists “terrorists”, if it considers the order to be flawed.</li>
<li>Apart from these two avenues, the individual can also move the courts to challenge the government’s order.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/home-ministry-designates-terrorists/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Is Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022 Flawless?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/draft-telecommunications-bill/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Right to Privacy</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Cyber security,Right to privacy,Technology</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641528" height="415" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 622px) 100vw, 622px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31.jpeg 1200w" width="622"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Keeping an eye on the telecommunication regulatory framework Supreme Court issued substantive legal reform on surveillance laws in India. Union government has published the Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022 to replace the Telegraph Act, 1885.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Over two decades ago, allegations of surveillance against politicians led to a CBI inquiry and report against V P Singh’s government. The allegations revealed that imaginary reasons were given for ordering phone tapping without authorization.</li>
<li>Last years, many publications reported that phones of several dozen Indian journalists, lawyers and human rights activists had been compromised using an invasive Israeli-developed malware called Pegasus.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641527" height="406" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58.jpeg 1024w" width="608"/>What is Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The draft Indian Telecommunication Bill, 2022 is an attempt by the Department of Telecommunications (DoT) to consolidate various legislations presently governing the telecommunication landscape in India.</li>
<li>The Bill seeks to replace three laws, the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885, the Indian Wireless Telegraphy Act, 1933 and the Telegraph Wires (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1950.</li>
<li>The new regulatory framework is to bring the law at par with technological advancements and remove obsolete provisions from the colonial era laws.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the current laws governing communication surveillance in India?</strong></h4>
<p>Communication surveillance in India takes place primarily under two laws:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Telegraph Act, 1885</strong>: It deals with interception of calls.</li>
<li><strong>Call interception:</strong>Under Section 5(2) of this law, the government can intercept calls only in certain situations.</li>
<li><strong>For sovereignty:</strong>They include the interests of the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the state, friendly relations with foreign states or public order, or for preventing incitement to the commission of an offense.</li>
<li><strong>Free speech restrictions:</strong>These are the same restrictions imposed on free speech under Article 19(2) of the Constitution.</li>
<li><strong>Exceptions for journalists:</strong>A provision in Section 5(2) states that even this lawful interception cannot take place against journalists.</li>
<li><strong>Information Technology Act, 2000: </strong>It was enacted to deal with surveillance of all electronic communication, following the Supreme Court’s intervention in 1996.</li>
<li><strong>Electronic surveillance:</strong>Section 69 of the IT Act and the IT (Procedure for Safeguards for Interception, Monitoring, and Decryption of Information) Rules, 2009 were enacted to further the legal framework for electronic surveillance.</li>
<li><strong>Data interception:</strong>Under the IT Act, all electronic transmission of data can be intercepted.</li>
<li>Section 69 of the IT Act adds another aspect that makes it broader — interception, monitoring, and decryption of digital information “for the investigation of an offense”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641524" height="631" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-278x300.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-278x300.jpeg 278w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-768x829.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-834x900.jpeg 834w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56.jpeg 949w" width="585"/>How the loopholes in the current system breaching the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-privacy/">Data Privacy?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>No comprehensive data Protection Law: </strong></li>
<li>No comprehensive data protection law leaving ambiguities over several laws.</li>
<li>A comprehensive data protection law to address the gaps in existing frameworks for surveillance is yet to enact.</li>
<li><strong>Unaccountable, opaque exercise of surveillance: </strong></li>
<li>The Telegraph Act contains broad and excessive powers of interception and surveillance of communications carried out through any telegraph.</li>
<li>The surveillance power is principally contained under Section 5(2), and has resulted in an unaccountable, opaque and unconstitutional exercise of surveillance that has led to accusations across the political spectrum.</li>
<li><strong>Less transparency:</strong></li>
<li>Ministry of Home Affairs refuses to disclose even aggregate data on the number of surveillance orders issued by it each year illegally gathered evidence is being sought to prosecute people.</li>
<li>For instance, the Bombay High Court about three years ago noted in a case that premier investigating agencies such as the CBI have used, interception orders (that) neither have sanction of law nor issued for legitimate aim.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641526" height="398" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 596px) 100vw, 596px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-1024x682.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-1200x800.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00.jpeg 1280w" width="596"/>Key features of</strong> <strong>the</strong> <strong>Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Broad Definitions: </strong></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>The Bill introduces a broad definition of ‘telecommunication services’.</li>
<li>It now includes internet-based services, in-flight and maritime connectivity, interpersonal communications services, machine to machine communication services, and over-the-top (OTT) based communication services that are made available to users by telecommunication</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>KYC and caller id requirements: </strong></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>The Bill requires licensed entities to ensure that they identify the persons to whom they provide telecommunication services.</li>
<li>The Bill places an obligation on telecommunication service providers to do this through a ‘verifiable mode’, as prescribed by the government.</li>
<li><strong>Licensing, registration, and authorization:</strong></li>
<li>Under the Bill, four types of permissions are identified – license, registration, authorization and assignment.</li>
<li>While the Bill does not differentiate between the four types of permissions, it clarifies that a license is only required for providing telecommunication services or operating telecommunication networks</li>
<li><strong>Wide ranging powers of Central Government: </strong></li>
<li>The Bill includes wide-ranging powers for the central and state governments in the event of a public emergency or in interest of public safety.</li>
<li>These powers include taking temporary possession of any telecommunication services, suspension of transmission in cases of public emergency, interception/detainment/disclosure of messages, suspension of communications, or otherwise transmit certain announcements for public safety and national security purposes.</li>
<li><strong>User protection and duties: </strong>User has been declared as an important policy objective of the Government. It places a duty on users to not furnish false information, suppress material information or impersonate others when proving identity to avail telecommunication services.</li>
<li><strong>Offences and penalties</strong>: Any offence under the Bill may be punished with a fine, imprisonment, suspension of telecommunication services or a combination of the above. For companies, the employees who were responsible for the conduct or the business relating to the offence at the time the offence was committed will be punished.</li>
<li><strong>Dispute resolution mechanism</strong>: The Bill provides for the right of appeal before the appellate authority. It also creates an enabling provision for the Central Government to set up an alternate dispute resolution mechanism such as arbitration, mediation or other processes of dispute resolution</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Concerns over the Draft Telecommunication bill, 2022?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Regulatory overlaps:</strong>The broad of the definition of ‘telecommunication services’ include OTT communication platforms such as WhatsApp, Telegram, Signal among others, may potentially lead to regulatory or jurisdictional overlaps.</li>
<li><strong>Unchecked use of State powers:</strong>The Bill gives broad powers to the central government in prescribed situations without any accompanying checks and balances. The Bill empowers the central and state government to intercept messages in the interest of public safety and emergency without the providing clearly defined guardrails for it.</li>
<li><strong>Undefined National security: </strong>The term, national security is left undefined and does not match constitutional precedent or text which instead uses the phrase,in the interests of the security of state</li>
<li><strong>Users Less choice in the privacy and security of their digital footprint:</strong></li>
<li>Power to prescribe standards under Clause 23, which may result in regulations as recently issued by the Computer Emergency Response Team (CERT-In) that have resulted in the closure of servers or services by leading, global VPN providers such as Proton and TunnelBear.</li>
<li>All of this practically means that users will have less choice in the privacy and security of their digital footprint, as these powers will lead to requirements to locally register and host data, and comply with requirements to identify users (KYC requirements).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There should be some reasonable basis or some tangible evidence to initiate or seek approval for interception by State authorities. Any digression from the ethical and legal parameters set by law would be tantamount to a deliberate invasion of citizens.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Any deviation from the moral and legal parameters set by the law would amount to a deliberate attack on citizens. In this context discuss the data privacy of citizens in the era of massive expansion of internet and mobile usage.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/draft-telecommunications-bill/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India-China: Hostile Neighbors</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-china/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>India china friction points</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Border security</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="China" class="alignnone wp-image-644197 size-full" height="781" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1341px) 100vw, 1341px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.03-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.03-1.jpeg 1341w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.03-1-300x175.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.03-1-1024x596.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.03-1-768x447.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.03-1-1200x699.jpeg 1200w" width="1341"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The National Congress of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP), scheduled in October, promises to deliver important outcomes, which will impact not just China but affairs of other nations, neighbour and beyond. A look into India-china Relationship as china has always been hostile towards its neighbours.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the recent anti- India moves by China?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>China continues to stake its claim to Arunachal Pradesh as Southern Tibet.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Beijing recently renamed 15 places in Arunachal Pradesh, following the six it had done in 2017.</li>
<li>China justifies the renaming as being done on the basis of its historical, cultural and administrative jurisdiction over the area — these old names existed since ancient times which had been changed by India with its “illegal occupation”.</li>
<li>On January 1, 2022, Beijing’s new land border law came into force, which provides the People’s Liberation Army (PLA) with full responsibility to take steps against “invasion, encroachment, infiltration, provocation” and safeguard Chinese territory</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="China" class="alignnone wp-image-644198 size-full" height="407" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.05.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.05.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.05-300x95.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.05-1024x326.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.05-768x244.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.05-1200x382.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>What is the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-china-border/">present situation of India-China relationship</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Troops in Ladakh</strong>: We have been on tenterhooks since the sanguinary Galwan clash of 2020, and borne a heavy cost for the “mirror-deployment” of 50,000-60,000 additional troops in Ladakh.</li>
<li><strong>LAC negotiations</strong>: Sino-Indian diplomatic parleys having been suspended, the task of LAC negotiations has been foisted on local military commanders.</li>
<li><strong>Truce for SCO</strong>: The 16th successive commanders’ meeting would have seen yet another futile conclusion, but for compulsions of the impending Shanghai Cooperative Organisation, which apparently led to a modest breakthrough. Consequently, the third round of troop disengagement and the creation of another buffer zone has taken place in Siachen, this time in the area of Gogra-Hot Springs<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Bilateral Trade: </strong>The India-China trade is on course to cross USD 100 billion for the second consecutive year as it has gone up to USD 67.08 billion in the first half of this year amid a big surge of Chinese exports.</li>
<li>“According to the statistics of Chinese competent authorities, bilateral trade volume between China and India stood at USD 125.66 billion in 2021.China remains the largest trade partner of India and for the first time the bilateral trade exceeded USD 100 billion in 2021.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="China" class="alignnone wp-image-644201 size-full" height="446" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 670px) 100vw, 670px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.16-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.16-1.jpeg 670w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.16-1-300x200.jpeg 300w" width="670"/>Why taking precautions is necessary?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Past behaviour of china</strong>: It is useful to review China’s past behaviour, since it may help avoid nasty future surprises. Ever since the end of its Civil War in 1949, China has been engaged in serial strife, domestic as well as external; invading neighbours, Korea, Tibet, Russia, Vietnam and India.</li>
<li><strong>Domestic turmoil</strong>: The prelude to the Sino-Indian war saw Chairman Mao Zedong launch the tumultuous and destructive Great Leap Forward, which resulted in 25-30 million deaths by starvation and state violence.</li>
<li><strong>Distraction amidst power-struggle</strong>: In the midst of ongoing domestic turmoil and devastation, Mao’s ruthless calculus perceived advantage in mounting a military campaign to deliver a sharp blow to India, both as a distraction from the ongoing power struggle, and to prove China’s superiority.</li>
<li><strong>Teach India a lesson attitude</strong>: According to Swedish author and China/India expert, Bertil Lintner, on the 1962 war. He maintains that the Chinese offensive was not a reaction to India’s “forward policy” but a pre-meditated operation, ordered well before October 1962 by Mao to divert attention from the ongoing domestic power struggle and to teach India a lesson.</li>
<li><strong>Continuing hostility</strong>: While repeatedly demonstrating its penchant for salami-slicing, at sea as well as on land, China continues to stake its claim to Arunachal Pradesh as Southern Tibet. Its determined hostility to India in international forums leaves little room for the hope that strategic patience will resolve bilateral problems.</li>
<li><strong>Separation of trade and strategic relation</strong>: Last year, the India-China bilateral trade hit a record high of over USD 125 billion crossing the USD 100 billion mark in a year when the relations touched a new low due to standoff by the militaries in Eastern Ladakh.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="China" class="alignnone wp-image-644211 size-large" height="768" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.14-1024x768.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.14-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.14-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.14-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.14-1200x900.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-07.56.14.jpeg 1280w" width="1024"/>What are the options for India to learn from the past and see what lies ahead in India-China relations?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inevitable Race: </strong>The prevailing tension on the China-India border is a symptom of the broader strategic competition between the two Asian neighbors.</li>
<li><strong>Quad grouping: </strong>Immediately after the clashes, India leaned toward the Quad a grouping of the United States, Australia, Japan, and India with multiple summit meetings and other engagements. Until that point, India was unwilling to refer to the Quad as the Quad, instead using the cumbersome India-Australia-Japan-United States grouping<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Equal seriousness</strong>: Both sides should treat the military escalation in eastern Ladakh with equal seriousness.</li>
<li><strong>Armed coexistence</strong>: Even after the resolution of the present standoff in eastern Ladakh, both sides may be in a prolonged period of armed coexistence as a new normal. As the forces on both sides are likely to be relatively balanced, it would be advantageous for both to return to the agreements and understandings from 1993 onward and improve upon them. Clarifying the LAC is a crucial step in this effort.</li>
<li><strong>Address trade imbalance</strong>: India has flagged the unsustainable trade imbalance at the front and centre of the relationship, and this has gone unaddressed. China will need to work on resolving the trade deficit with India. At any rate, decoupling will happen selectively, in the same way and for the same reasons that China is choosing to decouple from the United States. A balanced trade and economic relationship might lay a solid foundation for future relations, given the size of both economies.</li>
<li><strong>Dialogue is necessary</strong>: Better understanding of each other’s regional initiatives through open dialogue is important to build trust. The Indo-Pacific vision is as much a developmental necessity for India as the BRI may be to China. Part of building trust must be an open discussion on each other’s intentions in key regions South Asia and the northern Indian Ocean and East Asia and the western Pacific as well as respect for each other’s special positions in the western Pacific and northern Indian Oceans.</li>
<li><strong>Protect the core interest</strong>: The two sides would need to accommodate the legitimate interests of the other side on key partnerships: China’s with Pakistan and India’s with the United States. These may not be desirable, but in the current circumstances neither will give up its partners, and both India and China could talk through a modus vivendi on the red lines of concern.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The two countries are standing at a crossroads, and this might be the final chance to take the path to coexistence of cooperation and competition. If not, a new phase of antagonistic rivalry may be starting, with the countries sliding into possible confrontation as the strategic periphery of China collides with the strategic backyard of India in the Indian Ocean region.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>India and china are the two Asian giants aspiring for regional supremacy and global influence, clash is unavoidable. Discuss how India and china can coexist together.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-china/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Quantum Technology : Next generation Computers are achievible</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/quantum/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Quantum Technology</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Quantum Technology applications</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Quantum" class="alignnone wp-image-644200 size-full" height="776" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.04.03.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.04.03.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.04.03-300x182.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.04.03-1024x621.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.04.03-768x466.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.04.03-1200x728.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Nobel Prize committee decided to honour three scientists Alain Aspect of France, John Clauser of the US, and Anton Zeilinger of Austria for their work in domain quantum physics.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the contribution of these </strong><strong>three scientists?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Together, these three have made seminal contributions to not just the foundations of quantum theory but also to efforts that have now enabled the possibility of a wide range of applications.</li>
<li>Their experiments have conclusively established that the ‘entanglement’ phenomenon observed in quantum particles was real, not a result of any ‘hidden’ or unknown forces.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">What is the Significance of this Discovery?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Wide applications</strong>: It could be utilised to make transformative technological advances in computing, hack-free communications, and science fiction-like concept of ‘teleportation’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Quantum " class="alignnone wp-image-644195 size-full" height="675" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.00.27-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.00.27-1.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.00.27-1-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.00.27-1-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.00.27-1-768x432.jpeg 768w" width="1200"/>What is Quantum Theory?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Subatomic level: </strong>Quantum theory is a fundamental theory in physics that provides a description of the physical properties of nature at the scale of atoms and subatomic particles.It is the foundation of all quantum physics including quantum chemistry, quantum field theory, quantum technology, and quantum information science.</li>
<li><strong>Different from conventional physics: </strong>Quantum mechanics differs from classical physics in that energy, momentum, angular momentum.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/national-mission-on-quantum-technology-and-applications-nm-qta/">Development in Quantum Theory</a> so far</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Planck’s assumption: </strong>In 1900, Planck made the assumption that energy was made of individual units, or</li>
<li><strong>Albert Einstein’s theory </strong>: In 1905, Albert Einstein theorized that not just the energy, but the radiation itself was quantized in the same manner.</li>
<li><strong>Louis de Broglie theory: </strong>In 1924, Louis de Broglie proposed that there is no fundamental difference in the makeup and behaviour of energy and matter; on the atomic and subatomic level either may behave as if made of either particles or waves. This theory became known as the principle of wave-particle duality: elementary particles of both energy and matter behave, depending on the conditions, like either particles or waves<strong> (</strong>wave-particle duality).</li>
<li><strong>Heisenberg proposed: </strong>In 1927, Werner Heisenberg proposed that precise, simultaneous measurement of two complementary values – such as the position and momentum of a subatomic particle – is impossible. Contrary to the principles of classical physics, their simultaneous measurement is inescapably flawed; the more precisely one value is measured, the more flawed will be the measurement of the other value. This theory became known as the <strong>uncertainty principle</strong>, which prompted Albert Einstein’s famous comment, “God does not play dice.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> <img alt="Quantum" class="alignnone wp-image-644205 size-full" height="355" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 677px) 100vw, 677px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.00.24.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.00.24.jpeg 677w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.00.24-300x157.jpeg 300w" width="677"/></strong><strong>What is Entanglement?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Entanglement was another of several weird properties exhibited by these tiny particles. Two particles, having ‘interacted’ with each other at some stage, were found to have got ‘entangled’ in a way that the behaviour of one produced an instantaneous reaction in the othe<strong>r</strong> even if the two were no longer connected in any way and were separated by very large distances.</li>
<li>The entanglement property to open up new technological possibilities. first time that it was possible to ‘teleport’ the quantum states of a particle to another location without the particle moving anywhere and without a medium.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Superposition?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It’s a phenomenon where, a particle exists simultaneously at multiple locations, known as superposition. The chance of finding the particle at any given place was dictated by probabilistic calculations, and once it was found, or observed, at one location, it ceased to exist at all other places.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the Einstein’s assessment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Special theory of relativity</strong>: Einstein’s Special Theory of Relativity prohibited any signal from travelling faster than the speed of light. The seemingly instantaneous communication due to entanglement had the danger of further unravelling the foundations of physics<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Spooky behaviour</strong>: Einstein describes the strange behaviour by quantum particles as ‘spooky’.</li>
<li><strong>Speed of light</strong>: One major concern of Einstein, that entanglement allows for transmission of information at speeds faster than light, was not entirely accurate.When an operation is performed on one of the entangled particles, there is an instantaneous reaction in the other.</li>
<li><strong>Communication problem</strong>: There is no way for the observer at the other end to know the reaction has happened. The observer has to be made aware of the operation having been performed, and this happens only through classical communication channels limited by the speed of light restriction.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Quantum" class="alignnone wp-image-644209 size-full" height="580" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.00.23.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.00.23.jpeg 680w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-08.00.23-300x256.jpeg 300w" width="680"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The entanglement property is now being utilised to build the next generation of computers, called quantum computers, which exploit the quantum behaviour of particles to overcome challenges considered as unsurmountable. It is being used to create secure communication algorithms that would be immune to hacking.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>What is the quantum theory? How it is different from classical theory of physics? </strong><strong>How entanglement property is used in various applications?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/quantum/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Civil Services: The Backbone of Administration</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/civil/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>civils services</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Civil services and reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Civil" class="alignnone wp-image-644231 size-full" height="452" sizes="(max-width: 678px) 100vw, 678px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-11.15.31.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-11.15.31.jpeg 678w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-11.15.31-300x200.jpeg 300w" width="678"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India is rapidly integrating technology in both governance and in delivering goods and services. All this requires a worker (civil servant), who is not just committed but also has the competence to deliver on this evolving mandate.people centric governance is the need of the hour.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Civil Services in India: A backgrounder</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Civil Services refer to the career civil servants who are the permanent executive branch of the Republic of India. It is the backbone of the administrative machinery of the country.</li>
<li>As India is a parliamentary democracy, the ultimate responsibility for running the administration rests with the people’s elected representatives.</li>
<li>The elected executive decides the policy and it is civil servants, who serve at the pleasure of the President of India, implement it.</li>
<li>However, Article 311 of the constitution protects Civil Servants from politically motivated vindictive action.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who are<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/civil-servants/"> civil servants</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In a modern democracy, a civil servant is an official in the service of the people and is recruited based on predetermined qualifications. Civil servants are bureaucrats who need to be familiar with the laws and regulations of the country and are expected to act in the best interests of the country and its citizens.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is their expected role?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>They are responsible for managing the resources given to them by the government and making use of them efficiently and effectively. A sound parliamentary system of government requires civil servants to maintain their integrity, fearlessness, and independence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Civil" class="alignnone wp-image-644233 size-full" height="525" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 554px) 100vw, 554px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-11.16.03.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-11.16.03.jpeg 554w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-11.16.03-300x284.jpeg 300w" width="554"/>What is Mission Karmayogi ?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Mission Karmayogi  is a National Programme for Civil Services Capacity Building has been envisioned by the Government to address the changing needs and aspiration of the citizen.</li>
<li>The Programme has been designed to enhance the civil services under a national Programme, anchored by an apex body headed by the Prime Minister.</li>
<li>It is aimed at building a future-ready civil service with the right attitude, skills and knowledge, aligned to the vision of New India.</li>
<li>It is meant to be a comprehensive post-recruitment reform of the Centre’s human resource development.</li>
<li>As envisaged, the Karmayogi<strong> </strong>training mechanism will cover an estimated 4.6 million officials at all levels.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are people-centric public services</strong>?</h4>
<ul>
<li>People centricity means taking the needs and voices of people into account when designing, delivering, implementing and evaluating public policies and services. Broadly, a people centric approach is one where governments consult citizens about their needs and encourage their direct participation in policy making and service design and delivery.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is the need for people-centric governance immediately in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Empowered Citizens:</strong> India’s citizens are no longer content to passively receive benefits from a patronising government; they are actively making claims on the state and feel empowered to shape how it affects their lives.</li>
<li><strong>Interconnected world: </strong>With the rise of information and communication technology, we are becoming more interconnected globally. Young Indians living in small towns and villages are connected to the wider world, which is shaping their aspirations and desires.</li>
<li><strong>Informed citizenry:</strong> Better informed citizenry is giving shape to a more mature political system, in which politicians from across the spectrum recognise the importance of delivering on campaign promises of better health, education and social benefits.</li>
<li><strong>Emerging technology</strong>: The development of new technologies is opening up possibilities for governance. The state needs to leverage them to deliver the greatest good for the largest number.</li>
<li><strong>Towards less government, more governance: </strong>A post-Covid BANI (brittle, anxious, non-linear and incomprehensible) world is redefining the understanding of the future of work. The understanding of what is a public good is also evolving along with the aspirations of citizens. India is moving towards a “less government, more governance” approach.</li>
<li><strong>Evolution of partnership state:</strong></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>In response to the Covid-19 pandemic exemplified many aspects of this new partnership state. Indian state from being a provider and a provisioner state, to becoming a “partnership state”.</li>
<li>Different arms of the national government PMO to the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare and many other ministries, the NITI Aayog, ICMR and other central government organizations collaborated effectively with international bodies and state governments, bringing out the strength of India’s global relations and federal structure.</li>
<li>The government, the private sector, civil society and citizen volunteer groups all joined the effort against the virus. All these parts of society came together as one “Team India” to fight the pandemic. This is the true spirit of the partnership state.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Civil" class="alignnone wp-image-644240 size-full" height="520" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 756px) 100vw, 756px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-11.16.25.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-11.16.25.jpeg 756w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-11.16.25-300x206.jpeg 300w" width="756"/>What steps need to be taken to fulfill the aspirations of people-centric governance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>New Mindset and skills: </strong>Operating in this dynamic ecosystem requires a new mindset and an evolving skill set. It needs skills of collaboration, adaptiveness, credit sharing, persuasion, and conflict resolution along with a nuanced and practical understanding of disruptive innovations, digital arenas, big data management and emerging technologies.</li>
<li><strong>Transition under Mission Karmayogi :</strong>The National Programme for Civil Services Capacity Building (NPCSCB), encapsulates three transitions.</li>
<li><strong>Change in the mindset</strong>: Change in mindset of government officials from considering themselves karmacharis to becoming karmayogis.</li>
<li><strong>Change in the workplace:</strong> Change in the workplace from assigning individual responsibility for performance, to diagnosing the constraints to a civil servant’s performance and remediating them.</li>
<li><strong>Rule based to Role Based:</strong> Moving the public HR management system and the corresponding capacity building apparatus from being rule-based to role-based</li>
<li><strong>Capacity Building Commission (CBC): </strong>To build Credibility and shape a uniform approach to capacity building on a collaborative basis. As the custodian of the overall landscape, the CBC will determine the roll-out strategy of the NPCSCB, onboarding different ministries and departments, conduct the HR audit of government organisations, ensure functional oversight over all central training institutions and Karmayogi Bharat, conduct the Global HR Summit and provide policy inputs to Department of Personnel &amp; Training.</li>
<li><strong>Adopting emerging technological environment: </strong>Technology is redefining how goods and services can be rendered. From Aadhaar to DBT and Digilocker, from CPGRAMS to MyGov, from faceless transactions to drone deliveries, from online learning to a digital university. The structure and setup of the workplace is rapidly altering and work from anywhere to deliver good governance to all citizens will soon have to become the norm.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Civil" class="alignnone wp-image-644241 size-full" height="535" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 731px) 100vw, 731px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-11.24.55.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-11.24.55.jpeg 731w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-05-at-11.24.55-300x220.jpeg 300w" width="731"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The civil services have remained at the epicentre of all government activities in India, both as agents of policymaking as well as the executive hand that delivers and implements those policies. This unique moment of Amrit Mahotsav is the appropriate time for the civil services to pause, reflect and strategise on the approaches needed to shape its future. People-centric governance is no longer aspirational but is rapidly becoming the national imperative.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Civil servants in India are considered as the backbone of the country’s administrative system. In this context discuss the approach of civil servants to fulfill the aspirations of people-centric administration in new India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/civil/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>