<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 06:05:31 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Karnataka brings law giving Quota for Locals</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/karnataka-brings-law-giving-quota-for-locals/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Quota for Locals</p></div></div><p>The Karnataka government recently tabled The Kannada Language Comprehensive Development Bill which gives preference to Kannadigas in government jobs and also provides for a reservation to locals in private jobs generated in the state.</p>
<h4><strong>What does the Karnataka legislation envisage?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Apart from ensuring job guarantee to Kannada speakers, the Bill pushes for the use of Kannada in institutes of higher learning and for sops to industries that employ locals.</li>
<li>Features highlighted in the Bill include reservation in higher, technical and professional education to those who studied in Kannada medium schools.</li>
<li>It seeks introduction of Kannada as essential language for seeking employment in the state government.</li>
<li>Also, industries will be entitled to concessions, tax rebates and deferment of taxes if they provide reservation for Kannadigas, as per the state’s industrial policy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Quota for Locals?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Ans.</strong> Constitutional provision for Equal Treatment</p>
<ul>
<li>Article 16 of the Constitution guarantees equal treatment under the law in matters of public employment. It prohibits the state from discriminating on grounds of place of birth or residence.</li>
<li>Article 16(2) states that “no citizen shall, on grounds only of religion, race, caste, sex, descent, place of birth, residence or any of them, be ineligible for, or discriminated against in respect of, any employment or office under the State”.</li>
<li>The provision is supplemented by the other clauses in the Constitution that guarantee equality.</li>
<li>However, Article 16(3) of the Constitution provides an exception by saying that Parliament may make a law “prescribing” a requirement of residence for jobs in a particular state.</li>
<li>This power vests solely in the Parliament, not state legislatures.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why does the Constitution prohibit reservation based on domicile?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When the Constitution came into force, India turned itself into one nation from a geographical unit of individual principalities and the idea of the universality of Indian citizenship took root.</li>
<li>India has single citizenship, and it gives citizens the liberty to move around freely in any part of the country.</li>
<li>Hence the requirement of a place of birth or residence cannot be qualification for granting public employment in any state.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>But are reservations not granted on other grounds such as caste?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Equality enshrined in the Constitution is not mathematical equality and does not mean all citizens will be treated alike without any distinction.</li>
<li>To this effect, the Constitution underlines two distinct aspects which together form the essence of equality law:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Non-discrimination among equals, and</li>
<li>Affirmative action to equalize the unequal</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Supreme Court rulings on quota for locals</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court has ruled against reservation based on place of birth or residence.</li>
<li>In 1984, ruling in Dr Pradeep Jain v Union of India, the issue of legislation for “sons of the soil” was discussed.</li>
<li>The court expressed an opinion that such policies would be unconstitutional but did not expressly rule on it as the case was on different aspects of the right to equality.</li>
<li>In a subsequent ruling in Sunanda Reddy v State of Andhra Pradesh (1995), the Supreme Court affirmed the observation in 1984 ruling to strike down a state government policy that gave 5% extra weightage to candidates.</li>
<li>In 2002, the Supreme Court invalidated appointment of government teachers in Rajasthan in which the state selection board gave preference to “applicants belonging to the district or the rural areas of the district concerned”.</li>
<li>In 2019, the Allahabad HC struck down a recruitment notification by the UP PSC which prescribed preference for women who are “original residents” of the UP alone.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why it is a bad idea?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Against Equality as well as meritocracy</strong>: It goes against the Constitution of India. In fact, it violates several fundamental rights, such as freedom to move anywhere, the right not to be discriminated on the basis of place of birth, the right to be treated equally before laws and the right to pursue one’s livelihood.</li>
<li><strong>Migration criteria not justified</strong>: The actual data on inter-State migration shows that inter-State migration is relatively low in India. Migration often bring skills, motivation, energy which may be in short supply or lacking locally.</li>
<li><strong>Free movement of labour</strong>: A more analytical aspect to highlight is that free movement of labour partly compensates for the uneven economic progress of different States. The idea also goes against the established fact that migration of labour is good for the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Un-ease of doing business</strong>: Local reservation in the private sector may not be the ideal solution to tackle the unemployment crisis. In fact, it can deter the corporate sector from investing in states that come up with such a rule.</li>
<li><strong>Scapegoating the private sector: </strong>What distinguishes the private sector from the public sector is the inherent competition and a hunger for improvement. In such a scenario, chief ministers should do well to engage with the private sector in a much more holistic manner, and not burden it with unfeasible rules.</li>
<li><strong>MSMEs to be hit harder: </strong>MSMEs could be the hardest hit. They do not have the necessary capital to relocate and many studies have shown that more than 50 per cent of employees are not residents of the state.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Arguments in favour of quota in private</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Avoiding encroachments:</strong> Often the privileged castes (or groups) use nefarious arguments to protect their interests.</li>
<li><strong>Foul argument of merit:</strong> Reservations once accepted in the constitutional framework are not a charity that is to be kept away from the ‘meritocracy’ of ‘private’ operations.</li>
<li><strong>Ensuring equal opportunity:</strong> Like all other constitutional guarantees, one may feel the necessity to get ensured of equal opportunity in all spaces.</li>
<li><strong>Preventing exclusion:</strong> Giving preference and quotas for socially and educationally deprived sections in the private space is, therefore, in keeping with this fundamental tenet.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The politics of identity and polarization on region/religious lines seems inadequate for the elections.</li>
<li>The philosophy and pragmatism of universal excellence through equality of opportunity for education and advancement across the nation is part of our founding faith and constitutional creed.</li>
<li>Clearly, this is not the appropriate domain of being “vocal for local”.</li>
<li>Although some reservations may still be necessary for the socio-political condition in India, reservation on the basis of domicile or residence within a State would be highly discriminatory.</li>
<li>It is more likely that such politically motivated steps would be overturned by the judiciary as has been done several times in the past.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/karnataka-brings-law-giving-quota-for-locals/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SC takes up pleas against Places of Worship Act</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-takes-up-pleas-against-places-of-worship-act/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Places of Worship Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with the Act</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has set the ball rolling on a series of petitions challenging the validity of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-places-of-worship-act/">Places of Worship Act of 1991</a>, a parliamentary law that protects the identity and character of religious places as on August 15, 1947.</p>
<h4>What are the petitions about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A slew of petitions has been filed against the Act.</li>
<li>The Act has fixed a retrospective cut-off date illegally barring Hindus, Jains, Buddhists and Sikhs from approaching courts to re-claim their places of worship which were invaded and encroached.</li>
<li>The main objective of these petitions is to set right a historical wrong committed by barbaric invaders.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Places of Worship Act, 1991</h4>
<ul>
<li>It was passed in 1991 by the P V Narasimha Rao-led government.</li>
<li>The law seeks to maintain the “religious character” of places of worship as it was in 1947 — except in the case of the Ram Janmabhoomi-Babri Masjid dispute, which was already in court.</li>
<li>The law was brought in at the peak of the Ram Mandir movement, exactly a year before the demolition of the Babri Masjid.</li>
<li>Introducing the law, then Home Minister S B Chavan said in Parliament that it was adopted to curb communal tension.</li>
</ul>
<p>What are its provisions?</p>
<h4>What are its provisions?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Anti-conversion:</strong> Section 3 of the Act bars the conversion, in full or part, of a place of worship of any religious denomination into a place of worship of a different religious denomination — or even a different segment of the same religious denomination.</li>
<li><strong>Holiness of a place:</strong> Section 4(1) declares that the religious character of a place of worship “shall continue to be the same as it existed” on August 15, 1947.</li>
<li><strong>Litigation:</strong> Section 4(2) says any suit or legal proceeding with respect to the conversion of the religious character of any place existing on August 15, 1947, pending before any court, shall abate — and no fresh suit or legal proceedings shall be instituted.</li>
<li><strong>Exception for Ayodhya:</strong> Section 5 stipulates that the Act shall not apply to the Ramjanmabhoomi-Babri Masjid case, and to any suit, appeal or proceeding relating to it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the law under challenge?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>cut-off date of August 15, 1947, is “arbitrary, irrational and retrospective</u></strong>” and prohibits Hindus, Jains, Buddhists, and Sikhs from approaching courts to “reclaim” their places of worship.</li>
<li>Such places, he argued, were “<strong><u>invaded” and “encroached” upon by “fundamentalist barbaric invaders</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The right-wing politicians have opposed the law even when it was introduced, arguing that the Centre has no power to legislate on “pilgrimages” or “burial grounds” which is under the state list.</li>
<li>Another criticism against the law is that the cut-off is the date of Independence, which means that the status quo determined by a colonial power is considered final.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-takes-up-pleas-against-places-of-worship-act/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Process of sustainable tourism should be holistic and inclusive</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tourism-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Incredible India</p></div></div><p>“<em>To other Country, I may go as a tourist. But to India I come as a pilgrim</em>”, the words of Martin Luther King says a lot about India’s wisdom and tourism potential.</p>
<h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The three-day National Conference of State Tourism Minister was held at Dharamshala , a first of its kind meeting aimed  to discuss, debate and deliberate on modes and mechanisms to develop tourism in India .</li>
<li>The three-day National Conference concluded with the adoption of “Dharamshala Declaration” which affirms commitment toward developing “sustainable and responsible tourism” and positions India as a “global leader in the tourism sector by 2047”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism is travel for pleasure or business; also the theory and practice of touring, the business of attracting, accommodating, and entertaining tourists, and the business of operating tours.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Types of tourism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Domestic tourism</strong>: Refers to activities of a visitor within their country of residence and outside of their home (e.g. a Indian visiting other parts of India)</li>
<li><strong>Inbound tourism</strong>: Refers to the activities of a visitor from outside of country of residence (e.g. a Spaniard visiting Britain).</li>
<li><strong>Outbound tourism</strong>: Refers to the activities of a resident visitor outside of their country of residence (e.g. an Indian visiting an overseas country).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640662" height="327" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341.jpg 550w" width="580"/>What does sustainable tourism mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sustainable tourism is defined by the UN Environment Program and UN World Tourism Organization as “tourism that takes full account of its current and future economic, social and environmental impacts, addressing the needs of visitors, the industry, the environment and host communities.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the main importance of tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism boosts the revenue of the economy, creates thousands of jobs, develops the infrastructures of a country, and plants a sense of cultural exchange between foreigners and citizens.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640663" height="379" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 605px) 100vw, 605px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan.jpg 1024w" width="605"/>Why tourism is needed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism is not a fad. It is a compulsion driven by the urge to discover new places. Because we have this compulsion to venture into the unknown, we need each other. When humans travel, meet and exchange ideas, civilization flourishes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is “The Dharamshala Declaration” is all about?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Aim of the declaration: </strong>The Dharamshala Declaration aims to recognise India’s role in contributing towards global tourism as well as focusing on recovery by also promoting domestic tourism.</li>
<li><strong>Action plan:</strong> In the declaration, the Tourism Ministry has come up with a with a action plan to encourage more Indians to travel domestically and explore India’s natural, cultural, and spiritual beauty while simultaneously reaching the goal of an ‘Ek Bharat Shrestha Bharat’ (interaction and mutual understanding).</li>
<li><strong>Strategy: </strong>The Tourism Ministry has also been working with the Ministry of External Affairs to identify 20 Indian missions abroad with the highest tourist footfalls to India and build country-specific strategies to attract foreign tourists.</li>
<li><strong>Plan according to G-20: </strong>The Dharamshala Declaration affirms the plan to position India as a major tourism destination during its presidency of G-20 next year. India’s age-old dictum of ‘Atithi Devo Bhava’ will come to the fore as it welcomes delegates from the 20 countries/European Union.</li>
<li><strong>Necessary steps:</strong> The Ministry of Tourism also plans to work with other Ministries to bring in necessary interventions such as visa reforms, ease of travel, travel-friendly and improved immigration facilities at airports.</li>
<li><strong>National Tourism policy</strong><strong>:</strong> Drafted with a holistic vision and strategy to revive India’s tourism and targets to contribute USD 1 trillion to the GDP by 2047.<strong><br/>
</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640666" height="519" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 692px) 100vw, 692px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1200x900.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1980x1485.jpg 1980w" width="692"/>A draft on National <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gujarats-mice-tourism-policy/">Tourism Policy 2022</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Framework:</strong></li>
<li>Draft on National Tourism Policy 2022 aims at improving the framework conditions for tourism development in the country.</li>
<li>Supporting tourism industries, strengthening tourism support functions and developing tourism sub-sectors.</li>
<li>Impetus to digitalisation, innovation and technology through the National Digital Tourism Mission and skilling through the Tourism and Hospitality Sector Skill Mission.</li>
<li>The policy also gives a special impetus to private sector participation through public-private-partnerships (PPP)</li>
<li><strong>Guiding Principles</strong> :</li>
<li>Promoting sustainable, responsible and inclusive tourism in line with our civilisational ethos From Gautama to Gandhi, India has always spoken about the inherent need to live harmoniously with nature and within our means.</li>
<li>The National Green Tourism Mission aims at institutionalising green approach.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.incredibleindia.org/content/incredible-india-v2/en.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640665" height="375" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 666px) 100vw, 666px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-768x433.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism.jpg 1170w" width="666"/>Tourism Potential in India</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Employement generation:</strong> India has huge tourism potential. If capitalised properly it can emerge as one of the leading sectors to contribute to GDP and also has the potential to augment employment.</li>
<li><strong>The Pandemic cost and recovery: </strong>The pandemic has caused conspicuous losses for this sector but over the past few months, all the major tourism indices such as domestic air passenger traffic, hotel occupancy and tourist footfalls have shown signs of recovery and are going back to pre-pandemic levels.</li>
<li><strong>Short term estimate:</strong> By 2024, in short term the country is estimated to contribute USD 150 billion to the GDP from tourism, USD 30 billion in Foreign Exchange earnings and can get 15 million foreign tourist arrivals..</li>
<li><strong>Medium term by 2030:</strong> It is estimated to grow at seven to nine per cent Compound Annual Growth Rate in the coming decade. In the medium term, that is 2030, the tourism-related goals are USD 250 billion GDP contribution; 137 million jobs, 56 million foreign tourist arrivals and USD 56 billion in foreign exchange earnings.</li>
<li><strong>Visionary schemes</strong>: The visionary schemes like Swadesh Darshan or Dekho Apna Desh have the potential to increase tourism value while maintaining cultural integrity and ecological sustainability of the places.</li>
<li><strong>Dekho Apna Desh</strong>: Dekho apna desh rolled out in 2020 envisages encouraging domestic tourism, urging people to visit places in India. India is a land of rich cultural heritage.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>If the goal of positioning of India as one of the world’s best tourism destinations by 2047, there is need to integrate various schemes of different ministries. Need to involve various stakeholders, and local communities; necessary interventions at urban and rural level should be a priority.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Since the positive and negative outcomes of tourism depend on human factors, including the attitude and behavior of both tourists and hosts, in this context discuss India’s potential to become a global leader in tourism sector.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tourism-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Carl-Gustaf M4 to be produced in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gustaf-m4-to-be-produced-in-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Carl-Gustaf M4</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="gustaf" class="alignnone wp-image-641101 size-full" height="853" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav.jpg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav-300x237.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav-1024x809.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav-768x607.jpg 768w" width="1080"/></p>
<p>Swedish defense major SAAB announced plans to manufacture its Carl-Gustaf M4 weapon system in India.</p>
<h4>What is the Carl-Gustaf M4?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Carl-Gustaf recoilless rifle is a man-portable, multi-role weapon system that allows dismounted soldiers to effectively deal with multiple challenges on the modern battlefield.</li>
<li>A proven performer in battle, the Carl-Gustaf M4 is said to be adaptable and flexible.</li>
<li>The Indian Army has been using the iconic Carl-Gustaf since 1976 and currently operates the Mk2 and Mk3 versions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Key features of Carl-Gustaf M4</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lightweight, robust, reliable, effective and easy to use</li>
<li>Tactical flexibility through a wide range of ammunition</li>
<li>Combat proven system</li>
<li>Ammunition: Anti-armour, anti-structure, anti-personnel, support</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In recent years, the Indian government has taken several steps to boost the defense manufacturing sector under the ‘Make in India’ and <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-self-reliance-in-defence/">‘Atmanirbhar Bharat’</a></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gustaf-m4-to-be-produced-in-india/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Jaldoot App to capture data on Groundwater Levels</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/jaldoot-app-to-capture-data-on-groundwater-levels/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Jaldoot App</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-641102" height="451" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 372px) 100vw, 372px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-248x300.jpg 248w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-845x1024.jpg 845w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-768x931.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-743x900.jpg 743w" width="372"/></p>
<p>With the rapidly declining water table threatening to push many regions into drought, the Union government on has launched a mobile application — Jaldoot.</p>
<h4>Jaldoot App</h4>
<ul>
<li>Jaldoot is jointly developed by the Rural Development and Panchayati Raj Ministries to monitor the groundwater levels across the country.</li>
<li>The App will enable Gram Rojgar Sahyak to measure the water level of well twice a year pre-monsoon and post-monsoon.</li>
<li>Jaldoots, that is, officers assigned to measure the water levels, should also upload the geo-tagged photographs through the app on every occasion of measurement.</li>
<li>This Mobile app will work in both online and offline mode.</li>
<li>So water level can be captured even without internet connectivity and captured date will be stored in mobile and when mobile comes in the connectivity area, data will synchronize with the central server.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Utility of the app</h4>
<ul>
<li>The despite promoting watershed development, afforestation, waterbody development and renovation, rainwater harvesting like initiatives, the ground water level in various parts of the country has depleted.</li>
<li>The regular data to be input by the Jaldoots would be integrated with the database of National Water Informatics Centre (NWIC), which can be utilised for analysis and display.</li>
<li>The app will facilitate in observing water tables across the country and the resulting data can be utilised for Gram Panchayat Development Plan and Mahatma Gandhi NREGA Plans.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/jaldoot-app-to-capture-data-on-groundwater-levels/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Places in news: Ram Setu</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-ram-setu/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ram Setu</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="ram setu" class="alignnone wp-image-641104 size-full" height="313" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 556px) 100vw, 556px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/setu.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/setu.jpg 556w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/setu-300x169.jpg 300w" width="556"/></p>
<p>A movie has once again generated buzz around the chain of shoals off the southeast coast of India that many believe is the Ram Setu or the bridge to Lanka mentioned in the Ramayana.</p>
<h4>The Ram Setu</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Ram Setu, also known as Adam’s Bridge, is a 48-km chain of limestone shoals between Rameswaram on India’s southeast coast and Mannar Island near Sri Lanka’s northwest coast.</li>
<li>The structure has significance in both Hindu and Muslim mythology – while Hindus believe this is the bridge (Setu) built by Lord Ram and his army to cross to Lanka and fight Ravan.</li>
<li>As per Islamic legend, Adam used this bridge to reach Adam’s Peak in Sri Lanka, where he stood on one foot for 1,000 years in repentance.</li>
</ul>
<p>Factual details of the bridge</p>
<ul>
<li>Scientists believe Ram Setu is a natural structure formed due to tectonic movements and sand getting trapped in corals.</li>
<li>However, over the years, evidence has been offered to claim that the bridge is man-made.</li>
<li>The bridge is not entirely natural, Hindu right wing outfits argue, which proves that it was indeed built by Lord Ram.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When was the structure came into highlights?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Ram Setu issue snowballed into a major controversy when the Sethusamudram Project, flagged off during the UPA I government.</li>
<li>The project aimed to reduce travel time between the eastern and western coasts of India, as ships would no longer have to circle Sri Lanka to travel between the Bay of Bengal and Arabian Sea.</li>
<li>The project was perceived as an attack on Hindu sentiments.</li>
<li>Various studies have been proposed on the Ram Setu, with the most recent being in 2021, when the government approved an underwater research project to ascertain its origins.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Ecological arguments against the project</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Sethusamudram project has been opposed on environmental grounds.</li>
<li>Some claims that it will harm marine life, and that dredging of the line of shoals will make India’s coast more vulnerable to tsunamis.</li>
<li>In March 2018, the Centre told the Supreme Court that the Ram Setu will not be affected in the execution of the Sethusamudram Shipping Canal project.</li>
</ul>
<h4>NASA images, and other proofs</h4>
<ul>
<li>Images of the Ram Setu clicked by NASA have been used over and over again to claim that this proves the existence of a man-made bridge.</li>
<li>NASA has repeatedly clarified that it does not agree with these claims.</li>
<li>Remote sensing images or photographs from orbit cannot provide direct information about the origin or age of a chain of islands.</li>
<li>It certainly cannot be determined whether humans were involved in producing any of the patterns seen.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-ram-setu/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Maharashtra Election Symbols Issue</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/maharashtra-election-symbols-issue/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Allocation of election symbols</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>In a blow to one faction, a Constitution Bench of the Supreme Court allowed the Election Commission (EC) to take a decision on the Maharashtra CM claim that his faction represents the “real” party.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Bench led by Justice D.Y. Chandrachud rejected the plea to stay the EC proceedings under the Election Symbols (Reservation and Allotment) Order of 1968.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A party has lost a large number of members in the rebellion that eventually caused the fall of the government in Maharashtra.</li>
<li>The rebel has claimed to be the only original leader of the party on the basis of the support of more than two-thirds of the party’s legislators in the Maharashtra Assembly.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Options for ECI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ECI in all likelihood can freeze the symbol so that neither of the two sides is able to use it until a final decision is made.</li>
<li>EC hearings are long and detailed, and may take at least six months.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>EC’s powers in Election Symbol Dispute</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The question of a split in a political party outside the legislature is dealt by Para 15 of the Symbols Order, 1968.</li>
<li>It states that the ECI may take into account all the available facts and circumstances and undertake a test of majority.</li>
<li>The decision of the ECI shall be binding on all such rival sections or groups emerged after the split.</li>
<li>This applies to disputes in recognised national and state parties.</li>
<li>For splits in registered but unrecognized parties, the EC usually advises the warring factions to resolve their differences internally or to approach the court.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How did the EC deal with such matters before the Symbols Order came into effect?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Before 1968, the EC issued notifications and executive orders under the Conduct of Election Rules, 1961.</li>
<li>The most high-profile split of a party before 1968 was that of the CPI in 1964.</li>
<li>A breakaway group approached the ECI in December 1964 urging it to recognise them as CPI(Marxist). They provided a list of MPs and MLAs of Andhra Pradesh, Kerala and West Bengal who supported them.</li>
<li>The ECI recognised the faction as CPI(M) after it found that the votes secured by the MPs and MLAs supporting the breakaway group added up to more than 4% in the 3 states.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the first case decided under Para 15 of the 1968 Order?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It was the first split in the Indian National Congress in 1969.</li>
<li>Indira Gandhi’s tensions with a rival group within the party came to a head with the death of President Dr Zakir Hussain on May 3, 1969.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Is there a way other than the test of majority to resolve a dispute over election symbols?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In almost all disputes decided by the EC so far, a clear majority of party delegates/office bearers, MPs and MLAs have supported one of the factions.</li>
<li>Whenever the EC could not test the strength of rival groups based on support within the party organisation (because of disputes regarding the list of office bearers), it fell back on testing the majority only among elected MPs and MLAs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What happens to the group that doesn’t get the parent party’s symbol?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The EC in 1997 did not recognise the new parties as either state or national parties.</li>
<li>It felt that merely having MPs and MLAs is not enough, as the elected representatives had fought and won polls on tickets of their parent (undivided) parties.</li>
<li>The EC introduced a new rule under which the splinter group of the party — other than the group that got the party symbol — had to register itself as a separate party.</li>
<li>It could lay claim to national or state party status only on the basis of its performance in the state or central elections after registration.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/maharashtra-election-symbols-issue/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why India has lashed out at the US over its F-16 package to Pakistan?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-india-has-lashed-out-at-the-us-over-its-f-16-package/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>F-16</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>US's double standards over Pakistan</p></div></div><p><img alt="f-16" class="alignnone wp-image-641100 size-full" height="447" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f-16.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f-16.jpg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f-16-300x224.jpg 300w" width="600"/></p>
<p>EAM S Jaishankar has lashed out at the US for its decision to provide Pakistan with a $450 million package for F-16 case fighter aircraft upgrade.</p>
<h4>F-16 and Pakistan</h4>
<ul>
<li>The F-16 is a single-engine multirole fighter aircraft originally developed by General Dynamics for the United States Air Force (USAF).</li>
<li>Designed as an air superiority day fighter, it evolved into a successful all-weather multirole aircraft.</li>
<li>The F-16 were inducted into Pakistan Air Force in 1983 during the Soviet-Afghan War.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Suspicion over US move</h4>
<ul>
<li>This is the first American military assistance package to Pakistan after the Trump Administration.</li>
<li>Mr Trump ended defence and security co-operation with Pakistan in 2018 after accusing it of giving only “lies and deceit” for the billions of dollars that the US had “foolishly” given it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What specific reasons has the Biden Administration given for its decision?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As per US version, the proposed sale does not include any new capabilities, weapons, or munitions.</li>
<li>The upgrade package aimed to retain interoperability with US and partner forces in ongoing counter-terrorism efforts and in preparation for future contingency operations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did US provide F-16 to the US?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has been concerned about the F-16s from the time the US first gave Pakistan F-16s as a reward for its assistance in the first Afghan war.</li>
<li>The US then had supplied weapons and money to Pakistan to unleash armies of jihadists against the Soviet Army.</li>
<li>When the US objective was achieved with the Soviet Union’s departure from Afghanistan, the US too resized its relations with Pakistan.</li>
<li>The Pressler Amendment, aimed against Pakistan’s nuclear ambitions, froze it out of military assistance.</li>
<li>A decade later, the Bush Administration not only approved the release of previously blocked F-16s, but also provided a refurbishment package, and sale of new F-16s.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s concerns</h4>
<ul>
<li>As pointed out by EAM, how the F-16s help in counter-terrorism remains unclear.</li>
<li>Jaishankar questioned the merits of the US-Pakistan partnership.</li>
<li>He said that the relations had “not served” either country (but created more troubles for India).</li>
<li>This move by the US will alter the basic military balance in the region.</li>
<li>The decision to provide military aid to Pakistan incensed India as the F-16 was used against Indian warplanes following the 2019 Balakot air strikes.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>Washington’s $450 million package has only resurrected old prejudices centred on the US not being a dependable ally for ever.</li>
<li>India needs to respond firmly and in no uncertain terms to the PAF’s F-16 upgrade programme to convey the message that India cannot be taken for granted.</li>
<li>India will have to effectively enhance the conventional combat capability of the IAF to continue to meet the challenge of a resurgent PAF.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-india-has-lashed-out-at-the-us-over-its-f-16-package/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India and UNSC</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-quest-for-permanent-membership-of-unsc/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UN Security council</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>International Relations</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641313" height="506" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 843px) 100vw, 843px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5edc92b402a52-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5edc92b402a52-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5edc92b402a52.jpg 500w" width="843"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is greater support for India to be a permanent member of the UN Security Council and also a broad global consensus over the need to reform the Council, said External Affairs Minister S Jaishankar. India has once again renewed its bid for permanent membership of UNSC.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">What is UNSC?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The United Nations Security Council (UNSC) is one of the six principal organs of the United Nations (UN) and is charged with ensuring international peace and security, recommending the admission of new UN members to the General Assembly, and approving any changes to the UN Charter.</li>
<li>Its powers include establishing peacekeeping operations, enacting international sanctions, and authorizing military action. The UNSC is the only UN body with the authority to issue binding resolutions on member states.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641314" height="509" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 697px) 100vw, 697px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_11largeimg_1702223617-300x219.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_11largeimg_1702223617-300x219.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_11largeimg_1702223617.jpg 660w" width="697"/>What is the composition of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/g4-countries-call-for-unsc-reforms/">UNSC</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Presently there five permanent members (P-5) with veto and 10 non-permanent members without veto elected for tenure of 2 years.</li>
<li>India has been the non-permanent member multiple times. Presently India is serving its tenure that will end in December 2022.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641315" height="469" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 833px) 100vw, 833px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1658498206-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1658498206-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1658498206.jpg 715w" width="833"/>Who are P-5 members?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The victors of World War 2 – USA, RUSSIA, CHINA, UK, FRANCE.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the hurdles that India facing?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Elite club:</strong> Most exclusive club in international relations. All other clubs have been breached. Until a quarter century ago, the nuclear weapon club had five members, the same five as the P-5.India, Pakistan, North Korea and Israel have since joined the club. But UNSC is unbreachable till date.</li>
<li><strong>All are reluctant: </strong>The inescapable fact is that none of the P-5 wants the UNSC’s ranks to be increased. One or the other of them might make some noise about supporting one or more of the aspirants. Each is confident that someone among them will torpedo the enlargement of the club. Declarations of support for India’s candidature need to be taken with a fistful of salt.</li>
<li><strong>Veto issue: </strong>Former UN Secretary-General Kofi Annan bluntly told India not to expect to get the veto power. Though India has said it will not accept a seat without veto power.</li>
<li><strong>China-Pakistan axis: </strong>China, which has historically blocked India’s aspirations to become a permanent member of the UNSC. Beijing has an “all-weather ally” in Islamabad, another neighbour who also strongly opposes India’s candidature to the UNSC.</li>
<li><strong>Odd man out: </strong>Four out of the five permanent members of the United Nations Security Council have bilaterally expressed official affirmations of support for India’s candidature to a permanent seat in an expanded UN Security Council.</li>
<li><strong>Coffee club opposition: </strong>Members like Italy, South Korea, Canada, Spain, Mexico, Turkey, Argentina, Pakistan, and others, who have together formed the Uniting for Consensus (UfC) movement. Also known as the Coffee Club, the movement argues that bids for permanent seats by India, Japan, Germany, and Brazil (G4 countries) must not be considered without first reaching an international consensus regarding the form and size of the new Security council.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641318" height="310" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768.jpeg 770w" width="550"/>What are the Efforts taken by India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Text based negotiation: </strong>External affairs minister is canvassing for the country’s candidature, meeting his counterparts from several countries. He has repeated the call, made often in the past, for a text-based negotiation on what has been euphemistically referred to as the reform of the United Nations Security Council (UNSC), i.e., negotiation on a written document outlining the proposed reform instead of just holding forth verbally.</li>
<li><strong>Woking together with G-4: </strong>INDIA, JAPAN, GEMANY, BRAZIL works together to get permanent UNSC seat however these efforts are opposed by coffee club.</li>
<li><strong>Multilateral engagements: </strong>By expanding its footprint in multilateral organisations, India is gearing up to become a global rule-maker.</li>
<li>Distinguished group of experts suggested a few years ago that a new category of semi-permanent members should be created. Countries would be elected for a period of eight to 10 years and would be eligible for re-election. India ought to give serious consideration to this idea.</li>
<li><strong>With or without veto: </strong>According to former foreign secretary Chinmaya gharekhan, if by some miracle we are offered or manage to obtain permanent membership without veto, we must grab it. Even a permanent membership without veto will be tremendously helpful in protecting our interests.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Looking at the present geopolitical divide India’s dream of seat at the highest table is unlikely to get fulfilled in near future. India must analyse the utility of UNSC membership for securing its national interest. India should not give up anything in bargain against UNSC seat which harms its international interest.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. India’s quest for UNSC is like “Sisyphus carrying the boulder  just to see how it falls”. In this context Analyse the utility of Permanent seat at UNSC.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-quest-for-permanent-membership-of-unsc/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Urban planning can change the future of cities to happy cities</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-planning/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Urbanization issues</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Urban planning" class="alignnone wp-image-629340" height="285" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 506px) 100vw, 506px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city.jpg 1280w" width="506"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the recent few years, the growth of the economy and urbanization have accelerated. Rapid unplanned urbanization has put extreme pressure on natural resources.</li>
<li>Unplanned urbanization, however, exerts great strain on our cities. In fact, the Covid-19 pandemic has revealed the dire need for the planning and management of our cities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does urban planning mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Urban planning, also known as regional planning, town planning, city planning is a technical and political process that is focused on the development and design of land use and the built environment, including air, water, and the infrastructure passing into and out of urban areas, such as transportation, communications, and distribution networks and their accessibility.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are ‘Happy Cities’?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A term that follows the Green City, Sustainable City, Liveable City, in the lingo of urban planning</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a smart city?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A smart city is one that uses information and communication technologies to enhance citizen engagement. It is a neo-vision which seeks to improve the delivery of services in urban areas. The following story maps out the steps being taken by India to explore this concept in practice.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Smart Cities Mission?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sustainable cities</strong>: The Smart Cities Mission aims at developing 100 cities, which were shortlisted, into self-sustainable urban settlements.</li>
<li><strong>Chronology</strong>: The mission was launched on June 25, 2015 and was projected as one aimed at transforming the process of urban development in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Comprehensive revamp</strong>: Among its strategic components is ‘area-based development’, which includes city improvement (retrofitting), city renewal (redevelopment) and city extension (Greenfield development), plus a pan-city initiative in which ‘smart solutions’ are applied covering larger parts of the city.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Fast Facts – Urbanization in India</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Most Urbanized States: Tamil Nadu 43.9%; Maharashtra 4%; Gujarat  37.4%</li>
<li>3 out of world’s 21 mega cities: Mumbai (19 mill); Delhi (15 mill); Kolkata (14 mill)</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Urban planning" class="alignnone wp-image-629341" height="216" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 514px) 100vw, 514px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84-300x126.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84-300x126.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84.jpg 450w" width="514"/>Urban planning challenges </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Planning</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Many urban governments lack a modern planning framework</li>
<li>The multiplicity of local bodies obstructs efficient planning and land use</li>
<li>Rigid master plans and restrictive zoning regulations limit the land available for building, constricting cities’ abilities to grow in accordance with changing needs<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Housing</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Building regulations that limit urban density – such as floor space indexes – reduce the number of houses available, thereby pushing up property prices</li>
<li>Outdated rent control regulations reduce the number of houses available on rent – a critical option for the poor</li>
<li>Policy, planning, and regulation deficiencies lead to a proliferation of slums</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Service delivery</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is a strong bias towards adding physical infrastructure rather than providing financially and environmentally sustainable services</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Infrastructure</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Most urban bodies do not generate the revenues needed to renew infrastructure, nor do they have the creditworthiness to access capital markets for funds</li>
<li>Urban transport planning needs to be more holistic – there is a focus on moving vehicles rather than meeting the needs of the large numbers of people who walk or ride bicycles in India’s towns and cities.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Environment:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The deteriorating urban environment is taking a toll on people’s health and productivity and diminishing their quality of life.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Urban planning" class="alignnone wp-image-629343" height="301" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 572px) 100vw, 572px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120.jpg 1200w" width="572"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-reforms-in-urban-planning-capacity-in-india/">Solution offered by NITI ayog committee report on urban planning</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Demystifying Planning and Involving Citizens: </strong>While it is important to maintain the master plans’ technical rigour, it is equally important to demystify them for enabling citizens’ participation at relevant stages. Therefore, the committee strongly recommends a ‘Citizen Outreach Campaign’ for demystifying urban planning.</li>
<li><strong>Steps for Enhancing the Role of Private Sector: </strong>The report recommends that concerted measures must be taken at multiple levels to strengthen the role of the private sector to improve the overall planning capacity in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Revision of Town and Country Planning Acts: </strong>Most States have enacted the Town and Country Planning acts, that enable them to prepare and notify master plans for implementation. However, many need to be reviewed and upgraded.</li>
<li><strong>Revision of Town and Country Planning Acts: </strong>Most States have enacted the Town and Country Planning Acts, that enable them to prepare and notify master plans for implementation. However, many need to be reviewed and upgraded.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Interesting fact </strong></p>
<p>India is home to 11% of the total global urban population.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Government initiatives</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Atal Mission for Rejuvenation and Urban Transformation (AMRUT);</li>
<li>Pradhan Mantri Awas Yojana (PMAY) – Housing for all (Urban),</li>
<li>Smart Cities Mission (SCM),</li>
<li>Swachh Bharat Mission (SBM),</li>
<li>Heritage City Development and Augmentation Yojana (HRIDAY);</li>
<li>Deen Dayal Antyodaya Yojana – National Urban Livelihoods Mission (DAY-NULM).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>What is now increasingly understood, is that urban planning and design can be a powerful contributor to the happiness of citizens. The structure and layout of our streets, the availability of green spaces, the possibility of using urban spaces freely, the inclusion of beauty in public space.</li>
<li>It is safe to assume that when there are avenues for a community to come together in a pleasant environment, which is accessible to everyone, it can only increase well-being.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>Can urban planning and design change Indian cities to be happy cities? Express your views by addressing the roadblocks in the same.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-planning/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Advantage of Market Based Economic Dispatch</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/market-based-economic-dispatch-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economics,Energy,Infrastructure</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641126" height="316" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-3-1.jpg" width="565"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The game changing scheme is being proposed by the central government in power sector governance. The scheme under consideration is the market-based economic dispatch (MBED). When it comes to any drastic change in the power sector, a clash between the Centre and the states is inevitable.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Market Based Economic Dispatch (MBED)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Market Based Economic Dispatch (MBED) is new approach towards power distribution to help distribution companies save costs and transition to a new form of power market.</li>
<li>It is a shift to a centralised framework, marks a radical departure from the current decentralised, voluntary pool-based electricity market.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641122" height="291" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-1-2.jpg" width="508"/>What is the framework under MBED?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The cheapest power from across the country will be dispatched to meet the system wide demand. The architecture would also lead to a “Market clearing price”.</li>
<li>Sellers and buyers will place their bids for the day market, and an outcome of this will be the discovery of the market clearing price.</li>
<li>This process is expected to generate significant savings for consumers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Present system of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/assessment-of-discoms/">power Distribution?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Under the present regime, each distribution company (Discom) is bound by the power purchase agreements (PPAs) that it holds.</li>
<li>It can schedule power only from its own PPAs, starting from the cheapest PPA and then moving up; it cannot schedule power from the PPA of some other distribution company.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> <img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641124" height="365" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-2.jpg" width="488"/></strong><strong>What are the drawbacks of present system?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Financial Burdon:</strong></li>
<li>The Indian government responded to COVID-19’s economic shock with a stimulus package of Rs.20-lakh crore, out of which Rs.90,000 crore was earmarked for discoms (later upgraded to Rs.1,25,000 crore). While it was called a stimulus, it is really a loan, meant to be used by discoms to pay off generators.</li>
<li>Discoms owe one lakh crore rupees to generators, and without such an infusion the chain will collapse.</li>
<li><strong>States are defaulters:</strong></li>
<li>State governments are the biggest defaulters, responsible for an estimated a third of trade receivables, besides not paying subsidies in full or on time.</li>
<li>On an annual cash flow basis, the shortfall in subsidy payments appears very low, only about 1% but cumulative unpaid subsidies, with modest carrying costs, make discoms poorer by over Rs.70,000 crore just over the last 10 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641125" height="323" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-12-1.jpg" width="570"/>What will be the Advantages of MBED?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Centralized approach: </strong>The centralised dispatch will be done with the assistance of electricity exchanges. Each discom and each generator will place a bid in the day-ahead market of the electricity exchanges, which will indicate how much power is being demanded/ supplied at what price.</li>
<li><strong>Pan India market: </strong>These bids will enable the load dispatcher to construct a pan India demand and supply curve, the intersection of which will determine the market clearing price (MCP). All generators whose variable cost of generation is below the MCP will be asked to dispatch and all of them will receive the same MCP irrespective of what they had bid. Generators whose variable cost is higher than the MCP will sit idle.</li>
<li><strong>No loss to discom: </strong>The MBED is so devised that its operation will not affect the current finances of either the discoms or the generators for the following reasons.</li>
<li>First, the fixed cost of the generators will still be paid by the discoms outside the market as determined by the regulator.</li>
<li>Second, if the MCP comes out to be Rs 3 per unit, and if in the case of any PPA, the variable cost is Rs 2.75 per unit, then the generator will compensate the discom to the extent of Rs 0.25 per unit. Similarly, if the MCP so determined is Rs 2.50 per unit, then the discom will compensate the generator to the extent of Rs 0.25 per unit.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing efficiency: </strong>The logic is that by adopting MBED, only the relatively efficient plants will generate, without affecting the revenues of either the discoms or generators. Hence, the total cost of generation under the MBED system would be less.</li>
<li><strong>Less pollution: </strong>There would be less coal consumption and less carbon dioxide injected into the atmosphere.</li>
<li><strong>Easy integration with renewable: </strong>It would also mean less movement of coal leading to decongestion of railway tracks. Further, there would be enhanced renewable integration since the balancing area would shift from state to national level.</li>
<li><strong>Single market clearing price (MCP): </strong>Incidentally, since there are three electricity exchanges in operation today, there would be three different MCPs determined. What we need is a single MCP for which there will be an institution called the “market coupler”. It will be the job of the coupler to determine a national MCP based on what has arrived at the three different exchanges.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why states are opposing?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>High generation cost: </strong>The reason is the state-owned generators are relatively inefficient and may have to sit idle as their variable cost of generation is likely to be more than the MCP.</li>
<li><strong>Political backlash: </strong>Today, the states are operating their own generators to the hilt, even though they are inefficient, and drawing only the balance from the more efficient interstate generating stations. Keeping state generators idle has its own political implications and no state would be enamoured of this idea.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Power distribution companies (discom) are sinkhole of government finances. Every year budgetary support is needed to this loss-making companies , With due consultation, all states and union territories need to adopt and implement the MBED and save the resources for other development activities.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. </strong><strong>India has became the power surplus nation, however power distribution and financial unsustainability is still a nightmare for union and states. Elaborate.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/market-based-economic-dispatch-2/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian Railways powerful experiment on AC III tier economy class coaches</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ac-iii-tier-economy-class-coaches/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economics, Infrastructure,Transport</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="AC III tier economy class coaches" class="alignnone wp-image-641307" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 633px) 100vw, 633px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-300x171.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-300x171.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1024x583.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-768x437.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1536x874.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-2048x1166.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1200x683.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1980x1127.jpg 1980w" width="633"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian Railways’ experiment to introduce AC III tier economy class coaches has started to pay off. Since its introduction, in the last one year, these coaches have earned the Railways more than Rs.230 crore in revenue.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="AC III tier economy class" class="alignnone wp-image-641094" height="289" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-6.jpg" width="514"/>What is </strong><strong>AC III tier economy class coach?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AC 3 tier economy class in Indian Railways is a milestone concerning pocket-friendly traveling experience for common man.</li>
<li>With fare slightly more than sleeper class and lower than conventional AC class.</li>
<li>The objective of the railway is to move sleeper class passengers to a comfortable AC class with luxurious facilities. AC-3 tier comprises air-conditioned coaches with 64 sleeping berths.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>When it is introduced?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian Railway has introduced the first AC III tier Economy Class for North Central Railway Zone in 2021 to provide a convenient traveling experience to the passengers<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>As of now 7 trains are equipped with AC III tier economy class coaches are running on the tracks</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="AC III tier economy class coaches" class="alignnone wp-image-641308" height="377" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 669px) 100vw, 669px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038.jpg 1600w" width="669"/>Features of the AC </strong>III<strong> tier economy coach</strong><strong>:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pocket friendly</strong>: According to the Indian Railways, the fair in these coaches are cheaper than the normal AC three-tier coach. Fares in AC III tier economy are 6%-7% cheaper than the AC III tier class. The economy class has a capacity of 83 berths compared to 72 in the regular coach.</li>
<li><strong>Divyang friendly and modern designs: </strong>The coaches were specially designed for the convenience of the divyangs. Providing Improved and modular design of berths and ergonomically designed ladder for accessing the middle and upper berths etc.</li>
<li><strong>Modern features: </strong>In these, modern arrangements have been made for mobile phones and magazine holders, fire safety, personalised reading lights, AC vents, USB points, mobile charging points.</li>
<li><strong>Optimum Speed</strong>: These air-conditioned three-tier economy class coaches are capable of running at an optimum speed of 160 kilometers per hour.</li>
<li><strong>More Capacity:</strong> The economy class has a capacity of 83 berths compared to 72 in the regular coach.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the current status of AC </strong><strong>III tier class?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>AC- III tier, the favorite mode of train travel of people falling in the bottom rung of the middle class, is the only class that earns the Railways profit among all its passenger services.</li>
<li>The AC III tier is the only class of service which has generated consistent profits for the Railways. Between FY16 and FY20,</li>
<li>AC III tier coaches carried only 1% of the total passengers, but were responsible for 21% of the earnings from travelers. Such a low-passenger, high-revenue dichotomy was not seen in any other class.</li>
<li>It is not as expensive as the other AC classes and at the same time, its share in revenue has not been impacted by the relatively low pricing</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong style="letter-spacing: -0.0415625em;"><img alt="AC III tier economy class coaches" class="alignnone wp-image-641309" height="464" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 619px) 100vw, 619px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84998782-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84998782-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84998782.jpg 400w" width="619"/>Revenue of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vande-bharat-production-to-begin/">Indian railways</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The overall revenue of Indian Railways at the end of August 2022 was Rs 95,486.58 crore, showing an increase 38 per cent over the corresponding period of last year.</li>
<li>Goods revenue climbed by Rs 10,780.03 crore (or 20 per cent) to Rs 65,505.02 crore till August-end this year</li>
<li>The revenue from passenger traffic was Rs 25,276.54 crore, an increase of Rs 13,574.44 crore (116 per cent) year-on-year.</li>
<li>Passenger traffic also increased compared to last year in both the segments — reserved and unreserved</li>
<li>Railways’ total revenue during the entire last fiscal (2021-22) stood at Rs.1,91,278.29 crore.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the issues faced by Indian railways to increase its revenue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cross Subsidized: </strong>The cross-subsidiszation in respect of second class, ordinary class and suburban services has increased continuously in the past five years with subsidy on ordinary class being the maximum,</li>
<li><strong>Concessional fare</strong>: The revenue forgone in passenger earnings due to concessions to various categories of passengers (physically challenged persons, patients, senior citizens, Izzat monthly season tickets, press correspondents, sport persons and war widows among others) increased from Rs 1,994.83 crore in 2018-19 to Rs 2,058.61 crore in 2019-20.</li>
<li><strong>Low -Revenue dichotomy in Expensive class:</strong> A high-passenger, low-revenue dichotomy was seen in the inexpensive classes. For instance, over 90% passengers travelled by second class which accounted for only 37% of the earnings.</li>
<li><strong>Operational Los</strong><strong>s</strong>: Operational losses (in crore) incurred while operating various classes of service. For instance, in operating AC first class service, the Railways incurred a loss of 403 crore in FY20</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Adding more AC III tier economy class coaches is a step in the right direction as it has shown positive result in revenue generation for railways and it provides a travel with dignity to a common man. But If Indian railway has to benefit it have to work extensively on operational loss incurred out of low Revenue dichotomy in Expensive classes.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. Indian Railways is often referred to as the lifeline of the country but runs at a loss when it comes to running class-divided coaches. In this context discuss the utility of class divided coaches.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ac-iii-tier-economy-class-coaches/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Ranipur TR: 4th Tiger Reserve in UP</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ranipur-tr-4th-tiger-reserve-in-up/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ranipur Tiger Reserve</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="ranipur" class="alignnone wp-image-641605 size-full" height="939" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tiger-reserves.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tiger-reserves.jpg 780w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tiger-reserves-249x300.jpg 249w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tiger-reserves-768x925.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tiger-reserves-748x900.jpg 748w" width="780"/></p>
<p>The UP cabinet approved the notification of Ranipur Tiger Reserve under Section 38(v) of the Wild life (Protection) Act of 1972.</p>
<h4>About Ranipur WS</h4>
<ul>
<li>Ranipur WS, was founded in 1977, is one of the attractions of Chitrakoot district in Uttar Pradesh.</li>
<li>It is spread over 230 sq.km and is noted for its diverse wildlife, but is not very frequently visited by tourists because of the difficult access.</li>
<li>The Ranipur TR has tropical dry deciduous forests and is home to fauna such as tigers, leopards, sloth bears, spotted deer, sambhar, chinkara and a number of birds and reptiles, the statement added.</li>
<li>The Ranipur TR will be the fourth in UP, after Dudhwa, Pilibhit and Amangarh (buffer of Corbett Tiger Reserve).</li>
<li>It will also be the first in the state’s portion of the Bundelkhand region, which it shares with neighbouring Madhya Pradesh.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why make it a tiger reserve?</h4>
<ul>
<li>RWS has no tigers of its own.</li>
<li>But pugmarks of the animals are frequently seen there as tigers from nearby Panna frequent it.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ranipur-tr-4th-tiger-reserve-in-up/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Forex Reserves to dip by $23 billion by Dec</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/forex-reserves-to-dip-by-23-billion-by-dec/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Forex reserves, BoP</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>India’s depleted foreign exchange reserves are likely to drop further, falling to their lowest level in more than two years by end-2022.</p>
<h4><strong>Forex to dip<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In a battle that has so far failed to staunch the rupee’s fall to a record low against the greenback, the RBI has drawn down its foreign exchange reserves by close to $100 billion, to $545 billion.</li>
<li>Those reserves are forecast to fall another $23 billion to $523 billion by the end of this year.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Foreign Exchange (Forex) Reserve?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Foreign exchange reserves are important assets held by the central bank in foreign currencies as reserves.</li>
<li>They are commonly used to support the exchange rate and set monetary policy.</li>
<li>In India’s case, foreign reserves include Gold, Dollars, and the IMF’s quota for Special Drawing Rights.</li>
<li>Most of the reserves are usually held in US dollars, given the currency’s importance in the international financial and trading system.</li>
<li>Some central banks keep reserves in Euros, British pounds, Japanese yen, or Chinese yuan, in addition to their US dollar reserves.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>India’s forex reserves cover:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Foreign Currency Assets (FCAs)</li>
<li>Special Drawing Rights (SDRs)</li>
<li>Gold Reserves</li>
<li>Reserve position with the International Monetary Fund (IMF)</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Countries with the highest foreign reserves</strong></h4>
<p>Currently, China has the largest reserves followed by Japan and Switzerland. India has overtaken Russia to become the fourth largest country with foreign exchange reserves. (Data from August 2022)</p>
<ol>
<li>China – $3,349 Billion</li>
<li>Japan – $1,376 Billion</li>
<li>Switzerland – $1,074 Billion</li>
<li>India – $612.73 Billion</li>
<li>Russia – $597.40 Billion</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Why are these reserves so important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>All international transactions are settled in US dollars and, therefore, required to support India’s imports.</li>
<li>More importantly, they need to maintain support and confidence for central bank action, whether monetary policy action or any exchange rate intervention to support the domestic currency.</li>
<li>It also helps to limit any vulnerability due to sudden disturbances in foreign capital flows, which may arise during a crisis.</li>
<li>Holding liquid foreign currency provides a cushion against such effects and provides confidence that there will still be enough foreign exchange to help the country with crucial imports in case of external shocks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Initiatives taken by the government to increase forex</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To increase the foreign exchange reserves, the Government of India has taken many initiatives like AatmaNirbhar Bharat, in which India has to be made a self-reliant nation so that India does not have to import things that India can produce.</li>
<li>Other than AatmaNirbhar Bharat, the government has started schemes like Duty Exemption Scheme, Remission of Duty or Taxes on Export Product (RoDTEP), Nirvik (Niryat Rin Vikas Yojana) scheme, etc.</li>
<li>Apart from these schemes, India is one of the top countries that attracted the highest amount of Foreign Direct Investment, thereby improving India’s foreign exchange reserves.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/forex-reserves-to-dip-by-23-billion-by-dec/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre extends Free Ration Scheme PMGKAY for 3 months</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-extends-free-ration-scheme-pmgkay-for-3-months/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PMGKAY</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Schemes related to food security</p></div></div><p>The Union government has extended the Pradhan Mantri Garib Kalyan Anna Yojana (PMGKAY) for another three months from October 1.</p>
<h4><strong>What is PMGKAY?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>PMGKAY is a food security welfare scheme announced by the GoI in March 2020, during the COVID-19 pandemic in India.</li>
<li>The program is operated by the Department of Food and Public Distribution under the Ministry of Consumer Affairs, Food and Public Distribution.</li>
<li>The scale of this welfare scheme makes it the largest food security program in the world.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Targets of the scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To feed the <strong>poorest citizens of India</strong> by providing grain through the <strong>Public Distribution System</strong> to all the priority households (ration card holders and those identified by the Antyodaya Anna Yojana scheme).</li>
<li>PMGKAY provides <strong>5 kg of rice or wheat</strong> (according to regional dietary preferences) <strong>per person/month</strong> and <strong>1 kg of dal</strong> to each family holding a ration card.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>At what rate are food grains provided under the NFSA?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>NFSA beneficiaries are entitled to receive foodgrains at highly subsidised rates.</li>
<li>Under the food law, rice is provided at Rs 3 per kg, wheat at Rs 2 per kg, and coarse grains at Re 1 per kg.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why was such a scheme needed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The devastation by pandemic has increased manifold in the second wave resulting into localized restrictions and lockdowns from the States.</li>
<li>This resulted in massive jobs losses in urban areas since the largest employers being construction and hospitality sectors have been completely shut down.</li>
<li>The virus penetrated deeper in the countryside in rural areas halting almost every sources of livelihood.</li>
<li>These areas are such where 60% of the income was earned from non-pharm activities. This resulted in livelihood losses of large section of population.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Success of the scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It was the first step by the government when pandemic affected India.</li>
<li>The scheme reached its targeted population feeding almost 80Cr people.</li>
<li>It has proven to be more of a safety net to migrant people who had job and livelihood losses.</li>
<li>This has also ensured nutrition security to children of the migrant workers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Failures</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme has been affected by widespread corruption, leakages and failure to distribute grain to the intended recipients.</li>
<li>Several of the states above have claimed that the ineffective distribution has been caused by the beneficiaries, especially migrant workers, not being available to receive their rations.</li>
<li>Out of the 79.25 crore beneficiaries under the National Food Security Act (NFSA), only 55 crore have so far received their 5 kg.</li>
<li>However, almost 90% of beneficiaries have received their regular subsidized grain for the month, raising questions over why the free grain has reached fewer beneficiaries.</li>
<li>Many people were denied their share due to inability to access ration cards.</li>
<li>Livelihood losses led to decline in aggregate demand and resulted into lowest ever consumption expenditure by the people owing to scarcity of cash.</li>
<li>This in turn led to selling of the free grains obtained in the local markets for cash.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There should be an all-encompassing database for migrant workers and their family. This should accurately capture the data on migration.</li>
<li>The One Nation One Ration Card should be implemented in true spirit by all the states.</li>
<li>Along with food security, there should be a sustainable income support through schemes like MGNREGS accompanied by free vaccines in nearest future.</li>
<li>The leakages in PDS should be minimized through modernize PDS.</li>
<li>To avoid leakages, there should be food-token system.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-extends-free-ration-scheme-pmgkay-for-3-months/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>MHA bans PFI for five years under UAPA</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mha-bans-pfi-five-years-under-uapa/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UAPA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Terror financing and money laundering</p></div></div><p>The Union Home Ministry has declared the Popular Front of India (PFI) and its front organizations as an “unlawful association” under the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act (UAPA).</p>
<h4><strong>PFI under Unlawful (Activities) Prevention Act (UAPA)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The UAPA is aimed at effective prevention of unlawful activities associations in India.</li>
<li>Its main objective was to make powers available for dealing with activities directed against the integrity and sovereignty of India</li>
<li>It is an upgrade on the Terrorist and Disruptive Activities (Prevention) Act TADA, which was allowed to lapse in 1995 and the Prevention of Terrorism Act (POTA) was repealed in 2004.</li>
<li>It was originally passed in 1967 under the then Congress government led by former Prime Minister Indira Gandhi.</li>
<li>Till 2004, “unlawful” activities referred to actions related to secession and cession of territory. Following the 2004 amendment, “terrorist act” was added to the list of offences.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Unlawful Activities and Associations?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The UAPA lays down the definitions and rules for designating an organisation as an “unlawful association” if it is engaged in certain types of activities.</li>
<li>Under Section 3 of the UAPA Act, the government has powers to declare an association “unlawful”.</li>
<li>The government can then issue a notification designating such an organisation as a terrorist organisation, if it believes that the organisation is part of “terrorist activities.”</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(1) Unlawful Activites</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Under section 2(o) of the UAPA, an unlawful activity in relation to an individual or association means – Any action taken by such an individual or association (whether by committing an act or by words, either spoken or written, or by signs or by visible representation or otherwise), –</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Works for the <strong><u>Cession of a part of the territory of India</u></strong> or the secession of a part of the territory of India from the Union</li>
<li>Disclaims, questions, disrupts or is intended to <strong><u>Disrupt the sovereignty and territorial integrity of India</u></strong>; or</li>
<li>which causes or is intended to cause <strong><u>Disaffection against India</u></strong>;</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Related and ancillary acts, including financing, support or promotion of any such activities are also “unlawful activity”.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Unlawful Association</strong></p>
<p>The UAPA also defines an “Unlawful Association” under section 2(p) as meaning any association,–</p>
<ol>
<li>which has for its object any unlawful activity, or which <strong><u>encourages or aids persons to undertake any unlawful activity</u></strong>, or of which the members undertake such activity or</li>
<li>which <strong><u>encourages or aids persons to undertake any such activity</u></strong>, or of which the members undertake any such activity</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Reading the ban on PFI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At present, the MHA notification published has said that the PFI and its affiliated organisations are being notified as “Unlawful Associations” with immediate effect.</li>
<li>The charges against PFI are-</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Pursuing a secret agenda to radicalize a particular section of society</li>
<li>Working towards undermining the concept of democracy and</li>
<li>Showing sheer disrespect towards the constitutional authority and constitutional set up of the country</li>
<li>Gathering funds and ideological support from outside the country</li>
<li>Money laundering</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Immediate trigger for PFI’s ban</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PFI is accused of engaging in violent and barbaric acts.</li>
<li>Criminal violent acts carried out by PFI include chopping off the limb of a college professor, cold-blooded killings of persons associated with organisations espousing other faiths.</li>
<li>It has been allegedly involved in obtaining explosives to target prominent people and places and destruction of public property.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does the ‘ban’ mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The notification means that the membership of, support or financing to the PFI and the allied banned organizations, is now ILLEGAL.</li>
<li>Any person who is a member of these organisations can face arrest, and joining membership of these organisations is a criminal offence.</li>
<li>The government can also seize the properties, bank accounts and offices connected to these organisations.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mha-bans-pfi-five-years-under-uapa/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Is Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022 Flawless?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/draft-telecommunications-bill/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Right to Privacy</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Cyber security,Right to privacy,Technology</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641528" height="415" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 622px) 100vw, 622px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31.jpeg 1200w" width="622"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Keeping an eye on the telecommunication regulatory framework Supreme Court issued substantive legal reform on surveillance laws in India. Union government has published the Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022 to replace the Telegraph Act, 1885.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Over two decades ago, allegations of surveillance against politicians led to a CBI inquiry and report against V P Singh’s government. The allegations revealed that imaginary reasons were given for ordering phone tapping without authorization.</li>
<li>Last years, many publications reported that phones of several dozen Indian journalists, lawyers and human rights activists had been compromised using an invasive Israeli-developed malware called Pegasus.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641527" height="406" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58.jpeg 1024w" width="608"/>What is Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The draft Indian Telecommunication Bill, 2022 is an attempt by the Department of Telecommunications (DoT) to consolidate various legislations presently governing the telecommunication landscape in India.</li>
<li>The Bill seeks to replace three laws, the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885, the Indian Wireless Telegraphy Act, 1933 and the Telegraph Wires (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1950.</li>
<li>The new regulatory framework is to bring the law at par with technological advancements and remove obsolete provisions from the colonial era laws.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the current laws governing communication surveillance in India?</strong></h4>
<p>Communication surveillance in India takes place primarily under two laws:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Telegraph Act, 1885</strong>: It deals with interception of calls.</li>
<li><strong>Call interception:</strong>Under Section 5(2) of this law, the government can intercept calls only in certain situations.</li>
<li><strong>For sovereignty:</strong>They include the interests of the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the state, friendly relations with foreign states or public order, or for preventing incitement to the commission of an offense.</li>
<li><strong>Free speech restrictions:</strong>These are the same restrictions imposed on free speech under Article 19(2) of the Constitution.</li>
<li><strong>Exceptions for journalists:</strong>A provision in Section 5(2) states that even this lawful interception cannot take place against journalists.</li>
<li><strong>Information Technology Act, 2000: </strong>It was enacted to deal with surveillance of all electronic communication, following the Supreme Court’s intervention in 1996.</li>
<li><strong>Electronic surveillance:</strong>Section 69 of the IT Act and the IT (Procedure for Safeguards for Interception, Monitoring, and Decryption of Information) Rules, 2009 were enacted to further the legal framework for electronic surveillance.</li>
<li><strong>Data interception:</strong>Under the IT Act, all electronic transmission of data can be intercepted.</li>
<li>Section 69 of the IT Act adds another aspect that makes it broader — interception, monitoring, and decryption of digital information “for the investigation of an offense”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641524" height="631" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-278x300.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-278x300.jpeg 278w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-768x829.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-834x900.jpeg 834w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56.jpeg 949w" width="585"/>How the loopholes in the current system breaching the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-privacy/">Data Privacy?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>No comprehensive data Protection Law: </strong></li>
<li>No comprehensive data protection law leaving ambiguities over several laws.</li>
<li>A comprehensive data protection law to address the gaps in existing frameworks for surveillance is yet to enact.</li>
<li><strong>Unaccountable, opaque exercise of surveillance: </strong></li>
<li>The Telegraph Act contains broad and excessive powers of interception and surveillance of communications carried out through any telegraph.</li>
<li>The surveillance power is principally contained under Section 5(2), and has resulted in an unaccountable, opaque and unconstitutional exercise of surveillance that has led to accusations across the political spectrum.</li>
<li><strong>Less transparency:</strong></li>
<li>Ministry of Home Affairs refuses to disclose even aggregate data on the number of surveillance orders issued by it each year illegally gathered evidence is being sought to prosecute people.</li>
<li>For instance, the Bombay High Court about three years ago noted in a case that premier investigating agencies such as the CBI have used, interception orders (that) neither have sanction of law nor issued for legitimate aim.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641526" height="398" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 596px) 100vw, 596px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-1024x682.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-1200x800.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00.jpeg 1280w" width="596"/>Key features of</strong> <strong>the</strong> <strong>Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Broad Definitions: </strong></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>The Bill introduces a broad definition of ‘telecommunication services’.</li>
<li>It now includes internet-based services, in-flight and maritime connectivity, interpersonal communications services, machine to machine communication services, and over-the-top (OTT) based communication services that are made available to users by telecommunication</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>KYC and caller id requirements: </strong></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>The Bill requires licensed entities to ensure that they identify the persons to whom they provide telecommunication services.</li>
<li>The Bill places an obligation on telecommunication service providers to do this through a ‘verifiable mode’, as prescribed by the government.</li>
<li><strong>Licensing, registration, and authorization:</strong></li>
<li>Under the Bill, four types of permissions are identified – license, registration, authorization and assignment.</li>
<li>While the Bill does not differentiate between the four types of permissions, it clarifies that a license is only required for providing telecommunication services or operating telecommunication networks</li>
<li><strong>Wide ranging powers of Central Government: </strong></li>
<li>The Bill includes wide-ranging powers for the central and state governments in the event of a public emergency or in interest of public safety.</li>
<li>These powers include taking temporary possession of any telecommunication services, suspension of transmission in cases of public emergency, interception/detainment/disclosure of messages, suspension of communications, or otherwise transmit certain announcements for public safety and national security purposes.</li>
<li><strong>User protection and duties: </strong>User has been declared as an important policy objective of the Government. It places a duty on users to not furnish false information, suppress material information or impersonate others when proving identity to avail telecommunication services.</li>
<li><strong>Offences and penalties</strong>: Any offence under the Bill may be punished with a fine, imprisonment, suspension of telecommunication services or a combination of the above. For companies, the employees who were responsible for the conduct or the business relating to the offence at the time the offence was committed will be punished.</li>
<li><strong>Dispute resolution mechanism</strong>: The Bill provides for the right of appeal before the appellate authority. It also creates an enabling provision for the Central Government to set up an alternate dispute resolution mechanism such as arbitration, mediation or other processes of dispute resolution</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Concerns over the Draft Telecommunication bill, 2022?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Regulatory overlaps:</strong>The broad of the definition of ‘telecommunication services’ include OTT communication platforms such as WhatsApp, Telegram, Signal among others, may potentially lead to regulatory or jurisdictional overlaps.</li>
<li><strong>Unchecked use of State powers:</strong>The Bill gives broad powers to the central government in prescribed situations without any accompanying checks and balances. The Bill empowers the central and state government to intercept messages in the interest of public safety and emergency without the providing clearly defined guardrails for it.</li>
<li><strong>Undefined National security: </strong>The term, national security is left undefined and does not match constitutional precedent or text which instead uses the phrase,in the interests of the security of state</li>
<li><strong>Users Less choice in the privacy and security of their digital footprint:</strong></li>
<li>Power to prescribe standards under Clause 23, which may result in regulations as recently issued by the Computer Emergency Response Team (CERT-In) that have resulted in the closure of servers or services by leading, global VPN providers such as Proton and TunnelBear.</li>
<li>All of this practically means that users will have less choice in the privacy and security of their digital footprint, as these powers will lead to requirements to locally register and host data, and comply with requirements to identify users (KYC requirements).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There should be some reasonable basis or some tangible evidence to initiate or seek approval for interception by State authorities. Any digression from the ethical and legal parameters set by law would be tantamount to a deliberate invasion of citizens.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Any deviation from the moral and legal parameters set by the law would amount to a deliberate attack on citizens. In this context discuss the data privacy of citizens in the era of massive expansion of internet and mobile usage.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/draft-telecommunications-bill/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Transboundary Flood Disasters</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/transboundary-flood-disasters/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Transboundary Rivers</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Disaster Management</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Transboundary Flood Disasters" class="alignnone wp-image-641871 size-full" height="444" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 828px) 100vw, 828px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fld.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fld.jpg 828w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fld-300x161.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fld-768x412.jpg 768w" width="828"/></strong></h4>
<h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Pakistan experiencing devastation, with a spread of diseases and severe shortage of potable water after intense flooding. In June this year Assam experienced one of its worst floods in which it affected over 30 districts. Assam and Bihar frequently suffer from transboundary flood disasters.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-recurring-floods-in-india/">transboundary flood</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Floods that are originate in upper riparian state crosses the international boundary and also affects the lower riparian state. For example, river Brahmaputra causes flood both in China and India simultaneously.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Transboundary Flood Disasters" class="alignnone wp-image-641877 size-full" height="463" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.59.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.59.jpeg 800w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.59-300x174.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.59-768x444.jpeg 768w" width="800"/>How the transboundary floods are difficult to manage than <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/floods/">normal floods</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Flooding is still considered to be a natural phenomenon that cannot be entirely prevented. But it is compounded by the lack of transparency in the sharing of hydrological information and also information relating to activities (such as by one riparian state) that are transboundary in their effect (affecting other riparian states), thus serving as an obstacle in understanding the magnitude of flooding<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Transboundary Flood Disasters" class="alignnone wp-image-641552" height="370" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 654px) 100vw, 654px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1.jpeg 1085w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1-1024x579.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1-768x434.jpeg 768w" width="654"/>What is a riparian state?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A riparian state is state (or country) located alongside a river.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the International laws governing transboundary waters?</strong></h4>
<p>There are at two international treaties that governs the transboundary water</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>UNWC:</strong></li>
<li>United Nations Convention on the Law of the Non-Navigational Use of International Watercourses (UNWC) 1997.UNWC contains a direct reference to floods, which covers harmful conditions and the emergency situations.</li>
<li>Article 27 of the Convention says, Watercourse States shall individually and, where appropriate, jointly, take all appropriate measures to prevent or mitigate conditions that may be harmful to other watercourse States, whether resulting from natural causes or human conduct or desertification.</li>
<li><strong>Environmental Impact Assessment: </strong></li>
<li>The International Court of Justice (ICJ), in the Pulp Mills on the River Uruguay (Argentina vs Uruguay) case of 2010, upheld that conducting a transboundary environmental impact assessment (TEIA) of a planned measure or projects on the shared water course is part of customary international law.</li>
<li>In fact, the ICJ noted that the acting state must notify the affected party of the results of TEIA for assessment of its own damages that are likely to occur.</li>
<li><strong>UNECE: </strong>United Nations Economic Commission for Europe (UNECE) on the Protection and Use of Transboundary Watercourses and International Lakes 1992 (Water Convention).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Transboundary Flood Disasters" class="alignnone wp-image-641881" height="908" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 586px) 100vw, 586px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31.jpeg 720w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31-194x300.jpeg 194w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31-661x1024.jpeg 661w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31-581x900.jpeg 581w" width="586"/>How India manages transboundary flood?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Note:</strong>Neither India nor China are signatory to UNWC or UNCEC.</li>
<li><strong>River Brahmaputra:</strong> India has signed the memorandum of understanding (MoU) with China in 2013 with a view to sharing hydrological information during the flood season (June to September). The MoU does not allow India access to urbanisation and deforestation activities on the Chinese side of the river basin.</li>
<li><strong>Rivers Gandak and kosi</strong>: Floods are also a recurrent problem in the Kosi and Gandak river basins that are shared by India and Nepal.</li>
<li><strong>The India-Nepal Kosi agreement 1954: </strong>Agreement aimed at reducing devastating flooding in the river basin. The treaty-based joint bodies have also tried to refine the early warning systems for flood forecasting.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the suggestions?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Signing the treaty: </strong>Expert suggests, India by becoming a party to either the UNWC and the Water Convention could lay the groundwork for a bilateral treaty on the Brahmaputra but subject to the reservation that it should not insist on the insertion of a dispute settlement mechanism provision<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Information exchange: </strong>In contravention of procedural customary international law obligation, India considers data on transboundary rivers as classified information, which is one of the key challenges in developing cross-border flood warning systems. India needs to share the hydrological and river information for its own sake.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Climate change has accelerated the frequency and intensity of floods across the world. with Changing climate India should also change its strategy to protect its people, to preserve the soil and to save its resources from the scourge of floods.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Questions</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Climate change has created a more difficult challenge in flood management. In this context, what measures can be taken to deal with frequent transboundary floods in India. Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/transboundary-flood-disasters/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Stressed ecology of Bay of Bengal</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bay-of-bengal/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Location,BIMSTEC,Centre for Bay of Bengal Studies</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Foreign Policy,Regional Grouping</p></div></div><h4></h4>
<h4><strong><img alt="Bay of Bengal" class="alignnone wp-image-641718 size-large" height="487" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1024x487.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1024x487.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-300x143.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-768x365.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1536x731.jpeg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1200x571.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1980x942.jpeg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31.jpeg 2048w" width="1024"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At the fourth BIMSTEC summit, Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced the opening of the Centre for Bay of Bengal Studies (CBS) at Nalanda University. The launch of the CBS has once again demonstrated India’s commitment to advancing constructive agendas by forging connections and setting up platforms for all those with an interest in the of Bay of Benagl.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Bay of Bengal" class="alignnone wp-image-641724" height="547" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 545px) 100vw, 545px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-3-1.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-3-1.jpg 224w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-3-1-150x150.jpg 150w" width="545"/>Why <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/opportunity-to-propel-a-bay-of-bengal-dream/">Bay of Bengal</a> is so important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Commerce hub: </strong>The Bay has long been a major commerce hub for the Indian Ocean. It created a conduit between the East and the West in terms for trade and culture.</li>
<li><strong>Emerging arena of maritime warfare: </strong>An Indo-Pacific orientation and the realignment of global economic and military power towards Asia have had a considerable impact on the Bay region.</li>
<li><strong>Communication and Energy</strong>: The key sea lanes of communication in this area are lifelines for global economic security and are crucial to the energy security that powers the economies of many countries in the region.Further, non-traditional dangers including terrorism and climate change have become more prevalent.</li>
<li><strong>Under water resources: </strong>The Bay also provides an opportunity for greater regional cooperation in the environmentally friendly exploration of marine and energy resources. The Bay has a biodiverse marine environment.</li>
<li><strong>Fresh water resources: </strong>It receives the water from some of the world’s largest rivers. It is a partially enclosed sea that has given rise to several geological characteristics.</li>
<li><strong>Ecology: </strong>It is home to many rare and endangered marine species and mangroves, which are essential to the survival of the ecology and the fishing sector.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Bay of Bengal" class="alignnone wp-image-641722" height="422" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 632px) 100vw, 632px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S2352485520306678-gr1.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S2352485520306678-gr1.jpg 565w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S2352485520306678-gr1-300x200.jpg 300w" width="632"/>Why ecology in the region is under threat?</strong></h4>
<p>The region’s maritime environment has changed as are result of major powers expanding their economic and geopolitical influence.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Competition: </strong>Political and cultural engagement, together with economic competition, have taken on new dimensions. More crucially, the Bay’s ecosystem is going through an unprecedented crisis brought on by widespread environmental exploitation and geopolitical unrest.</li>
<li><strong>Resource exploitation</strong>: Species extinction is a result of careless exploitation of the maritime environment, which has severe consequences on biodiversity. Problems such as population growth, altered land use, excessive resource exploitation, salinity, sea level rise, and climate change are exerting significant strain on the Bay’s environment.</li>
<li><strong>Water pollution</strong>: Operational discharge from small and medium feeder ships, shipping collisions, unintentional oil spills, industrial waste, pollution, and the accumulation of non- biodegradable plastic litter are all contributing to the deterioration of the Bay.</li>
<li><strong>Declining ecology</strong>: A dead-zone has formed, and the mangrove trees that protect the shore from the fury of nature are under more threat than ever.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-641728" height="472" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S0959652620334545-fx1-e1664446288766.jpg" width="529"/>What could be the Solutions?</strong></h4>
<p>For a better knowledge of challenges, and strategies to overcome them for the sustainable development of the region, more focused and inter-disciplinary study is required on these issues.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Centre for Bay of Bengal studies: </strong>By founding the CBS, Nalanda University has already started its journey and given the nation a unique interdisciplinary research centre devoted to Bay focused teaching, research, and capacity building. Additionally, scholars from many countries and academic streams are already participating in CBS’s first certificate programme on the Bay.</li>
<li><strong>Inter-governmental cooperation: </strong>It is essential that nautical neighbours develop a partnership and cooperate because of the maritime domain’s interrelated and interdependent nature, transnational character, and cross-jurisdictional engagement of various governments and diverse organisations and enterprises.</li>
<li><strong>Maritime connectivity: </strong>A few concerns that need immediate attention include expanding cooperation in maritime safety and security, enhancing cooperation on maritime connectivity and the ease of maritime transit, and boosting investment possibilities in the maritime connectivity sector.</li>
<li><strong>Illegal activities: </strong>The latter subject involves addressing non-traditional threats and fostering group efforts to reduce illicit, unreported, and unregulated fishing.</li>
<li><strong>Data sharing: </strong>Standardising and harmonising data reporting.</li>
<li><strong>Balanced approach: </strong>Furthermore regional marine entities should strive to balance opportunities and goals on a national, regional, and international scale.</li>
<li><strong>Investment in R&amp;D: </strong>Littoral governments need to support and promote skill-building, research, and training.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Countries in the Bay of Bengal need to mobilise investments, manage maritime affairs more effectively. Alternative lifestyle should be explored. The cooperation of all member states, for information gathering, sharing and result oriented actions is crucial in protecting the ecology of Bay of Bengal.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Countries in the Indian subcontinent are developing rapidly, putting serious stress on the environment of the Bay of Bengal.Mention the challenges and suggest solutions.</strong></p></blockquote>
<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bay-of-bengal/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>All women have Right to Legal and Safe Abortion: Supreme Court</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-legal-and-safe-abortion/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>MRTP Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Abortion rights debate</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has held that all women, irrespective of their marital status, are entitled to safe and legal abortion till 24 weeks of pregnancy under the Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act.</p>
<h4><strong>A case for safe abortion<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A Bench led by Justice D.Y. Chandrachud was hearing the appeal of a woman who wanted to abort her 24-week pregnancy after her relationship failed and her partner left her.</li>
<li>The lower court had taken an “<strong><u>unduly restrictive view</u></strong>” that her plea for a safe abortion was not covered under the Medical Termination of Pregnancy Act.</li>
<li>This was since the pregnancy arose from a consensual relationship outside wedlock.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the last amendment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The court noted that an amendment to the Act in 2021 had <strong><u>substituted the term ‘husband’ with ‘partner’</u></strong>, a clear signal that the law covered unmarried women within its ambit.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reiterating the live-in recognition</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Chastising the lower court, the Bench said live-in relationships had already been recognised by the Supreme Court.</li>
<li>There were a significant number of people in social mainstream who see no wrong in engaging in pre-marital sex.</li>
<li>The law could not be used to quench “<strong><u>notions of social morality</u></strong>” and unduly interfere in their personal autonomy and bodily integrity.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>About Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Abortion in India has been a legal right under various circumstances for the last 50 years since the introduction of the<strong> <u>Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act in 1971</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Act was amended in 2003 to enable women’s access to safe and legal abortion services.</li>
<li>Abortion is covered 100% by the government’s public national health insurance funds, Ayushman Bharat and Employees’ State Insurance with the package rate for surgical abortion.</li>
</ul>
<p>The idea of terminating your pregnancy cannot originate by choice and is purely circumstantial. There are four situations under which a legal abortion is performed:</p>
<ol>
<li>If continuation of the pregnancy poses any <strong><u>risks to the life of the mother</u></strong> <strong>or <u>mental health</u></strong></li>
<li>If the <strong><u>foetus has any severe abnormalities</u></strong></li>
<li>If pregnancy occurred as a result of <strong><u>failure of contraception</u></strong> (but this is only applicable to married women)</li>
<li>If pregnancy is a result of <strong><u>sexual assault or rape</u></strong></li>
</ol>
<p>The pregnancy can be terminated upto 24 weeks of gestational age after the opinion of two registered medical practitioners under these conditions —</p>
<ul>
<li>If the woman is ​​either a survivor of sexual assault or rape or incest</li>
<li>If she is a minor</li>
<li>If her marital status has changed during the ongoing pregnancy (i.e. either widowhood or divorce)</li>
<li>If she has major physical disabilities or is mentally ill</li>
<li>On the grounds of foetal malformation incompatible with life or if the child is born, it would be seriously handicapped</li>
<li>If the woman is in humanitarian settings or disaster, or emergency situations as declared by the government</li>
</ul>
<p>These are the key changes that the Medical Termination of Pregnancy (Amendment) Act, 2021, has brought in:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong><u>The gestation limit for abortions has been raised from the earlier ceiling of 20 weeks to 24 weeks</u></strong>, but only for special categories of pregnant women such as rape or incest survivors. But this termination would need the approval of two registered doctors.</li>
<li><strong><u>All pregnancies up to 20 weeks require one doctor’s approval</u></strong>. The earlier law, the MTP Act 1971, required one doctor’s approval for pregnancies upto 12 weeks and two doctors’ for pregnancies between 12 and 20 weeks.</li>
<li><strong><u>Women can now terminate unwanted pregnancies caused by contraceptive failure</u></strong>, regardless of their marital status. Earlier the law specified that only a “married woman and her husband” could do this.</li>
<li><strong><u>There is also no upper gestation limit for abortion in case of foetal disability</u></strong> if so decided by a medical board of specialist doctors, which state governments and union territories’ administrations would set up.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Criticism of Abortion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Foetuses feel the pain:</strong> If the foetus is beyond 20 weeks of gestation, gynaecs assume that there will be pain caused to the foetus.</li>
<li><strong>Abortions cause psychological damage:</strong> Young adult women who undergo abortion may be at increased risk for subsequent depression.</li>
<li><strong>Abortions reduce the number of adoptable babies:</strong> Instead of having the option to abort, women should give their unwanted babies to people who cannot conceive. Single parenthood is also gaining popularity in the US.</li>
<li><strong>Cases of selective abortion:</strong> Such cases based on physical and genetic abnormalities (eugenic termination) is overt discrimination.</li>
<li><strong>Abortion as a form of contraception:</strong> It is immoral to kill an unborn child for convenience. Many women are using abortion as a contraceptive method.</li>
<li><strong>Morality put to question:</strong> If women become pregnant, they should accept the responsibility that comes with producing a child. People need to take responsibility for their actions and accept the consequences.</li>
<li><strong>Abortion promotes throwaway culture:</strong> The legalization of abortion sends a message that human life has little value and promotes the throwaway culture.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Arguments in favour for Abortion Rights</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Upholding individual conscience and decision-making:</strong>  The US Supreme Court has declared abortion to be a fundamental right guaranteed by the US Constitution.</li>
<li><strong>Reproductive choice empowers women:</strong> The choice over when and whether to have children is central to a woman’s independence and ability to determine her future.</li>
<li><strong>Foetal viability occurs post-birth:</strong>  Personhood begins after a foetus becomes “viable” (able to survive outside the womb) or after birth, not at conception. Abortion is the termination of a pregnancy, not a baby.</li>
<li><strong>No proof of foetal pain:</strong> Most neuroscientists believe that the cortex is necessary for pain perception. The cortex does not become functional until at least the 26th week of a foetus’ development.</li>
<li><strong>Preventing illegal abortions:</strong> Access to legal, professionally-performed abortions reduces maternal injury and death caused by unsafe, illegal abortions.</li>
<li><strong>Mother’s health:</strong> Modern abortion procedures are safe and do not cause lasting health issues such as cancer and infertility.</li>
<li><strong>Child’s health:</strong> Abortion gives pregnant women the option to choose not to bring fetuses with profound abnormalities to full term.</li>
<li><strong>Prevents women’s exclusion:</strong> Women who are denied abortions are more likely to become unemployed, to be on public welfare, to be below the poverty line, and to become victims of domestic violence.</li>
<li><strong>Reproductive choice protects women from financial disadvantage:</strong> Many women who choose abortion don’t have the financial resources to support a child.</li>
<li><strong>Justified means of population control:</strong> Many defends abortion as a way to curb overpopulation. Malnutrition, starvation, poverty, lack of medical and educational services, pollution, underdevelopment, and conflict over resources are all consequences of overpopulation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Hence it is now established that the right to abortion is a legal right of all women.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-legal-and-safe-abortion/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>