<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 01:49:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Backsliding on climate action</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/backsliding-on-climate-action/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Paris agreement</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Climate change</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>Europe is staring at a recession and its appetite for climate action is waning.</p>
<h4>Developed countries moving away from commitment</h4>
<ul>
<li>Countries in Europe led by Germany, Austria and the Netherlands are cranking up their coal plants again.</li>
<li>Fossil fuels are making a comeback and countries are rejecting the European Union (EU)’s plan to reduce natural gas consumption by 15%. Dutch, Polish and other European farmers are protesting against emission cuts from agriculture.</li>
<li>In the U.S. too, the Senate and the Supreme Court have struck blows to climate action.</li>
<li>And in the U.S. too, prices of fuel started increasing last year, not just this year.</li>
<li>Fossil fuels are making a quiet comeback, since the strength of the U.S. is its oil and gas industry.</li>
<li>That is why we have just witnessed a ‘re-calibration’ of U.S. policy towards the Gulf.</li>
<li>Coal, oil and gas are not going anywhere in the developed world; they are, in fact, making a comeback.</li>
<li>The West had rushed to draw down on fossil fuels even before technology for renewables were in place.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Global peaking issue</h4>
<ul>
<li>Article 4 of the Paris Agreement defines ‘Global Peaking’ thus: “In order to achieve the long-term temperature goal set out in Article 2, Parties aim <strong>to reach global peaking</strong> of greenhouse gas emissions as soon as possible, recognizing that peaking will take longer for developing country Parties.”</li>
<li>The developed countries, given their historical emissions, will have to peak first.</li>
<li>That’s why the reference is to<strong> ‘global peaking’</strong> and not ‘individual peaking’.</li>
<li>From this, it logically follows that when developing country parties peak later than developed countries, they will also achieve net zero later than developed countries.</li>
<li>Consequently, it is the logical conclusion of the Article 4 of the Paris Agreement that when we consider net zero, we should only consider ‘global net zero’ and not ‘individual net zero’ for 2050.</li>
<li>The statement calls on developed countries to do a net negative on mitigation by 2050 rather than just “net zero”, if they are serious about fighting climate change.</li>
<li>In effect, the West needs to do a net minus and not just net zero.</li>
<li>Thanks to the efforts of India, the phrase used in the 2021 summit-level declarations at both G-20 and Quad is ‘global net zero’. We need to build on this understanding.</li>
<li>India stands as beacon of hope in renewables.</li>
<li>It is time for all developing countries, especially the small island developing states, to make sure that the developed world doesn’t backslide on its commitments on mitigation yet again.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward for developing countries</h4>
<ul>
<li>With countries of the developed world almost sure to renege on their 2030 Paris Agreement commitments, countries of the developing world must do everything to hold the countries of the developed world to their commitments.</li>
<li>The Western nations have already started reinterpreting the Paris Agreement and look to downgrade their commitments.</li>
<li>The concept of net zero is being cleverly misinterpreted.</li>
<li> To bring this to the attention of the Global South, India, China and eight other countries from Africa, Asia and Latin America made a cross-regional statement on ‘global net zero’ on June 7 at the UN on World Environment Day.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>COP 27 in Egypt gives us that opportunity to hold their feet to the fire. It is time for the developed world to make net minus pledges. If we don’t collectively push for it, we will be collectively pushed back.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/backsliding-on-climate-action/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian breed of Pet Dogs</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-indian-breed-of-pet-dogs/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Various breeds mentioned</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p>Mudhol hounds, a breed of hunting dogs native to north Karnataka, could be inducted into the Special Protection Group (SPG), the elite force protecting the Prime Minister of India.</p>
<blockquote>
<h4><em>Try this PYQ:</em></h4>
<p><strong><em>Q.What is/are unique about ‘Kharai camel’, a breed found in India?</em></strong></p>
<ol>
<li><em> It is capable of swimming up to three kilometres in seawater.</em></li>
<li><em> It survives by grazing on mangroves.</em></li>
<li><em> It lives in the wild and cannot be domesticated.</em></li>
</ol>
<p><em>Select the correct answer using the code given below:</em></p>
<p><em>(a) 1 and 2 only </em></p>
<p><em>(b) 3 only </em></p>
<p><em>(c) 1 and 3 only </em></p>
<p><em>(d) 1, 2 and 3</em></p>
<p><strong><em>Answer: (a)</em></strong></p></blockquote>
<h4>Famous Indian dog breeds</h4>
<p><strong>(1)Mudhol hounds</strong></p>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273224" height="203" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 321px) 100vw, 321px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/mudhol.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/mudhol.jpg 668w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/mudhol-300x190.jpg 300w" width="321"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The Mudhol hounds come from the region bordering Karnataka and Maharashtra.</li>
<li>According to a popular legend Ch. Shivaji Maharaj bred and used these dogs in his army.</li>
<li>The breed was named after the erstwhile princely state of Mudhol, which was part of the Bombay Presidency in British India.</li>
<li>The last king of the state, King Malojirao Ghorpade, presented a pair of these puppies to King George V when he visited the UK and it was the English emperor who christened the dogs as Mudhol hounds.</li>
<li>Mudhol hounds have narrow heads that are disproportionately smaller to their bodies but are tall in height.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2)Himachali hounds</strong></p>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273223" height="243" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 252px) 100vw, 252px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/hima.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/hima.jpg 442w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/hima-300x289.jpg 300w" width="252"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The Himachali hounds are locally known as the ‘Gaddi’ dog and come from the Himalayan region. They are massive, mastiff-like dogs with thick fur to protect them from the cold.</li>
<li>They look similar to the Tibetan mastiff but are less bulky.</li>
<li>‘Gaddi’ means shepherd in Urdu, and these dogs are primarily guarding livestock.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3)Rajapalayam</strong></p>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273222" height="231" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/rpm.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/rpm.jpg 382w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/rpm-292x300.jpg 292w" width="225"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The breed Rajapalayam is believed to have originated from Tamil Nadu, and named after the state’s Rajapalayam city in the Virudhunagar district.</li>
<li>A rare breed, these dogs are only found in certain pockets of the state.</li>
<li>These dogs are white, lean, muscular, and have historically made good hunters.</li>
<li>They are believed to have fought alongside the Polygar soldiers against the British East India Company during the Polygar wars from 1799 to 1805.</li>
<li>This is why the Rajapalayam dogs are also known as ‘Polygar hounds’.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(4) Kanni and Chippiparai</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273221" height="221" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 296px) 100vw, 296px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/kanni.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/kanni.jpg 532w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/kanni-300x224.jpg 300w" width="296"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The Kanni dog is another breed from Tamil Nadu, and its name translates to “pure” in Tamil after its fierce loyalty.</li>
<li>Like the Rajapalayam, Kanni dogs specialise in hunting hares, wild boars, and blackbucks.</li>
<li>However, since the Wildlife Protection Act of 1972 was passed, these dogs have been acting as guard dogs.</li>
<li>The Kennel Club of India, which maintains a registry of purebred dogs in India, has registered this dog under two names — Kanni and Chippiparai.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(5)Combai</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273220" height="180" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/comba.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/comba.jpg 445w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/comba-300x202.jpg 300w" width="268"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The Combai dogs also originate from Tamil Nadu. They are tan-coloured with a black snout and appear shorter and stouter than the Rajapalayam. They are classified as terriers.</li>
<li>Like the Kanni and Rajapalayam, these dogs are rare and a dying breed and were historically used for boar hunting and guarding purposes.</li>
<li>The CRPF recently recruited Combai dogs into their Dog Breeding and Training School.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-indian-breed-of-pet-dogs/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Assessing anganwadi scheme</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/assessing-anganwadi-scheme/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>ICDS</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- Early childhood care and education</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-625107" height="341" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/anganwadi-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/anganwadi-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/anganwadi.jpg 600w" width="647"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The economic fallout of COVID-19 makes the necessity of quality public welfare services more pressing than ever.</li>
<li>The <strong>Integrated Child Development Services (ICDS)</strong> programme is one such scheme.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is ICDS?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>ICDS caters to the nutrition, health and pre-education needs of children till six years of age as well as the health and nutrition of women and adolescent girls.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is anganwadi scheme?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme was started in 1975 and aims at the holistic development of children and empowerment of mother.</li>
<li>It is a Centrally-Sponsored scheme. The scheme primarily runs through the Anganwadi centre. The scheme is under the Ministry of Women and Child Development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Need for focus on early childhood care and education (ECCE)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low enrolment</strong>: The National Family Health Survey-5 (NFHS-5) finds only 13.6 per cent of children enrolled in pre-primary schools.</li>
<li><strong>Weakest link</strong>: With its overriding focus on health and nutrition, ECCE has hitherto been the weakest link of the anganwadi system.</li>
<li><strong>Low awareness: </strong>Unfortunately, due to a lack of parental awareness compounded by the daily stresses of poverty, disadvantaged households are unable to provide an early learning environment.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Data to remember </strong></h4>
<p><strong>According to government data, the country has 13.77 lakh Anganwadi centres (AWCs).</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>A meaningful ECCE programme in anganwadis</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Activity-based framework which reflect local context: </strong>To design and put in place a meaningful activity-based ECCE framework that recognises the ground realities with autonomy to reflect the local context and setting.</li>
<li><strong>Remove non-ICDS work: </strong>Routine tasks of anganwadi workers can be reduced and non-ICDS work, such as surveys, removed altogether<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Extend Anganwadi time: </strong>Anganwadi hours can be extended by at least three hours by providing staff with an increase in their present remuneration, with the additional time devoted for ECCE.</li>
<li><strong>Change in policy mindset</strong>: ICDS needs a change in policy mindset, both at central and state levels, by prioritising and monitoring ECCE.</li>
<li><strong>Engagement with parents</strong>: Anganwadi workers must be re-oriented to closely engage with parents, as they play a crucial role in the cognitive development of young children.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Case study / value addition </strong></h4>
<p><strong>In Andhra Pradesh and Telangana, anganwadi centres have been geotagged to improve service delivery.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Gujarat has digitised the supply chain of take-home rations and real-time data is being used to minimise stockouts at the anganwadi centres.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Government must act on the three imperatives. First, while infrastructure development and capacity building of the anganwadi remains the key to improving the programme, the standards of all its services need to be upscaled.</li>
<li>Second, states have much to learn from each other’s experiences.</li>
<li>Third, anganwadi centres must cater to the needs of the community and the programme’s workers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Nearly 1.4 million anganwadis of the Integrated Child Development Services (ICDS) across India must provide ECCE for the millions of young children in low-income households.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Some educationists have suggested that owing to the high workload of anganwadi workers, ECCE in anganwadis would remain a non-starter. Critically examine this statement and give dynamic suggestions to improve EECE in anganwadis.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/assessing-anganwadi-scheme/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Tigray Crisis in Ethiopia</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tigray-crisis-in-ethiopia/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Tigray Crisis</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-625105" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tigray-285x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tigray-285x300.jpg 285w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tigray.jpg 343w" width="285"/></strong></p>
<p>The director-general of the World Health Organization (WHO), described the Tigray crisis region as the “worst humanitarian disaster on earth”.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-ethiopian-crisis/">Ethiopia has been on the brink of a civil war.</a></li>
<li>On Nov 4 2020, Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed declared war on the country’s Tigray region.</li>
<li>The Tigray region is ruled by the Tigray People’s Liberation Front (TPLF).</li>
<li>The war was declared in response to the TPLF’s attack on a federal military base in Tigray.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Tigray Crisis: A backgrounder</h4>
<ul>
<li>The animosity between Tigrayans and Eritrea goes back to the Ethiopian-Eritrean war that occurred between 1998 and 2000.</li>
<li>It occurred approximately two decades ago was extremely brutal and resulted in the deaths of thousands of soldiers.</li>
<li>The roots of this crisis can be traced to Ethiopia’s system of government. Since 1994, Ethiopia has had a federal system in which different ethnic groups control the affairs of 10 regions.</li>
<li>The Tigray People’s Liberation Front (TPLF) – was influential in setting up this system.</li>
<li>It was the leader of a four-party coalition that governed Ethiopia from 1991, when a military regime was ousted from power.</li>
<li>Under the coalition, Ethiopia became more prosperous and stable, but concerns were routinely raised about human rights and the level of democracy.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did it escalate into a crisis?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Eventually, discontent morphed into protest, leading to a government reshuffle that saw Mr Abiy appointed PM.</li>
<li>Abiy liberalized politics, set up a new party (the Prosperity Party), and removed key Tigrayan government leaders accused of corruption and repression.</li>
<li>Meanwhile, Abiy ended a long-standing territorial dispute with neighbouring Eritrea, earning him a Nobel Peace Prize in 2019.</li>
<li>These moves won Abiy popular acclaim, but caused unease among critics in Tigray.</li>
<li>Tigray’s leaders see Abiy’s reforms as an attempt to centralize power and destroy Ethiopia’s federal system.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How bad is the humanitarian situation?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Tigray and its neighbouring regions are facing starvation.</li>
<li>There is an absence of medical facilities, no access to their own money due to shut-down banking services, ethnic and physical violence, and raids at the hands of warring forces.</li>
<li>The government declared a ceasefire on humanitarian grounds but in an effort to break the TPLF in June last year, imposed a blockade on Tigray.</li>
<li>This made it impossible to deliver humanitarian, economic, and medical assistance to Tigrayans.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="aEE4Bf4ARr"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-ethiopian-crisis/">[Burning Issue] Ethiopian Crisis and the Geopolitics</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="aEE4Bf4ARr" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-ethiopian-crisis/embed/#?secret=Un8cgPhlLd#?secret=aEE4Bf4ARr" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Burning Issue] Ethiopian Crisis and the Geopolitics” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tigray-crisis-in-ethiopia/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Kerala Savari’: India’s first online taxi service as a public option</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/kerala-savari-indias-first-state-taxi/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Kerala Savari</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Cab aggregators malpractices and their regulation in India</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-625103" height="208" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cabie-300x208.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cabie-300x208.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cabie.jpg 598w" width="300"/></strong></p>
<p>Kerala has soft launched ‘Kerala Savari’, the country’s first online taxi service owned by a State government, to ensure fair and decent service to passengers along with fair remuneration to auto-taxi workers.</p>
<h4>What is Kerala Savari?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Operated by the Motor Workers Welfare Board under the aegis of the Labour Department, the Kerala Savari ensures safe travel for the public at ‘government approved fares’ without any ‘surge pricing’.</li>
<li>The ‘Kerala Savari’ app would be made available to the public on online platforms shortly as it is under the scrutiny of Google now.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why such initiative?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The alleged unfair trade practices and violation of consumer rights by private app-based cab aggregators have come as a major concern for governments.</li>
<li>Recently, the Central Consumer Protection Authority (CCPA) had issued notices to cab aggregators Ola and Uber for unfair trade practices and violation of consumer rights which include:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Charging exorbitant fares during peak hours</li>
<li>Unprofessional behaviour from the part of drivers</li>
<li>Lack of proper response from customer support, and</li>
<li>Undue levy of cancellation charges despite the cab driver refusing to accept the ride booked by the passenger etc.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>It is against this backdrop that the Kerala government has decided to come up with an app-based platform to offer auto-taxi service for the public.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the main attractions of ‘Kerala Savari’?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There will be <strong><u>no fluctuation in fares</u></strong> on Kerala Savari irrespective of day or night or rain.</li>
<li>But Kerala Savari <strong><u>only 8% service charge</u></strong> in addition to the rate set by the government, whereas the private cab aggregators charge up to 20 to 30% service charge.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the security-related features of ‘Kerala Savari’?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Kerala Savari is claimed as a safe and reliable online service <strong><u>for women, children, and senior citizens</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This consideration has been given importance in app designing and driver registration.</li>
<li>A <strong><u>police clearance certificate</u></strong> is mandatory for drivers joining the scheme apart from the required proper training.</li>
<li>A <strong><u>panic button</u></strong> system has been introduced in the app.</li>
<li>It has also been decided to install <strong><u>GPS</u></strong> in vehicles at a subsidised rate.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Will the new government initiative end the monopoly of private cab aggregators?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Kerala has over five lakh autorickshaws and one lakh cabs.</li>
<li>The State government plans to bring all auto-taxi workers engaged in the sector under the new platform.</li>
<li>Since smartphone literacy is high in Kerala, the State is hopeful of bringing them under the scheme in a short span of time.</li>
<li>In addition, the Kerala government has also decided to provide fuel, insurance, and tyre subsidies for vehicle owners in the future and has already initiated talks with major companies in this regard.</li>
<li>After the evaluation of the first phase of the project in Thiruvananthapuram, it will be extended to the entire State in a phased manner.</li>
<li>Kerala Savari is expected to reach Kollam, Ernakulam, Thrissur, Kozhikode, and Kannur municipal limits within a month.</li>
</ul>
<table width="712">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="712"><strong>Regulation of Cab Aggregators in India</strong>
<ul>
<li>The Motor Vehicles Amendment Act 2019 seeks to regulate Cab aggregators in India</li>
<li>It’s the first time cab aggregators have got statutory recognition as “digital intermediaries” or “transport aggregators”.</li>
<li>They are now defined as marketplaces that can be used by passengers to connect with a driver for moving from one place to another.</li>
<li>The Centre will issue broad guidelines from time to time and the states will rely on them to frame their own rules to regulate the industry.</li>
<li>The aggregators will also have to comply with the provisions of the Information Technology Act, 2000.</li>
<li>This means they will have to follow rules on storing data safely to protect the identity of users.</li>
</ul>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/kerala-savari-indias-first-state-taxi/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Tribute to women freedom fighters</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tribute-to-women-freedom-fighters/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Freedom fighters in news</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Feminist contribution in freedom struggle</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-625118" height="368" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 653px) 100vw, 653px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ff1-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ff1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ff1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ff1.jpg 1024w" width="653"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Prime Minister <a href="https://indianexpress.com/about/narendra-modi/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Narendra Modi</a>’s <a href="https://indianexpress.com/article/india/pm-modi-addresses-independence-day-2022-8090686/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Independence Day speech</a> underlined the role of women <strong>veeranganas</strong> in our freedom movement. The initiative highlighting the brave women of our freedom struggle, under the broader celebration of Azadi Ka Amrit Mahotsav, will mark a turning point in <strong>Indian feminist history writing from an Indic perspective.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What veerangana means?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Veerangana means a brave female, someone who can fight for their rights. A strong woman not only protects herself, but protects others too.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Veerangana’s in freedom struggle </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Rani Laxmibai</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The queen of the princely state of Jhansi, Rani Laxmibai is known for her role in the First War of India’s Independence in 1857.</li>
<li>Refusing to cede her territory, the queen decided to rule on behalf of the heir, and later joined the uprising against the British in 1857.</li>
<li>Cornered by the British, she escaped from Jhansi fort. She was wounded in combat near Gwalior’s Phool Bagh, where she later died.</li>
<li>Sir Hugh Rose, who was commanding the British army, is known to have described her as “personable, clever…and one of the most dangerous Indian leaders”.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Jhalkari Bai</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>A soldier in Rani Laxmibai’s women’s army, Durga Dal, she rose to become one of the queen’s most trusted advisers.</li>
<li>She is known for putting her own life at risk to keep the queen out of harm’s way.</li>
<li>Till date, the story of her valour is recalled by the people of Bundelkhand, and she is often presented as a representative of Bundeli identity.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Durga Bhabhi</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Durgawati Devi, who was popularly known as Durga Bhabhi, was a revolutionary who joined the armed struggle against colonial rule.</li>
<li>A member of the Naujawan Bharat Sabha, she helped Bhagat Singh escape in disguise from Lahore after the 1928 killing of British police officer John P Saunders.</li>
<li>Later, as revenge for the hanging of Bhagat Singh, Rajguru, and Sukhdev, she made an unsuccessful attempt to kill the former Punjab Governor, Lord Hailey.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Rani Gaidinliu</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Born in 1915 in present-day Manipur, Rani Gaidinliu was a Naga spiritual and political leader who fought the British.</li>
<li>She joined the Heraka religious movement which later became a movement to drive out the British. She rebelled against the Empire, and refused to pay taxes, asking people to do the same.</li>
<li>The British launched a manhunt, but she evaded arrest, moving from village to village.</li>
<li>Gaidinliu was finally arrested in 1932 when she was just 16, and later sentenced for life. She was released in 1947.</li>
<li>Then PM Nehru described Gaidinliu as the “daughter of the hills”, and gave her the title of ‘Rani’ for her courage.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Rani Chennamma</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The queen of Kittur, Rani Chennamma, was among the first rulers to lead an armed rebellion against British rule.</li>
<li>Kittur was a princely state in present-day Karnataka.</li>
<li>She fought back against the attempt to control her dominion in 1824 after the death of her young son. She had lost her husband, Raja Mallasarja, in 1816.</li>
<li>She is seen among the few rulers of the time who understood the colonial designs of the British.</li>
<li>Rani Chennamma defeated the British in her first revolt, but was captured and imprisoned during the second assault by the East India Company.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Begum Hazrat Mahal</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>After her husband, Nawab of Awadh Wajid Ali Shah, was exiled after the 1857 revolt, Begum Hazrat Mahal, along with her supporters, took on the British and wrested control of Lucknow.</li>
<li>She was forced into a retreat after the colonial rulers recaptured the area.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Velu Nachiyar</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Many years before the revolt of 1857, Velu Nachiyar waged a war against the British and emerged victorious. Born in Ramanathapuram in 1780, she was married to the king of Sivagangai.</li>
<li>After her husband was killed in battle with the East India Company, she entered the conflict, and won with support of neighbouring kings.</li>
<li>She went on to produce the first human bomb as well as establish the first army of trained women soldiers in the late 1700s.</li>
<li>Her army commander Kuyili is believed to have set herself ablaze and walked into a British ammunition dump.</li>
<li>She was succeeded by her daughter in 1790, and died a few years later in 1796.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The veeranganas are a potent symbol of nationalism and patriotism. They can overturn oppressive attitudes towards women in society. Their role and celebration in popular culture also refutes the colonial allegations about the suppression of women throughout Indian history. But it is essential to discover, rewrite and reinterpret the role and representation of these heroic women in the liberation of the motherland.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>The veerangana’s are a potent symbol of nationalism and patriotism. They can overturn oppressive attitudes towards women in society. Discuss examples of them showing how they inspire women’s today.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tribute-to-women-freedom-fighters/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Pandurang Khankhoje: Ghadarite revolutionary and a hero of Mexico</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pandurang-khankhoje-ghadarite/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Pandurang Khankhoje</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Ghadr party</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-625104" height="332" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 589px) 100vw, 589px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pandurang-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pandurang-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pandurang-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pandurang.jpg 929w" width="589"/></strong></p>
<p>Lok Sabha Speaker, who is currently in Canada for the 65th Commonwealth Parliamentary Conference, will travel to Mexico where he will unveil statues of Swami Vivekananda and Maharashtra-born freedom fighter and agriculturalist Pandurang Khankhoje.</p>
<h4>Who was Pandurang Khankhoje (1883-1967)?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Born in Wardha, Maharashtra, in the late 19th century, Pandurang Khankhoje came in contact with other revolutionaries early on.</li>
<li>As a student, Khankhoje was an ardent admirer of the French Revolution and of the American War of Independence.</li>
<li>Closer to home, the Hindu reformer Swami Dayanand and his Arya Samaj movement, which called for a spirit of reform and social change, became the hero to a young student group led by Khankhoje.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Revolutionary activities abroad</h4>
<ul>
<li>Khankhoje decided to go abroad for further training in revolutionary methods and militaristic strategy.</li>
<li>At this time, the British government’s suspicions of him were also growing due to his anti-government activities.</li>
<li>Before leaving, he visited Bal Gangadhar Tilak, by whom he was inspired.</li>
<li>Tilak advised him to go to Japan, which was itself a strong, anti-West Asian imperialistic force then.</li>
<li>After spending time with nationalists from Japan and China, Khankhoje eventually moved to the US, where he enrolled in college as a student of agriculture.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Participation in the Indian independence movement</h4>
<ul>
<li>Khankhoje was one of the founding members of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/important-historical-literature-books-newspapers-in-the-freedom-struggle-and-important-social-religious-reforms-movements-2/">Ghadar Party</a>, established by Indians living abroad in 1914, mostly belonging to Punjab.</li>
<li>Its aim was to lead a revolutionary fight against the British in India.</li>
<li>While in the US, Khankhoje met Lala Har Dayal, an Indian intellectual teaching at Stanford University.</li>
<li>Har Dayal had begun a propaganda campaign, publishing a newspaper that featured patriotic songs and articles in the vernacular languages of India.</li>
<li>This was the seed from which the Ghadar Party would emerge.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did Khankhoje reach Mexico?</h4>
<ul>
<li>At the military academy, Khankhoje met many people from Mexico.</li>
<li>The Mexican Revolution of 1910 had led to the overthrow of the dictatorial regime, and this inspired Khankhoje.</li>
<li>He also reached out to Indians working on farms in the US with the aim of discussing the idea of Indian independence with them.</li>
<li>Along with the Indian workers, militant action was planned by Khankhoje in India, but the outbreak of the First World War halted these plans.</li>
<li>He then reached out to Bhikaji Cama in Paris, and met with Vladimir Lenin in Russia among other leaders, seeking support for the Indian cause.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Association with Mexico</h4>
<ul>
<li>As he was facing possible deportation from Europe and could not go to India, he sought shelter in Mexico.</li>
<li>Soon, in part due to his prior friendship with Mexican revolutionaries, he was appointed a professor at the National School of Agriculture in Chapingo, near Mexico City.</li>
<li>He researched corn, wheat, pulses and rubber, developing frost and drought-resistant varieties, and was part of efforts to bring in the Green Revolution in Mexico.</li>
<li>Later on, the American agronomist Dr Norman Borlaug, called the Father of the Green Revolution in India, brought the Mexican wheat variety to Punjab.</li>
<li>Khankhoje was revered as an agricultural scientist in Mexico.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Return to India</h4>
<ul>
<li>Both Pandurang and Jean returned to India after 1947.</li>
<li>His application for visa was initially rejected by the Indian government due to the ban by the British Indian Government, but was eventually overturned.</li>
<li>He settled in Nagpur and subsequently embarked on a political career.</li>
<li>Pandurang Khankhoje died on 22 January 1967.</li>
</ul>
<table width="747">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="747">
<h4><strong>Back2Basics: Ghadar Party</strong></h4>
<p>Founder: Sohan Singh Bhakna, 15 July 1913</p>
<ul>
<li>The Ghadar Movement was an early 20th century, international political movement founded by expatriate Indians to overthrow British rule in India.</li>
<li>Earlier activists had established a ‘Swadesh Sevak Home’ in Vancouver and a ‘United India House’ in Seattle to carry out revolutionary activities. Finally, in 1913, the Ghadr was founded.</li>
<li>The Ghadar Party, originally known as the Pacific Coast Hindustan Association, was founded on July 15, 1913 in the US by Lala Har Dayal, Sant Baba Wasakha Singh Dadehar, Baba Jawala Singh, Santokh Singh, and Sohan Singh Bhakna.</li>
<li>The Ghadar party drew a sizable following among Indian expatriates in the United States, Canada, East Africa, and Asia.</li>
<li>It fought against colonialism from 1914 to 1917, with the support of Imperial Germany and the Ottoman Empire, both of which were Central Powers opposed to the British.</li>
<li>The party was organized around the weekly newspaper The Ghadar, which featured the masthead caption: Angrezi Raj Ka Dushman (an enemy of British rule); “Wanted brave soldiers to stir up rebellion in India,” the Ghadar declared.</li>
</ul>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pandurang-khankhoje-ghadarite/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What are Cloudbursts? Why are they rising across India?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cloudbursts-in-india-ias/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Cloudburst</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Flash floods and cloudbursts</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-625102" height="427" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cloudburst-300x219.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cloudburst-300x219.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cloudburst-768x561.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/cloudburst.jpg 771w" width="585"/></strong></p>
<p>Over 20 people have been killed in destruction caused by cloudbursts and flash floods in different parts of Himachal Pradesh and Uttarakhand over the last three days.</p>
<h4>What are Cloudbursts?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A cloudburst is a localised but intense rainfall activity.</li>
<li>Short spells of very heavy rainfall over a small geographical area can cause widespread destruction, especially in hilly regions where this phenomenon is the most common.</li>
<li>Not all instances of very heavy rainfall, however, are cloudbursts.</li>
<li>A cloudburst has a very specific definition: Rainfall of 10 cm or more in an hour over a roughly 10 km x 10-km area is classified as a cloudburst event.</li>
<li>By this definition, 5 cm of rainfall in a half-hour period over the same area would also be categorized as a cloudburst.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How is it different from normal rainfall?</h4>
<ul>
<li>To put this in perspective, in a normal year, India, as a whole, receives about 116 cm of rainfall over the entire year.</li>
<li>This means if the entire rainfall everywhere in India during a year was spread evenly over its area, the total accumulated water would be 116 cm high.</li>
<li>There are, of course, huge geographical variations in rainfall within the country, and some areas receive over 10 times more than that amount in a year.</li>
<li>But on average, any place in India can be expected to receive about 116 cm of rain in a year.</li>
<li>During a cloudburst event, a place receives about 10% of this annual rainfall within an hour.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How common are cloudbursts?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Cloudbursts are not uncommon events, particularly during the monsoon months.</li>
<li>Most of these happen in the Himalayan states where the local topology, wind systems, and temperature gradients between the lower and upper atmosphere facilitate the occurrence of such events.</li>
<li>However, not every event that is described as a cloudburst is actually, by definition, a cloudburst.</li>
<li>That is because these events are highly localized.</li>
<li>They take place in very small areas which are often devoid of rainfall measuring instruments.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why are they so destructive?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The consequences of these events, however, are not confined to small areas.</li>
<li>Because of the nature of terrain, the heavy rainfall events often trigger landslides and flash floods, causing extensive destruction downstream.</li>
<li>This is the reason why every sudden downpour that leads to destruction of life and property in the hilly areas gets described as a “cloudburst”, irrespective of whether the amount of rainfall meets the defining criteria.</li>
<li>At the same time, it is also possible that actual cloudburst events in remote locations aren’t recorded.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Can cloudbursts be forecasted?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The India Meteorological Department forecasts rainfall events well in advance, but it does not predict the quantum of rainfall — in fact, no meteorological agency does.</li>
<li>The forecasts can be about light, heavy, or very heavy rainfall, but weather scientists do not have the capability to predict exactly how much rain is likely to fall at any given place.</li>
<li>Additionally, the forecasts are for a relatively large geographical area, usually a region, a state, a meteorological sub-division, or at best a district.</li>
<li>As they zoom in over smaller areas, the forecasts get more and more uncertain.</li>
<li>Theoretically, it is not impossible to forecast rainfall over a very small area as well, but it requires a very dense network of weather instruments and computing capabilities that seem unfeasible with current technologies.</li>
<li>As a result, specific cloudburst events cannot be forecast. No forecast ever mentions a possibility of a cloudburst.</li>
<li>But there are warnings for heavy to very heavy rainfall events, and these are routinely forecast four to five days in advance.</li>
<li>Possibility of extremely heavy rainfall, which could result in cloudburst kind of situations, are forecast six to 12 hours in advance.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Are cloudburst incidents increasing?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There is no long-term trend that suggests that cloudbursts, as defined by the IMD, are rising.</li>
<li>What is well established, however, is that incidents of extreme rainfall, as also other extreme weather events, are increasing — not just in India but across the world.</li>
<li>While the overall amount of rainfall in India has not changed substantially, an increasing proportion of rainfall is happening in a short span of time.</li>
<li>That means that the wet spells are very wet, and are interspersed with prolonged dry spells even in the rainy season.</li>
<li>This kind of pattern, attributed to climate change, does suggest that cloudburst events might also be on the rise.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cloudbursts-in-india-ias/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Skewed divisible pool</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/skewed-divisible-pool/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Finance commission</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Fiscal federalism</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="divisible pool " class="alignnone wp-image-625138" height="292" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 487px) 100vw, 487px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fiscal-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fiscal-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fiscal-768x461.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fiscal.jpg 800w" width="487"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The centralisation of fiscal powers in India has been blamed for the poor fiscal health of the states.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Chief Ministers expressed their concern about <strong>dwindling State revenues</strong> in a NITI Aayog meeting chaired by the Prime Minister.</li>
<li>They sought <strong>a higher share in the divisible pool of taxes</strong> and an extension of GST compensation, both of which have long remained a bone of contention between the Union government and the States.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Need for financial devolution</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To strengthen democracy at grass root level with more revenue resources for better service delivery.</li>
<li>To increase accountability to people so performance can be realized as direct contact with people.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is divisible pool of taxes?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The divisible pool is that portion of gross tax revenue which is distributed between the Centre and the States. The divisible pool consists of all taxes, except surcharges and cess levied for specific purpose, net of collection charges.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is fiscal federalism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fiscal federalism refers to how federal, state, and local governments share funding and administrative responsibilities within our federal system. The funding for these programs comes from taxes and fees.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Poor state of state finances </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Stagnant revenue: </strong>Since States cannot raise tax revenue because of curtailed indirect tax rights — subsumed in GST, except for petroleum products, electricity and alcohol — the revenue has been stagnant at 6% of GDP in the past decade.</li>
<li><strong>Distorted expenditure</strong>: While States lost their capacity to generate revenue by surrendering their rights in the wake of the Goods and Services Tax (GST) regime, their expenditure pattern too was distorted by the Union’s intrusion, particularly through its centrally sponsored schemes.</li>
<li><strong>Decline in share</strong>: The ability of States to finance current expenditures from their own revenues has declined from 69% in 1955-56 to less than 38% in 2019-20.</li>
<li><strong>Stress on finance:</strong> States’ financial health had taken a turn for the worse with the implementation of the Ujwal DISCOM Assurance Yojana, farm loan waivers, as also the slowdown in growth in 2019- 20.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Key fact to remember </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Finance Commission keeps tax devolution for states at 41% in FY22</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<h4><strong>How fiscal centralisation impacts on states?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cut in the corporate tax: </strong>The recent drastic cut in corporate tax, with its adverse impact on the divisible pool, and ending GST compensation to States have had huge consequences.</li>
<li><strong>States paying high interest rates</strong>: States are forced to pay differential interest — about 10% against 7% — by the Union for market borrowings<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Centrally sponsored schemes curbing autonomy: </strong>There are 131 centrally sponsored schemes, with a few dozen of them accounting for 90% of the allocation, and States required to share a part of the cost.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong> Suggestions for strong fiscal federalism </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Creation of federal institution</strong><strong>: </strong>We need to create another institution in the form of a GST state secretariat that can bring together senior officers from the Centre and states in an institutional forum registered under the Society Act.</li>
<li><strong>State Finance Commissions</strong>: should be accorded the same status as the Union Finance Commission and the 3Fs of democratic decentralization (funds, functions, and functionaries) should be implemented properly.</li>
<li><strong>Robust GST regime</strong>: Transparency, simplification and rationalisation of GST will help states to recover soon.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way Forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Relook on various exemptions to rationalise the taxes/levies</strong></li>
<li><strong>Augmentation of Tax Administration Structure</strong></li>
<li><strong>Technology-based Tax Administration may also be further expanded to cover even utility charges like water, street lights, sanitation charges, etc.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is important now to rethink the design and structure of a genuine <strong>fiscal partnership</strong>, which should not merely be a race to garner more resources, but a creative attempt to move towards a vibrant Indian value chain that can catapult India’s growth rate closer to the quest for double-digit growth.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Why it is important now to rethink the design and structure of a genuine fiscal partnership? Discuss this in context of Skewed divisible pool and state of fiscal federalism in India.</strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/skewed-divisible-pool/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Central Bank Digital Currency (CBDC): the Digital Rupee</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/central-bank-digital-currency-cbdc/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Central Bank Digital Currency (CBDC)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Prospects and challenges to CBDC</p></div></div><p>Reports have said the Reserve Bank of India’s (RBI) digital rupee — the Central Bank Digital Currency (CBDC) — may be introduced in phases beginning with wholesale businesses in the current financial year.</p>
<h4>What is Central Bank Digital Currency (CBDC)?</h4>
<ul>
<li>CBDC is a central bank issued digital currency which is backed by some kind of assets in the form of either gold, currency reserves, bonds and other assets, recognised by the central banks as a monetary asset.</li>
<li>The present concept of CBDCs was directly inspired by Bitcoin, but a CBDC is different from virtual currency and cryptocurrency.</li>
<li>Cryptocurrencies are not issued by a state and lack the legal tender status declared by the government.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong><em>What is Currency chest?</em></strong></p>
<p><em>Currency in India is managed by Currency chest. Currency chest is a place where the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) stocks the money meant for banks and ATMs. These chests are usually situated on the premises of different banks but administrated by the RBI.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4>Why India needs a digital rupee?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Online transactions:</strong> India is a leader in digital payments, but cash remains dominant for small-value transactions.</li>
<li><strong>High currency in circulation:</strong> India has a fairly high currency-to-GDP ratio.</li>
<li><strong>Cost of currency management:</strong> An official digital currency would reduce the cost of currency management while enabling real-time payments without any inter-bank settlement.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is CBDC preferred over Cryptocurrency?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sovereign guarantee</strong>: Cryptocurrencies pose risks to consumers.  They do not have any sovereign guarantee and hence are not legal tender.</li>
<li><strong>Market volatility</strong>: Their speculative nature also makes them highly volatile.  For instance, the value of Bitcoin fell from USD 20,000 in December 2017 to USD 3,800 in November 2018.</li>
<li><strong>Risk in security</strong>: A user loses access to their cryptocurrency if they lose their private key (unlike traditional digital banking accounts, this password cannot be reset).</li>
<li><strong>Malware threats</strong>: In some cases, these private keys are stored by technical service providers (cryptocurrency exchanges or wallets), which are prone to malware or hacking.</li>
<li><strong>Money laundering</strong>: Cryptocurrencies are more vulnerable to criminal activity and money laundering.  They provide greater anonymity than other payment methods since the public keys engaging in a transaction cannot be directly linked to an individual.</li>
<li><strong>Regulatory bypass</strong>: A central bank cannot regulate the supply of cryptocurrencies in the economy.  This could pose a risk to the financial stability of the country if their use becomes widespread.</li>
<li><strong>Power consumption</strong>: Since validating transactions is energy-intensive, it may have adverse consequences for the country’s energy security (the total electricity use of bitcoin mining, in 2018, was equivalent to that of mid-sized economies such as Switzerland).</li>
</ul>
<h4>Features of CBDC</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>High-security instrument:</strong> CBDC is a high-security digital instrument; like paper banknotes, it is a means of payment, a unit of account, and a store of value.</li>
<li><strong>Uniquely identifiable:</strong> And like paper currency, each unit is uniquely identifiable to prevent counterfeit.</li>
<li><strong>Liability of central bank:</strong> It is a liability of the central bank just as physical currency is.</li>
<li><strong>Transferability:</strong> It’s a digital bearer instrument that can be stored, transferred, and transmitted by all kinds of digital payment systems and services.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Key benefits offered</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Faster system:</strong> CBDC can definitely increase the transmission of money from central banks to commercial banks and end customers much faster than the present system.</li>
<li><strong>Financial inclusion:</strong> Specific use cases, like financial inclusion, can also be covered by CBDC that can benefit millions of citizens who need money and are currently unbanked or banked with limited banking services</li>
<li><strong>Monetary policy facilitation:</strong> The move to bring out a CBDC could significantly improve monetary policy development in India.</li>
<li><strong>Making of a regional currency:</strong> In the cross border payments domain, India can take a lead by leveraging digital Rupee especially in countries such as Bhutan, Saudia Arabia and Singapore where NPCI has existing arrangements.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Others:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>It is efficient than printing notes (cost of printing, transporting, and storing paper currency)</li>
<li>It reduces the risk of transactions</li>
<li>It makes tax collection transparent</li>
<li>Prevents money laundering</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues involved with CBDC</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Innovation with centralization:</strong> The approach of bringing a sovereign digital currency stands in stark contrast to the idea of decentralization.</li>
<li><strong>Liability on RBI:</strong>  when bank customers wish to convert their deposits into digital rupee, the RBI will have to take these liabilities from the books of banks and onto its own balance sheet.</li>
<li><strong>Inflationary risk:</strong> Central banks would indulge in issuing more digital currencies which could potentially trigger higher inflation.</li>
<li><strong>User adoption:</strong> User adoption could also pose a major setback for the smooth roll out of the CBDC in India. The main challenges would always be user adoption and security.</li>
<li><strong>Reduced savings:</strong> Many, including various central bankers, fear that people may begin withdrawing money from their bank accounts as digital currencies issued by Central banks become more popular.</li>
<li><strong>Volatility:</strong> the risk is higher and there is more price volatility and lesser acceptance as a money instrument globally, unless the trust factor and investor protection factors change.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>The launch of CBDCs may not be a smooth affair and still requires more clarity in India. There are still a lot of misconceptions about the concept of digital currency in the country.</li>
<li>The effectiveness of CBDCs will depend on aspects such as privacy design and programmability.</li>
<li>There is a huge opportunity for India to take a lead globally via a large-scale rollout and adoption of digital currencies.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/central-bank-digital-currency-cbdc/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Constitution Bench to hear Delhi statehood plea</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/constitution-bench-to-hear-delhi-statehood-plea/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Article 239AA, Consititution Bench</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Centre vs. Delhi Govt</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-625106" height="419" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 632px) 100vw, 632px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/delhistate-300x199.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/delhistate-300x199.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/delhistate-768x509.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/delhistate.jpg 876w" width="632"/></strong></p>
<p>A Constitution Bench led by Justice D.Y. Chandrachud will hear the legal battle between the Centre and the Government of Delhi for control over officials in the national capital.</p>
<h4>What is a Constitution Bench?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The constitution bench is the name given to the benches of the Supreme Court of India.</li>
<li>The Chief Justice of India has the power to constitute a Constitution Bench and refer cases to it.</li>
</ul>
<p>Constitution benches are set up when the following circumstances exist:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Interpretation of the Constitution:</strong> Article 145(3) provides for the constitution of at least five judges of the court which sit to decide any case “involving a substantial question of law as to the interpretation” of the Constitution of India.</li>
<li><strong>President of India seeking SC’s opinion:</strong> When the President has sought the Supreme Court’s opinion on a question of fact or law under Article 143 of the Constitution. Article 143 of the Constitution provides for Advisory jurisdiction to the SC. As per the provision, the President has the power to address questions to the apex Court, which he deems important for public welfare.</li>
<li><strong>Conflicting Judgments:</strong> When two or more three-judge benches of the Supreme Court have delivered conflicting judgments on the same point of law, necessitating a definite understanding and interpretation of the law by a larger bench.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The Constitution benches are set up on ad hoc basis as and when the above-mentioned conditions exist.</li>
<li>Constitution benches have decided many of India’s best-known and most important Supreme Court cases, such as:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>K. Gopalan v. State of Madras (Preventive detention)</li>
<li>Kesavananda Bharati v. State of Kerala (Basic structure doctrine) and</li>
<li>Ashoka Kumar Thakur v. Union of India (OBC reservations) etc.</li>
</ol>
<h4>Why in news now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A 2018 Constitution bench decision interpreting Article 239AA had not dealt with an aspect having a bearing on the dispute over services, CJI agreed.</li>
<li>The proceedings have their genesis in the Delhi HC judgment of August 4, 2017, whereby it held that for the purposes of administration, the L-G was not bound by the aid and advice of the Council of Ministers in every matter.</li>
<li>On appeal, the SC on February 15, 2017, referred the matter to decide on the interpretation of Article 239AA.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the 2018 Judgment all about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>By a majority decision in July, 2018, the Constitution bench upheld the respective powers of the state Assembly and the Parliament.</li>
<li>It said that while the CoM must communicate all decisions to the L-G, this <strong><u>does not mean that the L-G’s concurrence is required. </u></strong></li>
<li>In case of a difference of opinion, the L-G can refer it to the President for a decision.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>L-G has no independent decision-making power</u></strong> but has to either act on the ‘aid and advice’ of the CoM or is bound to implement the decision of the President on a reference being made.</li>
<li>The bench, which limited itself to the interpretation of Article 239AA, left individual issues to be decided by regular benches.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When power tussle began?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Subsequently in 2019, a two-judge bench of the SC dealt with some individual issues arising from the power tussle between the Centre and the NCT government.</li>
<li>It ruled that the Anti-Corruption Branch of the <strong><u>Delhi government cannot investigate corruption cases against central government officials</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The power to appoint commissions under the Commission of Inquiry Act, 1952, would be vested with the Centre and not the Delhi government, the judgment said.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issue over control of administrative services</h4>
<ul>
<li>The judges, however, differed on who should have control over administrative services.</li>
<li>This was challenged again in the SC where the Centre contended that the two judges could not take a decision on the question.</li>
<li>The 2018 Constitution bench judgment had not interpreted the expression “insofar as any such matter as applicable to Union Territories” appearing in Article 239AA.</li>
<li>The Centre has urged SC CJI Ramana to refer the matter to a five-judge Constitution bench so that the question of law can be settled before the dispute over who has control over services can be looked into.</li>
</ul>
<table width="740">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="740">
<h4><strong>Article 239AA of the Indian Constitution </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Article 239AA granted Special Status to Delhi among Union Territories (UTs) in the year 1991 through the 69th Constitutional Amendment.</li>
<li>It provided a Legislative Assembly and a Council of Ministers responsible to such Assembly with appropriate powers.</li>
<li>That’s when Delhi was named as the National Capital Region (NCT) of Delhi.</li>
<li>As per this article – Public Order, Police &amp; Land in NCT of Delhi fall within the domain and control of Central Government which shall have the power to make laws on these matters.</li>
<li>For remaining matters of State List or Concurrent List, in so far as any such matter is applicable to UTs, the Legislative Assembly shall have the power to make laws for NCT of Delhi.</li>
</ul>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/constitution-bench-to-hear-delhi-statehood-plea/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Need of scientific temper for positive growth</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/scientific-temper/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>article 51 a</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>scientific literacy</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-625564" height="338" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 100vw, 542px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/10bgmarchforscience-300x187.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/10bgmarchforscience-300x187.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/10bgmarchforscience-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/10bgmarchforscience.jpg 615w" width="542"/></p>
<h4><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has not produced any Nobel Prize winner in science in the last 85 years — largely because of the lack of a scientific environment in the country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is scientific temper?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Jawaharlal Nehru coined the term ‘scientific temper’; he defines it as an attitude of logical and rational thinking. An individual is considered to have scientific temper if she employs the scientific method when making decisions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why it is important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Scientific temper is very important for bringing forth a progressive society. It is free from superstitions. Irrational practices in developing the nation are in all aspects like political, economic and social.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Its components </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The vital parts of scientific temper are discussion, argument, and analysis. Various elements like fairness, equality, and democracy. The most important characteristic of a scientific temper is: – untiring search for truth with an open mind and spirit of inquiry.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Constitutional mandate of scientific temper </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In 1976, the Government of India reemphasised its commitment to cultivate scientific temper through a constitutional amendment <strong>(Article 51A).</strong></li>
<li>Article 51A in the 42nd Amendment of the Constitution in 1976 says “It shall be the duty of every citizen of Indian to develop the scientific temper, humanism and the spirit of enquiry and reform.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Importance of scientific temper in nation building</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Formation of public policy:</strong> Scientific temperament can become a part of the policy formation and plan through analyzing the performance of our nations, especially all the hardships and shortfalls that occurred in the past years.</li>
<li><strong>Self -Reliance: </strong>There is a relationship between scientific temperament and becoming self-reliant. Our country is becoming self-reliant with the available technology and industrial infrastructure.</li>
<li><strong>Quality education</strong>: It will help the children to assimilate the knowledge acquired through the practical observations in a scientific framework; thus, laying down a basis for the growth of a scientific perspective in the children.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="scientific temper" class="alignnone wp-image-625579" height="342" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/sci-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/sci-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/sci-1024x614.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/sci-768x461.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/sci-1536x922.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/sci-1200x720.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/sci.jpg 1600w" width="570"/>Challenges before scientific temper </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Political unwillingness</strong>: Most of the policymakers and the politicians to increase their vote banks include the stagnant ideologies and beliefs of the people in their public policies, and the government tends to give away in the popular public opinion rather than try to improve their thinking by including a more scientific approach to the various societal problems.</li>
<li><strong>Prevalent orthodoxy</strong>: In India, people still have an orthodox ideology and will not adhere to the scientifically obtained solutions.</li>
<li><strong>Low budget</strong>: Even after seventy years of independence, Indian Scientists are working on tight budgets, and they don’t have resources like other nations for conducting scientific research.</li>
<li><strong>Pseudoscience</strong>: Pseudoscience is everywhere, whether in denying the science of climate change or the evolution theory that explains the secret of diversity that we see around us.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Value addition / case study / Innovation </strong></h4>
<p><strong>An IIT Kanpur alumni Mr.Arvind Gupta tries to inculcate a spirit of inquiry among children through toys made from inexpensive everyday items.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><br/>
<img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-625578" height="431" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 441px) 100vw, 441px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/science-300x293.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/science-300x293.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/science-1024x999.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/science-768x749.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/science-922x900.jpg 922w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/science.jpg 1200w" width="441"/>What can be done?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Directional efforts</strong>: Activities focused on school children can be undertaken like nature walks, visit to museums etc. ‘Science Express’, a collaborative effort of Ministry of railways and Ministry of Environment &amp; Forests &amp; Climate Change, is a progressive step because it provides a platform that can expose children and common people in far-flung areas of the country to scientific aspects of our everday life.</li>
<li><strong>Policy initiatives</strong>: Children’s Science Congress organized by National Council for Science &amp; Technology Communication (NCSTC) is a good way to encourage scientific temper in children.</li>
<li><strong>Public initiative:</strong> Civil Society organizations like, Kerala Sastra Sahitya Parishad (KSSP) and Delhi Science Forum, which are People’s Science Movement, can also go a long way in boosting scientific temper amongst the community.</li>
<li><strong>From Sensationalism to Sensible Science Journalism:</strong>The media must monitor the content to discourage and limit superstition and blind belief.</li>
<li><strong>Scientific journalism</strong>: Science communicators do the critical job of bridging the gap between science, society, and policymakers. Science journalism should be promoted at the university level. Science agencies should fund science communication activities in their domains.</li>
<li><strong>From Exclusive to Inclusive Science: </strong>Inequitable participation concerning gender and social diversity must be eliminated. The ‘open source science’ or ‘open science’ movement includes, at the core, open access, open data, open-source, and available standards that offer unfettered dissemination of scientific discourse.</li>
<li><strong>Open science:</strong> Government has a significant role in facilitating open science and promoting and preserving a free-thinking, open-minded society.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Let’s hope that someday all cultures free themselves from the shackles of blind faith  with science likely to play a major hand in this endeavour. Unto a similar goal, we should celebrate India’s constitutional provision for the scientific temper and vigorously safeguard it.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. The shrinking space for scientific temper in India today is worrisome for some reasons. Do you think so? Identify these reasons and suggest way forward for scientific future of India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="73BLi3AGdS"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/discuss-the-importance-of-scientific-temper-what-kind-of-public-culture-is-needed-to-advance-it-10-marks/">Discuss the importance of scientific temper, what kind of public culture is needed to advance it? 10 Marks</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="73BLi3AGdS" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/discuss-the-importance-of-scientific-temper-what-kind-of-public-culture-is-needed-to-advance-it-10-marks/embed/#?secret=JNA0BuSoUt#?secret=73BLi3AGdS" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“Discuss the importance of scientific temper, what kind of public culture is needed to advance it? 10 Marks” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="rsBxSHo5vy"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/q-4-explain-why-superstitious-beliefs-and-practices-abound-in-india-in-this-context-discuss-the-importance-of-inculcating-scientific-temper-to-remove-superstitions-10-marks/">Q.4  Explain why superstitious beliefs and practices abound in India. In this context, discuss the  importance of inculcating scientific temper to remove superstitions. (10 Marks)</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="rsBxSHo5vy" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/q-4-explain-why-superstitious-beliefs-and-practices-abound-in-india-in-this-context-discuss-the-importance-of-inculcating-scientific-temper-to-remove-superstitions-10-marks/embed/#?secret=wxKFe7PA41#?secret=rsBxSHo5vy" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“Q.4  Explain why superstitious beliefs and practices abound in India. In this context, discuss the  importance of inculcating scientific temper to remove superstitions. (10 Marks)” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/scientific-temper/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>5G revolution and challenges</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/5g-revolution/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of 5G</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>scientific achievements and issues with it</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="5G revolution " class="alignnone wp-image-625615" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful.jpeg 1200w" width="581"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Prime Minister Narendra Modi recently announced that 5G revolution deployment in India will commence sooner than expected.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is 5G technology?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>5G or fifth generation revolution  is the latest upgrade in the long-term evolution (LTE) mobile broadband networks.</li>
<li>5G enables a new kind of network that is designed to connect virtually everyone and everything together including machines, objects, and devices.</li>
<li>It’s a unified platform which is much more capable than previous mobile services with more capacity, lower latency, faster data delivery rate and better utilisation of spectrum.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How it evolved from 1G to 5G?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>1G: </strong>Launched in the 1980s. Analog radio signals and supported only voice calls.</li>
<li><strong>2G:</strong> Launched in the 1990s. Uses digital radio signals and supported both voice and data transmission with a Bandwidth (BW) of 64 Kbps.</li>
<li><strong>3G:</strong> Launched in the 2000s. With a speed of 1 Mbps to 2 Mbps it has the ability to transmit telephone signal including digitized voice, video calls and conferencing.</li>
<li><strong>4G</strong>: With a peak speed of 100 Mbps-1 Gbps it also enables 3D virtual reality.</li>
<li><strong>5G:</strong> with a speed of more than 1Gbps, it is capable of connecting entire world without limits.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="5G revolution" class="alignnone wp-image-625641" height="291" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 552px) 100vw, 552px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g1-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g1-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g1.jpg 392w" width="552"/>Salient features</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Capability:</strong> 5G will provide much faster mobile broadband service as compared to the previous versions and will provide support to previous services like mission critical communication and the massive Internet Of Things (IoT).</li>
<li><strong>Upgraded LTE</strong>: 5G is the latest upgrade in the long-term evolution (LTE) mobile broadband networks.</li>
<li><strong>Speed:</strong> With peak delivering rate of up to 20 Gbps and an average of 100Mbps, it will be much faster as compared to its predecessors. The speed increment is partly achieved partly by using higher-frequency radio waves than previous networks.</li>
<li><strong>Capacity</strong>: There will be up to 100 x increase in traffic capacity and network efficiency.</li>
<li><strong>Spectrum usage</strong>: Will provide better usage for every bit of spectrum, from low bands below 1 GHz to high bands.</li>
<li><strong>Latency</strong>: It’s expected to have lower latency with better instantaneous, real-time access of the data. The 5G, like 4G LTE, also uses Orthogonal Frequency Division Multiplexing (OFDM) but the new 5G NR (New Radio) air interface will enhance OFDM and provide better flexibility in data delivery.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><br/>
<img alt="5G revolution" class="alignnone wp-image-625634" height="176" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-300x81.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-300x81.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g.jpg 718w" width="650"/>Applications of 5G technology</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>High-Speed mobile network</strong>: 5G will revolutionize the mobile experience with supercharged wireless network. Compared to conventional mobile transmission technologies, voice and high-speed data can be simultaneously transferred efficiently in 5G.</li>
<li><strong>Entertainment and multimedia</strong>: 5G can provide 120 frames per second, high resolution and higher dynamic range video streaming without interruption. Audiovisual experience will be rewritten after the implementation of the latest technologies powered by 5G wireless. Augmented Reality and virtual Reality services will be better experienced over 5G.</li>
<li><strong>Internet of Things</strong>: IoT applications collects huge amount of data from millions of devices and sensors and thus requires an efficient network for data collection, processing, transmission, control and real-time analytics which 5G network is a better candidate.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Interesting facts about 5G</strong></h4>
<p><strong>According to researchers, about 1.5 billion people will have access to 5G by 2024. </strong></p>
<p><strong>It may not seem like it at present, however, 5G will cover about 40% of the world.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>The security risks introduced BY 5G</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increased attack surface</strong>: With millions and even billions more connected devices, 5G makes it possible for larger and more dangerous attacks. Current and future vulnerabilities of the existing internet infrastructure are only exacerbated. The risk of more sophisticated botnets, privacy violations, and faster data extraction can escalate with 5G.</li>
<li><strong>More IoT, more problems</strong>: IoT devices are inherently insecure; security is often not built-in by design. Each insecure IoT device on an organization’s networks represents another potential hole that an attacker can expose.</li>
<li><strong>Decreased network visibility</strong>: With 5G, our networks will only expand and become more usable by mobile users and devices. This means much more network traffic to manage. But without a robust wide area network (WAN) security solution like Secure Access Service Edge (SASE) in place, companies may not be able to gain the network traffic visibility required to identify abnormalities or attacks.</li>
<li><strong>Increased supply chain and software vulnerabilities</strong>: Currently and for the foreseeable future, 5G supply chains are limited. Vulnerabilities exist — particularly as devices are rushed to market — increasing the potential for faulty and insecure components. Compared to traditional mobile networks, 5G is also more reliant on software, which elevates the risk of exploitation of the network infrastructure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges in rolling out 5G</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enabling critical infrastructures</strong>: 5G will require a fundamental change to the core architecture of the communication system. The major flaw of data transfer using 5G is that it can’t carry data over longer distances. Hence, even 5G technology needs to be augmented to enable infrastructure.</li>
<li><strong>Financial liability on consumers</strong>: For transition from 4G to 5G technology, one has to upgrade to the latest cellular technology, thereby creating financial liability on consumers.</li>
<li><strong>Capital Inadequacy</strong>: Lack of flow of cash and adequate capital with the suitable telecom companies (like Bharti Airtel and Vodafone Idea) is delaying the 5G spectrum allocation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India should not miss the opportunity and should proactively work to deploy 5G technology. We should focus on strengthening our cyber infrastructure.</li>
<li>5G start-ups that enable this design and manufacturing capabilities should be promoted. This will spur leaps in the coverage, capacity and density of wireless networks.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">Conclusion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The recent recommendation of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India to the government to develop a national road map for India to implement 5G in the best possible manner should include cyber security concerns.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. 5G is already transforming and enhancing connectivity. In this context Discuss India’s preparedness and cybersecurity challenges that needs to be taken care of for earlier roll out of 5G.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/5g-revolution/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Tomato Flu cases found in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tomato-flu/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Tomato Flu</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>With cases of tomato flu reported from at least four states — Kerala, Tamil Nadu, Haryana, and Odisha — the Union Health Ministry has issued a set of guidelines on prevention, testing, and treatment of the infection.</p>
<p>Researchers believe that it is a different clinical presentation of hand-foot-and mouth disease (HFMD) caused by a group of enteroviruses (viruses transmitted through the intestine).</p>
<h4>What is Tomato Flu?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Tomato flu or tomato fever is characterized by fever, joint pain, and red, tomato-like rashes usually seen in children below the age of five years.</li>
<li>This is accompanied by other symptoms of viral fevers such as diarrhoea, dehydration, nausea and vomiting, and fatigue.</li>
<li>This was thought to be an aftereffect of dengue and chikungunya that is commonly seen in Kerala.</li>
<li>However, researchers now believe that it is HFMD caused by enteroviruses like Coxsackievirus A-6 and A-16.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Is it very uncommon?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Tomato flu could be an after-effect of chikungunya or dengue fever in children rather than a viral infection.</li>
<li>It could also be a new variant of the viral hand, foot, and mouth disease, a common infectious disease targeting mostly children aged 1–5 years and immunocompromised adults.</li>
<li>HFMD is not a new infection, we have read about it in our textbooks. It is reported from time to time across the country, but it is not very common.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the infection spreading now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There actually are more cases or because we are more vigilant about viral infections and testing after Covid-19.</li>
<li>Since the disease is self-limiting, doctors do not usually test for it.</li>
<li>There are so many viral infections in children, but we cannot — and there is no need to — test for each and every one of it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Which pathogen is causing it now? And how is the clinical presentation different?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The current HFMD cases are mainly caused by Coxsackievirus A-6 and A-16.</li>
<li>Another pathogen — Enterovirus71 — that also causes the disease is not very prevalent now, according to her.</li>
<li>This is good because the pathogen was known to lead to severe neurologic symptoms, including fatal encephalitis (brain inflammation).</li>
<li>In almost all cases, say 99.9% cases, the disease is self-limiting.</li>
<li>But, in a small number of cases it can lead to CNS (central nervous system) complications.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Is there a treatment for the infection?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There is no specific treatment or vaccine available for the disease.</li>
<li>Those with the infection are treated symptomatically, such as prescription of paracetamol for fever.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How can the infection be prevented?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As it happens mainly in children, the Centre’s advisory focuses on preventions in these age groups.</li>
<li>As per the advisory, anyone suspected to have the infection should remain in isolation for five to seven days after the onset of the symptoms.</li>
<li>It states that children must be educated about the infection and asked not to hug or touch other children with fever or rashes.</li>
<li>The children should be encouraged to maintain hygiene, stop thumb or finger sucking, and use a handkerchief for a running nose, the advisory states.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tomato-flu/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Equitable education and health care needed for better future</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/equitable-education-and-health-care-needed-for-better-future/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>equitable health and education</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Equitable health and education" class="alignnone wp-image-625661" height="396" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-1.jpeg" width="595"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To create the foundation for the next century, we need to invest in equitable education and health care in the next 25 years not just for the elite, but for all.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is current status of education? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Expenditure on Education</strong>: The expenses on education as a percentage to GDP, India lags behind some developed/ developing nations.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure deficit</strong>: Dilapidated structures, single-room schools, lack of drinking water facilities, separate toilets and other educational infrastructure is a grave problem.</li>
<li><strong>Student-teacher ratio:</strong> Another challenge for improving the Indian education system is to improve the student teacher ratio.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is current status of healthcare?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Weak delivery</strong>: Current health infrastructure in India paints a dismal picture of the healthcare delivery system in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Unpreparedness</strong>: Public health experts believe that India is ill-equipped to handle emergencies.</li>
<li><strong>Technical glitches in urban areas:</strong> It is not prepared to tackle health epidemics, particularly given its urban congestion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>A systemic approach to reforming education system in the country needs</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dynamic pedagogy</strong>: Academic interventions involve the adoption of grade competence framework instead of just syllabus completion.</li>
<li><strong>Directional efforts</strong>: Effective delivery of remedial education for weaker students like after-school coaching, audio-video based education.</li>
<li><strong>Administrative reforms</strong>: that enable and incentivize teachers to perform better through data-driven insights, training, and recognition. Example: Performance based increments in Salary.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="equitable education and health" class="alignnone wp-image-625672" height="364" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 646px) 100vw, 646px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/school-298680_1280-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/school-298680_1280-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/school-298680_1280-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/school-298680_1280-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/school-298680_1280.jpeg 1200w" width="646"/>A systemic approach to reforming healthcare system in the country needs</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Universal health coverage</strong>: Access to healthcare in India is not equitable—the rich and the middle class would survive the COVID-19 or any other crisis but not the poor.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing healthcare professionals in numbers</strong>: India has handled the COVID-19 pandemic exceptionally well. However, India is in dire need of more medical staff and amenities.</li>
<li><strong>Revamping medical education</strong>: If the government wants to stay successful in fighting the COVID-19 pandemic, it needs to rapidly build medical institutions and increase the number of doctors.</li>
<li><strong>Cross-subsidization of health-care:</strong> How the poor managed without, or even with, any government insurance scheme is a big question. They can make up for the loss by cross-subsidizing treatments of patients with premium insurance policies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Recent initiatives</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>PLI scheme</strong>: In view of these challenges, the government announced various policies like PLI scheme for domestic manufacturing of active pharmaceutical ingredients (APIs).</li>
<li><strong>National Digital Health Mission</strong>: It also announced the National Digital Health Mission.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s healthcare system is too small for such a large population.</li>
<li>There seems to be a long battle ahead. The public healthcare system cannot be improved overnight.</li>
<li>The country needs all hands on deck during and after this crisis—both public and private sectors must work together and deliver universal health coverage for all citizens.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Providing expanded access to high quality education and healthcare supports—particularly for those young people who today lack such access—will not only expand economic opportunity for those individuals, but will also likely do more to strengthen the overall state economy.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. To create the foundation for the next century, we need to invest in education and health in the next 25 years not just for the elite, but for all. Critically examine</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/equitable-education-and-health-care-needed-for-better-future/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Vertical Launch Short Range Surface-to-Air Missile (VL-SRSAM)</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vertical-launch-short-range-surface-to-air-missile/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>VL-SRSAM</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Short range missiles development</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-625682" height="254" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 435px) 100vw, 435px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vrlsam-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vrlsam-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vrlsam.jpg 735w" width="435"/></p>
<p>The Defence Research and Development Organisation (DRDO) and the Indian Navy has successfully flight-tested the indigenously developed Vertical Launch Short Range Surface-to-Air Missile (VL-SRSAM) from the Integrated Test Range (ITR) at Chandipur off the coast of Odisha.</p>
<h4>What is Vertical Launch Short Range Surface-to-Air Missile (VLSRSAM) ?</h4>
<ul>
<li>VL-SRSAM has been designed and developed jointly by three facilities of the DRDO for deployment of Indian Naval warships.</li>
<li>The missile has the capability of neutralising various aerial threats at close ranges including sea-skimming targets.</li>
<li>The tactic of sea skimming is used by various anti-ship missiles and some fighter jets to avoid being detected by the radars onboard warships.</li>
<li>For this, these assets fly as close as possible to sea surface and thus are difficult to detect and neutralise.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Features of VL-SRSAM</h4>
<ul>
<li>The missile has been designed to strike at the high-speed airborne targets at the <strong><u>range of 40 to 50 km</u></strong> and at an <strong><u>altitude of around 15 km</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Its design is based on <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/astra-mk-i-air-to-air-missile-features-strategic-significance/">Astra missile</a> which is a <strong><u>Beyond Visual Range Air to Air missile</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Two key features of the VL-SRSAM are <strong><u>cruciform wings</u></strong> and <strong><u>thrust vectoring</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>cruciform wings</u></strong> are four small wings arranged like a cross on four sides and give the projective a stable aerodynamic posture.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>thrust vectoring</u></strong> is an ability to change the direction of the thrust from its engine control the angular velocity and the attitude of the missile.</li>
<li>VL-SRSAM is a <strong><u>canisterised system</u></strong>, which means it is stored and operated from specially designed compartments.</li>
<li>In the canister, the inside <strong><u>environment is controlled</u></strong>, thus making its transport and storage easier and improving the shelf life of weapons</li>
</ul>
<h4>Strategic significance of the missile</h4>
<ul>
<li>The launch was conducted from a vertical launcher against an electronic target at a very low altitude.</li>
<li>The flight path of the vehicle along with health parameters was monitored using a number of tracking instruments deployed by ITR, Chandipur.</li>
<li>The successful testing of these systems was crucial for future launches of the missile from Indian Naval Ships.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vertical-launch-short-range-surface-to-air-missile/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>With eye on defaulters, Centre tweaks Overseas Investment Rules</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-tweaks-overseas-investment-rules/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Preventive fugitive offences</p></div></div><p>The Finance Ministry has released the Rules for Foreign Exchange Management (Overseas Investment Rules), 2022 subsuming extant regulations for Overseas Investments and Acquisition and Transfer of Immovable Property outside India Regulations, 2015.</p>
<h4>What are the news Overseas Investment Rules?</h4>
<ul>
<li>With an eye on wilful defaulters, the new rules stipulate that:</li>
<li>Any Indian resident will have to seek an no objection certificate before making any overseas financial commitment:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Who has an account appearing as a non-performing asset</li>
<li>Or is classified as a wilful defaulter by any bank</li>
<li>Or is under investigation by a financial service regulator or by investigative agencies in India</li>
</ol>
<h4>What are the tweaks in overseas investment norms?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Any resident in India acquiring equity capital in a foreign entity or overseas direct investment (ODI), will have to submit an Annual Performance Report (APR) for each foreign entity, every year by December 31.</li>
<li>No such reporting shall be required where a person resident in India is holding less than 10% of the equity capital without control in the foreign entity.</li>
<li>There is no other financial commitment other than equity capital or a foreign entity is under liquidation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Ceiling on investment</h4>
<ul>
<li>Any resident individual can make ODI by way of investment in equity capital or overseas portfolio investment (OPI) subject to the overall ceiling under the Liberalised Remittance Scheme (LRS) of the Reserve Bank.</li>
<li>Currently, the LRS permits $2,50,000 outward investment by an individual in a year.</li>
<li>These norms make it easier for domestic corporates to invest abroad.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the prohibitions?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Any Indian resident, who has been classified as a wilful defaulter or is under investigation by the CBI, the ED or the Serious Frauds Investigation Office (SFIO), will have to obtain a no-objection certificate (NOC).</li>
<li>NOC can be obtained from his or her bank, regulatory body or investigative agency before making any overseas “financial commitment” or disinvestment of overseas assets.</li>
<li>The rules also provide that if lenders, the concerned regulatory body or investigative agency fail to furnish the NOC within 60 days of receiving an application, it may be presumed that they have no objection to the proposed transaction.</li>
<li>Additionally, the new rules also prohibit Indian residents from making investments into foreign entities that are engaged in real estate activity, gambling in any form, and dealing with financial products linked to the Indian rupee without the specific approval of the RBI.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-tweaks-overseas-investment-rules/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran drops some of its key demands for Nuclear Pact</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/iran-drops-some-of-its-key-demands-for-nuclear-deal/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>JCPOA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>US sanctions on Iran, Nuclear deal</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-625683" height="284" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 510px) 100vw, 510px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/iranus-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/iranus-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/iranus-768x429.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/iranus.jpg 824w" width="510"/></p>
<p>Iran has dropped some of its main demands on resurrecting a deal to rein in Tehran’s nuclear programme, including its insistence that international inspectors close some probes of its program, bringing the possibility of an Iran–US agreement closer.</p>
<p><strong>Which agreement is this article referring to?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>It is an alternative name of the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action (JCPOA).</li>
</ul>
<h4>What demands of Iran are we talking about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Iran had already largely relented on its demand that the US lift its designation of the Iran Revolutionary Guard Corps as a <strong><u>foreign terrorist organization (FTO) entity</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This designation was a <strong><u>more of symbolic move</u></strong> and <strong><u>insulting to Iranian authorities</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Iran also wanted a guarantee that the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/international-atomic-energy-agency-iaea/">International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA)</a> would close investigations involving unexplained traces of uranium.</li>
<li>Iran wants guarantees that the IAEA would close all of them.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is JCPOA?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Iran nuclear deal, formally known as the JCPOA is a landmark accord reached between Iran and several world powers, including the United States, in July 2015.</li>
<li>Under its terms, Iran agreed to dismantle much of its nuclear program and open its facilities to more extensive international inspections in exchange for billions of dollars’ worth of sanctions relief.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Expected outcomes of the deal</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Curb on the nuclear program:</strong> Proponents of the deal said that it would help prevent a revival of Iran’s nuclear weapons program.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing regional engagement:</strong> It would thereby reduce the prospects for conflict between Iran and its regional rivals, including Israel and Saudi Arabia.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Background of the JCPOA</h4>
<ul>
<li>Iran had previously agreed to forgo the development of nuclear weapons as a signatory to the Nuclear Non-proliferation Treaty, which has been in force since 1970.</li>
<li>However, after the overthrow of the Pahlavi dynasty in 1979, Iranian leaders secretly pursued this technology.</li>
<li>In 2007, U.S. intelligence analysts concluded that Iran halted its work on nuclear weapons in 2003 but continued to acquire nuclear technology and expertise.</li>
<li>Prior to the JCPOA, the P5+1 had been negotiating with Iran for years, offering its government various incentives to halt uranium enrichment.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with the deal</h4>
<p><strong>(1) US withdrawal</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The deal has been in jeopardy since President Donald Trump withdrew the US from it in 2018.</li>
<li>In retaliation for the US, Iran resumed some of its nuclear activities.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Iran’s insistence over sanctions removal</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In 2021, President Joe Biden said the US will return to the deal if Iran comes back into compliance, though Iran’s leaders have insisted that Washington lift sanctions first.</li>
<li>Iran now has indicated that he will take a harder line than his predecessor in nuclear negotiations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who are the participants?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The JCPOA, which went into effect in January 2016, imposes restrictions on Iran’s civilian nuclear enrichment program.</li>
<li>At the heart of negotiations with Iran were the five permanent members of the UN Security Council (China, France, Russia, the United Kingdom, and the United States) and Germany—collectively known as the P5+1.</li>
<li>The European Union also took part. Israel explicitly opposed the agreement, calling it too lenient.</li>
<li>Some Middle Eastern powers, such as Saudi Arabia, said they should have been consulted or included in the talks because they would be most affected by a nuclear-armed Iran.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What did Iran agree to?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nuclear restrictions:</strong> Iran agreed not to produce either the highly enriched uranium or the plutonium that could be used in a nuclear weapon.</li>
<li><strong>Monitoring and verification:</strong>  Iran agreed to eventually implement a protocol that would allow inspectors from the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA), the United Nations’ nuclear watchdog.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What did the other signatories agree to?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sanctions relief:</strong> The EU, United Nations, and United States all committed to lifting their nuclear-related sanctions on Iran. However, many other U.S. sanctions on Iran, some dating back to the 1979 hostage crisis, remained in effect.</li>
<li><strong>Weapons embargo:</strong> The parties agreed to lift an existing UN ban on Iran’s transfer of conventional weapons and ballistic missiles after five years if the IAEA certifies that Iran is only engaged in civilian nuclear activity.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How has the deal affected Iran’s economy?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Prior to the JCPOA, Iran’s economy suffered <strong><u>years of recession, currency depreciation, and inflation, largely because of sanctions on its energy sector</u></strong>.</li>
<li>With the sanctions lifted, inflation slowed, exchange rates stabilized, and exports—especially of oil, agricultural goods, and luxury items­—skyrocketed as Iran regained trading partners, particularly in the EU.</li>
<li>After the JCPOA took effect, Iran began exporting more than 2.1 million barrels per day (approaching pre-2012 levels, when the oil sanctions were originally put in place).</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this question from CSP 2020:</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Q.In India, why are some nuclear reactors kept under “IAEA Safeguards” while others are not?</strong></p>
<p>(a) Some use Uranium and others use thorium.</p>
<p>(b) Some use imported uranium and others use domestic supplies.</p>
<p>(c) Some are operated by foreign enterprises and others are operated by domestic enterprises.</p>
<p>(d) Some are State- owned and others are privately-owned.</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA)</h4>
<ul>
<li>IAEA is an international organization that seeks to promote the peaceful use of nuclear energy and to inhibit its use for any military purpose, including nuclear weapons.</li>
<li>As the preeminent nuclear watchdog under the UN, the IAEA is entrusted with the task of upholding the principles of the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty of 1970.</li>
<li>It was established as an autonomous organization on July 29, 1957, at the height of the Cold War between the U.S. and the Soviet Union.</li>
<li>Though established independently of the UN through its own international treaty, the agency reports to both the UN General Assembly and the UNSC.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What are its safeguards?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Safeguards are activities by which the IAEA can verify that a State is living up to its international commitments not to use nuclear programs for nuclear weapons purposes.</li>
<li>Safeguards are based on assessments of the correctness and completeness of a State’s declared nuclear material and nuclear-related activities.</li>
<li>Verification measures include on-site inspections, visits, and ongoing monitoring and evaluation.</li>
</ul>
<p>Basically, two sets of measures are carried out in accordance with the type of safeguards agreements in force with a State.</p>
<ol>
<li>One set relates to verifying State reports of declared nuclear material and activities.</li>
<li>Another set enables the IAEA not only to verify the non-diversion of declared nuclear material but also to provide assurances as to the absence of undeclared nuclear material and activities in a State.</li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/iran-drops-some-of-its-key-demands-for-nuclear-deal/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Reinvigorating the Chabahar Port</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/chabahar-port/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>India-Iran Ties</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p> </p>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-239541" height="258" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/chaba-300x258.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/chaba-300x258.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/chaba-768x660.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/07/chaba.jpg 900w" width="300"/></p>
<p>After months of what appeared to be a go-slow, the Union government has pushed up its interest in using Iran’s Chabahar port to connect to Afghanistan and Central Asia for trade, with the visit of the Union Minister of Ports, Shipping &amp; Waterways to the port.</p>
<h4>Chabahar Port</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2016, India signed a deal with Iran entailing $8 billion investment in Chabahar port and industries in Chabahar Special Economic Zone.</li>
<li>The port is being developed as a transit route to Afghanistan and Central Asia.</li>
<li>India has already built a 240-km road connecting Afghanistan with Iran.</li>
<li>All this were expected to bring cargo to Bandar Abbas port and Chabahar port, and free Kabul from its dependence on Pakistan to reach the outer world.</li>
<li>Completion of this project would give India access to Afghanistan and beyond to Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, Tajikistan, Kyrgyzstan, Kazakhstan, Russia and Europe via 7,200-km-long multi-modal North-South Transport Corridor (INSTC).</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is Chabahar back in the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The visit is a chance to strengthen ties and the maritime relationship between the two countries.</li>
<li>Due to pandemic, there were less number of visits from India to Iran and vice-versa and the pace of the project is also allegedly slower.</li>
<li>This visit will also highlight the importance of Chabahar as a gateway for Indian trade with Europe, Russia and CIS [Commonwealth of Independent States] countries.</li>
<li>India is keen in developing the Shahid Beheshti port as a “a transit hub” and link it to the International North South Trade Corridor (INSTC), that also connects to Russia and Europe.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is India’s strategic vision for Chabahar?</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-625684" height="653" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 409px) 100vw, 409px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/chabahar-188x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/chabahar-188x300.jpg 188w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/chabahar-565x900.jpg 565w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/chabahar.jpg 632w" width="409"/></p>
<ul>
<li>When the first agreement for Chabahar was signed by then PM Atal Bihari Vajpayee in 2003, the plan had a three-fold objective:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>To build India’s first offshore port and to project Indian infrastructure prowess in the Gulf</li>
<li>To circumvent trade through Pakistan, given the tense ties with India’s neighbour and build a long term, sustainable sea trade route and</li>
<li>To find an alternative land route to Afghanistan, which India had rebuilt ties with after the defeat of the Taliban in 2001</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Subsequently, PM Manmohan Singh’s government constructed the Zaranj -Delaram Highway in Afghanistan’s South.</li>
<li>It would help connect the trade route from the border of Iran to the main trade routes to Herat and Kabul, handing it over to the Karzai government in 2009.</li>
<li>In 2016, PM Modi travelled to Tehran and signed the agreement to develop Chabahar port, as well as the trilateral agreement for trade through Chabahar with Afghanistan’s President Ashraf Ghani.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Commencement of operations</h4>
<ul>
<li>Since the India Ports Global Chabahar Free Zone (IPGCFZ) authority took over the operations of the port in 2018, it has handled 215 vessels, 16,000 TEUs (Twenty-foot Equivalent Units) and four million tons of bulk and general cargo.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is it gaining importance?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the last few years, a fourth strategic objective for the Chabahar route has appeared, with <strong><u>China’s Belt and Road Initiative making inroads</u></strong> in the region.</li>
<li>The government hopes to provide Central Asia with an alternate route to the <strong><u>China-Pakistan Economic Corridor (CPEC)</u></strong> through Iran for future trade.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the Chabahar dream taking so long to realise?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s quest for Chabahar has hit <strong><u>geopolitical road-block</u></strong> after road-block; the biggest issue has been over Iran’s relationship with western countries, especially the United States.</li>
<li>In years when <strong><u>western sanctions</u></strong> against Iran increased, the Chabahar project has been put on the back-burner.</li>
<li>However, the nuclear talks resulted in the <strong><u>Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action (JCPOA)</u></strong> in 2015 came into being, the Chabahar port has been easier to work on.</li>
<li>In 2018, the <strong><u>Trump administration</u></strong> put paid to India’s plans by <strong><u>walking out of the JCPOA</u></strong> and slapping <strong><u>new sanctions</u></strong> on dealing with Iran.</li>
<li>This led to the Modi government <strong><u>“zeroing out” all its oil imports from Iran</u></strong>, earlier a major supplier to India, causing a strain in ties.</li>
<li>India also <strong><u>snapped ties with Afghanistan after the Taliban takeover</u></strong> in August 2021, which put an end to the humanitarian aid of wheat and pulses that was being sent to Kabul via Chabahar.</li>
<li>When India restarted wheat aid this year, it <strong><u>negotiated with Pakistan</u></strong> to use the <strong><u>land route to Afghanistan instead. </u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/chabahar-port/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Benami Law can’t be applied retrospectively: SC</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/benami-law-cant-be-applied-retrospective/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Benami Properties</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has declared as “unconstitutional and manifestly arbitrary” the amendments introduced to the Benami Property Transactions Act, 1988  in 2016, which apply retrospectively and can send a person to prison for three years even as it empowers the Centre to confiscate “any property” subject to a benami transaction.</p>
<h4>What is Benami Property?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Benami in Hindi means without name. So, a property bought by an individual not under his or her name is benami property.</li>
<li>It can include property held in the name of spouse or child for which the <strong><u>amount is paid out of known sources of income. </u></strong></li>
<li>A joint property with brother, sister or other relatives for which the amount is paid out of known sources of income also falls under benami property.</li>
<li>The transaction involved in the same is called benami transaction.</li>
<li>The benami transactions include buying assets of any kind — movable, immovable, tangible, intangible, any right or interest, or legal documents.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why do people indulge in such transactions?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As a usual practice, to evade taxation, people invest their black money in buying benami property.</li>
<li>The real owner of these properties are hard to trace due to fake names and identities.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the Benami Law?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The first act against benami properties was passed in 1988 as the Prohibition of Benami Property Transactions Act, 1988.</li>
<li>To block all <strong><u>loopholes</u></strong>, the government in July 2016 decided to amend the original act.</li>
<li>So after further amendment, Benami Transactions (Prohibition) Amendment Act, 2016 came into force on November 1, 2016.</li>
<li>The PBPT Act defines benami transactions, prohibits them and further provides that violation of the PBPT Act is punishable with imprisonment and fine.</li>
<li>The PBPT Act <strong><u>prohibits recovery of the property</u></strong> held benami from benamidar by the real owner.</li>
<li>Such, <strong><u>properties are liable for confiscation</u></strong> by the Government without payment of compensation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What amendment is this article talking about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 2016 law amended the original Benami Act of 1988, expanding it to 72 Sections from a mere nine.</li>
<li>Sections 3(2) and 5 were introduced through the Benami Transactions (Prohibition) Amendment Act, 2016.</li>
<li>A Bench, led by CJI N.V. Ramana, declared Sections 3(2) and 5 introduced through this amendment as unconstitutional.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Which sections did the Supreme Court declare unconstitutional?</h4>
<h4>(b) Section 3(2)</h4>
<ul>
<li>A/c to this, a <strong><u>person can be sent behind bars for a benami transaction entered into 28 years before the Section even came into existence</u></strong>.</li>
<li>CJI Ramana held that the <strong><u>provision violated Article 20(1) of the Constitution</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Article 20(1) mandates that <strong><u>no person should be convicted of an offence, which was not in force “at the time of the commission </u></strong>of the act charged as an offence”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(b) Section 5</h4>
<ul>
<li>It said that “any <strong><u>benami property shall be liable to be confiscated</u></strong> by the Central Government”.</li>
<li>The court held that this confiscation provision<strong><u> cannot be applied retrospectively</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The CJI dismissed the government’s version that forfeiture, acquisition and confiscation of property under the 2016 Act was <strong><u>not in the nature of prosecution</u></strong> and cannot be restricted under Article 20.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What else did the apex court observe?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court observed that the 2016 Act condemned not only transactions that were traditionally denominated as benami but also a “new class of fictitious and sham transactions”.</li>
<li>The court said the intention of Parliament was to condemn property acquired from ill-gotten wealth.</li>
<li>These proceedings cannot be equated as enforcing civil obligations, the CJI noted.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why curb benami transactions?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inflationary implications:</strong> Rather than hoarding the black money in cash, the tax evader invest their accumulated illegal money in buying benami properties.</li>
<li><strong>Loss of economic activity:</strong> The whole process affects the revenue generation of government hampering growth and development of the state.</li>
<li><strong>Tax evasion:</strong> Since the percentage of tax payer in the country is a dismal low, the government fails to successfully implement its policies and schemes due to lack of resources.</li>
<li><strong>Money laundering:</strong> Benami transactions also serves the illicit purpose of money laundering.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>A tough law against benami properties is the need of the hour to check corruption.</li>
<li>However, due process of law needs to be followed in true letter and spirit.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/benami-law-cant-be-applied-retrospective/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>