<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 04:51:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>India’s tax-GDP ratio may be too high</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-tax-gdp-ratio-may-be-too-high/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Tax buoyancy</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Tax-to-GDP ratio</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>What the data conclusively show is that the debate on the Indian economy should shift away from simplistic notions (borrowed from the West?) of the tax-GDP ratio being low in India.</p>
<h4>India’s low tax-to-GDP ratio</h4>
<ul>
<li>One of the stylised beliefs in India, and amongst some leading economic commentators both in India and abroad, is that our tax/GDP ratio is lower than what it “should” be.</li>
<li>This low tax-to-GDP ratio is blamed for a<strong> lower rate of investment</strong>, a<strong> higher fiscal deficit</strong>, and lower GDP growth — and all because the tax ratio is too low.</li>
<li>There can be reasonable doubts about the presumed links.</li>
<li>There are three important fiscal variables in the economy — <strong>taxes, fiscal deficit, and debt. </strong></li>
<li>They are inter-related — lower tax revenue means higher fiscal deficit, for the same level of expenditures, and higher deficit means higher debt.</li>
<li>All three, directly or indirectly, are assumed <strong>to affect growth and/or inflation.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>Analysing India’s tax-to-GDP ratio</h4>
<ul>
<li>Two common observations on tax-to-GDP for India — first, it is low at around<strong> 10-11 per cent of GDP</strong> and it has stayed at close to that level for the last 20 years.</li>
<li>In 2019, it hit a decade low of 10 per cent of GDP, the same as in 2014.</li>
<li>Second, in comparison with our peers, it is much lower.</li>
<li>Hence, logic dictates that we should strive to increase it.</li>
<li>But which country should we compare India with?</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with comparing tax-to-GDP with other countries</h4>
<ul>
<li>A common observation is to look at the tax-GDP ratio in G20 countries.</li>
<li><strong>Function of average level of per capita income:</strong> This is the beginning of a set of misinterpretations committed either knowingly, or unknowingly.</li>
<li>Because simple logic dictates that tax collected is <strong>a function of the average level of per capita income.</strong></li>
<li>Per capita income in the G20 varies from around $2,100 (India) to around $65,000 (US).</li>
<li>The 10-11 per cent figure for India is the tax/GDP <strong>ratio for taxes administered at the central level.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Challenges in data collection</strong>: Taxes in India, as in many other large, especially federal, countries, are collected at both a federal and state level.</li>
<li>And many economies have local (municipal) taxes as well. The tax collected is the sum of all these taxes.</li>
<li>Until now, collecting such disaggregated data for a large set of countries was challenging.</li>
<li>However, in a recent web publication, the IMF on their World Revenue Longitudinal Data set has published such data for all countries, from 1990-2019.</li>
<li>In this pre-pandemic year, among G20 economies, India’s tax-GDP (Xtax) ratio of 16.7 per cent was higher than that of China (15.9 per cent), Mexico (14.1 per cent), Indonesia (11.0 per cent), Saudi Arabia (5.9 per cent) and Turkey (15.9 per cent).</li>
<li>A more informative indicator of whether a country is taxing too much or too little in comparison with others is to look at the <strong>tax-GDP ratio adjusted for PPP per capita income.</strong></li>
<li>Prediction via a simple regression of tax-to-GDP on log PPP per capita GDP can yield one estimate of the tax gap — the difference between actual and actual adjusted for level of income.</li>
<li>The world average tax gap is -1.3 per cent;<strong> India is +1.2 per cent for the nine years 2011-2019.</strong></li>
<li>So, India’s tax GDP ratio averages 2.5 percentage points more than an average economy.</li>
<li>For every year for which data are available 1990-2019, India has had a positive tax gap — there is little evidence that a higher tax/GDP ratio helps growth.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How corporate tax cut helped India</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Corporate tax cut 2019:</strong> For years, the advocacy in India was to increase revenue from corporate tax which is one of three major components of tax revenue, the other being income and indirect taxes.</li>
<li>In September 2019, Finance Minister going well against Indian established conventional wisdom, lowered the corporate tax rate by around 10 percentage points.</li>
<li><strong>Avoiding triple whammy</strong>: Opponents said that empirical evidence around the world (for example, the US) meant that <strong>if tax rates were lowered, revenues would decline, the fisc would increase, as would inequality.</strong></li>
<li>A triple whammy that is best avoided.</li>
<li>However, now, three years later, we can assess the efficacy (or not) of this bold experiment.</li>
<li>For the three months April-June 2022, corporate tax revenues, y-o-y, are up 30 per cent.</li>
<li>Using fiscal 2019-20 as a base, corporate tax revenue has increased by 66 per cent, GDP by 33 per cent —<strong> an average tax buoyancy of 2.0 over three years. </strong></li>
<li>The previous largest tax buoyancy was in 2006-7 when the world was buoyant.</li>
<li>Tentatively, the tax-GDP ratio in the fiscal year 2022-23 will <strong>average over 18 per cent in India</strong>, a level close to Japan and the US.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>In India, the debate should shift to expenditures, and quality of expenditures (and perhaps to reform of the direct tax code). In this regard, suggestion that freebies be critically examined is most timely and welcome.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<hr/>
<h4> Back2Basics: Tax buoyancy and tax elasticity</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tax buoyancy:</strong> The buoyancy of a tax system <b>measures the total response of tax revenue both to changes in</b>. <b>national income and to discretionary changes in tax policies over time</b>, and it is traditionally interpreted as the percentage change in revenue associated to a one percent change in income.</li>
<li>Tax elasticity: It refers to changes in tax revenue in response to <strong>changes in tax rate. </strong></li>
<li>For example, how tax revenue changes if the government reduces corporate income tax from 30 per cent to 25 per cent indicate tax elasticity.</li>
</ul>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-tax-gdp-ratio-may-be-too-high/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Artforms in news: Yakshagana dance</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/artforms-in-news-yakshagana/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Yakshagana</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-535016" height="186" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/yaksh-300x186.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/yaksh-300x186.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/yaksh-768x476.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/yaksh.jpg 822w" width="300"/></strong></p>
<p>This newscard is an excerpt of the original article published in TH.</p>
<h4>What is Yakshagana?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Yakshagana is a traditional theater, developed in Dakshina Kannada, Udupi, Uttara Kannada, Shimoga and western parts of Chikmagalur districts, in the state of <strong>Karnataka</strong> and in Kasaragod district in <strong>Kerala</strong>.</li>
<li>It emerged in the Vijayanagara Empire and was performed by<strong> Jakkula Varu.</strong></li>
<li><strong><u>It combines dance, music, dialogue, costume, make-up, and stage techniques with a unique style and form.</u></strong></li>
<li>Towards the south from Dakshina Kannada to Kasaragod of Tulu Nadu region, the form of Yakshagana is called as ‘<strong>Thenku thittu’</strong> and towards north from Udupi up to Uttara Kannada it’s called as ‘<strong>Badaga Thittu</strong>‘.</li>
<li>It is sometimes simply called “Aata” or āṭa (meaning “the play”). Yakshagana is traditionally presented from dusk to dawn.</li>
<li>Its stories are drawn from <strong>Ramayana</strong>, <strong>Mahabharata</strong>, <strong>Bhagavata</strong> and other epics from both <strong>Hindu</strong> and <strong>Jain</strong> and other ancient Indic traditions.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this question from CSP 2017:</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Q.With reference to Manipuri Sankirtana, consider the following statements:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>It is a song and dance performance.</li>
<li>Cymbals are the only musical instruments used in the performance.</li>
<li>It is performed to narrate the life and deeds of Lord Krishna.</li>
</ol>
<p>Which of the statements given above is/are correct?</p>
<p>(a) 1, 2 and 3.</p>
<p>(b) 1 and 3 only</p>
<p>(c) 2 and 3 only</p>
<p>(d) 1 only</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/artforms-in-news-yakshagana/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Explained: The Competition (Amendment) Bill, 2022</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-the-competition-amendment-bill-2022/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Competition Amendment Bill 2022</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The long-awaited Bill to amend the Competition Act, 2002, was finally tabled in the Lok Sabha recently.</p>
<p><strong>What is the Indian Competition Act?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Indian Competition Act was passed in 2002, but it came into effect only seven years later.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-competition-commission-of-india/">Competition Commission</a> primarily pursues three issues of anti-competitive practices in the market: anti-competitive agreements, abuse of dominance and combinations.</li>
<li>As the dynamics of the market changes rapidly due to technological advancements, AI, and the increasing importance of factors other than price, amendments became necessary to sustain and promote market competition.</li>
<li>Therefore, a review committee was established in 2019 which proposed several major amendments.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Competition (Amendment) Bill, 2022: Key features</strong></p>
<p><strong>(1) Regulation of combinations based on transaction value</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Act prohibits any person or enterprise from entering into a combination which may cause an appreciable adverse effect on competition.</li>
<li>Combinations imply mergers, acquisitions, or amalgamation of enterprises.</li>
<li>The prohibition applies to transactions where parties involved have: (i) cumulative assets of more than Rs 1,000 crore, or (ii) cumulative turnover of more than Rs 3,000 crore, subject to certain other conditions.</li>
<li>The Bill expands the definition of combinations to include transactions with a value above Rs 2,000 crore.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2)  Definition of control for classification of combination:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>For classification of combinations, the Act defines control as control over the affairs or management by one or more enterprises over another enterprise or group.</li>
<li>The Bill modifies the definition of control as the ability to exercise material influence over the management, affairs, or strategic commercial decisions.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Time limit for approval of combinations</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Act specifies that any combination shall not come into effect until the CCI has passed an order or 210 days have passed from the day when an application for approval was filed, whichever is earlier.</li>
<li>The Bill reduces the time limit in the latter case to 150 days.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Anti-competitive agreements</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Under the Act, anti-competitive agreements include any agreement related to production, supply, storage, or control of goods or services, which can cause an appreciable adverse effect on competition in India.</li>
<li>Any agreement between enterprises or persons, engaged in identical or similar businesses, will have such adverse effect on competition if it meets certain criteria.</li>
<li>These include: (i) directly or indirectly determining purchase or sale prices, (ii) controlling production, supply, markets, or provision of services, or (iii) directly or indirectly leading to collusive bidding.</li>
<li>The Bill adds that enterprises or persons not engaged in identical or similar businesses shall be presumed to be part of such agreements, if they actively participate in the furtherance of such agreements.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Settlement and Commitment in anti-competitive proceedings</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Under the Act, CCI may initiate proceedings against enterprises on grounds of: (i) entering into anti-competitive agreements, or (ii) abuse of dominant position.</li>
<li>Abuse of dominant position includes: (i) discriminatory conditions in the purchase or sale of goods or services, (ii) restricting production of goods or services, or (iii) indulging in practices leading to the denial of market access.</li>
<li>The Bill permits CCI to close inquiry proceedings if the enterprise offers: (i) settlement (may involve payment), or (ii) commitments (may be structural or behavioral in nature).</li>
<li>The manner and implementation of settlement and commitment may be specified by CCI through regulations.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Relevant product market</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Act defines relevant product market as products and services which are considered substitutable by the consumer.</li>
<li>The Bill widens this to include the production or supply of products and services considered substitutable by the suppliers.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(7) Decriminalization of certain offences</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Bill changes the nature of punishment for certain offences from imposition of fine to penalty.</li>
<li>These offences include failure to comply with orders of CCI and directions of Director General with regard to anti-competitive agreements and abuse of dominant position.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Most notable amendment on: Merger and acquisition</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Any acquisition, merger or amalgamation may constitute a combination.</li>
<li>Section 5 currently says parties indulging in merger, acquisition, or amalgamation need to notify the Commission of the combination only on the basis of ‘asset’ or ‘turnover’.</li>
<li>The new Bill proposes to add a ‘deal value’ threshold.</li>
<li>It will be mandatory to notify the Competition Commission of any transaction with a deal value in excess of ₹2,000 crore and if either of the parties has ‘substantial business operations in India’.</li>
</ul>
<p>Key note on gun-jumping</p>
<ul>
<li>Parties should not go ahead with a combination prior to its approval.</li>
<li>If the combining parties close a notified transaction before the approval, or have consummated a reportable transaction without bringing it to the Commission’s knowledge, it is seen as gun-jumping.</li>
<li>The penalty for gun-jumping was a total of 1% of the asset or turnover.</li>
<li>This is now proposed to be 1% of the deal value.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What next?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>By implementing these amendments, the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-competition-commission-of-india/">Competition Commission</a> should be better equipped to handle certain aspects of the new-age market and transform its functioning to be more robust.</li>
<li>The proposed amendments are undoubtedly needed; however, these are heavily dependent on regulations that will be notified by the Commission later.</li>
<li>These regulations will influence the proposals.</li>
<li>Also, the government needs to recognize that market dynamics change constantly, so it is necessary to update laws regularly.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-the-competition-amendment-bill-2022/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Floor Test?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/626095/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Floor Test</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>Bihar Chief Minister has won the floor test in the Assembly.</p>
<h4>What is a floor test?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A floor test is a measure to check whether the executive is enjoying the confidence of the legislature.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>It is a constitutional mechanism under which a Chief Minister appointed by the Governor can be asked to prove majority on the floor of the Legislative Assembly of the state.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How is it conducted?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As per the Constitution, the Chief Minister is appointed by the Governor of the state.</li>
<li>When a single party secures the majority of the seats in the house, the Governor appoints the leader of the party as the Chief Minister.</li>
<li>In case the majority is questioned, the leader of the party which claims majority has to move a vote of confidence and prove majority among those present and voting.</li>
<li>The Chief Minister has to resign if they fail to prove their majority in the house.</li>
<li>This happens both in the parliament and the state legislative assemblies.</li>
<li>In situations when there are differences within a coalition government, the Governor can ask the Chief Minister to prove majority in the house.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Can a floor test be postponed?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court recently had given some respite to some rebel leaders in Maharashtra to respond to the disqualification notice issued by the Speaker.</li>
<li>Citing this as the reason, the original party leaders and loyalists have stated that it is ‘unlawful’ to initiate a floor test when the disqualification decision of the rebel leaders is pending.</li>
<li>However, the previous judgments of the Supreme Court had ruled that the floor test needs not to be deferred even if the decision to disqualify the members is pending.</li>
<li>In the 2020 Shivraj Singh Chouhan v/s Speaker case, the court had clarified the same.</li>
<li>Additionally, the top court had allowed the rebel leaders to skip the floor test during the political crisis in Karnataka in 2019.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is composite floor test?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There is another test, Composite Floor Test, which is <strong><u>conducted only when more than one person stakes claim to form the government.</u></strong></li>
<li>When the majority is not clear, the governor might call for a special session to see who has the majority.</li>
<li>The majority is counted based on those present and voting. This <strong><u>can also be done through a voice vote</u></strong> where the member can respond orally or through division voting.</li>
<li>Some legislators may be absent or choose not to vote.</li>
<li>In division vote, voting can be done through electronic gadgets, ballots or slips.</li>
<li>The person who has the majority will form the government. In case of tie, the speaker can also cast his vote.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Governors’ discretion</h4>
<ul>
<li>When no party gets a clear majority, the governor can use his discretion in the selection of chief ministerial candidate to prove the majority as soon as possible.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with the floor test</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sometimes ruling party MLAs are lured with rewards, political or otherwise.</li>
<li>Thus, the “floor test” becomes constitutionally immoral and unjust.</li>
<li>This will amount to circumventing the Tenth Schedule through engineered defections through the judicial process.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: No Confidence Motion</h4>
<ul>
<li>The process is explained under rule 198 of the Lok Sabha.</li>
<li>Though there is no mention of the term ‘No confidence motion’ or ‘floor test’ in the Constitution, <strong><u>Articles 75 and 164</u></strong> do mention that the executive both at the Centre and state is collectively responsible to their respective legislatures.</li>
<li>Any member from the Opposition can move the no-confidence motion against the ruling government.</li>
<li>The motion has to receive the backing of at least 50 members before it is accepted and subsequently.</li>
<li>A date for the discussion of the motion is announced by the Speaker, which has to be within 10 days from the date of acceptance.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/626095/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Automatic Number Plate Reader (ANPR) cameras for toll collection</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/automatic-number-plate-reader-anpr-cameras-for-toll-collection/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Automatic Number Plate Reader (ANPR)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Toll collection models in India</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-626097" height="289" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 525px) 100vw, 525px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/anpr-300x165.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/anpr-300x165.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/anpr-768x423.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/anpr.jpg 879w" width="525"/></p>
<p>In light of congestion at toll plazas, the Road Transport and Highways Ministry is now moving ahead with a plan to replace toll plazas with cameras that could read number plates, also known as Automatic Number Plate Reader (ANPR) cameras.</p>
<h4>ANPR cameras</h4>
<ul>
<li>The plan is to remove toll plazas on national highways and instead rely on ANPR cameras, which will read vehicle number plates and automatically deduct toll from the linked bank accounts of vehicle owners.</li>
<li>The model is simple: Entry and exit of toll roads will have cameras capable of reading number plates, and toll will be deducted based on these cameras.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Can all number plates be read by the cameras?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Not all number plates in India can be read, and only those that have come after 2019 will be registered by the cameras.</li>
<li>The government, in 2019, had come up with a rule mandating passenger vehicles to have company-fitted number plates, and only these number plates can be read by cameras.</li>
<li>The government plans to come up with a scheme to replace older number plates.</li>
<li>A pilot of this scheme is underway and legal amendments to facilitate this transition are also being moved to penalise vehicle owners who skip toll plazas and do not pay.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Current model for toll collection: FASTags</h4>
<ul>
<li>Currently, about 97 per cent of the total toll collection of nearly Rs 40,000 crore happens though FASTags — the remaining 3 per cent pay higher than normal toll rates for not using FASTags.</li>
<li>With FASTags, it takes about 47 seconds per vehicle to cross a toll plaza.</li>
<li>There’s a marked throughput enhancement – more than 260 vehicles can be processed per hour via electronic toll collection lane as compared to 112 vehicles per hour via manual toll collection lane, according to government data.</li>
<li>While FASTags have eased traffic at toll plazas across the country, congestion is still reported as there are toll gates that need to be crossed after authentication.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why such move?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Congestion at toll plazas on national highways continues to impact commuters despite 97 per cent of tolling happening through <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-fastags/">FASTags</a>.</li>
<li>Apart from ANPR helping to ease congestion, the government is also looking at GPS technology as one of the options for toll collection.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Are there issues with ANPR?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The success of ANPR cameras will depend on creating an ecosystem that is in sync with the requirements of the camera.</li>
<li>The biggest problem being faced during the trials is when things are written on number plates, beyond the nine digit registration number, such as ‘Govt of India/Delhi’ etc.</li>
<li>Another problem that ANPR cameras face is in reading number plates on trucks, as most of the time they are hidden or soiled etc.</li>
<li>A pilot on a key expressway has found that about 10 per cent of vehicles with such number plates are being missed by the ANPR cameras.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: <strong>What is ‘FASTag’?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As per Central Motor Vehicles Rules, 1989, since 1st December 2017, the FASTag had been made mandatory for all registered new four-wheelers and is being supplied by the Vehicle Manufacturer or their dealers.</li>
<li>It has been mandated that the renewal of fitness certificate will be done only after the fitment of FASTag.</li>
<li>For National Permit Vehicles, the fitment of FASTag was mandated since 1st October 2019.</li>
<li>FASTags are stickers that are affixed to the windscreen of vehicles and use Radio Frequency Identification (RFID) technology to enable digital, contactless payment of tolls without having to stop at toll gates.</li>
<li>The tags are linked to bank accounts and other payment methods.</li>
<li>As a car crosses a toll plaza, the amount is automatically deducted, and a notification is sent to the registered mobile phone number.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>How does it work?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The device employs Radio Frequency Identification (RFID) technology for payments directly from the prepaid or savings account linked to it.</li>
<li>It is affixed on the windscreen, so the vehicle can drive through plazas without stopping.</li>
<li>RFID technology is similar to that used in transport access-control systems, like Metro smart card.</li>
<li>If the tag is linked to a prepaid account like a wallet or a debit/credit card, then owners need to recharge/top up the tag.</li>
<li>If it is linked to a savings account, then money will get deducted automatically after the balance goes below a pre-defined threshold.</li>
<li>Once a vehicle crosses the toll, the owner will get an SMS alert on the deduction. In that, it is like a prepaid e-wallet.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/automatic-number-plate-reader-anpr-cameras-for-toll-collection/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was Vannuramma?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-vannuramma/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Vannuramma</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-626098" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 265px) 100vw, 265px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vanuramma-265x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vanuramma-265x300.jpg 265w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vanuramma.jpg 389w" width="265"/></strong></p>
<p>The fort of legendry Vannuramma in Nallamala forest in the present day Mydukur mandal of Kadapa district is trending due to its rundown condition.</p>
<h4>Who was Vannuramma?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Vannuramma ruled five ‘Durgams’ (under fiefdom) between 1781 and 1796 with Sakarlapadu as the administrative headquarters.</li>
<li>According to historical accounts, she was born in Pathimadugu Rekulakunta, now in Kadapa district, and got married to Veerneni Chinna Narasimha Naidu in 1764.</li>
<li>The family had the practice of praying at Vannuru Swamy temple in Kalyanadurgam of Anantapur district.</li>
<li>Vannuramma thus got her name as she was born, as believed, as the god’s gift.</li>
<li>Though there are not many historical accounts, Kadapa-based writer Bommisetty Ramesh brought out the first book last year on her.</li>
<li>Based on information culled out from the Mackenzie Kaifiyat of Kadapa, he extensively toured the region ruled by her, collected folklore and verified the same with historians.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Her legend</h4>
<ul>
<li>The very mention of the name ‘Vannuramma’ brought chill to the spine of the Matli kings and Kadapa Nawabs.</li>
<li>Of all the Polegars (local chieftains) who had ruled the regional territories of Rayalaseema before the advent of the British, the lone woman ruler remains forgotten from the pages of history.</li>
<li>Under attack from fellow Polegars, Vannuramma’s family fled Thippireddypalle and took shelter in Chagalamarri fort, where they lived for eight years before her husband breathed his last in 1780.</li>
<li>Vannuramma wielded the sword when the Matli king Appayya Raju and Mysore Sultan Hyder Ali’s follower Meeru Saheb waged a war, invaded Sakerlapadu Durgam and robbed the property of locals.</li>
<li>Mobilising her army, she declared a war and brought the territory back into her fold in 1781.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Her death</h4>
<ul>
<li>Even the Golconda Nawabs, through their Kadapa henchman Khadarvali Khan, tried in vain to control her.</li>
<li>It was then they hatched a plan to woo her adopted son and arrested her on some flimsy charges.</li>
<li>When the unsuspecting Vannuramma attended the Matli king’s court to prove her innocence, she was slapped with charges of treason.</li>
<li>The Nawabs captured her and sentenced her with ‘Korthi’, an inhuman form of punishment where a person is made to sit on a sharpened tree stump and left to die.</li>
<li>Vannuramma died in full public view in the year 1718 of Salivahana Saka, which translates to August 16, 1796, i.e., 226 years back.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-vannuramma/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>In news: James Webb Space Telescope</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/in-news-james-webb-space-telescope/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>James Webb Space Telescope, Jupiter</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-626103" height="273" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/jupiter-300x273.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/jupiter-300x273.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/jupiter.jpg 629w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The James Webb Space Telescope, NASA’s latest and most powerful telescope, has captured new images of our solar system’s largest planet, Jupiter, presenting it in a never before seen light.</p>
<h4>What is so special about snapping Jupiter?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The photographs have captured a new view of the planet, presenting in detail its massive storms, colourful auroras, faint rings and two small moons — <strong><u>Amalthea</u></strong> and <strong><u>Adrastea</u></strong>.</li>
<li>While most of us are familiar with the yellow and reddish-brown gas giant.</li>
<li>The JSWT’s Near-Infrared Camera, with its specialized infrared filters, has shown Jupiter encompassed in blue, green, white, yellow and orange hues.</li>
<li>Jupiter’s famous <strong><u>Great Red Spot</u></strong>, a storm so big that it could swallow Earth, appeared bright white in the image, since it was reflecting a lot of sunlight.</li>
<li>The brightness here indicates high altitude — so the Great Red Spot has <strong><u>high-altitude hazes</u></strong>, as does the equatorial region.</li>
<li>The numerous bright white <strong><u>‘spots’ and ‘streaks’</u></strong> are likely very high-altitude cloud tops of condensed convective storms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>About James Webb Space Telescope</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-505370" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 297px) 100vw, 297px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/jswt-1-297x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/jswt-1-297x300.jpg 297w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/jswt-1.jpg 613w" width="297"/></p>
<ul>
<li>JWST is a space telescope jointly developed by NASA, the European Space Agency (ESA), and the Canadian Space Agency (CSA).</li>
<li>It is planned to succeed the Hubble Space Telescope as NASA’s flagship astrophysics mission.</li>
<li>It will conduct a broad range of investigations across the fields of astronomy and cosmology, including:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Observing some of the most distant events and objects in the universe such as the formation of the first galaxies</li>
<li>Detailed atmospheric characterization of potentially habitable exoplanets</li>
</ol>
<h4>How is it different from other telescopes?</h4>
<ul>
<li>JWST is much more powerful and has the ability to look in the infrared spectrum, which will allow it to peer through much deeper into the universe, and see through obstructions such as gas clouds.</li>
<li>As electromagnetic waves travel for long distances, they lose energy, resulting in an increase in their wavelength.</li>
<li>An ultraviolet wave, for example, can slowly move into the visible light spectrum and the infrared spectrum, and further weaken to microwaves or radio waves, as it loses energy.</li>
<li>Hubble was designed to look mainly into the ultraviolet and visible regions of the electromagnetic spectrum.</li>
<li>JWST is primarily an infrared telescope, the first of its kind.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Special features of JWST</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Time machine in space</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Powerful space telescopes, like JWST or the Hubble Telescope, are often called time machines because of their ability to view very faraway objects.</li>
<li>The light coming from those objects, stars or galaxies, which is captured by these telescopes, began its journey millions of years earlier.</li>
<li>Essentially, what these telescopes see are images of these stars or galaxies as they were millions of years ago.</li>
<li>The more distant the planet or star, the farther back in time are the telescopes able to see.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Farthest from Earth</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>JWST will also be positioned much deeper into space, about a million miles from Earth, at a spot known as L2.</li>
<li>It is one of the five points, known as Lagrange’s points, in any revolving two-body system like Earth and Sun, where the gravitational forces of the two large bodies cancel each other out.</li>
<li>Objects placed at these positions are relatively stable and require minimal external energy to keep them there. L2 is a position directly behind Earth in the line joining the Sun and the Earth.</li>
<li>It would be shielded from the Sun by the Earth as it goes around the Sun, in sync with the Earth.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Engineering marvel</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>JWST has one large mirror, with a diameter of 21 feet (the height of a typical two-storey building), that will capture the infra-red light coming in from the deep universe while facing away from the Sun.</li>
<li>It will be shielded by a five-layer, tennis court-sized, kite-shaped sunscreen that is designed to block the heat from Sun and ensure the extremely cool temperatures that the instruments are built to operate at.</li>
<li>Temperatures on the sun-facing side can get as high as 110°C, while the other side would be maintained at –200° to –230°C.</li>
<li>The extremely cold temperatures are needed to detect the extremely faint heat signals from distant galaxies.</li>
<li>The mirror as well as the sunscreen is so large they could not have fit into any rocket. They have been built as foldable items and would be unravelled in space.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/in-news-james-webb-space-telescope/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>When pharma companies cross red lines</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pharma-companies/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Pharma sector malpractices in India</p></div></div><p><img alt="pharma companies" class="alignnone wp-image-626306" height="339" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 636px) 100vw, 636px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-2-300x160.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-2-300x160.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-2.jpeg 308w" width="636"/>Marketing practices of pharma companies are under scrutiny after tax officials searched the premises of a drugmaker, and an association of medical representatives moved the Supreme Court alleging unethical marketing practices by drugmakers.</p>
<h4><img alt="paharma companies" class="alignnone wp-image-626307" height="415" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 623px) 100vw, 623px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pharma-money-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pharma-money-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pharma-money-1024x684.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pharma-money-768x513.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pharma-money-1536x1026.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pharma-money-2048x1368.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pharma-money-1200x801.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pharma-money-1980x1322.jpg 1980w" width="623"/>The Dolo controversy</h4>
<ul>
<li>Bengaluru-based pharmaceuticals company Micro Labs Ltd came under the spotlight recently over the promotion of its anti-fever drug Dolo 650, which was widely used during the covid-19 pandemic.</li>
<li>Surprisingly, this drug which contained paracetamol was widely endorsed by doctors all across the India.</li>
<li>The Supreme Court last week ordered the central government to respond to a petition filed on the issue of unethical marketing practices by drug makers.</li>
<li>The Income Tax department too has accused it of claiming unallowable expenses made on freebies meant to boost sales.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/pharma-sector/">How do drugmakers incentivize doctors?</a></h4>
<ul>
<li>While many medical professionals claim that financial incentives do not influence their practice, some say that <strong><u>private sector doctors are enticed by pharmaceutical companies’</u></strong> marketing agents to promote their drugs.</li>
<li>Pharma companies’ sales executives visit doctors to brief them about new drugs or a new drug component.</li>
<li>They try to impress upon them to <strong><u>prescribe their brands and in return, doctors are offered some gifts</u></strong> name reminders such as pens, writing pads, books and sometimes expensive gifts and holidays.</li>
<li>Such benefits extended to doctors depend upon the kind of drug, the disease burden etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/a-no-to-pharma-freebies/"><img alt="pharma companies" class="alignnone wp-image-626309" height="382" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pharma.jpeg" width="506"/>Is this a widespread industry practice?</a></h4>
<ul>
<li>A government doctor said <strong><u>no pharma firm can sustain without marketing</u></strong> its drug.</li>
<li>It mostly happens when there is an outbreak, or if there is great demand for a particular drug or when a drug is being launched.</li>
<li>Unlike in the case of other products, the decision to buy a drug is not made by the consumer, but by the doctor.</li>
<li>This makes pharma a marketing-driven industry.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Are hospitals incentivized too?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Yes; doctors at a top private hospital which treated a large number of covid-19 patients said drug giants do try to incentivize hospitals.</li>
<li>The possibilities increase when a large corporate hospital chain operating across the country buys a drug in bulk.</li>
<li>A doctor at a corporate hospital does not have any control over the drugs sold in the in-house pharmacy of the hospital.</li>
<li>Doctors running small clinics see limited patients, and they do not have pharmacies; so, the issue of incentivization does not arise.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What does the I-T dept find wrong in this?</h4>
<ul>
<li>While <strong><u>pharma companies treat freebies as a marketing expense</u></strong> which is deducted while computing their taxable income, getting the beneficiary of this spending to report it as his income has been a challenge.</li>
<li>In some cases, <strong><u>tax officials have denied promotional expenses</u></strong> as a deduction.</li>
<li>Hence, the government introduced a 10<strong><u>% tax to be deducted at source (TDS)</u></strong> effective 1 July, so that doctors and social media influencers report such benefits in their tax returns and pay tax on what it is worth.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pharma-companies/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>G20 presidency opportunities for India’s growth and prosperity</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/g20/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of G20</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>global governance</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="G20 " class="alignnone wp-image-626158" height="351" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 623px) 100vw, 623px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/g20-1024x576-1-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/g20-1024x576-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/g20-1024x576-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/g20-1024x576-1.jpg 1024w" width="623"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s presidency of the G20 grouping next year arguably the sole remaining effective forum for global governance presents an enormous opportunity to accelerate sustainable growth within India, in the emerging world, and beyond.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=g20+upsc+civilsdaily&amp;ei=rAwHY9eMJJaKseMPhreqoA8&amp;oq=g20+CIVILSD&amp;gs_lcp=Cgdnd3Mtd2l6EAMYADIGCAAQHhAWOggIABCPARDqAjoICC4QjwEQ6gI6CggAELEDEIMBEEM6BQgAEJECOgsIABCABBCxAxCDAToUCC4QgAQQsQMQgwEQxwEQ0QMQ1AI6BwgAELEDEEM6BAgAEEM6CAgAEIAEELEDOgUIABCABDoHCAAQgAQQCjoICAAQHhAWEAo6BQgAEIYDSgQIQRgASgQIRhgAUM4JWNY5YOtHaAFwAXgAgAHFA4gBgBSSAQkwLjYuMy4wLjKYAQCgAQGwAQrAAQE&amp;sclient=gws-wiz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>About G20</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Formed in 1999, the G20 is an international forum of the governments and central bank governors from 20 major economies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Features </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Collectively, the G20 economies account for around 85 percent of the Gross World Product (GWP), 80 percent of world trade.</li>
<li>To tackle the problems or the address issues that plague the world, the heads of governments of the G20 nations periodically participate in summits.</li>
<li>In addition to it, the group also hosts separate meetings of the finance ministers and foreign ministers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/op-ed-snap-india-must-build-the-capacity-to-make-its-g20-presidency-in-the-future-a-success/"><strong>Objectives</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Stability</strong>: The Group was formed with an aim of studying, reviewing, and promoting high-level discussion of policy issues pertaining to the promotion of international financial stability.</li>
<li><strong>Fiscal responsibilities</strong>: The forum aims to pre-empt balance of payments problems and turmoil on financial markets by improved coordination of monetary, fiscal, and financial policies.</li>
<li><strong>Universal Support:</strong> The forum seeks to address issues that go beyond the responsibilities of any one organisation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="G20" class="alignnone wp-image-626160" height="427" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 664px) 100vw, 664px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/g20-300x193.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/g20-300x193.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/g20-768x495.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/g20.jpg 854w" width="664"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/a-new-global-vision-for-g20/">Is India ready for G20 leadership?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At some levels, India is ready.</li>
<li>Indian business and industry is becoming a noteworthy competitor globally.</li>
<li>The country’s domestic economy is starting to pick up, thanks to structural economic reforms.</li>
<li>The central government is economically stronger, and the states are starting to learn about economic independence, making them more aligned with their global counterparts.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Punchline </strong></h4>
<p><strong>It is said that “those who hold the pen, write the rules”.</strong></p>
<p><strong>The time has come for India to both hold the pen and write the rules for a more equitable global economics and governance.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Issues and Challenges</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India need to have a clear global financial agenda.</li>
<li>The country should also have the capacity to lead the G20 year intellectually, financially, managerially and administratively.</li>
<li>Geopolitically, India is more internationally engaged but less so geoeconomically.</li>
<li>Its narrow focus is on the World Bank, IMF, WTO and foreign investment issues.</li>
<li>But India has much to contribute on issues like reconfiguration of global financial regulations, design of a new framework for trade in services and the digital economy and establishing better cross-border standards for transparency in financial flows.</li>
<li>To make its G20 year a success, India has to address organisational challenges, where the country has an infrastructure, management and intellectual gap.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="G20" class="alignnone wp-image-626161" height="356" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 631px) 100vw, 631px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/G20-1-1280x720-1-scaled-1-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/G20-1-1280x720-1-scaled-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/G20-1-1280x720-1-scaled-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/G20-1-1280x720-1-scaled-1.jpg 800w" width="631"/>What could India bring to the table?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Mediation: </strong>Firstly, it remains pertinent for the world that escalating tensions between Russia and Ukraine come to a halt. Maintaining its balanced stance, India needs to neutralise this situation by introducing peace talks between the two nations.</li>
<li><strong>Open trade:</strong> It’s about time for India to raise its voice in support of a transparent New Economic Order and building a prosperous and just world. Unreasonable bans on certain commodities from various countries limits commerce between states when trade liberty exists.</li>
<li><strong>Collaboration around science and technology: </strong>The global agenda has been tilted towards investment, whereas science and technology are the driving force for economic diversification, sustainably urbanising the world, and ushering the hydrogen economy and new crop varieties as the answer to both human well-being and global climate change.</li>
<li><strong>Redefining digital access as universal service</strong>: Harnessing the potential of the digital-information-technology revolution requires redefining digital access as a “universal service” that goes beyond physical connectivity to sharing specific opportunities available<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s presidency must leave the grouping with the agility and energy to respond to new realities, and it must create a future-ready multilateralism through a novel and robust institutional architecture.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. It is said that “those who hold the pen, write the rules”. The time has come for India to both hold the pen and write the rules for a more equitable global economics and governance. Discuss in the context of India’s presidency of G20 summit with challenges and opportunities ahead.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/g20/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Dam safety bill for sustainable water management</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dam-safety/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>mullaperiyar dam</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>dam safety bill ,DRIP.</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="dam safety bill" class="alignnone wp-image-626168" height="439" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 711px) 100vw, 711px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/hirakud-1-300x185.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/hirakud-1-300x185.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/hirakud-1-768x475.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/hirakud-1.jpg 1024w" width="711"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Integrated risk assessment of dam safety required to prevent human-made disasters: Experts</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The recent floods in the Mahanadi basin in Odisha have brought to the fore, the faulty management of dam safety, which were built to mitigate floods and not be the cause of them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a dam?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A dam is a barrier that stops the flow of water and results in the creation of a reservoir. Dams are mainly built in order to produce electricity by using water. This form of electricity is known as hydroelectricity.</li>
<li>Reservoirs created by dams not only suppress floods but also provide water for activities such as irrigation, human consumption, industrial use, aquaculture, and navigability.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Key facts </strong></h4>
<p>India has 5,745 large dams according to the National Register of Large Dams, 2019, prepared by the Central Water Commission. Some 5,334 of them are operational and the remaining 411 are under construction.</p></blockquote>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-how-india-intends-to-make-its-dams-safer/"><strong>What is the Dam Safety Act, 2021?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Act comprehensively postulates for surveillance, inspection, operation and maintenance of dams to prevent disasters.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Features</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>National Committee on Dam Safety (NCDS):</strong> It will be constituted and will be chaired by the chairperson, Central Water Commission. Its’ functions will include formulating policies and regulations regarding dam safety standards and prevention of dam failures, analyzing the causes of major dam failures, and suggesting changes in dam safety practices.</li>
<li><strong>National Dam Safety Authority (NDSA):</strong> It will be headed by an officer, not below the rank of an Additional Secretary, to be appointed by the central government. The main task of this authority includes implementing the policies formulated by the NCD, resolving issues between State Dam Safety Organisations (SDSOs), or between an SDSO and any dam owner in that state, specifying regulations for inspection and investigation of dams.</li>
<li><strong>State Dam Safety Organisation (SDSO):</strong> Its functions will be to keep perpetual surveillance, inspection, monitoring the operation and maintenance of dams, keeping a database of all dams, and recommending safety measures to owners of dams.</li>
<li><strong>Dam Safety Unit:</strong> The owners of the specified dams are required to provide a dam safety unit in each dam. This unit will inspect the dams before and after the monsoon session, and during and after any calamity or sign of distress.</li>
<li><strong>Emergency Action Plan</strong>: Dam owners will be required to prepare an emergency action plan, and carry out risk assessment studies for each dam at specified regular intervals.</li>
<li><strong>Certain offences:</strong> The act provides for two types of offences – obstructing a person in the discharge of his functions, and refusing to comply with directions issued under the proposed law.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="dam safety" class="alignnone wp-image-626169" height="392" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 695px) 100vw, 695px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/dam-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/dam-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/dam-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/dam.jpg 1024w" width="695"/>Dam rehabilitation and improvement programme DRIP</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Government of India, with financial assistance from the World Bank initiated Dam Rehabilitation and Improvement Project (DRIP) in April 2012 with an objective to improve the safety and operational performance of selected existing dams along with dam safety institutional strengthening with system wide management approach. It was a State Sector Scheme with Central component.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Do you know?</strong></h4>
<p>Four dams — <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dam-safety-act-can-end-disputes-says-supreme-court/">Mullaperiyar</a>, Parambikulam, Thunakkadavu and Peruvaripallam — located in Kerala but owned, operated and maintained by the Tamil Nadu Government.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The bill aims to help all States and Union Territories to adopt uniform dam safety procedures which will ensure safety of dams and safeguard benefits from such dams. In order to iron out the differences and issues in the bill, central government should take the state governments into consideration and hold talks with all the stakeholders. This will go a long way in ensuring the safety of dams in India, which ranks third in the world in terms of number of large dams.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. India, which ranks third in the world in terms of number of large dams.</strong> <strong>Ageing dams poses several challenges for India. In this context discuss the importance of dam safety bill 2021.</strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dam-safety/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Universal basic income for complete social security</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/universal-basic-income/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>various schemes for vulnerable section</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>social security, universal basic income</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="universal basic income " class="alignnone wp-image-626175" height="386" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 685px) 100vw, 685px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/basic-income-2021-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/basic-income-2021-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/basic-income-2021-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/basic-income-2021.jpg 1024w" width="685"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>New evidence from two Kenyan counties shows that universal basic income  and other income supplements reduce hunger, illness, and risk exposure during crises.</li>
<li>Countries should consider building universal basic income that can be activated at short notice to help people weather unanticipated shocks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When the COVID-19 pandemic and the resulting recession pushed 120 million people worldwide into extreme poverty in 2020, many countries relied on social-protection measures to cushion the blow.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is social protection?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Social protection is concerned with preventing, managing, and overcoming situations that adversely affect people’s well-being.</li>
<li>Social protection programs that assist low-income families, insure against shocks, and break poverty traps offer a potential solution.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="universal basic income " class="alignnone wp-image-626176" height="401" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 711px) 100vw, 711px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/UBI-2-x433-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/UBI-2-x433-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/UBI-2-x433-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/UBI-2-x433.jpg 770w" width="711"/>Universal basic income meaning</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Universal basic income (UBI) is a model for providing all citizens of a country or other geographic area with a given sum of money, regardless of their income, resources or employment status.</li>
<li>The purpose of UBI is to prevent or reduce poverty and increase equality among citizens.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/universalisation-of-social-security-remains-an-unfulfilled-aspiration/"><strong>What is social security?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Social securityin India includes a variety of statutory insurances and social grant schemes bundled into a formerly complex and fragmented system run by the Indian government.</li>
<li>These are retirement, healthcare, disability, childcare, gratuity and provident fund and insurance programs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is insurance simple words?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An agreement by which a person pays a company and the company promises to pay money if the person becomes injured or dies or to pay for the value of property lost or damaged.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Constitutional mandate </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Directive Principles of State Policy, enshrined in Part IV of the Indian Constitution reflects that India is a welfare state.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Interesting fact </strong></p>
<p><strong>India operates the widest spectrum of social security schemes which cater to the largest number of people than any other country.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/op-ed-snap-ensure-a-minimum-income-for-all/"><strong>What are the benefits of Universal Basic Income?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Ending poverty: </strong>Advocates for UBI say that it could help bring everyone’s income above the poverty line.</li>
<li><strong>Discouraging low wages: </strong>UBI would give employees enough security to have bargaining power.</li>
<li><strong>Redistributing wealth: </strong>The economic growth of high-income countries is making the rich richer, but having very little effect on the working classes.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Case study / value addition </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Namibia</strong></p>
<p>Namibia had a basic income pilot program between 2008 and 2009. Every resident of Otjivero-Omitara was entitled to 100 Namibian dollars ($6.75) every month. The program was funded by donors from around the world.</p>
<p>Findings from the pilot program showed that cases of child malnutrition had dropped significantly while school enrollment went up. Also, social crimes such as theft had significantly dropped.</p></blockquote>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/op-ed-snapgood-jobs-not-universal-basic-income-are-needed-for-a-good-society/"><strong><img alt="universal basic income " class="alignnone wp-image-626177" height="470" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ubi1.jpeg" width="706"/>Negative implications of UBI</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Induce lethargy: </strong>UBI removes the incentive to work, adversely affecting the economy and leading to a labour and skills shortage.</li>
<li><strong>Inequity:</strong> Universal basic income would be just that: universal. That means that everyone, regardless of how poor, or rich, they were would get the same amount of money.</li>
<li><strong>Huge Cost</strong>: The cost of implementing UBI could be huge. In the United States it’s estimated to be about $3.9 trillion per year.</li>
<li><strong>Motivation to work</strong>: One concern is that UBI would incite millions of workers to stop working. If people aren’t working, there is less taxable income.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Some government initiatives </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>National Pension Scheme for Traders and Self Employed Persons.</li>
<li>Pradhan Mantri Suraksha Bima Yojana.</li>
<li>Employees’ State Insurance Scheme.</li>
<li>Minimum Wages for various employment roles.</li>
<li>National Pension System.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>One of the major criticisms of poverty alleviation programs is significant leakages. UBI is seen as a more efficient alternative. Though UBI has many advantages, there are many practical challenges too. The idea should be to save costs with better targeting. This will help create the necessary conditions for higher growth which will decisively lift people out of poverty.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. India operates the widest spectrum of social security schemes which cater to the largest number of people than any other country. Do you think they are enough? Discuss in context of rising demand for universal basic income and its pros and cons for ensuring social security.</strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/universal-basic-income/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Forest fire management for positive sustainable forest growth</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/forest-fire/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>National Action Plan on Forest Fires</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>environment conservation</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="forest fire" class="alignnone wp-image-626486" height="390" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 692px) 100vw, 692px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.49259600_1661422079_wildfire-in-california-2013-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.49259600_1661422079_wildfire-in-california-2013-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.49259600_1661422079_wildfire-in-california-2013-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.49259600_1661422079_wildfire-in-california-2013.jpg 1024w" width="692"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Forest fires are becoming more common and wildfires are destroying nearly twice as much tree cover globally as they did in 2001.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Climate change is driving more intense and widespread forest fire by fuelling more extreme heat and deepening drought, which dries out forests.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How to define <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-forest-fires-are-sometimes-a-good-thing/">forest fire</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A wildfire, forest fire, bushfire, wildland fire or rural fire is an unplanned, uncontrolled and unpredictable fire in an area of combustible vegetation starting in rural and urban areas.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What causes forest fires?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Human activities</strong>: Forest fires can be caused by a number of natural causes, but officials say many major fires in India are triggered mainly by human activities.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/subject/climate-change/"><strong>Climate change</strong></a>: Emerging studies link climate change to rising instances of fires globally, especially the massive fires of the Amazon forests in Brazil and in Australia in the last two years. Fires of longer duration, increasing intensity, higher frequency and highly inflammable nature are all being linked to climate change.</li>
<li><strong>Season</strong>: In India, wildfires are most commonly reported during March and April, when the ground has large quantities of dry wood, logs, dead leaves, stumps, dry grass and weeds that can make forests easily go up in flames if there is a trigger.</li>
<li><strong>Natural reasons:</strong> Under natural circumstances, extreme heat and dryness, friction created by rubbing of branches with each other also have been known to initiate fire.</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="forest fire " class="alignnone wp-image-626490" height="508" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 761px) 100vw, 761px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/main_1500-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/main_1500-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/main_1500-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/main_1500-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/main_1500-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/main_1500.jpg 1500w" width="761"/></p>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Key fact </strong></h4>
<p><strong>7.4 million acres of forest are getting burnt annually now an area roughly the size of Belgium.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>What factors make forest fires a concern?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-must-commit-to-net-zero-emissions/"><strong>Carbon emission</strong>:</a> They act as a sink, reservoir and source of carbon.</li>
<li><strong>Livelihood loss</strong>: In India, with 1.70 lakh villages in close proximity to forests (Census 2011), the livelihood of several crores of people is dependent on fuelwood, bamboo, fodder, and small timber.</li>
<li><strong>Destruction of animals’ habitat</strong>: Heat generated during the fire destroys animal habitats. Soil quality decreases with the alteration in their compositions.</li>
<li><strong>Soil degradation</strong>: Soil moisture and fertility, too, is affected. Thus forests can shrink in size. The trees that survive fire often remain stunted and growth is severely affected.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Measures to curb Forest fires</strong></h4>
<p><strong>1) National Action Plan on wild fires</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The MoEFCC has prepared a National Action Plan on wild fire in 2018 after several rounds of consultation with all states and UTs.</li>
<li>The objective of this plan is to minimize forest fires by informing, enabling and empowering forest fringe communities and incentivizing them to work in tandem with the State Forest Departments.</li>
<li>The plan also intends to substantially reduce the vulnerability of forests across diverse forest ecosystems in the country against fire hazards, enhance capabilities of forest personnel and institutions in fighting fires and swift recovery subsequent to fire incidents.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2) Forest Fire Prevention and Management scheme</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The MoEFCC provides wildfire prevention and management measures under the Centrally Sponsored Forest Fire Prevention and Management (FPM) scheme.</li>
<li>The FPM is the only centrally funded program specifically dedicated to assist the states in dealing with forest fires.</li>
<li>The FPM replaced the Intensification of Forest Management Scheme (IFMS) in 2017. By revamping the IFMS, the FPM has increased the amount dedicated for forest fire work.</li>
<li>Funds allocated under the FPM are according to the 90:10 ratio of central to state funding in the Northeast and Western Himalayan regions and 60:40 ratio for all other states.</li>
<li>Nodal officers for forest fire prevention and control have been appointed in each state.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="forest fire" class="alignnone wp-image-626491" height="539" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 539px) 100vw, 539px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-1-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-1-1.jpeg 225w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-1-1-150x150.jpeg 150w" width="539"/>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Awareness should be created among the villagers residing near the forests with respect to the long-term ill effects of forest fires.</li>
<li>Measures to prevent wildfires have to be taken before summer season when fires are prevalent.</li>
<li>Local people should be given skills to use online portals or mobile apps in order to monitor the forests for fires and inform forest authorities regarding the same.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Climate change is driving more intense and widespread forest fires by fueling more extreme heat and deepening drought. Why forest fires are cause of concern? Discuss our preparedness level for the same in the above context.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/forest-fire/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Manusmriti: the controversial ancient Sanskrit text</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/manusmriti-the-controversial-ancient-sanskrit-text/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Manusmriti</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Vice Chancellor of a renowned university recently criticized the Manusmriti, the ancient Sanskrit text, over its gender bias.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The VC said that the Manusmriti has categorised all women as shudras, which is extraordinarily regressive.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Manusmriti?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Mānavadharmaśāstra</u></strong>, also known as Manusmriti or the Laws of Manu, is a Sanskrit text belonging to the Dharmaśāstra literary tradition of Hinduism.</li>
<li>Composed sometime between the <strong><u>2nd century BCE and 3rd century CE</u></strong>, the Manusmriti is <strong><u>written in sloka verses</u></strong>, containing two non-rhyming lines of 16 syllabus each.</li>
<li>The text is attributed to the mythical figure of Manu, considered to be ancestor of the human race in Hinduism.</li>
<li>There has been considerable debate between scholars on the authorship of the text.</li>
<li>Many have argued that it was compiled by many Brahmin scholars over a period of time.</li>
<li>However, Indologist Patrick Olivelle argues that Manusmṛiti’s “unique and symmetrical structure,” means that it was composed by a “single gifted individual,” or by a “strong chairman of a committee” with the aid of others.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the text about?</h4>
<h4>(A) Social aspects</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Manusmriti is encyclopaedic in scope, covering subjects such as the <strong><u>social obligations and duties of the various castes</u></strong> and of individuals in different stages of life.</li>
<li>It seeks to <strong><u>govern the suitable social and sexual relations of men and women of different castes</u></strong>, on <strong><u>taxes</u></strong>, the <strong><u>rules for kingship</u></strong>, on <strong><u>maintaining marital harmony</u></strong> and the procedures for <strong><u>settling everyday disputes.</u></strong></li>
<li>At its core, the Manusmriti <strong><u>discusses life in the world, how it is lived in reality</u></strong>, as well as how it ought to be.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(B) Political aspects</h4>
<ul>
<li>They argue that the <strong><u>text is about dharma, which means duty, religion, law and practice</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It also discusses <strong><u>aspects of the Arthashashtra</u></strong>, such as issues relating to statecraft and legal procedures.</li>
<li>The aim of the text is to present a blueprint for a properly <strong><u>ordered society</u></strong> under the <strong><u>sovereignty of the king and the guidance of Brahmins.</u></strong></li>
<li>It was <strong><u>meant to be read by the priestly caste and Olivelle</u></strong> argues that it would likely have been part of the curriculum for young Brahmin scholars at colleges.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is its significance?</h4>
<ul>
<li>By the early centuries of the Common Era, Manu had become, and remained, the standard source of authority in the orthodox tradition for that centrepiece of Hinduism, varṇāśrama-dharma (social and religious duties tied to class and stage of life)”.</li>
<li>Indologists argue that it was a very significant text for Brahmin scholars — it attracted 9 commentaries by other writers of the tradition, and was cited by other ancient Indian texts far more frequently than other dharmaśāstra.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did colonists consider this text?</h4>
<ul>
<li>European Orientalists considered the Manusmṛiti to be of great historical and religious significance as well. It was the first Sanskrit text to be translated into a European language, by the British philologist Sir William Jones in 1794.</li>
<li>Subsequently, it was translated into French, German, Portuguese and Russian, before being included in Max Muller’s edited volume, Sacred Books of the East in 1886.</li>
<li>For colonial officials in British India, the translation of the book served a practical purpose.</li>
<li>In 1772, Governor-General Warren Hastings decided to implement laws of Hindus and Muslims that they believed to be “continued, unchanged from remotest antiquity.</li>
<li>For Hindus, the dharmasastras were to play a crucial role, as they were seen by the British as ‘laws,’ whether or not it was even used that way in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is it controversial?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ancient text has 4 major divisions: 1) Creation of the world. 2) Sources of dharma. 3) The dharma of the four social classes. 4) Law of karma, rebirth, and final liberation.</li>
<li>The third section is the longest and most important section.</li>
<li>The text is deeply concerned with maintaining the <strong><u>hierarchy of the four-fold varna system</u></strong> and the rules that each caste has to follow.</li>
<li>Then, the <strong><u>Brahmin is assumed to be the perfect representative of the human race</u></strong>.</li>
<li>While Shudras, who are relegated to the bottom of the order, are given the sole duty of serving the ‘upper’ castes.</li>
<li>Some verses also contain highly prejudicial sentiments against women on the basis of their birth.</li>
<li>There are many verses in the text that are considered highly controversial.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Dr. Ambedkar and Manusmriti</h4>
<ul>
<li>On December 25, 1927, Dr B R Ambedkar had famously burned the Manusmṛiti, which he saw as a source of gender and caste oppression.</li>
<li>However, he widely acknowledged that Manusmriti is <strong><u>NOT a religious decree</u></strong> but a social doctrine, manipulated since centuries to normalize oppression of the population.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/manusmriti-the-controversial-ancient-sanskrit-text/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>One Nation One Fertiliser (ONOF) Scheme</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/one-nation-one-fertiliser-onof-scheme/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>One Nation One Fertiliser (ONOF)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India's fertilizer subsidy</p></div></div><p>The Ministry of Chemicals and Fertilisers will implement One Nation One Fertiliser (ONOF) by introducing a Single Brand for Fertilisers and Logo under the fertiliser subsidy scheme named “Pradhanmantri Bhartiya Janurvarak Pariyojna” (PMBJP).</p>
<h4>One Nation One Fertiliser (ONOF)</h4>
<ul>
<li>The single brand name for UREA, DAP, MOP and NPK etc. would be BHARAT UREA, BHARAT DAP, BHARAT MOP and BHARAT NPK etc. respectively for all Fertiliser Companies, State Trading Entities (STEs) and Fertiliser Marketing Entities (FMEs).</li>
<li>Also a logo indicating Fertiliser subsidy scheme namely Pradhanmantri Bhartiya Janurvarak Pariyojna will be used on said fertiliser bags.</li>
<li>Under the scheme, companies are allowed to display their name, brand, logo and other relevant product information only on one-third space of their bags.</li>
<li>On the remaining two-thirds space, the “Bharat” brand and Pradhanmantri Bharatiya Jan Urvarak Pariyojana logo will have to be shown.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the government’s argument for introducing this scheme?</h4>
<p>The government’s logic for introducing a <strong><u>single ‘Bharat’ brand</u></strong> for all subsidised fertilisers being marketed by companies is as follows:</p>
<p><strong>(1) Subsidies normalization</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The maximum retail price of urea is currently fixed by the government, which compensates companies for the higher cost of manufacturing or imports incurred by them.</li>
<li>The MRPs of non-urea fertilisers are, on paper, decontrolled.</li>
<li>But companies cannot avail of subsidy if they sell at MRPs higher than that informally indicated by the government.</li>
<li>Simply put, there are some 26 fertilisers (inclusive of urea), on which government bears subsidy and also effectively decides the MRPs;</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Harmonizing markets</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Apart from subsidising and deciding at what price companies can sell, the government also decides where they can sell.</li>
<li>This is done through the Fertiliser (Movement) Control Order, 1973.</li>
<li>Under this, the department of fertilisers draws an agreed monthly supply plan on all subsidised fertilisers in consultation with manufacturers and importers.</li>
<li>This supply plan is issued before the 25th of each month for the following month, with the department also regularly monitoring movement to ensure fertiliser availability as per requirement, including remote areas.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Farmers welfare</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The government is spending vast sums of money on fertiliser subsidy (the bill is likely to cross Rs 200,000 crore in 2022-23).</li>
<li>By deciding where and at what price companies can sell, it would obviously want to take credit and send that message to farmers.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What can be the drawbacks of the scheme?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It may <strong><u>disincentivise fertiliser companies</u></strong> from undertaking marketing and brand promotion activities.</li>
<li>They will now be <strong><u>reduced to contract manufacturers</u></strong> and importers for the government. Any company’s strength ultimately is its brands and farmer trust built over decades.</li>
<li>Currently, in case of any bag or batch of fertilisers not meeting the required standards, the <strong><u>blame is put on the company</u>. </strong>But now, that may be passed on fully to the government.</li>
<li>Politically, the scheme might well boomerang rather than benefit the ruling party.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/one-nation-one-fertiliser-onof-scheme/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Labour Codes empower workers: PM</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/labour-codes-empower-workers-pm/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Labour codes</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>Addressing to the National Labour Conference, Prime Minister said that the Centre had taken initiatives to abolish laws from “the period of slavery” that reflected a slavery mentality through the Labour Codes.</p>
<h4>New Labour Codes</h4>
<p>The four codes likely to be implemented in FY23 are:</p>
<ol>
<li>Code on Wages</li>
<li>Industrial Relations Code</li>
<li>Social Security Code, and</li>
<li>Occupational Safety, Health and Working Conditions Code</li>
</ol>
<h4>Objectives of the Labour Code</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-new-labour-laws/">new labor codes</a> are aimed at facilitating ease of doing business in the country and seek to replace 29 cumbersome laws.</li>
<li>The objective is to encompass over 500 million organized and unorganized sector workers—90% of the workforce which has been outside labour laws.</li>
<li>The idea is to ensure that they receive wage security, social security and health security, gender equality in terms of remuneration, a minimum floor wage, make the lives of inter-state migrant workers easier.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the current status of the codes?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The central government has completed the process of finalizing the draft rules, state governments are in the process of drafting the same.</li>
<li>With labor being a concurrent subject, states are in the process of pre-publishing draft rules for these reforms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How many labour laws do Indian states have?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The simplification of 29 labour laws into the four labour codes is expected be a watershed moment for labour reforms.</li>
<li>India currently has a web of multiple labour legislations, over 40 central laws and 100 state laws involving labour.</li>
<li>The Second National Commission on Labour (2002) recommended simplification to bring about transparency and uniformity.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the major reforms in these codes?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Social security benefits:</strong> With organized sector workers being approximately 10% of the total workforce, the new codes may ensure that social security benefits are for all.</li>
<li><strong>Take-home salary:</strong> As per the proposed labour codes, total allowances such as house rent, leave, travel etc. are to be capped at 50% of the salary, while basic pay should account for the remaining 50%.</li>
<li><strong>Four days work:</strong> There could also be a permissible four-day work week of 12 hours per day.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How will it affect ease of doing business?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Labour productivity:</strong> It is likely to improve with both employees and employers developing a sense of being partners in wealth creation.</li>
<li><strong>Labour reform:</strong> A transparent environment in terms of workers’ compensation, clear definition of employee rights and employer duties.</li>
<li><strong>Compliance un-burdening:</strong> Simplified labour codes making compliance easier are likely to attract investments.</li>
<li><strong>Formalization of the economy:</strong> With more workers in the organized sector, leakage in terms of direct as well as indirect taxes may be plugged.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="JQsCoVPwp7"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-new-labour-laws/">[Burning Issue] New Labour Laws</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="JQsCoVPwp7" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-new-labour-laws/embed/#?secret=pEgHi1HIRf#?secret=JQsCoVPwp7" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Burning Issue] New Labour Laws” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/labour-codes-empower-workers-pm/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Robust Sport governance for national pride</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sport-governance/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>sports bodies</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>sport governance transparency</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="sport governance" class="alignnone wp-image-626497" height="377" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 669px) 100vw, 669px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/3fe7feec-209c-11ed-8c4d-fc6273086eb8_1661009205543.jpg 1600w" width="669"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The judicial push for reforms in sport governance of various sporting bodies, football, hockey, table tennis and the Indian Olympic Association has understandably received mixed reactions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The national sports federation’s usual governance practices do not place either the sport or the athlete front and centre; that space is reserved for official egos, whims and political clout.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is sport governance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sport governance refers to the power a government has over institutions and allows their decisions to be made with due consideration to their influence, authority, and organizational structure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-mudda-aapka-sports-as-a-fundamental-right/">Sports in India</a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Physical activity is fundamental to human beings:</strong>  The report states that having a fundamental right to literacy would mean identifying the intrinsic value of physical activity to human living.</li>
<li><strong>Part of elementary education:</strong> It would mean not seeing physical activity as an end in itself, and the establishment of physical activity/ physical education as a core component of the education curriculum.</li>
<li><strong>Supportive to other FRs:</strong> A fundamental right to physical literacy would actualise and enhance the enjoyment of other fundamental rights. It would go a long way in enhancing the opportunities and freedom to express oneself.</li>
<li><strong>Enhancing life quality:</strong> A physically literate individual would have a more fulfilling life of higher quality than one who is not.  Physical literacy, as a building block, would go a long way in the promotion and realisation of the right to health and the right to education.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="sport governance " class="alignnone wp-image-626496" height="409" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 576px) 100vw, 576px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/93726271-300x213.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/93726271-300x213.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/93726271.jpg 600w" width="576"/>Issues with the Current Sports governance </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of check and balance</strong>: The biggest concern regarding these bodies so far has been a complete lack of checks and balances.</li>
<li><strong>Excessive autonomy</strong>: In the pretext of autonomy, they have been allowed to function in any manner.</li>
<li><strong>Less people centric approach</strong>: The federations have generally fallen short of public expressions and have failed to carry out their jobs. It has been largely attributed to the way they are governed.</li>
<li><strong>Accountability</strong>: The current sports model faces accountability issues such as that of having unlimited discretionary powers and also there is no transparency in the decision-making.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="sport governance" class="alignnone wp-image-626499" height="291" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download-3.jpeg" width="343"/></strong></h4>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong>Sport governance in India is administered by </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Ministry of Youth Affairs and Sports (MYAS)</li>
<li>National Sports Federation (NSF)</li>
<li>Indian Olympic Association (IOA)</li>
<li>State Olympic Association (SOA)</li>
<li>Sports Authority of India (SAI)</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Positive Suggestions</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Legislation</strong>: There must be presence of powerful and defined sports legislation in India covering all the nuances of sports and giving no arbiter powers to any authority.</li>
<li><strong>Transparency</strong>-: To maintain transparency with expenditure and fund utilization, Information like a board of members, administrative officials, and remuneration information must be in public domain.</li>
<li><strong>Women Representation</strong>: It is very important to have sufficient women representation in sports as well as in the administrative bodies, and it is the responsibility of these admin bodies to ensure sufficient representation from women in the board too, to maintain the diversity within the board.</li>
<li><strong>Plans</strong>: There should be fix timelines disclosed which are to be adopted by sports bodies for the purpose of growth and development of sports in future, which is to be achieved in a given specific period of time. These kinds of timelines and plans would be motivational for players and bodies to. Goals to be targeted in future must be predecided, which can be well monitored and regulated by the authorities. Effective implementation would bring positive results in future.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-olympic-association-ioa/"><strong>Committees</strong>:</a> To set up specific committees for specific activities relating to sports activities, like for planning, financing, research and development purposes. These committees would look after the particular task, which would bring transparency in work and achieving the common objective.</li>
<li><strong>Rules and Regulations</strong>: like other fields, sports also have conflicts regarding disciplinary, administrative and management issues, to solve this issues governing bodies must set up a common judicial system (tribunal) to deal with sports-related conflicts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is a close association of sports with national pride and the kind of influence it has on the psyche of the nation, a role for the State is urgent in sports reforms.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. The national sports federation’s usual governance practices do not place either the sport or the athlete front and centre; that space is reserved for official egos what do you think on this ? Explain the term sport governance with some dynamic changes needed in it.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sport-governance/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Arth Ganga Model: New govt model for the River’s Sustainable Development</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/arth-ganga-model/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Arth Ganga Model</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Director General of the National Mission for Clean Ganga, spoke about the Arth Ganga Model during his virtual keynote address to the Stockholm World Water Week 2022.</p>
<h4>What is Arth Ganga Model?</h4>
<ul>
<li>PM Modi first introduced the concept during the first National Ganga Council meeting in Kanpur in 2019.</li>
<li>He urged for a shift from <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/quick-catch-up-on-the-namami-gange-program/">Namami Gange</a>, the Union Government’s flagship project to clean the Ganga, to the model of Arth Ganga.</li>
<li>The latter focuses on the sustainable development of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/drainage-system-part-4/">Ganga</a> and its surrounding areas, by focusing on economic activities related to the river.</li>
<li>At its core, the Arth Ganga model seeks to use economics to bridge people with the river.</li>
<li>It strives to contribute at least 3% of the GDP from the Ganga Basin itself.</li>
<li>The Arth Ganga project’s interventions are in accordance with India’s commitments towards the UN sustainable development goals.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Features</h4>
<p>Under Arth Ganga, the government is working on six verticals.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong><u>Zero Budget Natural Farming</u></strong> that includes chemical-free farming for 10 kms on either side of the river, generating “more income, per drop”, ‘Gobar Dhan’ for farmers,</li>
<li><strong><u>Monetization and Reuse of Sludge &amp;Wastewater</u></strong> that envisages reuse of treated water for irrigation; industrial purposes and revenue generation for ULBs,</li>
<li><strong><u>Livelihood Opportunities Generation</u></strong> such as ‘Ghat Mein Haat’, promotion of local products, Ayurveda, medicinal plants, capacity building of volunteers like Ganga Praharis,</li>
<li><strong><u>Public Participation</u></strong> to ensure increased synergies between stakeholders,</li>
<li><strong><u>Cultural Heritage &amp;Tourism</u></strong> that looks to introduce boat tourism through community jettis, promotion of yoga, adventure tourism etc. and Ganga Artis and</li>
<li><strong><u>Institutional Building</u></strong> by enhancing the local capacities for better decentralized water governance.</li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/arth-ganga-model/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Jharkhand CM may face disqualification</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cm-disqualification-office-of-profit/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Office of Profit</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>Jharkhand CM’s chair remains uncertain as the Election Commission (EC) is understood to have conveyed its decision in an office-of-profit complaint against him to the Governor.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Under Section 9A of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/prominent-features-of-the-representation-of-peoples-act/">Representation of the People Act, 1951</a>, the CM could face disqualification for entering into a government contract.</li>
<li>The Constitution of India does not define the Office of Profit. It has only mentioned it under Article 102 (1) and Article 191 (1).</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Office of Profit?</h4>
<ul>
<li>MPs and MLAs, as members of the legislature, hold the government accountable for its work.</li>
<li>The essence of disqualification is if legislators hold an ‘office of profit’ under the government, they might be susceptible to government influence, and may not discharge their constitutional mandate fairly.</li>
<li>The intent is that <strong><u>there should be no conflict between the duties and interests of an elected member.</u></strong></li>
<li>Hence, the office of profit law simply seeks to enforce a basic feature of the Constitution- the principle of separation of power between the legislature and the executive.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What governs the term?</h4>
<ul>
<li>At present, the <strong><u>Parliament (Prevention of Disqualification) Act, 1959</u></strong>, bars an MP, MLA or an MLC from holding any office of profit under the central or state government unless it is exempted.</li>
<li>However, <strong><u>it does not clearly define what constitutes an office of profit.</u></strong></li>
<li>Legislators can face disqualification for holding such positions, which bring them financial or other benefits.</li>
<li>Under the provisions of <strong><u>Article 102 (1)</u> and <u>Article 191 (1)</u></strong> of the Constitution, an MP or an MLA (or an MLC) is barred from holding any office of profit under the Central or State government.</li>
</ul>
<h4>An undefined term</h4>
<ul>
<li>The officials of the law ministry are of the view that defining an office of profit could lead to the filing of a number of cases with the Election Commission and the courts.</li>
<li>Also, once the definition is changed, one will also have to amend various provisions in the Constitution including Article 102 (1) (a) and Article 109 (1) (a) that deal with the office of profit.</li>
<li>It will have an overarching effect on all the other sections of the Constitution.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Factors constituting an ‘office of profit’</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 1959 law does not clearly define what constitutes an office of profit but the <strong><u>definition has evolved over the years with interpretations made in various court judgments.</u></strong></li>
<li>An office of profit has been interpreted to be a position that brings to the office-holder some financial gain, or advantage, or benefit. The amount of such profit is immaterial.</li>
<li>In 1964, the Supreme Court ruled that the test for determining whether a person holds an office of profit is the test of appointment.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the ‘test of appointment’?</h4>
<p>Several factors are considered in this determination including factors such as:</p>
<ol>
<li>whether the government is the appointing authority,</li>
<li>whether the government has the power to terminate the appointment,</li>
<li>whether the government determines the remuneration,</li>
<li>what is the source of remuneration, and</li>
<li>the power that comes with the position.</li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cm-disqualification-office-of-profit/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India, Bangladesh discuss River Water Sharing issues</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/river-water-sharing-issues/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Rivers mentioned</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India-Bangladesh Relations</p></div></div><p>India and Bangladesh discussed a wide range of River Water Sharing issues related to the major common rivers such as the Ganga, Teesta and several others during the 38th meeting of the Joint River Commission (JRC).</p>
<h4>Rivers between India and Bangladesh</h4>
<ul>
<li>Overall, India and Bangladesh have 54 transboundary rivers between them, all of which are part of the drainage system of the Ganga-Brahmaputra-Meghna (GBM) basin.</li>
<li>The Padma (the Ganga), the Jamuna (the Brahmaputra) and the Meghna (the Barak) and their tributaries are integral in maintaining food and water security in Bangladesh.</li>
<li>In most of these cases, Bangladesh is the lower riparian.</li>
<li>This causes concern in Bangladesh that India—being both the upper riparian and first to develop the water resources—can have far more disproportionate control over the rivers.</li>
<li>Compounded by the lack of transparent data regarding trans-boundary rivers, such concern can lead to a more serious conflict between the two otherwise friendly neighbours.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Genesis of the disputes</h4>
<ul>
<li>The issues between India and Bangladesh regarding water resource allotment can be traced to the time <strong><u>Bangladesh was still East Pakistan</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In <strong><u>1961</u></strong>, India began <strong><u>construction of the Farakka Barrage</u></strong>—which was to be operational by April 1975—to divert a portion of the dry-season flow and increase the navigability of Kolkata port.</li>
<li>When India began its preliminary planning for the project in 1950-51, <strong><u>Pakistan immediately expressed concerns</u></strong> over the potential effect of the project on East Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Moves for disputes resolution: Joint River Commission</h4>
<ul>
<li>Soon after the <strong><u>independence of Bangladesh in 1971</u></strong>, the <strong><u>Joint River Commission</u></strong> was formed between India and Bangladesh in 1972.</li>
<li>In a joint declaration issued on 16 May 1974, the PM of Bangladesh and India acknowledged the need for the flow augmentation of the Ganga in the lean season to meet the requirements of both countries.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Often in news: Teesta River Dispute</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Bangladesh government has been insistent on sealing the <strong><u>Teesta Waters Agreement</u></strong>, which has eluded settlement so far.</li>
<li>Teesta River is a 315 km long river that rises in the eastern Himalayas, flows through the Indian states of Sikkim and West Bengal through Bangladesh and enters the Bay of Bengal.</li>
<li>It is a tributary of the Brahmaputra (known as Jamuna in Bangladesh), flowing through India and Bangladesh.</li>
<li>It originates in the Himalayas near Chunthang, Sikkim and flows to the south through West Bengal before entering Bangladesh.</li>
<li>Originally, it continued southward to empty directly into the Padma River but around 1787 the river changed its course to flow eastward to join the Jamuna river.</li>
<li>The Teesta Barrage dam helps to provide irrigation for the plains between the upper Padma and the Jamuna.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the dispute about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The point of contention between India and Bangladesh is mainly the lean season flow in the Teesta draining into Bangladesh.</li>
<li>The river covers nearly the entire floodplains of Sikkim while draining 2,800 sq km of Bangladesh, governing the lives of hundreds of thousands of people.</li>
<li>For West Bengal, Teesta is equally important, considered the lifeline of half-a-dozen districts in North Bengal.</li>
<li>Bangladesh has sought an “equitable” distribution of Teesta waters from India, on the lines of the Ganga Water Treaty of 1996, but to no avail.</li>
<li>The failure to ink a deal had its fallout on the country’s politics, putting the ruling party of PM Sheikh Hasina in a spot.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>Q.The hydrological linkages between India and Bangladesh are a product of geography and a matter of shared history. Discuss this statement in line with the Teesta water-sharing dispute.</p></blockquote>
<h4>The deal</h4>
<ul>
<li>Following a half-hearted deal in 1983, when a nearly equal division of water was proposed, the countries hit a roadblock. The transient agreement could not be implemented.</li>
<li>Talks resumed after the Awami League returned to power in 2008 and the former Indian PM Manmohan Singh visited Dhaka in 2011.</li>
<li>In 2015, PM Modi’s visit to Dhaka generated more ebullient lines: deliberations were underway involving all the stakeholders to conclude the agreement as soon as possible.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues from the Indian side</h4>
<ul>
<li>It remains an unfinished project and one of the key stakeholders — West Bengal CM is yet to endorse the deal.</li>
<li>Her objection is connected to “global warming. Many of the glaciers on the Teesta basin have retreated.</li>
<li>The importance of the flow and the seasonal variation of this river is felt during the lean season (from October to April/May) as the average flow is about 500 million cubic metres (MCM) per month.</li>
<li>The CM opposed an arrangement in 2011, by which India would get 42.5% and Bangladesh 37.5% of the water during the lean season, and the plan was shelved.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why does this deal matters?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India and Bangladesh have resolved border problems through the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/land-boundary-agreement-lba-with-bangladesh/">Land Boundary Agreement of 2015</a>.</li>
<li>However, both nations have locked horns over the sharing of multiple rivers that define the borders and impact lives and livelihoods on both sides.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/river-water-sharing-issues/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Digital health holds promising future for India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/digital-health/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Digital health id</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>National digital health mission</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="digital health" class="alignnone wp-image-626507" height="362" sizes="(max-width: 724px) 100vw, 724px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/digital-health-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/digital-health-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/digital-health-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/digital-health.jpg 800w" width="724"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The covid-19 pandemic has presented a watershed moment, bringing the world’s healthcare systems to a halt, forcing us to rethink existing healthcare delivery models and embrace the digital health transformation of the sector.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Definition of digital health care</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Digital health is a discipline that includes digital care programs, technologies with health, healthcare, living, and society to enhance the efficiency of healthcare delivery and to make medicine more personalized and precise.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Digital Health: A Backgrounder</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The National Health Policy 2017 had envisaged creation of a digital health technology eco-system aiming at developing an integrated health information system.</li>
<li>A Digital Health ID was proposed to reduce the risk of preventable medical errors and significantly increase the quality of care.</li>
<li>It recognised the need to establish a specialised ecosystem, called the National Digital Health Mission (NDHM).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="digital health" class="alignnone wp-image-626513" height="585" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 605px) 100vw, 605px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ndhmc-300x290.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ndhmc-300x290.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ndhmc.jpg 595w" width="605"/>The National Digital Health Mission</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The NDHM is a digital health ecosystem under which every Indian citizen will now have unique health IDs, digitized health records with identifiers for doctors and health facilities.</li>
<li>The mission will significantly improve the efficiency, effectiveness, and transparency of health service delivery and will be a major step towards the achievement of the UN Sustainable Development Goal 3.8 of Universal Health Coverage, including financial risk protection.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Digital health is a discipline that includes digital care programs, technologies with health, healthcare, living, and society to enhance the efficiency of healthcare delivery and to make medicine more personalized and precise." class="alignnone wp-image-626523" height="418" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/dh.jpeg" width="628"/>Significance of digital health </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Prioritizing patients: </strong>Say, mortality from Covid-19 is significantly increased by comorbidities or the presence of other underlying conditions like hypertension or diabetes.With digital health records, doctors can prioritise patients based on their test results.</li>
<li><strong>Portability of health records: </strong>Portability of records fairly eases in a patient with the first hospital visit, or her/his most frequently visited hospital. If she/he wishes to change a healthcare provider for cost or quality reasons, she can access her health records without carrying pieces of paper prescriptions and test reports. People will able to access their lab reports, x-rays and prescriptions irrespective of where they were generated, and share them with doctors or family members — with consent.</li>
<li><strong>Easy facilitation: </strong>This initiative will allow patients to access healthcare facilities remotely through e-pharmacies, online appointments, teleconsultation, and other health benefits. Besides, as all the medical history of the patient is recorded in the Health ID card, it will help the doctor to understand the case better, and improved medication can be offered.</li>
<li><strong>Technology impetus in policymaking: </strong>Meanwhile, it is also not just individuals who could emerge beneficiaries of the scheme. With large swathes of data being made available, the government too can form policies based on geographical, demographical, and risk-factor based monitoring of health.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Critical point to remember </strong></h4>
<p><strong>In the case of lung cancer, only 18.5 % of patients survive five or more years once diagnosed. These are threats that data-led technology will help address.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/on-digital-health-id-proceed-with-caution/"><strong>Major privacy issues involved</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Informed Consent:</strong>The citizen’s consent is vital for all access. A beneficiary’s consent is vital to ensure that information is released.</li>
<li><strong>Data leakages issue:</strong>Personalised data collected at multiple levels are a “sitting gold mine” for insurance companies, international researchers, and pharma companies.</li>
<li><strong>Digital divide:</strong>Other experts add that lack of access to technology, poverty, and lack of understanding of the language in a vast and diverse country like India are problems that need to be looked into.</li>
<li><strong>Data Migration:</strong>The data migration and inter-State transfer are still faced with multiple errors and shortcomings in addition to concerns of data security.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other challenges</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Existing digitalization is yet incomplete:</strong>India has been unable to standardise the coverage and quality of the existing digital cards like One Nation One Ration card, PM-JAY card, Aadhaar card, etc., for accessibility of services and entitlements.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of healthcare facilities:</strong>The defence of data security by expressed informed consent doesn’t work in a country that is plagued by the acute shortage of healthcare professionals to inform the client fully.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of finance:</strong>With the minuscule spending of 1.3% of the GDP on the healthcare sector, India will be unable to ensure the quality and uniform access to healthcare that it hoped to bring about.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>With an enabling ecosystem, supported by effective policies for digital healthcare and increased innovation, the promise of digital solutions in healthcare is immense. It’s not long before precision healthcare becomes central to the health and well-being of every citizen.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. The covid-19 pandemic has presented a watershed moment, bringing the world’s healthcare systems to a halt, forcing us to rethink existing healthcare delivery models. In this context discuss challenges and opportunities of digital health ecosystem in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/digital-health/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>