<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 01:42:24 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>A new global vision for G20</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/a-new-global-vision-for-g20/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>G-20</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- New framework for G20</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>While India has taken a clear view of the role of the G20, there is concern that the agenda, themes and focus areas which India will set for 2023 lack vision.</p>
<h4>What is G-20?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Formed in 1999, the G20 is an international forum of the governments and central bank governors from 20 major economies.</li>
<li>Collectively, the G20 economies account for around 85 percent of the Gross World Product (GWP), 80 percent of world trade.</li>
<li>To tackle the problems or address issues that plague the world, the heads of governments of the G20 nations periodically participate in summits.</li>
<li>In addition to it, the group also hosts separate meetings of the finance ministers and foreign ministers.</li>
<li>The G20 has no permanent staff of its own and its chairmanship rotates annually between nations divided into regional groupings.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of G20 in shaping global order</h4>
<ul>
<li>The G20 plays an important role in shaping and strengthening global architecture and governance on all major international economic issues.</li>
<li>It recognises that global prosperity is<strong> interdependent</strong> and economic <strong>opportunities and challenges are interlinked.</strong></li>
<li>The challenge is to craft new approaches to overcome the acute global discord.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why we need new model of cooperation</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multilateral commitments are faltering:</strong> Governance in a world that is steadily becoming more equal needs institutional innovation.</li>
<li>This is because the role of the United Nations and the World Trade Organization in securing cooperation between donor and recipient country groups is losing centrality.</li>
<li> There are now <strong>three socio-economic systems</strong> — the G7, China-Russia, and India and the others — and they will jointly set the global agenda.</li>
<li><strong>Strategic competition:</strong> Ukraine conflict, rival finance, the expanding influence of the trade and value chains dominated by the U.S. and China, and the <strong>reluctance of developing countries to take sides in the strategic competition</strong> as they have a real choice requires fresh thinking.</li>
<li><strong>Preventing the clash of ideas through reorientation</strong>: The primary role of the G20, which accounts for 95% of the world’s patents, 85% of global GDP, 75% of international trade and 65% of the world population, needs to be reoriented to prevent a clash of ideas to the detriment of the global good.</li>
<li>The solution lies in <strong>a new conceptual model</strong> seeking agreement on an agenda limited to principles rather than long negotiated anodyne text.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What should be on agenda when India hosts G20 in 2023</h4>
<h4>1] Underlining the need for new framework</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Redefining common concerns:</strong> First, the presumed equality that we are all in the same boat, recognised in the case of climate change, needs to be expanded to other areas with a global impact redefining ‘common concerns’.</li>
<li>Second, emerging economies are no longer to be considered the source of problems needing external solutions but source of solutions to shared problems.</li>
<li>Third, the BRICS provides an appropriate model for governance institutions suitable for the 21st century where a narrow group of states dominated by one power will not shape the agenda.</li>
<li>Ensuring adequate food, housing, education, health, water and sanitation and work for all should guide international cooperation.</li>
<li><strong>Principles of common but differentiated responsibilities</strong> for improving the quality of life of all households can guide deliberations in other fora on problems that seem intractable in multilateralism based on trade and aid.</li>
</ul>
<h4>2] Collaboration around science and technology</h4>
<ul>
<li> The global agenda has been tilted towards investment, whereas <strong>science and technology are the driving force for economic diversification</strong>, sustainably urbanising the world, and ushering the hydrogen economy and new crop varieties as the answer to both human well-being and global climate change.</li>
<li> A forum to exchange experiences on societal benefits and growth as complementary goals would lead to fresh thinking on employment and environment.</li>
</ul>
<h4>3] Redefining digital access as universal service</h4>
<ul>
<li>Harnessing the potential of the digital-information-technology revolution requires redefining digital access as a “universal service” that goes beyond physical connectivity to sharing specific opportunities available.</li>
<li>For global society to reap the fruits of the new set of network technologies,<strong> open access software</strong> should be offered for more cost-effective service delivery options, good governance and sustainable development.</li>
</ul>
<h4>4] Collaboration in space technology</h4>
<ul>
<li>Space is the next frontier for finding solutions to problems of <strong>natural resource management</strong> ranging from climate change-related natural disasters, supporting agricultural innovation to urban and infrastructure planning.</li>
<li><strong> Analysing Earth observation data</strong> will require regional and international collaboration through existing centres which have massive computing capacities, machine learning and artificial intelligence.</li>
</ul>
<h4>5] Collaboration in health sector</h4>
<ul>
<li>Public health has to learn from the COVID-19 fiasco with infectious diseases representing a market failure.</li>
<li>A major global challenge is the rapidly growing antimicrobial resistance which needs <strong>new antibiotics and collaboration between existing biotechnology facilities.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>6]  Avoiding strategic competition</h4>
<ul>
<li>Overriding priority to development suggests avoiding strategic competition.</li>
<li>Countries in the region will support building on the 1971 UNGA Declaration designating for all time the Indian Ocean as a zone of peace and non-extension into the region of rivalries and conflicts that are foreign to it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>7] Reviving Global Financial Transaction Tax</h4>
<ul>
<li> A<strong> Global Financial Transaction Tax</strong>, considered by the G20 in 2011, needs to be revived to be paid to a Green Technology Fund for Least Developed Countries.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>Given the significance of G20 for the global order it should lead the way in formulating the new framework based on collaboration in areas such as science and technology, innovation and away from aid and trade.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/a-new-global-vision-for-g20/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Lessons for India from the Taiwan standoff</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/lessons-for-india-from-the-taiwan-standoff/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Not much</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- Lessons for India in China-Taiwan crisis</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>The brief visit by the United States House Speaker, Nancy Pelosi, to Taiwan, against stern warnings issued by China, has the potential to increase the already deteriorating relationship between the U.S. and China. For those of us in India watching the events as they unfold around Taiwan, there are valuable lessons to be learnt.</p>
<h4>Background</h4>
<ul>
<li>The crisis that began with the visit of Ms. Pelosi to Taipei is still unfolding and there is little clarity today on how it will wind down.</li>
<li> For China, its <strong>claims about a rising superpower</strong> might ring hollow if it is unable to unify its claimed territories, in particular Taiwan.</li>
<li>For the U.S., it is about<strong> re-establishing steadily-diminishing American credibility</strong> in the eyes of its friends and foes.</li>
<li>For Taiwan, it is about standing up to Chinese bullying and making its red lines clear to Beijing.</li>
<li><strong>Lessons for India:</strong> To be fair, there is growing recognition in New Delhi that it is important to meet the challenge posed by a belligerent China, but there appears to be a lack of clarity on how to meet this challenge.</li>
<li>To that extent, the Taiwan crisis offers New Delhi three lessons, at the very least.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Takeaways for India</h4>
<h4>1] Articulate red lines</h4>
<ul>
<li>The most important lesson from the Taiwan standoff for policymakers in New Delhi is the importance of articulating red lines and <strong>sovereign positions in an unambiguous manner.</strong></li>
<li> New Delhi needs to unambiguously highlight the threat from China and the sources of such a threat.</li>
<li>Any absence of such clarity will be cleverly utilised by Beijing to push Indian limits, as we have already seen.</li>
<li><strong>Stop confusing international community</strong>: Even worse, ambiguous messaging by India also <strong>confuses its friends in the international community.</strong></li>
<li>If India <strong>does not clearly articulate that China is in illegal occupation of its territory</strong>, how can it expect its friends in the international community to support India diplomatically or otherwise?</li>
<li>In other words, India’s current policy amounts to poor messaging, and confusing to its own people as well as the larger international community, and is therefore counterproductive.</li>
</ul>
<h4>2] Avoid appeasement</h4>
<ul>
<li>Taiwan could have avoided the ongoing confrontation and the economic blockade during Chinese retaliatory military exercises around its territory by avoiding Ms. Pelosi’s visit to Taipei, or perhaps even keeping it low key.</li>
<li>Appeasement of China, Taiwan knows, is not the answer to Beijing’s aggression.</li>
<li> India’s policy of meeting/hosting Chinese leaders while the Chinese People’s Liberation Army (PLA) continue(d) to violate established territorial norms on the LAC is a deeply flawed one.</li>
<li>Unilaterally catering to Chinese sensitivities even during the standoffs between the two militaries is a mistake.</li>
<li>For instance, the parliamentary delegation visits and legislature-level dialogues between India and Taiwan have not taken place since 2017.</li>
<li>S<strong>oft-peddling of the Quad was a mistake:</strong> During the 2000s, India (as well as Australia) decided to soft-peddle the Quad in the face of strong Chinese objections.</li>
<li>It is only in the last two years or so that we have witnessed renewed enthusiasm around the Quad.</li>
<li>In retrospect, appeasing Beijing by almost abandoning the Quad was bad strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4>3] Economic relationship is a two way process</h4>
<ul>
<li>Given that the economic relationship is a two-way process and that, as a matter of fact, the trade deficit is in China’s favour, China too has a lot to lose from a damaged trade relationship with India.</li>
<li>More so, if the Taiwan example (as well as the India-China standoff in 2020) is anything to go by, trade can continue to take place despite tensions and without India making any compromises vis-à-vis its sovereign claims.</li>
<li>India for sure should do business with China, but not on China’s own terms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>The recent crisis offers valuable lessons for India in its dealing with China.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/lessons-for-india-from-the-taiwan-standoff/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>RBI, government must act in coordination during an economically challenging period</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rbi-government-must-act-in-coordination-during-an-economically-challenging-period/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Standing Deposit Facility rate</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Dealing with economically challenging period</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>In the recent MPC meeting, the policy rate hike was widely expected, more anticipated were the MPC and the RBI Governor’s forward guidance on the trajectory of policy — on both monetary policy and liquidity instruments. So, how do we see monetary policy evolve over the rest of the year and beyond?</p>
<h4>Tightening of monetary policy</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Repo rate at 5.4 per cent:</strong> In its latest meeting, the members of the monetary policy committee voted unanimously to increase the policy repo rate by 50 basis points to<strong> 5.4 per cent.</strong></li>
<li>The repo rate was 5.15 per cent in February 2020.</li>
<li>So, in effect, the RBI’s policy has not only been normalised, but has actually tightened <strong>compared to the pre-pandemic level.</strong></li>
<li> Even the lower bound of the rate corridor, the <strong>Standing Deposit Facility (SDF) rate,</strong> at 5.25 per cent is now above the pre-pandemic repo rate.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Forward guidance on stance</h4>
<ul>
<li>The MPS indicated the retaining the policy stance rather than shifting to “neutral”.</li>
<li>This <strong>retention of stance</strong> might be interpreted as being a bit more hawkish than “neutral”, which implies that rates might be both increased or cut, depending on economic conditions.</li>
<li>Now that policy is largely normalised, the <strong>pace of tightening</strong> is likely to moderate.</li>
<li>The urgency of aggressive rate hikes and tightening of liquidity has somewhat moderated, although risks remain.</li>
<li>RBI’s research suggests that the “real natural rate” — the rate at which policy is neither loose nor tight – is 0.8-1 per cent.</li>
<li>This operative interest rate is usually the<strong> three-month T-bill rate,</strong> which in “normal” times averages 10-15 basis points above the repo rate.</li>
<li>Considering that monetary policy is calibrated over a one-year horizon and using the RBI’s inflation forecast of 5 per cent for the first quarter of 2023-24, <strong>the “natural” repo rate will be around 5.85 per cent.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>Inflation and growth conditions</h4>
<ul>
<li>The RBI’s growth projection for 2022-23 has been retained at 7.2 per cent, with growth frontloaded in the first half.</li>
<li>CPI inflation is still forecast to average 6.7 per cent.</li>
<li>Inflationary pressures are likely to wane in the second half of 2022-23, particularly if the recent drop in industrial metals prices persists over the next few months.</li>
<li>A more or less normal monsoon might help in keeping food prices stable. However, risks remain.</li>
<li><strong>Robust growth prospects</strong>: Demand for consumption goods seems to be resilient, enabling some further pass-through of input costs.</li>
<li>Combine this with tight labour markets and rising wage costs in some tech-oriented sectors.</li>
<li>High frequency indicators of economic activity have recovered after some weakness in June.</li>
<li>In addition to resilient demand, there is evidence of a closing of the “output gap”.</li>
<li><strong>Global growth:</strong> Global growth and trade are forecast to significantly slow down in 2022 and 2023, largely due<strong> to aggressive tightening by G-10 central banks</strong> and a slowdown in China.</li>
<li>The IMF predicts global trade volume (both merchandise and services) to slow to 4.1 per cent and 3.2 per cent in 2022 and 2023, down from 10.1 per cent in 2021.</li>
<li>With world growth and trade flows moderating, along with a drop in commodities prices,<strong> India’s export growth is likely to be lower than last year.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>External financial condition</h4>
<ul>
<li>The current account deficit remains a concern.</li>
<li>India’s<strong> external balance sheet</strong> remains quite robust, as is evident from various balance of payments and debt metrics, and reportedly <strong>low unhedged foreign currency borrowings.</strong></li>
<li>Continued <strong>tightening by global central banks</strong>, particularly the US Federal Reserve over the rest of 2022, will keep India’s external financial conditions tight and likely <strong>limit portfolio capital flows. </strong></li>
<li>However, there are some signs emanating from these central banks that the hitherto front-loaded tightening might moderate going forward.</li>
<li>This will <strong>take some pressure off the rupee,</strong> though, exchange rate volatility management will remain a part of the overall monetary policy management framework.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Challenge of surplus liquidity</h4>
<ul>
<li>During the earlier phase of policy normalisation and the recent tightening, liquidity management has played an important role in influencing short-term money market interest rates.</li>
<li><strong>The current latent surplus liquidity</strong> — the existing funds with banks and the Union government’s unspent revenues parked with RBI — is over Rs 5 lakh crore.</li>
<li>While the extent of liquidity surplus during the Covid months has come down, these levels are still much higher than RBI estimates of non-inflationary levels of surplus, <strong>which is around Rs 1.8-2.4 lakh crore. </strong></li>
<li>This will gradually fall with cash withdrawals and some potential RBI dollar sales in the coming months.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>The central bank, in coordination with the government, has ensured an orderly evolution of economic conditions during a very complex and challenging environment. The exit process now will also need the same adroit use of policy instruments.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Standing Deposit Facility rate</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) in April 2022 introduced the <strong>Standing Deposit Facility (SDF)</strong>, an additional tool for absorbing liquidity, at an interest rate of 3.75 per cent.</li>
<li>The main purpose of SDF is to reduce the excess liquidity  in the system, and control inflation.</li>
<li>In 2018, the amended Section 17 of the RBI Act empowered the Reserve Bank to introduce the SDF –<strong> an additional tool for absorbing liquidity without any collateral. </strong></li>
<li>By removing the binding collateral constraint on the RBI, the SDF strengthens the operating framework of monetary policy.</li>
<li>The SDF is also a financial stability tool in addition to its role in liquidity management.</li>
<li>The SDF replaced the fixed rate reverse repo (FRRR) as the floor of the liquidity adjustment facility corridor.</li>
<li>The SDF rate will be 25 bps below the policy rate (Repo rate), and it will be applicable to overnight deposits at this stage.</li>
<li>It would, however, retain the flexibility to absorb liquidity of longer tenors as and when the need arises, with appropriate pricing.</li>
</ul>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rbi-government-must-act-in-coordination-during-an-economically-challenging-period/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Using a rupee route to get around a dominating dollar</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/using-a-rupee-route-to-get-around-a-dominating-dollar/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Foreign Exchange Management (Deposit) Regulations, 2016</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Trade and settlement of payments in rupee</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>A number of countries, including India, are now considering the use of other currencies to avoid the U.S. dollar and its hegemonic role in settling international transactions.</p>
<h4>Currency hierarchy</h4>
<ul>
<li>For India, currency hierarchy goes back to colonial times when the Indian rupee was virtually <strong>linked to the British pound</strong> rather than to gold which it earned through exports.</li>
<li>In the post-War period, the neo-colonial currency hierarchy has been clubbed with the continued use, primarily of the U.S. dollar, for the majority of international transactions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Rupee settlement of trade</h4>
<ul>
<li>In recent times, India has been taking an active interest in having the rupee used for trade and the settlement of payments with other countries, which include Russia, now facing sanctions.</li>
<li>The Reserve Bank of India has recently taken a proactive stand to have rupee settlement of trade (circular dated July 11, 2022).</li>
<li>While options for invoicing in rupees were already legal in terms of Regulation 7(1) of the <strong>Foreign Exchange Management (Deposit) Regulations, 2016,</strong> the current circular aims to operationalise the special<strong> Vostro accounts with Russian banks in India</strong>, in a bid to promote trade and also gain a better status for the rupee as an international currency.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Opportunities for India</h4>
<ul>
<li>The advantages India is currently seeking in these arrangements include avoidance of transactions in the highly priced dollar which has an exchange value of ₹80, impacting the Indian economy with inflation, capital flight and the <strong>drop in foreign exchange reserves</strong> by $70 billion since September 2021.</li>
<li> Buying oil with a depreciated ruble, and at discounts, is not only cost-saving but also saves transport time with the use of multi-modal routes using land, sea and air routes.</li>
<li>In addition, India is looking forward to trade expansion in sanctions-affected Russia.</li>
<li>With India having a trade deficit with Russia, which has been around $<strong>3.52 billion</strong> on average over the last two financial years, India’s opportunities include the possible use, by Russia, of the surpluses in the Vostro rupee account in Russian banks for additional purchases from India.</li>
<li><strong>Past attempts</strong>: Attempts to use the rupee for invoicing and trading is, however, not new to India.</li>
<li>A comprehensive bilateral trade and payments agreement was signed by India in 1953 with the Soviet bloc countries.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Challenges</h4>
<ul>
<li>There are quite a few problems that may prevail in implementing the desired rupee payments and avoiding dollar transactions.</li>
<li><strong>Willingness of banks and private parties:</strong> Apart from issues that concern an agreed<strong> exchange rate</strong> between the rupee and the ruble (R-R), two volatile currencies, there is also the question of the willingness of private parties (companies, banks) to accept the rupee for trade and settlements.</li>
<li> If Russia opens its door for exports from India, the ‘R-R’ route may prove attractive for Indian exporters.</li>
<li><strong>Concerns of the US:</strong> There are official concerns for reactions, particularly from the U.S., to deals, especially for purchase of the S-400 defence equipment.</li>
<li><strong>Reaction of the Europe:</strong> Moreover, the deals between India and Russia, especially on oil, can be considered by the West as ‘indirect back door support’ — as India is importing Russian crude<strong> at 30% discount,</strong> processing at refineries in Gujarat which include Reliance, and then exporting those to the West.</li>
<li><strong>Trade deficit:</strong> There were attempts even before the novel coronavirus pandemic to initiate a clearing account on the BRICS platform.</li>
<li>The quantitative implications indicate a skewed pattern of transactions — with China having most of the trade surplus.</li>
<li>It is a pattern similar to what is happening in India-Russia trade at the moment.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>The India-Soviet agreements of the past may provide a clue on how the current ‘R-R’ trade and the problems can be managed by initiating a push for Indian exports to Russia and, of course, avoiding all deals in dollars — benefiting both trade partners and countering, globally, the on-going currency hierarchy.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/using-a-rupee-route-to-get-around-a-dominating-dollar/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Personal Data Protection Bill</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/implications-of-withdrawal-of-the-personal-data-protection-bill/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>European Union’s Digital Services Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- Need for personal data protection act</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>In a surprise development last week, the Government withdrew the Personal Data Protection (PDP) Bill, 2019, thereby abruptly halting the country’s quest for a national data protection law that had been in the works for over five years.</p>
<h4>Reasons for withdrawal of the Bill</h4>
<ul>
<li>The short circular issued by the Minister of Electronics and Information Technology states that considering the report of the Joint Parliamentary Committee (JPC) — it had proposed 81 amendments and made 12 recommendations — <strong>“a comprehensive legal framework is being worked on”. </strong></li>
<li>There is no elaboration on what such a “comprehensive legal framework” entails.</li>
<li><strong>Possible plan of action: </strong>The Government could enact a fresh privacy legislation or <strong>a comprehensive data protection law</strong> (covering both personal and non-personal data).</li>
<li><strong>Subsuming data protection in IT Act:</strong> Alternatively, it could subsume data protection under its ongoing attempts at revising the existing Information Technology Act, 2000.</li>
<li><strong>Digital markets law:</strong> It could also enact a digital markets law, along the lines of the<strong> European Union’s Digital Services Act</strong>, focusing on competition and innovation in the digital space.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Background of the introduction of Personal Data Protection Bill</h4>
<ul>
<li>When the Supreme Court of India affirmed the right to privacy in  <strong>K.S. Puttaswamy judgment in 2017</strong>, the nine-judge Bench of the Court referred to the Government’s Office Memorandum constituting the<strong> B.N. Srikrishna Committee</strong> to suggest a draft Data Protection Bill.</li>
<li>The committee released its draft Personal Data Protection Bill in 2018, which was the first public articulation of a data protection law in India.</li>
<li>When the Supreme Court upheld the constitutionality of the Aadhaar Act, the majority emphasised that it believed that “there is a need for a proper legislative mechanism for data protection”.</li>
<li>In December 2019, the Government introduced the PDP Bill, 2019 in the Lok Sabha as a comprehensive personal data protection regime.</li>
<li>The Bill was referred to the JPC for its recommendations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What were the issues with the Bill?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Power to exemption with state:</strong> The Bill’s expansive exemptions <strong>allowed the state to exempt the entire application of the law</strong> simply as if it was “expedient” to do so in the interest of national security or public order.</li>
<li><strong>Powers without accountability:</strong> The PDP Bill, 2019 as well as the JPC’s version established a strong regulator (the Data Protection Authority) with a lot of power, but very little independence or accountability.</li>
<li><strong>Data localisation:</strong> The Bill imposed a s<strong>trong data localisation mandate</strong>, requiring companies to store all sensitive personal data and critical personal data (which was not defined) in India.</li>
<li><strong>Subsuming the personal and non-personal data:</strong> The JPC recommended subsuming the regulation of personal data and non-personal data within a single legislation, even though it undermined the Puttaswamy mandate to ensure protection of personal data.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why we need data protection law?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increasing internet use:</strong> India currently has over <strong>750 million Internet users</strong>, with the number only expected to increase in the future.</li>
<li>The Government is also making a strong push for a <strong>‘Digital India’,</strong> with increased focus on digitisation of access to health, ration, banking, insurance, especially after the COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
<li>There is<strong> a greater focus on the inter-linking of data,</strong> whether through facial recognition, Aadhaar, or the Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022.</li>
<li><strong>Data breaches:</strong> At the same time, India has among the highest data breaches in the world.</li>
<li>Without a data protection law in place, the data of millions of Indians continues to be at risk of being exploited, sold, and misused without their consent.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of writ proceeding against corporate action:</strong> Unlike state action, corporate action or misconduct is not subject to writ proceedings in India.</li>
<li>This is because fundamental rights are, by and large, not enforceable against private non-state entities.</li>
<li>This leaves individuals with limited remedies against private actors.</li>
<li>A personal data protection legislation would remedy this lacuna by providing individuals with proper grievance redress options and creating sufficient deterrence among private actors.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>It is imperative that the Government soon introduces a fresh data protection legislation, drawn after proper public consultation. Such a law should take into consideration the criticisms that have been raised by civil society as well as the private sector.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/implications-of-withdrawal-of-the-personal-data-protection-bill/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India’s tax-GDP ratio may be too high</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-tax-gdp-ratio-may-be-too-high/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Tax buoyancy</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Tax-to-GDP ratio</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>What the data conclusively show is that the debate on the Indian economy should shift away from simplistic notions (borrowed from the West?) of the tax-GDP ratio being low in India.</p>
<h4>India’s low tax-to-GDP ratio</h4>
<ul>
<li>One of the stylised beliefs in India, and amongst some leading economic commentators both in India and abroad, is that our tax/GDP ratio is lower than what it “should” be.</li>
<li>This low tax-to-GDP ratio is blamed for a<strong> lower rate of investment</strong>, a<strong> higher fiscal deficit</strong>, and lower GDP growth — and all because the tax ratio is too low.</li>
<li>There can be reasonable doubts about the presumed links.</li>
<li>There are three important fiscal variables in the economy — <strong>taxes, fiscal deficit, and debt. </strong></li>
<li>They are inter-related — lower tax revenue means higher fiscal deficit, for the same level of expenditures, and higher deficit means higher debt.</li>
<li>All three, directly or indirectly, are assumed <strong>to affect growth and/or inflation.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>Analysing India’s tax-to-GDP ratio</h4>
<ul>
<li>Two common observations on tax-to-GDP for India — first, it is low at around<strong> 10-11 per cent of GDP</strong> and it has stayed at close to that level for the last 20 years.</li>
<li>In 2019, it hit a decade low of 10 per cent of GDP, the same as in 2014.</li>
<li>Second, in comparison with our peers, it is much lower.</li>
<li>Hence, logic dictates that we should strive to increase it.</li>
<li>But which country should we compare India with?</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with comparing tax-to-GDP with other countries</h4>
<ul>
<li>A common observation is to look at the tax-GDP ratio in G20 countries.</li>
<li><strong>Function of average level of per capita income:</strong> This is the beginning of a set of misinterpretations committed either knowingly, or unknowingly.</li>
<li>Because simple logic dictates that tax collected is <strong>a function of the average level of per capita income.</strong></li>
<li>Per capita income in the G20 varies from around $2,100 (India) to around $65,000 (US).</li>
<li>The 10-11 per cent figure for India is the tax/GDP <strong>ratio for taxes administered at the central level.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Challenges in data collection</strong>: Taxes in India, as in many other large, especially federal, countries, are collected at both a federal and state level.</li>
<li>And many economies have local (municipal) taxes as well. The tax collected is the sum of all these taxes.</li>
<li>Until now, collecting such disaggregated data for a large set of countries was challenging.</li>
<li>However, in a recent web publication, the IMF on their World Revenue Longitudinal Data set has published such data for all countries, from 1990-2019.</li>
<li>In this pre-pandemic year, among G20 economies, India’s tax-GDP (Xtax) ratio of 16.7 per cent was higher than that of China (15.9 per cent), Mexico (14.1 per cent), Indonesia (11.0 per cent), Saudi Arabia (5.9 per cent) and Turkey (15.9 per cent).</li>
<li>A more informative indicator of whether a country is taxing too much or too little in comparison with others is to look at the <strong>tax-GDP ratio adjusted for PPP per capita income.</strong></li>
<li>Prediction via a simple regression of tax-to-GDP on log PPP per capita GDP can yield one estimate of the tax gap — the difference between actual and actual adjusted for level of income.</li>
<li>The world average tax gap is -1.3 per cent;<strong> India is +1.2 per cent for the nine years 2011-2019.</strong></li>
<li>So, India’s tax GDP ratio averages 2.5 percentage points more than an average economy.</li>
<li>For every year for which data are available 1990-2019, India has had a positive tax gap — there is little evidence that a higher tax/GDP ratio helps growth.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How corporate tax cut helped India</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Corporate tax cut 2019:</strong> For years, the advocacy in India was to increase revenue from corporate tax which is one of three major components of tax revenue, the other being income and indirect taxes.</li>
<li>In September 2019, Finance Minister going well against Indian established conventional wisdom, lowered the corporate tax rate by around 10 percentage points.</li>
<li><strong>Avoiding triple whammy</strong>: Opponents said that empirical evidence around the world (for example, the US) meant that <strong>if tax rates were lowered, revenues would decline, the fisc would increase, as would inequality.</strong></li>
<li>A triple whammy that is best avoided.</li>
<li>However, now, three years later, we can assess the efficacy (or not) of this bold experiment.</li>
<li>For the three months April-June 2022, corporate tax revenues, y-o-y, are up 30 per cent.</li>
<li>Using fiscal 2019-20 as a base, corporate tax revenue has increased by 66 per cent, GDP by 33 per cent —<strong> an average tax buoyancy of 2.0 over three years. </strong></li>
<li>The previous largest tax buoyancy was in 2006-7 when the world was buoyant.</li>
<li>Tentatively, the tax-GDP ratio in the fiscal year 2022-23 will <strong>average over 18 per cent in India</strong>, a level close to Japan and the US.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>In India, the debate should shift to expenditures, and quality of expenditures (and perhaps to reform of the direct tax code). In this regard, suggestion that freebies be critically examined is most timely and welcome.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<hr/>
<h4> Back2Basics: Tax buoyancy and tax elasticity</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tax buoyancy:</strong> The buoyancy of a tax system <b>measures the total response of tax revenue both to changes in</b>. <b>national income and to discretionary changes in tax policies over time</b>, and it is traditionally interpreted as the percentage change in revenue associated to a one percent change in income.</li>
<li>Tax elasticity: It refers to changes in tax revenue in response to <strong>changes in tax rate. </strong></li>
<li>For example, how tax revenue changes if the government reduces corporate income tax from 30 per cent to 25 per cent indicate tax elasticity.</li>
</ul>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-tax-gdp-ratio-may-be-too-high/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian breed of Pet Dogs</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-indian-breed-of-pet-dogs/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Various breeds mentioned</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p>Mudhol hounds, a breed of hunting dogs native to north Karnataka, could be inducted into the Special Protection Group (SPG), the elite force protecting the Prime Minister of India.</p>
<blockquote>
<h4><em>Try this PYQ:</em></h4>
<p><strong><em>Q.What is/are unique about ‘Kharai camel’, a breed found in India?</em></strong></p>
<ol>
<li><em> It is capable of swimming up to three kilometres in seawater.</em></li>
<li><em> It survives by grazing on mangroves.</em></li>
<li><em> It lives in the wild and cannot be domesticated.</em></li>
</ol>
<p><em>Select the correct answer using the code given below:</em></p>
<p><em>(a) 1 and 2 only </em></p>
<p><em>(b) 3 only </em></p>
<p><em>(c) 1 and 3 only </em></p>
<p><em>(d) 1, 2 and 3</em></p>
<p><strong><em>Answer: (a)</em></strong></p></blockquote>
<h4>Famous Indian dog breeds</h4>
<p><strong>(1)Mudhol hounds</strong></p>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273224" height="203" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 321px) 100vw, 321px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/mudhol.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/mudhol.jpg 668w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/mudhol-300x190.jpg 300w" width="321"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The Mudhol hounds come from the region bordering Karnataka and Maharashtra.</li>
<li>According to a popular legend Ch. Shivaji Maharaj bred and used these dogs in his army.</li>
<li>The breed was named after the erstwhile princely state of Mudhol, which was part of the Bombay Presidency in British India.</li>
<li>The last king of the state, King Malojirao Ghorpade, presented a pair of these puppies to King George V when he visited the UK and it was the English emperor who christened the dogs as Mudhol hounds.</li>
<li>Mudhol hounds have narrow heads that are disproportionately smaller to their bodies but are tall in height.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2)Himachali hounds</strong></p>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273223" height="243" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 252px) 100vw, 252px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/hima.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/hima.jpg 442w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/hima-300x289.jpg 300w" width="252"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The Himachali hounds are locally known as the ‘Gaddi’ dog and come from the Himalayan region. They are massive, mastiff-like dogs with thick fur to protect them from the cold.</li>
<li>They look similar to the Tibetan mastiff but are less bulky.</li>
<li>‘Gaddi’ means shepherd in Urdu, and these dogs are primarily guarding livestock.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3)Rajapalayam</strong></p>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273222" height="231" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/rpm.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/rpm.jpg 382w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/rpm-292x300.jpg 292w" width="225"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The breed Rajapalayam is believed to have originated from Tamil Nadu, and named after the state’s Rajapalayam city in the Virudhunagar district.</li>
<li>A rare breed, these dogs are only found in certain pockets of the state.</li>
<li>These dogs are white, lean, muscular, and have historically made good hunters.</li>
<li>They are believed to have fought alongside the Polygar soldiers against the British East India Company during the Polygar wars from 1799 to 1805.</li>
<li>This is why the Rajapalayam dogs are also known as ‘Polygar hounds’.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(4) Kanni and Chippiparai</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273221" height="221" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 296px) 100vw, 296px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/kanni.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/kanni.jpg 532w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/kanni-300x224.jpg 300w" width="296"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The Kanni dog is another breed from Tamil Nadu, and its name translates to “pure” in Tamil after its fierce loyalty.</li>
<li>Like the Rajapalayam, Kanni dogs specialise in hunting hares, wild boars, and blackbucks.</li>
<li>However, since the Wildlife Protection Act of 1972 was passed, these dogs have been acting as guard dogs.</li>
<li>The Kennel Club of India, which maintains a registry of purebred dogs in India, has registered this dog under two names — Kanni and Chippiparai.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(5)Combai</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273220" height="180" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/comba.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/comba.jpg 445w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/comba-300x202.jpg 300w" width="268"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The Combai dogs also originate from Tamil Nadu. They are tan-coloured with a black snout and appear shorter and stouter than the Rajapalayam. They are classified as terriers.</li>
<li>Like the Kanni and Rajapalayam, these dogs are rare and a dying breed and were historically used for boar hunting and guarding purposes.</li>
<li>The CRPF recently recruited Combai dogs into their Dog Breeding and Training School.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-indian-breed-of-pet-dogs/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Long road ahead: Towards women empowerment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/long-road-ahead-towards-women-empowerment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Global Gender Gap Report 2022.</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Women issues,Affirmative actions.</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-623245" height="365" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 548px) 100vw, 548px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/wemp1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/wemp1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/wemp1.jpg 650w" width="548"/>Context</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Gender parity is not recovering, according to the <strong>Global Gender Gap Report 2022.</strong> It will take another <strong>132 years to close the global gender gap</strong>.</li>
<li>As crises are compounding, women’s workforce outcomes are suffering and the risk of <strong>global gender parity</strong> backsliding further intensifies.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Why in news?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India has one of the world’s lowest female labour force participation rates (LFPR).</li>
<li>This means the productive potential of half of the population goes unutilized.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What is women’s empowerment all about?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Women’s empowerment can be defined to promoting women’s sense of <strong>self-worth</strong>, their ability to determine their <strong>own choices</strong>, and their right to influence <strong>social change</strong> for themselves and others.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Why it is needed?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Human resource</strong>: Empowerment of women is a necessity for the very development of a society, since it enhances both the quality and the quantity of human resources available for development.</li>
<li><strong>Sustainable development:</strong> Women’s empowerment and achieving gender equality is essential for our society to ensure the sustainable development of the country.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-623247" height="409" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 403px) 100vw, 403px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/positive-296x300.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/positive-296x300.jpeg 296w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/positive.jpeg 453w" width="403"/>Constraints in women empowerment </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Illiteracy</strong>: Illiteracy has been found as major constraints for the attainment of women Empowerment in the nation. It is the rate of literacy which governs the reservation, takeover and competition among women for their right in country. Female child are less privileged for attaining schools.</li>
<li><strong>Discriminatory nature of male towards female</strong>: In India, since the olden days, the men have been in control of politics, social, economical as well as cultural and traditional spheres of life.</li>
<li><strong>Religious and cultural beliefs</strong>: This is another important constraint of women’s empowerment in India which tightens up the female population. It is because of unknowing believes and following superstitions.</li>
<li><strong>Less participation of women in political field</strong>: In particular, women them self involves less in the political filed. Their participation is very insignificant in political issues and right as compared to male population.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What happens if we don’t act?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Economical losses</strong>: Evidence shows that economic disempowerment of women can result in losses of 10% of GDP in industrialized economies and over 30% in South Asia and in the Middle East and North Africa.</li>
<li><strong>Work opportunities</strong>: India’s GDP could grow by nearly ₹3 trillion if women were brought into the labour market and given access to formal, ‘decent’ work opportunities.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Case study </strong></p>
<p><strong>Mahila Sanatkar</strong> a craftswomen cooperative located in Hyderabad.</p>
<p><strong>Economic and social  effects</strong>: It  is  noticeable  some  social  results  such  as  <strong>skill building, self-confidence  enhancement,  the  mobility acquired  by the  women.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong>What is needed to improve women’s welfare?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Community sensitization:</strong> Persistent effort must be directed toward community sensitization to root out patriarchal social norms.</li>
<li><strong>Directional efforts</strong>: In addition to enforcing existing regulations like minimum wages, there must be supportive ancillary policies including childcare; secure transport; lighting; safety at work; and quotas in hiring, corporate boards, and politics to foster more  women  in  leadership.</li>
<li><strong>Universal social mobilization</strong>: Identification and inclusion of the poor remains a challenge. There is need to develop community resource persons for participatory identification of poor.</li>
<li><strong>Training, Capacity Building &amp; Skill Upgradation</strong>: There is lack of appropriate training plans, quality training and availability of expert training institutions.</li>
<li><strong>Universal Financial Inclusion</strong>: Lack of uniform financial management systems at all tiers of SHGs has impacted the growth in bank accounts, improvement in financial literacy, and absorption capacity of community members.</li>
<li><strong>Multiple &amp; Diversified Livelihoods</strong>: There is lack of progressive leadership for inclusiveness of small-sized enterprises at the federal level. Market/ forward linkages, is largely missing.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>If we improve women’s labour force participation, not only do we harness the massive productive potential of half of the population, but their earnings will yield enormous dividends for the future of the country and economy<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you consider as true women empowerment? Assess the constraints for the same and give directional efforts needed to overcome it.  </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/long-road-ahead-towards-women-empowerment/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian Olympic Association (IOA)</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-olympic-association-ioa/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>IOC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Olympics and India</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-623259" height="210" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ioa-300x210.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ioa-300x210.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ioa.jpg 465w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has ordered status quo on the implementation of a Delhi High Court order to hand over the affairs of the Indian Olympic Association (IOA) to a Committee of Administrators (CoA).</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The FIFA had recently gone ahead and suspended the AIFF, citing “third party interference”, leaving an air of uncertainty on the prospect of India hosting the Under-17 Women’s World Cup in October.</li>
<li>The governance of the AIFF had similarly been transferred to a CoA by the Supreme Court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Delhi HC case</h4>
<ul>
<li>The high court had passed the order on a petition seeking a direction for redrafting of the IOA constitution in accordance with the National Sports Code, 2021.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Controversy with IOC</h4>
<ul>
<li>According to IOC rules, if any national body is governed by a non-elected body, it is seen as interference by a third party.</li>
<li>The moment the CoA takes charge, there is 99 per cent chance that India and our sportspersons will get suspended from all international events and Olympic Games.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Olympics and India</h4>
<ul>
<li>India first participated in the Olympics in 1900 in Paris.</li>
<li>The country was represented by Norman Pritchard, an Anglo Indian who was holidaying in Paris during that time.</li>
<li>The seeds for creation of an organisation for coordinating the Olympic movement in India was related to India’s participation in the 1920 and 1924 Olympics.</li>
<li>Back then, Sir Dorabji Tata suggested the need for a Sports body at National level for promoting Olympic Sport in united India.</li>
<li>After the 1920 Games, the Committee sending the team to these Games met, and, on the advice of Sir Dorabji Tata, invited Dr. A.G. Noehren (Physical Education Director of YMCA India) to also join them.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Establishment of Indian Olympic Association (IOA)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Subsequently, in 1923-24, a provisional All India Olympic Committee was set-up, which organised the All India Olympic Games in February 1924.</li>
<li>Eight athletes from these Games were selected to represent India at the 1924 Paris Summer Olympics, accompanied by manager Harry Crowe Buck.</li>
<li>This gave impetus to the development and institutionalization of sports in India, and, in 1927, the Indian Olympic Association (IOA) was formed, with Sir Dorabji Tata as its founding President and Dr. A.G. Noehren as Secretary.</li>
<li>The same year as it was formed, 1927, the Indian Olympic Association was officially recognised by the International Olympic Committee.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="cItjbZQe0Z"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/better-time-for-sports-in-india-pm/">Better time for Sports in India: PM</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="cItjbZQe0Z" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/better-time-for-sports-in-india-pm/embed/#?secret=0nFyJRmfx4#?secret=cItjbZQe0Z" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“Better time for Sports in India: PM” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-olympic-association-ioa/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Labour policies need to change for better quality livelihoods</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/labour-policies-need-to-change-for-better-quality-livelihoods/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Universal basic income.</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Social security ,Inclusive growth.</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-623256" height="356" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 521px) 100vw, 521px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/labour-300x205.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/labour-300x205.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/labour.jpg 660w" width="521"/>Context</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>One of the biggest economic fallout of the pandemic has been the deteriorating labour market conditions.</li>
<li>Given the ebb and flow of the pandemic, the growth recovery is likely to be fragmented and will weigh on the number and types of jobs available.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What is quality and sustainable livelihood?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>“A livelihood comprises the capabilities, assets and activities required for a means of living. A livelihood is sustainable when it can cope with and recover from stresses and shocks and maintain or enhance its capabilities and assets both now and in the future, while not undermining the natural resource base.’’</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Sustainable livelihoods objectives</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>improved access to high-quality education, information, technologies and training and better nutrition and health;</li>
<li>a more supportive and cohesive social environment;</li>
<li>more secure access to, and better management of, natural resources;</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Definition of labour welfare </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Labour welfare relates to taking care of the well-being of workers by employers, trade unions, governmental and non-governmental institutions and agencies.</li>
<li>Welfare includes anything that is done for the comfort and improvement of employees and is provided over and above the wages.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Why labour law is needed </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Labour law aims to correct the imbalance of power between the worker and the employer; to prevent the employer from dismissing the worker without good cause; to set up and preserve the processes by which workers are recognized as ‘equal’ partners in negotiations about their working conditions etc<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Constitutional mandate </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Article 41</strong> – The state shall within the limits of its economic capacity and development make effective provision for securing the right to work, to education and to public assistance in cases of unemployment, old age, sickness and disablement and in other cases of underserved want.</li>
<li><strong>Article 42</strong> – The state shall make provision for securing just and humane conditions of work and for maternity relief.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Challenges in labour welfare in India </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Technical glitches:</strong> Under the Constitution of India, Labour is a subject in the concurrent list where both the Central and State Governments are competent to enact legislations. As a result, a large number of labour laws have been enacted catering to different aspects of labour e.g. occupational health, safety, employment etc.</li>
<li><strong>Loopholes:</strong> Because of the predominantly heavy handed labour regulations (also called as Inspector Raj) with exploitable gaps, the MNCs and domestic organizations have resorted to alternate ways i.e. employing contract labour at less than half the payroll of a permanent employee.</li>
<li><strong>Gaps in labour laws:</strong> One of the main reasons for labour reforms is the concept of contract labour. Trade Unions suggest that this concept itself should be removed. There is stringent hiring and firing process defined in Industry Disputes Act. It makes it mandatory for the organization to seek Government permission before removing an employee.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Global best practices  </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Universal basic income pilot project:</strong> For two years Finland’s government gave 2,000 unemployed citizens €560 a month with no strings attached. It was the first nationwide basic income experiment. The concept is slowly becoming difficult for people to ignore.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>How will dynamic policies and labour codes respond?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Labour productivity</strong>: It is likely to improve with both employees and employers developing a sense of being partners in wealth creation.</li>
<li><strong>Labour reform</strong>: A transparent environment in terms of workers’ compensation, clear definition of employee rights and employer duties.</li>
<li><strong>Compliance un-burdening</strong>: Simplified labour codes making compliance easier are likely to attract investments.</li>
<li><strong>Formalization of the economy</strong>: With more workers in the organized sector, leakage in terms of direct as well as indirect taxes may be plugged.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The guiding principle for India’s labour policy reformers should not merely be ring fencing jobs but safeguarding workers through <strong>social assistance, re-employment</strong> support (such as that which is provided in several Western nations) and <strong>skill building</strong>, and supporting employers in employee training and development.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. Why there is need to make labour policies more dynamic? Do you think universal basic income approach will be the best way forward for achieving quality livelihood?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/labour-policies-need-to-change-for-better-quality-livelihoods/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Species in news: Great Indian Bustard</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/species-great-indian-bustard/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Great Indian Bustard</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-623258" height="274" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/bst-300x274.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/bst-300x274.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/bst.jpg 669w" width="300"/></strong></p>
<p>The critically endangered Great Indian Bustard (GIB) has adopted an altogether new behaviour of giving clutch of two eggs at a time after getting additional protein diet during the monsoon season.</p>
<h4>Great Indian Bustards</h4>
<ul>
<li>GIBs are the largest among the four bustard species found in India, the other three being MacQueen’s bustard, lesser florican, and the Bengal florican.</li>
<li>GIBs’ historic range included much of the Indian sub-continent but it has now shrunken to just 10 percent of it. Among the heaviest birds with flight, GIBs prefer grasslands as their habitats.</li>
<li>GIBs are considered the flagship bird species of grassland.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Protection accorded</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Birdlife International:</strong> uplisted from Endangered to Critically Endangered (2011)</li>
<li><strong>Protection under CITES</strong>: Appendix I</li>
<li><strong>IUCN status:</strong> Critically Endangered</li>
<li><strong>Protection under Wildlife (Protection) Act:</strong> Schedule I</li>
</ul>
<h4>Threats</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Overhead power transmission</strong></li>
<li><strong>Poor vision:</strong> Due to their poor frontal vision, can’t detect powerlines in time and their weight makes in-flight quick maneuvers difficult.</li>
<li><strong>Windmills:</strong> Coincidentally, Kutch and Thar desert are the places that have witnessed the creation of huge renewable energy infrastructure.</li>
<li><strong>Noise pollution:</strong> Noise affects the mating and courtship practices of the GIB.</li>
<li><strong>Changes in the landscape:</strong> by way of farmers cultivating their land, which otherwise used to remain fallow due to frequent droughts in Kutch.</li>
<li><strong>Cultivation changes:</strong> Cultivation of cotton and wheat instead of pulses and fodder are also cited as reasons for falling GIB numbers.</li>
</ul>
<h4>On the brink of extinction</h4>
<ul>
<li>The GIB population in India had fallen to just 150.</li>
<li>Pakistan is also believed to host a few GIBs and yet openly supports their hunting.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Supreme Court’s intervention</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court has ordered that all overhead power transmission lines in core and potential GIB habitats in Rajasthan and Gujarat should be undergrounded.</li>
<li>The SC also formed a three-member committee to help power companies comply with the order.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conservation measures</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2015, the Central government launched the GIB species recovery program.</li>
<li>Under the program, the WII and Rajasthan Forest departments have jointly set up conservation breeding centers where GIB eggs are harvested from the wild.</li>
<li>They have been incubated artificially and hatchlings raised in a controlled environment.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ</h4>
<p><strong>Q.Consider the following pairs:</strong></p>
<p><strong>Protected Area: Well-known for </strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Bhiterkanika, Odisha — Salt Water Crocodile</li>
<li>Desert National Park, Rajasthan — Great Indian Bustard</li>
<li>Eravikulam, Kerala — Hoolock Gibbon</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Which of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched? (CSP 2014)</strong></p>
<p>(a) 1 only</p>
<p>(b) 1 and 2</p>
<p>(c) 2 only</p>
<p>(d) 1, 2 and 3</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/species-great-indian-bustard/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Mystery of milk price going up when WPI inflation is down</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mystery-of-milk-price-going-up-when-wpi-inflation-is-down/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Milk inflation</p></div></div><p>Milk prices are rising, as producers and marketers pass on higher costs to consumers.  Amul and Mother Dairy raised milk prices by ₹2 each this week, the second such hike this year.</p>
<h4>Why are milk prices going up?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>High operating cost:</strong> For dairy companies and cooperatives, the cost of operation and production of milk has increased.</li>
<li><strong>Fodder price hike:</strong> Prices of cattle feed, which includes maize, wheat and soybean, are up 20% over the year.</li>
<li><strong>High procurement cost:</strong> Given the rise in input costs, its member unions from where it procures milk have increased farmers’ price in the range of 8-9% year-on-year.</li>
<li><strong>Cost sharing:</strong> In an already inflationary environment, dairies are compelled to pass on price increases to consumers as procurement prices go up.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Has demand for milk picked up as well?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A better rate of vaccination, resumption of offices, schools and even opening up of channels such as hotels and restaurants have led to higher out-of-home consumption of foods and beverages in the last two to three quarters.</li>
<li>This has led to greater demand for milk and other dairy beverages.</li>
<li>Analysts cited higher skimmed milk prices in the international markets that they said make exports of the commodity out of India more attractive.</li>
<li>A combination of these factors is pushing up milk procurement prices, and leading to higher retail prices.</li>
</ul>
<h4>But isn’t wholesale inflation cooling down nowadays?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Yes; India’s wholesale price-based inflation eased to 13.93% in July.</li>
<li>In fact, <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/concept-of-inflation-deflation-wpi-cpi-iip/">WPI</a> inflation in milk eased in July to 5.45% compared  to  6.35%  in  June,  though it remained high compared to February.</li>
<li>However, companies also pass on hikes with a lag to lessen the impact on demand. Amul says the increase is less than 4% — below the food inflation rate of 8-9%.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When will milk prices cool down?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Milk procurement is also dependent on the flush season that runs between September to February.</li>
<li>This is the peak lactating period for cattle due to better availability of green fodder and water.</li>
<li>As a result, the period in general sees higher milk production and availability.</li>
<li>The onset of  the  flush  season  could offer some relief to dairy companies in the second half of the current fiscal year.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What does this mean for consumers?</h4>
<ul>
<li>For households, an  increase  in milk prices obviously means shelling out more money; this in a country that is among largest consumers of milk.</li>
<li>In fact,  by July,  dairy companies had raised milk selling prices by 5-8% in a six-month window.</li>
<li>Consumer demand typically sees an impact in the first few days after price hikes are initiated. However, recovery happens gradually.</li>
<li>Consequently, higher milk procurement prices could also hurt companies that make bakery products or food items that use milk or milk solids.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="8WGId0RAeu"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/concept-of-inflation-deflation-wpi-cpi-iip/">Concept of Inflation/Deflation/WPI/CPI/IIP</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="8WGId0RAeu" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/concept-of-inflation-deflation-wpi-cpi-iip/embed/#?secret=OhM3d1XKbJ#?secret=8WGId0RAeu" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“Concept of Inflation/Deflation/WPI/CPI/IIP” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mystery-of-milk-price-going-up-when-wpi-inflation-is-down/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Thin line between freebies and public welfare</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/thin-line-between-freebies-and-public-welfare/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Social security,Populist measures.</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-623266" height="268" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 536px) 100vw, 536px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/frb-1-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/frb-1-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/frb-1-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/frb-1.jpg 832w" width="536"/>Context</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>‘Revdi Culture’ (sweet) or Govt’s Basic Responsibility? What Prioritising Welfare Is Really About</li>
<li>While hearing a petition demanding the de-recognition of political parties that promise “irrational freebies” to voters, the Supreme Court recently drew attention to the substantial fiscal cost of freebies.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What are freebies? </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>A freebie is any public policy intervention that will have a long-term impact on production as well as productivity.</li>
<li>Any public policy intervention that doesn’t support medium-term to long-term production and productivity may be termed as a freebie.</li>
<li>The term Freebies is not new; rather it is a prevalent culture in Indian politics (in the name of socialism).</li>
<li>The political parties are always trying to outdo each other in luring the Indian voters with</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Examples of freebies</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Promise of Rs 15 lakh in our bank accounts</li>
<li>Free TV, Laptops</li>
<li>Free electricity</li>
<li>Loan waivers</li>
<li>Offering free public transport ride to all women in Delhi</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Why are such policies popular among the public?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Failure of economic</strong> policies: The answer lies in the utter failure of our economic policies to create decent livelihood for a vast majority of Indians.</li>
<li><strong>Quest for decent livelihood</strong>: The already low income had to be reoriented towards spending a disproportionately higher amount on education and health, from which, the state increasingly withdrew.</li>
<li><strong>Prevailing unemployment</strong>:  Employment surveys have shown that employment growth initially slowed down from the 1990s, and then has turned negative over the past few years.</li>
<li><strong>Increased cost of living:</strong> Real income growth of the marginal sections has actually slowed down since 1991 reforms.</li>
<li><strong>Increased consumerism</strong>: The poor today also spend on things which appear to be luxuries; cellphones and data-packs are two such examples which are shown as signs of India’s increased affluence.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Thin line between freebie and public welfare </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Using freebies to lure voters is not good.</li>
<li>Voter’s greediness may lead to a problem in choosing a good leader.</li>
<li>When we don’t have a good leader then democracy will be a mockery.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Negative implications </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Never ending trail</strong>: The continuity of freebies is another major disadvantage as parties keep on coming up with lucrative offers to lure more number of votes to minimize the risk of losing in the elections.</li>
<li><strong>Burden on exchequer</strong>: People forget that such benefits are been given at the cost of exchequer and from the tax paid.</li>
<li><strong>Ultimate loss of poors</strong>: The politicians and middlemen wipe away the benefits and the poor have to suffer as they are deprived from their share of benefits which was to be achieved out of the money.</li>
<li><strong>Inflationary practice</strong>: Such distribution freebie commodity largely disrupts demand-supply dynamics.</li>
<li><strong>Lethargy in population:</strong> Freebies actually have the tendency to turn the nation’s population into: Lethargy and devoid of entrepreneurship.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Rational elements in freebies </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Social investment:</strong><strong> </strong>Aid to the poor is seen as a wasteful expenditure. But low interest rates for corporates to get cheap loans or the ‘sop’ of cutting corporate taxes are never criticized.</li>
<li><strong>Socialistic policy:</strong><strong> </strong>This attitude comes from decades of operating within the dominant discourse of market capitalism.</li>
<li><strong>Election manifesto</strong>: Proponents of such policies would argue that poll promises are essential for voters to know what the party would do if it comes to power and have the chance to weigh options.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Why they need to stop?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Winning election and good governance are two different things. The role of freebies to avail good governance is definitely questionable.</li>
<li>The social, political and economic consequences of freebies are very short-lived in nature.</li>
<li>There are many freebies and subsidies schemes available in many States but we still find starvation deaths, lack of electricity, poor education and health service.</li>
<li>Hence the sorrow of the masses of India cannot be solved by freebies or by incentives<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is nothing wrong in having a policy-led elaborate social security programme that seeks to help the poor get out of poverty.</li>
<li>But such a programme needs well thought out preparation and cannot be conjured up just before an election.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Do you think freebies are justified under the name of social security? Critically evaluate the rising freebie culture in India with its negative implications.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> <a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/thin-line-between-freebies-and-public-welfare/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Solar energy is the future</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/solar-energy-is-the-future/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>International solar alliance.</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Energy security.</p></div></div><p> </p>
<h4><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-623629" height="337" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/download.jpeg" width="506"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tesla and SpaceX CEO Elon Musk has said that civilisation will be mostly solar-powered in the future, a world without Sun will turn into a dark ice ball as the Earth gets all of its energy from it.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Definition of solar energy </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Solar energy is radiant light and heat from the Sun that is harnessed using a range of technologies such as solar power to generate electricity, solar thermal energy, and solar architecture.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>India’s solar target</strong>.</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Target</strong>: India is targeting <strong>about 500 GW by 2030</strong>, of renewable energy deployment, out of which ~<strong>280 GW is expected from solar PV</strong>. This necessitates the deployment of nearly <strong>30 GW of solar capacity every year until 2030.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Commitment: </strong>Solar power is a major prong of India’s commitment to address global warming according to the terms of the Paris Agreement, as well as achieving net zero, or no net carbon emissions, by 2070.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>International solar alliance and India’s pledge </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Climate action commitment</strong>: It symbolizes about the sincerity of the developing nations towards their concern about climate change and to switch to a low-carbon growth path.</li>
<li><strong>Clean energy</strong>: India’s pledge to the Paris summit offered to bring 40% of its electricity generation capacity from non-fossil sources (renewable, large hydro, and nuclear) by 2030.</li>
<li><strong>Global electrification</strong>: India has pledged to let solar energy reach to the most unconnected villages and communities and also towards creating a clean planet.</li>
<li><strong>Global cooperation</strong>: It is based on world cooperation irrespective of global boundaries.</li>
<li><strong>India’s Soft power</strong>: For India, possible additional benefits from the alliance can be a strengthening of ties with the major African countries and increasing goodwill for India among them.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Some Interesting facts</strong></h4>
<h4><strong style="font-family: NonBreakingSpaceOverride, 'Hoefler Text', Garamond, 'Times New Roman', serif; letter-spacing: normal; font-size: 21px;">Solar power is the most abundant energy source on earth.</strong></h4>
<h4><strong style="font-family: NonBreakingSpaceOverride, 'Hoefler Text', Garamond, 'Times New Roman', serif; letter-spacing: normal; font-size: 21px;">Solar is the cheapest source of energy in the world.</strong></h4>
<h4><strong style="font-family: NonBreakingSpaceOverride, 'Hoefler Text', Garamond, 'Times New Roman', serif; letter-spacing: normal; font-size: 21px;">Solar electricity has been around since 1839.</strong></h4>
<h4><strong style="font-family: NonBreakingSpaceOverride, 'Hoefler Text', Garamond, 'Times New Roman', serif; letter-spacing: normal; font-size: 21px;">Solar panels can produce power without direct sunlight.</strong></h4>
</blockquote>
<h4><strong>Challenges before solar future </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>High Imports</strong>: Indian solar deployment or installation companies depend heavily on imports. It currently imports 100% of silicon wafers and around 80% of cells even at the current deployment levels.</li>
<li><strong>Field deployment</strong>: Also, out of the 15 GW of module manufacturing capacity, only 3-4 GW of modules are technologically competitive and worthy of deployment in grid-based projects.</li>
<li><strong>Land issue</strong>: Land, the most expensive part of solar projects, is scarce in India — and Indian industry has no choice but to move towards newer and superior technologies as part of expansion plans.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of investment</strong>: India has hardly invested in this sector which can help the industry to try and test the technologies in a cost-effective manner.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Supportive policies and innovative technological approaches are needed for the sector to achieve its potential.</li>
<li>Indian policymakers need to plan for rooftop solar plus storage, rather than rooftop solar alone with the grid as storage (net / gross metering).</li>
<li>The declining cost of storage solutions, along with that of rooftop solar solutions, is likely to change the future of the Indian power sector.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the foreseeable future, one can witness a just and equitable energy order if solar energy, along with other forms of renewable energy, can be harnessed more positively.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q.</strong> <strong>Fossil fuels have a 60% share in India’s total energy mix in this context discuss solar future for India with challenges for the same.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/solar-energy-is-the-future/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Panch prans for better India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/panch-prans-for-better-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Challenges of future.</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>PM Modi’s Independence Day speech outlined agenda for a radical transformation of society and nation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are 5 resolves given by PM?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Take pride in India’s history.</li>
<li>The power of unity.</li>
<li>Duties of citizens, such as those of the PM and CMs.</li>
<li>Advance with greater conviction and the determination of a developed India.</li>
<li>Get rid of any signs of slavery.</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-623634" height="356" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 356px) 100vw, 356px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pm-300x300.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pm-300x300.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pm-150x150.jpeg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pm.jpeg 680w" width="356"/></p>
<h4><strong>Detail analysis 5 resolves of pm </strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1)First pran:</strong> The first pran is about inculcating a culture of <strong>thinking big and at scale</strong>.</p>
<ul>
<li>The first vow is for the country to move ahead with <strong>a big resolve</strong>. And that big resolution is of a <strong>developed India</strong>; and now we should not settle for anything less than that. <strong>Big resolution!</strong></li>
<li>Some examples include the world’s largest financial inclusion programme, the largest vaccination drive, the largest health insurance programme and the largest social security schemes.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2)Second pran:</strong> The second Pran is that in no part of our existence, not even in the deepest corners of our mind or habits <strong>should there be any ounce of slavery</strong>. It should be nipped there itself.</p>
<ul>
<li>Now, 100 per cent this slavery of hundreds of years has kept us bound, has forced us to keep our emotions tied up, have developed distorted thinking in us.</li>
<li>We have to liberate ourselves from the slavery mind set which is visible in innumerable things within and around us. This is our second Pran Shakti.</li>
</ul>
<p>(3)<strong>Third pran</strong>: The third Pran is that we should feel <strong>proud of our heritage and legacy.</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Since it is this same legacy which had given India its golden period in the past. And it is this legacy that has an innate capability of transforming itself with time.</li>
<li>It is this rich heritage that transcends tests of tide and times. It embraces the new. And hence we should be proud of this heritage.</li>
</ul>
<p>(4)<strong>Fourth pran</strong>: Fourth pran which is equally important is <strong>unity and solidarity</strong>.</p>
<ul>
<li>Amongst 130 million countrymen when there is harmony and bonhomie, unity becomes its strongest virtue.</li>
<li><strong>“Ek Bharat Shreshtha Bharat”</strong> – is one of the unifying initiatives to actuate the dream of the fourth Pran.</li>
</ul>
<p>(5)<strong>Fifth pran</strong>: Fifth Pran is <strong>the duty of the citizens</strong>, in which even the Prime Minister, Chief Minister cannot be an exclusion.</p>
<ul>
<li>As they are also responsible citizens and have a duty towards the nation. This virtue is going to be the vital life force if we want to achieve the dreams we have for the next 25 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges before India in next 25 years </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Skill development and employment for the future: </strong>workforce According to the World Economic Forum’s report “The Future of Jobs 2018”, more than half of Indian workers will require reskilling by 2022 to meet the talent demands of the future. They will each require an extra 100 days of learning, on average.</li>
<li><strong>Socioeconomic inclusion of rural India</strong>: By 2030, 40% of Indians will be urban residents. However, there will also be more than 5,000 small urban towns (50,000-100,000 persons each) and more than 50,000 developed rural towns (5,000-10,000 persons each) with similar income profiles, where aspirations are fast converging with those of urban India.</li>
<li><strong>A healthy and sustainable future:</strong> As India marches forward, it faces new challenges in health and sustainable living, even as it has achieved key health targets such as polio eradication.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The nation should now only be setting big goals. That big goal is a developed India and nothing less.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What are the challenges India will face in next 25 years? Discuss the panch pran resolves of PM showing how they will address these challenges.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/panch-prans-for-better-india/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Need of robust Justice delivery</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/need-of-robust-justice-delivery/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<h4><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-623638" height="284" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/justice.jpeg" width="419"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Over 6,000 Signatories Demand To Reverse Bilkis Bano Convicts’ Release.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Eleven convicts, sentenced to life imprisonment, released from Godhra sub-jail on August 15 after the Gujarat government allowed their release under its remission policy. They had completed more than 15 years in jail.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the issue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bilkis Bano was 21-years-old and five months pregnant when she was gang-raped while fleeing the violence that broke out after the Godhra train burning. Among those killed were her 3-year-old daughter.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is remission?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The duration of the sentence announced by the court can be cut short under special circumstances while the nature of the sentence remains the same, depending upon the nature of the crime.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Indian Judiciary: A Backgrounder</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Saviour of democracy</strong>: It speaks truth to political power, upholds the rights of citizens, mediates between Centre-state conflicts, provides justice to the rich and poor alike, and on several momentous occasions, saved democracy itself.</li>
<li><strong>Visible gaps:</strong> Despite its achievements, a gap between the ideal and reality has been becoming clear over the years.</li>
<li><strong>Slow in speed</strong>: The justice delivery is slow, the appointment of judges is mired in controversy, disciplinary mechanisms scarcely work, hierarchy rather than merit is preferred, women are severely under-represented, and constitutional matters often languish in the Supreme Court for years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What led to under-performance of Indian Judiciary?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Population explosion</li>
<li>Litigation explosion</li>
<li>Hasty and imperfect drafting of legislation</li>
<li>Plurality and accumulation of appeals (Multiple appeals for the same issue)</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges to the judicial system</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Lack of infrastructure of courts</li>
<li>High vacancy of judges in the district judiciary</li>
<li>Pendency of Cases</li>
<li>Ineffective planning in the functioning of the courts</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Judicial initiative </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The CJI has pitched to set up <strong>a National Judicial Infrastructure Corporation (NJIC)</strong> to develop judicial infrastructure in trial courts.</li>
<li>He indicated a substantial gap in infrastructure and availability of basic amenities in the lower judiciary.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Enrich your mains answer with this</strong></h4>
<h4>Finland’s criminal justice system was voted the world’s best.</h4>
<ul>
<li>Under the Constitution of Finland, everyone is entitled to have their case heard by a court or an authority appropriately and without undue delay. This is achieved through the judicial system of Finland.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<h4><strong>Dynamic suggestions </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Creating NJIC</strong>: It will bring a revolutionary change in the judicial functioning provided the proposed body is given financial and executive powers to operate independently of the Union and the State governments.</li>
<li><strong>Appointment reforms</strong>: There are many experts who advocate the need to appoint more judges with unquestionable transparency in such appointments.</li>
<li><strong>Creating All Indian Judiciary Services</strong>: It would be a landmark move to create a pan-India Service that would result in a wide pool of qualified and committed judges entering the system.</li>
<li><strong>Technology infusion</strong>: The ethical and responsible use of AI and ML for the advancement of efficiency-enhancing can be increasingly embedded in legal and judicial processes. Ex. SUPACE.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is time for courts to wake up from their colonial stupor and face the practical realities of Indian society.</li>
<li>Rules and procedures of justice delivery should be made simple.</li>
<li>The ordinary, poor, and rural Indian should not be scared of judges or the courts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s capacity to deliver justice has serious deficits with under-capacity and gender imbalance plaguing police, prisons and the judiciary and fund crunch affecting state services like free-legal aid. So there is urgent need of <strong>National Judicial Infrastructure Authority</strong>for the standardization and improvement of judicial infrastructure and robust justice delivery.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Do you think there are serious gaps in our judicial infrastructure and justice delivery? Identify these gaps and provide some dynamic suggestions from your end in the context of Bilkis Bano verdict. </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/need-of-robust-justice-delivery/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Species in news: Tasmanian Tiger</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/species-in-news-tasmanian-tiger/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Tasmanian Tiger</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-623646" height="220" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tas-300x220.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tas-300x220.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tas.jpg 607w" width="300"/></p>
<p>Scientists in the US and Australia have embarked on a $15-million project to resurrect the thylacine or Tasmanian Tiger, a marsupial that went extinct in the 1930s, using gene-editing technology.</p>
<h4>Tasmanian Tiger</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Tasmanian tiger or thylacine (a dog-headed pouched dog) was an exclusively carnivorous marsupial that is considered to be extinct.</li>
<li>It has a resemblance to a dog, with its distinguishing features being the dark stripes beginning at the rear of its body and extending into its tail, its stiff tail and abdominal pouch.</li>
<li>The last known thylacine died in captivity over 80 years ago, in Tasmania’s Hobart Zoo in 1936.</li>
<li>It may also be the only mammal to have become extinct in Tasmania since the European settlement.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did they become extinct?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It was confined to Tasmania in recent times and disappeared from mainland Australia over 2000 years ago, mainly because of over-hunting by humans, diseases and competition from the Dingo (Canis lupus), a wild dog native to Australia.</li>
<li>The Thylacine was also persecuted because it was believed to be a threat to sheep and in its latter years it was hunted for the purposes of collection by museums and zoos.</li>
<li>As per some accounts, the introduction of sheep in 1824 led to a conflict between the settlers and thylacine.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ambitious project aims to reintroduce the animal to its native place Tasmania to revive the region’s lost ecological balance.</li>
<li>Interestingly, this is not the first attempt to revive thylacines.</li>
<li>In 1999, an Australian scientist, Dr Michael Archer, embarked on an unsuccessful journey to resurrect the animal using cloning technology from a perfectly preserved specimen in a museum.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The resurrection process</h4>
<ul>
<li>Even though the last living thylacine died over 86 years ago, many embryos and young specimens of the species have been preserved.</li>
<li>Scientists will be using a genome sequenced from a DNA extracted from a 108-year-old specimen held at Australia’s Victoria Museum.</li>
<li>This genome will be compared with the closest living animal of the species– the fat tailed dunnart — to identify all the differences.</li>
<li>Once all the differences are identified, scientists will engineer the living cell’s DNA where it is different, essentially engineering the extinct species back.</li>
<li>The fat-tailed dunnart is a mouse-like species in the Dasyuridae family in Australia. With an average body length of 2.4–3.5 inches, they are one of the smallest carnivorous marsupials.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Criticisms of the move</h4>
<ul>
<li>Researchers have raised concerns about the practicality of the technology.</li>
<li>De-extinction is a fairytale science a/c to them and is more about media attention for the scientists and less about doing serious science.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: De-extinction technology</h4>
<ul>
<li>De-extinction, or resurrection biology, is the method of creating a species that went extinct or is endangered, in order to revitalise ecological diversity and balance shattered due to reasons ranging from biodiversity loss to climate change.</li>
<li>While cloning is the most widely used method of de-extinction, genome editing and selective breeding are also considered effective ways.</li>
<li>The Pyrenean ibex, a subspecies of Spanish ibex, was one of the first extinct animals that have been resurrected using somatic cell nuclear transfer (SCNT).</li>
<li>However, the baby Ibex died minutes after its birth from lung defect.</li>
<li>One of the challenges of de-extinction is that reintroducing the species to its former habitat may make it an invasive species, which will also impact the balance of the current ecological system.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/species-in-news-tasmanian-tiger/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was Lord Curzon, the Viceroy of India who partitioned Bengal in 1905?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-lord-curzon-the-viceroy-of-india-who-partitioned-bengal-in-1905/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Partition of Bengal, Lord Curzon</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Partition of Bengal and its aftermath</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-623644" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 194px) 100vw, 194px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/curz-194x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/curz-194x300.jpg 194w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/curz.jpg 224w" width="194"/></p>
<p>The 119-year-old Curzon Gate in Bardhaman in West Bengal is at the centre of a political row.</p>
<h4>Who was Lord Curzon?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Born in 1859, Curzon was a British conservative politician who was educated at the elite institutions of Eton and Oxford.</li>
<li>He served as Under-Secretary of State for India (1891-1892), and for Foreign Affairs (1895-1898), before being appointed Viceroy of India in 1899.</li>
<li>As viceroy, his administration was known for intense activity and emphasis on efficiency.</li>
<li>He stated in his budget speech in 1904, “Efficiency of administration is, in my view, a synonym for the contentment of the governed”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Rise to infame</h4>
<ul>
<li>Of all the Viceroys of India, Curzon is possibly the most criticised — he is the man who partitioned Bengal in 1905, and triggered a wave of Bengali nationalism that contributed to the wider Indian national movement.</li>
<li>He was also one of the more openly imperialist of viceroys, and a man who saw Britain’s rule over India as critical to the survival of empire.</li>
<li>In 1900, Curzon famously stated, “We could lose all our [white settlement] dominions and still survive, but if we lost India, our sun would sink to its setting.”</li>
</ul>
<h4>His works</h4>
<ul>
<li>Curzon created a separate Muslim majority province of the North-West Frontier Province, sent a British expedition to Tibet and established a separate police service.</li>
<li>He was instrumental in establishing the Archaeological Survey of India, in order to study and protect historical monuments.</li>
<li>Early on in his career, Curzon earned some praise from his colonial subjects for taking action against Europeans in a number of high-profile racist attacks against Indians.</li>
<li>In 1899, he punished white soldiers for raping a woman in Rangoon; he disciplined soldiers of the 9th Lancers for beating an Indian cook in Sialkot to death in 1902.</li>
<li>He had tried unsuccessfully to get the Calcutta High Court to change the meagre punishment given to an Assam tea manager for murdering a “coolie”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why was he disliked then?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Curzon was both vexed and enraged by the growing nationalist movement in India and he sought to throttle the growing aspirations of the educated Indian middle class.</li>
<li>A staunch imperialist, he took a series of extremely unpopular measures, including passing, in 1899, the Calcutta Municipal Amendment Act.</li>
<li>He reduced the number of elected representatives in the Calcutta Corporation.</li>
<li>Among others was the Indian Universities Act (1904), that placed Calcutta University under government control, and the Indian Official Secrets Amendment Act (1904) which reduced the freedom of the press even further.</li>
<li>Ironically though, it was his biggest and most reviled decision — to partition Bengal in 1905 — that led to a spurt in nationalist sentiment and revitalized the Congress.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How and why did the partition of Bengal take place?</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-623647" height="229" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/partn-300x229.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/partn-300x229.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/partn.jpg 596w" width="300"/></p>
<ul>
<li>Calcutta was the capital of the British Raj, and Bengal Presidency was one of the largest provinces in India, populated by more than 78 million people.</li>
<li>It was such a huge province encompassing present-day West Bengal, Bangladesh, Bihar, parts of Chhattisgarh, Odisha, and Assam.</li>
<li>For long, the British had maintained that Bengal was too large to efficiently manage and administer; it was also believed that with Calcutta as the nerve centre of the educated nationalists, the resistance to colonial rule would only increase.</li>
<li>Home Secretary H H Risley noted in 1904, “Bengal united is a power; Bengal divided will pull in several different ways.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Actual course of Partition</h4>
<ul>
<li>In July 1905, Curzon announced the partition of Bengal into two provinces.</li>
<li>East Bengal and Assam, with a population of 38 million, was predominately Muslim, while the western province, called Bengal, and was reduced to 55 million people, primarily Hindus.</li>
<li>Protests began almost immediately after the announcement, with meetings taking place in more than 300 cities, towns, and villages across Bengal.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What were the consequences of the partition?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In opposition to the partition, nationalist leaders organized a campaign <strong><u>a boycott British goods and institutions</u></strong> and encouraged the use of local products.</li>
<li>After a <strong><u>formal resolution</u></strong> was passed at a meeting in Calcutta in August 1905, the Swadeshi movement began.</li>
<li>Students were at the forefront of the movement, which was characterized by <strong><u>boycotts of British educational institutions and law courts</u></strong>, and large bonfires of imported cotton textiles.</li>
<li>There was a surge in nationalist rhetoric, and the <strong><u>song ‘Bande Mataram’</u></strong>, set to music by Rabindranath Tagore, became the informal anthem of the movement.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Swadeshi movement and boycott</u></strong> was not restricted to Bengal, and spread to other parts of the country, including Punjab, Maharashtra, and parts of the Madras Presidency.</li>
<li>A number of <strong><u>secret societies</u></strong>, such as the <strong><u>Anushilan Samiti of Bengal</u></strong>, sought to overthrow British rule through violent means.</li>
<li>Revolutionary groups used bombs, attempted to assassinate colonial officials, and engaged in armed robberies to finance their activities.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(Irreversible) Revocation of the Partition</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 1905, Curzon resigned and returned to England after losing a power struggle with the commander-in-chief of the British Army, Lord Kitchener.</li>
<li>The protests continued after his exit, and the colonial government in 1911 announced the reunification of Bengal.</li>
<li>Thenceforth the capital of the Raj was shifted from Calcutta to Delhi.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-lord-curzon-the-viceroy-of-india-who-partitioned-bengal-in-1905/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian team deliberating on Ocean Diversity Pact</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-team-deliberating-on-ocean-diversity-pact/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UNCLOS</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>High seas regulation</p></div></div><p>A delegation from India and other member countries of the UN are in New York to deliberate on a one-of-its-kind agreement to conserve marine biodiversity in the high seas, namely the oceans that extend beyond countries’ territorial waters.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The agreement follows a resolution by the UN General Assembly.</li>
<li>The pact is expected to be the final in a series set in motion since 2018 to draft an international legally binding instrument under the 1982 United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea (UNCLOS).</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why need Ocean Diversity Pact?</h4>
<h4>(1) Deciding on rights of explorers</h4>
<ul>
<li>A key aspect of the agreement is <strong><u>deciding on the rights of companies </u></strong>that undertake exploration<strong> <u>for biological resources in the high seas. </u></strong></li>
<li>It is under discussion if companies have <strong><u>absolute rights</u></strong> on any discovery or extraction in these regions <strong><u>or should they share their gains</u></strong>, in terms of intellectual property and royalties with an UN-prescribed body.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(2) Regulation for exotic items</h4>
<ul>
<li>The focus of mining activity in the sea has been for <strong><u>gas hydrates, precious metals and other fossil fuel</u></strong></li>
<li>However, with advances in biotechnology and genetic engineering, several companies see potential in exotic microbes and other organisms — several of them undiscovered — that abide in the deep ocean and could be used for drugs and vaccines.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(3) ‘Blue Economy’ policy of India</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Union Cabinet approved a ‘<strong><u>Blue Economy’ policy for India</u></strong>, a nearly ₹4,000-crore programme spread over five years.</li>
<li>This among other things will develop a manned submersible vessel as well as work on bio-prospecting of deep-sea flora and fauna including microbes.</li>
<li>Studies on sustainable utilisation of deep sea bio-resources will be the main focus.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is UNCLOS?</h4>
<ul>
<li>UNCLOS is sometimes referred to as the Law of the Sea Convention or the Law of the Sea treaty.</li>
<li>It came into operation and became effective from 16th November 1982.</li>
<li>It defines the rights and responsibilities of nations with respect to their use of the world’s oceans, establishing guidelines for businesses, the environment, and the management of marine natural resources.</li>
<li>It has created three new institutions on the international scene :</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>International Tribunal for the Law of the Sea,</li>
<li>International Seabed Authority</li>
<li>Commission on the Limits of the Continental Shelf</li>
</ol>
<blockquote><p><strong>Note:</strong> UNCLOS does not deal with matters of territorial disputes or to resolve issues of sovereignty, as that field is governed by rules of customary international law on the acquisition and loss of territory.</p></blockquote>
<p><strong>Major conventions:</strong></p>
<p>There had been three major conferences of UNCLOS:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>UNCLOS I:</strong> It resulted in the successful implementation of various conventions regarding Territorial Sea and Contiguous Zones, Continental Shelf, High Seas, Fishing Rights.</li>
<li><strong>UNCLOS II:</strong> No agreement was reached over breadth of territorial waters.</li>
<li><strong>UNCLOS III:</strong> It introduced a number of provisions. The most significant issues covered were setting limits, navigation, archipelagic status and transit regimes, exclusive economic zones (EEZs), continental shelf jurisdiction, deep seabed mining, the exploitation regime, protection of the marine environment, scientific research, and settlement of disputes.</li>
</ol>
<p>The convention set the limit of various areas, measured from a carefully defined baseline.</p>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-500460" height="262" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 595px) 100vw, 595px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/unclos-300x132.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/unclos-300x132.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/unclos-768x339.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/unclos.jpg 850w" width="595"/></p>
<p>These terminologies are as follows:</p>
<p><strong>(1) Baseline</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The convention set the limit of various areas, measured from a carefully defined baseline.</li>
<li>Normally, a sea baseline follows the low-water line, but when the coastline is deeply indented, has fringing islands or is highly unstable, straight baselines may be used.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Internal waters</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>It covers all water and waterways on the landward side of the baseline.</li>
<li>The coastal state is free to set laws, regulate use, and use any resource. Foreign vessels have no right of passage within internal waters.</li>
<li>A vessel in the high seas assumes jurisdiction under the internal laws of its flag State.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Territorial waters</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Out to 12 nautical miles (22 km, 14 miles) from the baseline, the coastal state is free to set laws, regulate use, and use any resource.</li>
<li>Vessels were given the <strong>Right of Innocent Passage</strong> through any territorial waters.</li>
<li>“Innocent passage” is defined by the convention as passing through waters in an expeditious and continuous manner, which is not “prejudicial to the peace, good order or the security” of the coastal state.</li>
<li>Fishing, polluting, weapons practice, and spying are not “innocent”, and submarines and other underwater vehicles are required to navigate on the surface and to show their flag.</li>
<li>Nations can also temporarily suspend innocent passage in specific areas of their territorial seas, if doing so is essential for the protection of their security.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Archipelagic waters</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The convention set the definition of “Archipelagic States”, which also defines how the state can draw its territorial borders.</li>
<li>All waters inside this baseline are designated “Archipelagic Waters”.</li>
<li>The state has sovereignty over these waters mostly to the extent it has over internal waters, but subject to existing rights including traditional fishing rights of immediately adjacent states.</li>
<li>Foreign vessels have right of innocent passage through archipelagic waters, but archipelagic states may limit innocent passage to designated sea lanes.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Contiguous zone</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Beyond the 12-nautical-mile (22 km) limit, there is a further 12 nautical miles (22 km) from the territorial sea baseline limit, the contiguous zone.</li>
<li>Here a state can continue to enforce laws in four specific areas (customs, taxation, immigration, and pollution) if the infringement started or is about to occur within the state’s territory or territorial waters.</li>
<li>This makes the contiguous zone a hot pursuit area.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Exclusive economic zones (EEZs)</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>These extend 200 nm from the baseline.</li>
<li>Within this area, the coastal nation has sole exploitation rights over all natural resources.</li>
<li>In casual use, the term may include the territorial sea and even the continental shelf.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(7) Continental shelf</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The continental shelf is defined as the natural prolongation of the land territory to the continental margin’s outer edge, or 200 nautical miles (370 km) from the coastal state’s baseline, whichever is greater.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India and UNCLOS</h4>
<ul>
<li>As a State party to the UNCLOS, India promoted utmost respect for the UNCLOS, which established the international legal order of the seas and oceans.</li>
<li>India also supported freedom of navigation and overflight, and unimpeded commerce based on the principles of international law, reflected notably in the UNCLOS 1982.</li>
<li>India is committed to safeguarding maritime interests and strengthening security in the Indian Ocean Region (IOR) to ensure a favorable and positive maritime environment.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-team-deliberating-on-ocean-diversity-pact/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Historical and cultural connections between India and Thailand</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/historical-and-cultural-connections-between-india-and-thailand/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Read the attached story</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India- SE Asia Cultural Linkages</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-623645" height="206" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/eamj-300x206.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/eamj-300x206.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/eamj.jpg 595w" width="300"/></p>
<p>As part of his visit to Thailand for the ninth India-Thailand joint commission meeting, External Affairs Minister S. Jaishankar visited a temple in Bangkok.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The temple is the Royal Brahmin Office of the Thai Royal Court and is the official centre of Hinduism in Thailand.</li>
<li>It highlights the long history of cultural contacts between India and Thailand.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Making of ‘Greater India’ in Southeast Asia</h4>
<ul>
<li>India and the Southeast Asia region share a long history of cultural and commercial relations.</li>
<li>The classical Sanskrit and Pali texts from India carry references of the region using various names such as <strong><u>Kathakosha</u></strong>, <strong><u>Suvarnabhumi (the land of god)</u></strong> or <strong><u>Suvarnadvipa (the golden island)</u></strong>, indicating that this was a region that attracted Indian merchants.</li>
<li>Trade in spices, aromatic wood and most importantly gold is known to have flourished.</li>
<li>In more recent times, European and Indian scholars have referred to <strong><u>Southeast Asia as ‘Farther India’, ‘Greater India’, or ‘Hinduised or Indianized states’.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>What one mean by ‘Farther India’?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The first person to do an in-depth study of the process of ‘Indianisation’ in Southeast Asian countries was a <strong><u>French scholar named George Coedes</u></strong>.</li>
<li>He coined the term ‘Farther India’ to refer to those states that experienced “<strong><u>the civilizing activity of India’</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Geographically, it refers to <strong><u>Vietnam, Cambodia, Laos, Thailand, Myanmar and the Malay states</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Sanskrit, Buddhist, and Jain <strong><u>texts indicate that interactions between the two regions</u></strong> go back more than two thousand years ago, mainly through sea voyages and that trade played an important role.</li>
<li>They were also accompanied by <strong><u>Brahmin priests</u></strong>, <strong><u>Buddhist monks</u></strong>, scholars and adventurers and all of them played an important role in the transmission of Indian culture to the natives of Southeast Asia.</li>
<li>Some of the <strong><u>merchants and Brahmin priests</u></strong> married the local girls and were often employed by the local rulers.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Limitations to Indian influence</h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian expansion into Southeast Asia <strong><u>cannot be compared to European colonization</u></strong> since Indians were not complete strangers to the population of Southeast Asia and had pre-existing trade relations.</li>
<li>In the early 20th century, the nationalist historians of India frequently referred to the ancient Indian kingdoms in Southeast Asia as its ‘colony’.</li>
<li>Historian RC Majumdar noted that the Hindu colonists brought with them the whole framework of their culture and civilization.</li>
<li>This was transplanted in its entirety among the people who had not emerged from their primitive barbarism.</li>
<li>More recently the colonization theory has been rejected on the ground that there is very little evidence of conquest or direct political influence in the ancient Southeast Asian kingdoms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Visible cultural influence</h4>
<ul>
<li>The first Indian kingdom to come up in <strong><u>Southeast Asia was Funan</u></strong>, which is the predecessor of modern Cambodia and Lin-yi in southern Vietnam, both of which came up in the second century CE.</li>
<li>Contemporary Southeast Asian society <strong><u>carries several pieces of evidence</u></strong> of the cultural impact of these interactions.</li>
<li>Many <strong><u>local languages</u></strong> in the region, including Thai, Malay, and Javanese contain words of Sanskrit, Pali and <strong><u>Dravidian origin</u></strong> in significant proportions.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Thai language</u></strong> is written in script derived from <strong><u>Southern Indian Pallava alphabet</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Perhaps the most important influence of India on Southeast Asia was in the field of religion and how <strong><u>Shivaism, Vaishnavism, Theravada Buddhism, Mahayana Buddhism and later Sinhalese Buddhism</u></strong> came to be practised in the region.</li>
<li>The political and administrative institutions and ideas, especially the con<strong><u>cept of divine authority and kingship</u></strong>, are largely shaped by the Indian practices.</li>
<li>For example, the Thai <strong><u>king is considered as an incarnation of Vishnu</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>episodes of Ramayana and Mahabharata</u></strong> are regularly featured in <strong><u>puppet shows</u></strong> and theatre events.</li>
<li>In terms of architecture, monuments like <strong><u>Borobodur Stupa in Java</u></strong>, the <strong><u>Angkor Vat temple in Cambodia</u></strong>, <strong><u>My Son temple in Vietnam</u></strong> are some of the best examples of Indian influence in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s religious links to Thailand</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the early centuries of the <strong><u>Common Era, Thailand</u></strong>, which was historically known as <strong><em><u>Siam</u></em></strong>, was under the rule of the Funan Empire.</li>
<li>Following the decline of the Funan Empire in the sixth century CE, it was under the <strong><u>rule of the Buddhist kingdom of Dvaravati. </u></strong></li>
<li>In the 10th century, the region came under <strong><u>Khmer rule</u></strong>, which is also known to have <strong><u>links with India</u></strong>.</li>
<li>A <strong><u>Tamil inscription found in Takua-pa</u></strong> testifies to trade links between the Pallava region of South India and southern Thailand.</li>
<li>A mercantile corporation of South Indians called <strong><u>Manikarramam</u></strong> had established a settlement here and built its own temple and tank, and lived as a <strong><u>‘self-contained’ colony</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It is important to note that <strong><u>Brahmanism and Buddhism existed alongside</u></strong> each other in Thailand in the pre-Sukhothai period of the 13th century.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Cult of Rama</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Ramayana known in Thailand as <strong><u>Ramakriti (the glory of Rama) or Ramakien (the account of Rama)</u></strong> — has provided an outlet of cultural expression in Thailand for both the elite and the common man.</li>
<li>Episodes from the epic are painted on the walls of Buddhist temples and enacted in dramas and ballets.</li>
<li>Although <strong><u>there is no archaeological evidence of the story of Rama in Thailand</u></strong>, certain towns in the country have legends related to Rama’s life connected with them.</li>
<li>For instance, <strong><u>Ayutthaya in Central Thailand</u></strong>, which emerged in the 10th century CE, is <strong><u>derived from Ayodhya</u></strong>, birthplace of Lord Rama.</li>
<li>Desai writes that “<strong><u>from the 13th century onwards, several Thai kings assumed the title Rama</u></strong>, which has become hereditary during the present dynasty.”</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/historical-and-cultural-connections-between-india-and-thailand/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>