<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 20:11:37 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Nord Stream Pipeline to remain shut</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nord-stream-pipeline-to-stay-shut/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nord Stream Pipelines</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economic impact of Russian invasion</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-597151" height="295" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 443px) 100vw, 443px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nord-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nord-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nord-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/07/nord.jpg 770w" width="443"/></p>
<p>Russian has said that it can‘t resume the supply of natural gas through a key pipeline to Germany for now because of what it said was a need for urgent maintenance work.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There are growing concerns in European countries that Russia would shut down its gas supplies in retaliation against the current sanctions against Moscow.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Nord Stream 1?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is a system of offshore natural gas pipelines running under the Baltic Sea from Russia to Germany.</li>
<li>Nord Stream 1 is a 1,224 km underwater gas pipeline that runs from Vyborg in northwest Russia to Lubmin in northeastern Germany via the Baltic Sea.</li>
<li>Two further pipelines under construction running from Ust-Luga to Lubmin termed Nord Stream 2.</li>
<li>Majority owned by the Russian energy giant Gazprom, the pipeline is the primary route through which its gas enters Germany.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Worry for Europe</h4>
<ul>
<li>There have been growing concerns that there could be further restrictions to European gas supplies.</li>
<li>European countries rely on Russian energy for their cold winters.</li>
<li>But now they believe that Russia could weaponized their dependency as a response to their sanction due to the conflict in Ukraine.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are Europe’s alternative sources of energy?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As an alternative source for energy, European countries have increasingly turned towards the US, from whom they purchase liquified natural gas (LNG) that comes via ships.</li>
<li>Since ship-delivered gas ends up being far more expensive, there are also attempts to get non-Russian pipeline gas from Norway and Azerbaijan.</li>
<li>While EU countries were earlier seeking to phase out fossil fuels and emphasize renewable forms of energy, many are now returning to coal to deal with the energy crisis.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nord-stream-pipeline-to-stay-shut/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What causes Rainbow Clouds (Cloud Iridescence)?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-causes-rainbow-clouds-cloud-iridescence/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Cloud iridescence</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-630169" height="299" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 399px) 100vw, 399px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-1200x900.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloud-1980x1485.jpg 1980w" width="399"/></strong></p>
<p>Last week, pictures of an unusually-shaped rainbow cloud that appeared over China were widely shared on social media.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The cloud in question resembles a pileus cloud.</li>
<li>Such phenomenon of bright colours appearing on a cloud is called cloud iridescence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Pileus Cloud? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A pileus cloud is usually formed over a <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/water-in-the-atmosphere/"><strong>cumulus or cumulonimbus cloud</strong></a>.</li>
<li>It is formed when the base cloud pushes a moist current of air upwards and the water vapour from the current condenses to somewhat resemble wave-like crests, or umbrellas.</li>
<li>In popular western culture, it is called as an “accessory cloud” that is “rather like a cloud haircut”.</li>
<li>A pileus cloud is transient in nature and <strong><u>lasts barely for a few minutes</u></strong>, making it difficult, and at the same time, exciting, to spot.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is cloud iridescence? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cloud iridescence or Irisation is an optical phenomenon that mostly occurs in wave-like clouds, including pileus and Altocumulus lenticularis.</li>
<li>Iridescence in clouds means the appearance of colours on clouds, which can either be in the form of parallel bands like in a rainbow, or mingled in patches.</li>
<li>In ancient Greek mythology, Iris is the goddess of rainbow. “Irisation”, the phenomenon of rainbow-like colours in clouds, is derived from her name.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a photometeor? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Iridescence of clouds is a photometeor.</li>
<li>It is an optical phenomenon produced by the reflection, refraction, diffraction or interference of sunlight.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What causes cloud iridescence? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In pileus clouds, <strong><u>small water droplets or ice crystals</u></strong>, usually of a similar size, <strong><u>diffract the sunlight</u></strong> falling on them.</li>
<li>The thinness of the cloud ensures more exposure to sunlight for each water droplet or ice crystal.</li>
<li>To ensure its wave crest-like appearance, water droplets or ice crystals in these clouds are always moving – droplets form at one side of the cloud and evaporate from the other end – and hence these clouds remain small and thin since the droplets have no way of combining and growing in size.</li>
<li>In its International Cloud Atlas, the World Meteorological Organisation says that iridescence or Irisation is caused by diffraction within 10 degrees from the sun.</li>
<li>Beyond ten degrees and up till about 40 degrees, interference of light is the main cause of iridescence.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-causes-rainbow-clouds-cloud-iridescence/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India to host Quad officials’ meet</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-to-host-quad-officials-meet/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>QUAD</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>New Delhi will host an official-level meeting of the Quad grouping with the US, Japan and Australia next week, the first such “senior officers meeting” (SOM) to be held since the recent escalation of tensions over the Taiwan Strait.</p>
<h4>Quadrilateral Security Dialogue: A Backgrounder</h4>
<p>Quadrilateral Security Dialogue or the Quad is an informal strategic forum between the United States, Japan, India and Australia that is maintained by semi-regular summits, information exchanges and military drills between member countries.</p>
<ul>
<li>The US, Japan, India and Australia came together in the aftermath of the 2004 Indian Ocean tsunami to assist the devastated countries.</li>
<li>Later, officials of the four countries met in 2007 “to look at issues of common interest.” During an India visit, then Japanese PM Shinzo Abe unveiled the idea of “the Confluence of the Two Seas” that gave birth to the concept of the Indo-Pacific.</li>
<li>A decade later officials of the four countries met in the Philippines in 2017 to talk about an aggressively rising China.</li>
<li>In 2019, the foreign ministers of the Quad countries met in Washington for the first time.</li>
<li>In November, the Quad nations came together to participate in a two-phase joint military exercise, Malabar 2020, in the Bay of Bengal and in the Arabian Sea.</li>
</ul>
<p>Now it is increasingly viewed as ‘Asian NATO’.</p>
<h4>Focus on Indo-Pacific: For the China-wary world</h4>
<ul>
<li>The latest meeting of Quad comes at a time when all four countries have either trade or security disputes with China.</li>
<li>Despite not explicitly mentioning China, Quad has been openly supporting a “free and fair” Indo-Pacific which is seen as a clear message to Beijing that it needs to curb its assertive behaviour.</li>
<li>The optics were hard to miss when India, the US, Japan and Australia joined their navies for the mega Malabar military exercise late last year, an activity which raised alarm in Beijing.</li>
<li>This posturing by the Quad nations sent a strong signal to China.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(1) US vs China</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>USA had followed a policy to contain China’s increasing influence in East Asia. Therefore, USA sees the coalition as an opportunity to regain its influence in the Indo-Pacific region.</li>
<li>The US has described China, along with Russia, as a strategic rival in its National Security Strategy, National Defence Strategy and the Pentagon’s report on Indo-Pacific Strategy.</li>
<li>Both are navigating intense disagreements over trade and human rights in Tibet, Hong Kong and the western Xinjiang region, as well as the coronavirus pandemic and increasing Chinese assertiveness in the South China Sea.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Australia vs China</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Australia is concerned about China’s growing interest in its land, infrastructure and politics, and influence on its universities.</li>
<li>Ties have been on a downward spiral since 2018 when Australia, accusing China of meddling in its domestic affairs, passed a new law against foreign interference and espionage.</li>
<li>It also barred Huawei from building the country’s 5G mobile network, among the first countries to do so, citing national security.</li>
<li> The atmosphere worsened when  PM Scott Morrison’s government called for an international inquiry into the origins of the coronavirus that causes Covid-19.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Japan vs. China</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Tensions between Japan and China over the Senkaku/Diaoyu Islands dispute have recently increased.</li>
<li>China has relentlessly continued attempts to unilaterally change the status quo by coercion in the sea area around the Senkaku Islands.</li>
<li>The more salient indicator is the number of Chinese patrols inside the territorial sea of the islands, which Japan sees as an explicit violation of its territorial sovereignty.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) India vs. Quad</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India’s strained relations with China needs no explanation. The year long border dispute is the testimony.</li>
<li>The Quad summit is taking place in the backdrop of an ongoing military disengagement between India and China following their months-long border standoff in eastern Ladakh.</li>
<li>China is increasing its footprint in our neighborhood through its Belt and Road policy and political coercion following the debt trap are some of the increasing concerns other than economic imbalance.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Opportunities unveiled for India</h4>
<p>India’s engagement with the Quad goes back to China’s expanding footprint in South Asia and the Indian Ocean Region over the last few years. India can reap some benefits as discussed below:</p>
<p><strong> (1) Checkmating the Chinese</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The maritime sphere is wide open to India to undertake coalition building, rule sets, and other forms of strategic exploration than compared to land borders.</li>
<li>The maritime space is more important to China than engaging in land grab attempts in the Himalayas. A huge chunk of Chinese trade happens via the Indian oceanic routes that pass through maritime chokepoints.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Channelizing geo-politics</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is a growing great power interest in the maritime sphere, especially with the arrival of the concept of ‘Indo-Pacific’. For instance, many European countries have recently released their Indo-Pacific strategies.</li>
<li>The most recent was for France to send its warship in the international waters of the South China Sea.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Maritime domain for India</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Above is the backdrop against which one must see the progressive evolution of Exercise “Malabar”,</li>
<li>In the beginning, it was a bilateral event involving just the Indian and US navies. It became tri-lateral with the inclusion of Japan in 2015.</li>
<li>And now it has transformed into a four-cornered naval drill that will also include Australia.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Check on China’s India Ocean Ambitions</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Quad has a valuable role to play as a check on China’s Indian Ocean ambitions.</li>
<li>India must develop ingrained habits of interoperable cooperation with its Quad partners.</li>
<li>This interoperable cooperation could pre-emptively dissuade China from mounting a naval challenge in its backyard.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Eccentricity in South Asia</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>With India, located right at the centre of the Indo-Pacific geopolitical imagination can realize the vision of a ‘broader Asia’ that can extend its influence away from geographical boundaries.</li>
<li>Further, India with Quad countries can check the imperialist policies of China in the Indian Ocean region and ensure Security and growth for all in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with Quad</h4>
<p><strong>(1) Structural problems</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Quad has a core structural problem as its objective pivots around the U.S.</li>
<li>The Quad riles China as a hostile grouping, but hardly serves the security interests of its members.</li>
<li>Despite rhetoric relating to the promotion of a ‘rules-based’ world order, the Quad neither shares a strategic vision nor is it animated by a shared agenda.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> (2) Nature of alliance</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Alliances involve written commitments to come to the defence of the other against a third party.</li>
<li>Despite the potential for cooperation, the Quad remains a mechanism without a defined strategic mission.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Economic alliance not feasible</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Quad is neither a military alliance nor an economic partnership.</li>
<li>Its intention to counter China in the rare-earth sector is logical given the dominant role the country plays in supplying more than half of the world’s such key materials.</li>
<li>But, for a country like India, the lack of relevant technologies and talent pool could obstruct its progress in building up a supply chain from scratch.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> (4) Overt emphasis on Maritime domain</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The entire focus on the Indo-Pacific makes the Quad a maritime, rather than a land-based grouping, raising questions whether the cooperation extends to the Asia-Pacific and Eurasian regions.</li>
<li>India’s core concerns with China are primarily undemarcated borders and trade deficit.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> (5) Lack of existence of Indo-Pacific system</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There has never been Indo-Pacific system ever since the rise of the port-based kingdoms of Indochina in the first half of the second millennium.</li>
<li>There were two Asian systems — an Indian Ocean system and an East Asian system — with intricate sub-regional balances.</li>
<li>The effort by a U.S. to artificially manufacture to combine the Indo and the Pacific into a unitary system is unlikely to succeed.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Indian borders can go more vulnerable</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>A lesson for India is China’s long-held and strategic interest in parts of Jammu and Kashmir.</li>
<li>It is wrongly argued that it is Pakistan that is the issue in J&amp;K.</li>
<li>China undoubtedly is as big an issue but has quietly hidden behind Pakistan’s cover.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Challenges: China will retaliate</h4>
<p><strong>(1) China’s assertiveness</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>China claims that it has historical ownership over nearly the entire region of South China Sea, which gives it the right to manufacture islands.</li>
<li>However, the International Court of Arbitration rejected the claim in 2016.</li>
<li>Since then, the incidences of Chinese transgression has only increased making China more assertive for its interest.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Preying small nations</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The ASEAN countries have a well-knit relationship with China. So are other SAARC countries have fallen prey to Chinese debt traps.</li>
<li>The Regional Cooperation Economic Partnership (RCEP) is a recent example of China’s increasing influence over ASEAN nations to which Australia is even a forerunner.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Chinese monopoly</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Considering the economic might of China and the dependence of Quad nations like Japan and Australia on China, the Quad nations cannot afford to have strained relations with it in the long run.</li>
<li>India too, is still very heavily dependent on Chinese exports.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way Forward</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Need for a clearer vision:</strong> It is important for members of the Quad not to be reactive. It is also important to exhibit openness, and ensure that all talk of a ‘Free and Open Indo-Pacific’ is more than just a mere slogan.</li>
<li><strong>Consensus for a common objective:</strong> The Quad nations need to better explain the Indo-Pacific Vision in an overarching framework with the objective of advancing everyone’s economic and security interests.</li>
<li><strong>Setting an agenda:</strong> This will reassure the littoral States that the Quad will be a factor for regional benefit, and a far cry from Chinese allegations that it is some sort of a military alliance. Future meetings can be an opportunity to define the idea and chart a future path.</li>
<li><strong>Expanding Quad:</strong> India has many other partners in the Indo-Pacific; therefore India should pitch for countries like Indonesia, Singapore to be invited to join in the future. There is also a vital need to economically expand the Quad.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-to-host-quad-officials-meet/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Millet crop is the best solution for climate smart agriculture</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/millet/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>examples of nutri-cereals</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>climate resilient agriculture</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="millet" class="alignnone wp-image-629923" height="285" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 498px) 100vw, 498px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Millet02-300x172.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Millet02-300x172.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Millet02.jpg 680w" width="498"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Government push to coarse cereals as climate change affects wheat, paddy cultivation</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/important-food-crops-rice-wheat-maize-millets-pulses-geographical-conditions-producing-areas-important-varieties-horticulture-fruits-vegetables/"><strong>What are millets crops? </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Millets are a group of highly variable small-seeded grasses, widely grown around the world as cereal crops or grains for human food and as fodder.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Features Millet crops in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Big three</strong>: The three major millet crops currently growing in India are jowar (sorghum), bajra (pearl millet) and ragi (finger millet).</li>
<li><strong>Examples</strong>: India also grows a rich array of bio-genetically diverse and indigenous varieties of “small millets” like kodo, kutki, chenna and sanwa.</li>
<li><strong>Area of production</strong>: Major producers include Rajasthan, Andhra Pradesh, Telangana, Karnataka, Tamil Nadu, Maharashtra, Gujarat and Haryana.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="millet" class="alignnone wp-image-629924" height="351" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 100vw, 527px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/millet-farmer-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/millet-farmer-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/millet-farmer.jpg 640w" width="527"/>What are Advantages of millet cultivation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low input cost</strong>: cereals are good for the soil, have shorter cultivation cycles and require less cost-intensive cultivation.</li>
<li><strong>Climate resilience</strong>: These unique features make millets suited for and resilient to India’s varied agro-climatic conditions.</li>
<li><strong>Drought tolerance</strong>: cereals are not water or input-intensive, making them a sustainable strategy for addressing climate change and building resilient agri-food systems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="millet" class="alignnone wp-image-629925" height="309" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 464px) 100vw, 464px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1456304251-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1456304251-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1456304251.jpg 555w" width="464"/>Reduction in millet production</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Effects of Green Revolution</strong>: The Green Revolution succeeded in making India food sufficient, however, it also led to water-logging, soil erosion, groundwater depletion and the unsustainability of agriculture.</li>
<li><strong>Deficit mind-set</strong>: Current policies are still based on the “deficit” mind-set of the 1960s.</li>
<li><strong>Biased policies</strong>: The procurement, subsidies and water policies are biased towards rice and wheat.</li>
<li><strong>Skewed cropping pattern</strong>: Three crops (rice, wheat and sugarcane) corner 75 to 80 per cent of irrigated water.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of diversification</strong>: Diversification of cropping patterns towards cereals, pulses, oilseeds, horticulture is needed for more equal distribution of water, sustainable and climate-resilient agriculture.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to promote millets as nutri-cereals? </strong></h4>
<p><strong>1) Rebranding the cereals as nutri-cereals</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The first strategy from a consumption and trade point of view was to re-brand coarse cereals/millets as nutri-cereals.</li>
<li>As of 2018-19, millet production had been extended to over 112 districts across 14 states.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2) Incentive through hiking MSP</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Second, the government hiked the MSP of nutri-cereals, which came as a big price incentive for farmers.</li>
<li>From 2014-15 to 2020 MSPs for ragi has jumped by 113 per cent, by 72 per cent for bajra and by 71 per cent for jowar.</li>
<li>MSPs have been calculated so that the farmer is ensured at least a 50 per cent return on their cost of production.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>3) Providing steady markets through inclusion in PDS</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>To provide a steady market for the produce, the Modi government included millets in the public distribution system.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>4) Increasing area, production and yield</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Ministry of Agriculture &amp; Farmers’ Welfare is running a Rs 600-crore scheme to increase the area, production and yield of nutri-cereals.</li>
<li>With a goal to match the cultivation of nutri-cereals with local topography and natural resources, the government is encouraging farmers to align their local cropping patterns to India’s diverse 127 agro-climatic zones.</li>
<li>Provision of seed kits and inputs to farmers, building value chains through Farmer Producer Organisations and supporting the marketability of nutri-cereals are some of the key interventions that have been put in place.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>5) Intersection of agriculture and nutrition</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Ministry of Women and Child Development has been working at the intersection of agriculture and nutrition by -1) setting up nutri-gardens, 2) promoting research on the interlinkages between crop diversity and dietary diversity 3) running a behaviour change campaign to generate consumer demand for nutri-cereals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India should aim for a food systems transformation, which can be inclusive and sustainable, ensure growing farm incomes and nutrition security<strong>. </strong>As the government sets to achieve its agenda of a malnutrition-free India and doubling of farmers’ incomes, the promotion of the production and consumption of nutri-cereals seems to be a policy shift in the right direction.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Promotion of millet crops serves the dual purpose of securing health and supporting farmers. Elucidate.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/millet/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>MGNREGA roadblocks should be removed urgently</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mgnrega/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of the scheme</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>social security</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="MGNREGA" class="alignnone wp-image-629928" height="389" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 499px) 100vw, 499px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/MGNREGA_Logo-300x234.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/MGNREGA_Logo-300x234.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/MGNREGA_Logo-1024x799.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/MGNREGA_Logo-768x599.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/MGNREGA_Logo.jpg 1145w" width="499"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The delay in payment of wages has pushed MGNREGS workers in West Bengal to the brink. There are allegations of corruption against the State government, the Centre’s reluctance in releasing payments, and the plight of the workers caught in this tussle.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is MGNREGA?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The MGNREGA stands for Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act of 2005. This is labour law and social security measure that aims to guarantee the ‘Right to Work’. The act was first proposed in 1991 by P.V. Narasimha Rao.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Significant Features of the scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Fixed employment</strong>: MGNREGA is unique in not only ensuring at least 100 days of employment to the willing unskilled workers, but also in ensuring an enforceable commitment on the implementing machinery i.e., the State Governments, and providing a bargaining power to the labourers.</li>
<li><strong>Assured compensation</strong>: The failure of provision for employment within 15 days of the receipt of job application from a prospective household will result in the payment of unemployment allowance to the job seekers.</li>
<li><strong>Locality is ensured</strong>: Employment is to be provided within 5 km of an applicant’s residence, and minimum wages are to be paid.</li>
<li><strong>Legal backing:</strong> Thus, employment under MGNREGA is a legal entitlement.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/mgnrega-scheme/"><strong><img alt="MGNREGA" class="alignnone wp-image-629930" height="320" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 427px) 100vw, 427px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/NREGAintro-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/NREGAintro-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/NREGAintro.jpg 400w" width="427"/>What are the issues?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Non-purposive spending and corruptions: </strong>Many works sanctioned under MGNREGA often seem to be non-purposive. Quite often, they are politically motivated hotspots to create rampant corruption by dominant sections of the local population. Even social audits of such projects are locally manipulated.</li>
<li><strong>Workers penalized for administrative lapses: </strong>The ministry withholds wage payments for workers of states that do not meet administrative requirements within the stipulated time period (for instance, submission of the previous financial year’s audited fund statements, utilization certificates, bank reconciliation certificates etc). There is no logical or legal explanation for this bizarre arrangement. It is beyond any logic as to why workers would be penalized for administrative lapses.</li>
<li><strong>Genuine job cards being deleted: </strong>Genuine job cards are being randomly deleted as there is a huge administrative pressure to meet 100 per cent DBT implementation targets in MGNREGA. In states like Jharkhand, there are multiple examples where the districts had later requested to resume job cards after civil society interventions into the matter.</li>
<li><strong>Too much centralization weakening local governance: </strong>A real-time MIS-based implementation and a centralised payment system has further left the representatives of the Panchayati Raj Institutions with literally no role in implementation. It has become a burden as they hardly have any power to resolve issues or make payments.</li>
<li><strong>Local priorities being ignored: </strong>MGNREGA could be a tool to establish decentralized governance. But, with the administration almost dictating its implementation, it is literally a burden now for the people and especially for the local elected representatives. The Gram Sabhas and gram panchayats’ plans are never honoured. This is a blatant violation of the Act as well.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="MGNREGA" class="alignnone wp-image-629929" height="297" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 435px) 100vw, 435px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mgnrega_660_040319050732-300x205.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mgnrega_660_040319050732-300x205.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mgnrega_660_040319050732.jpg 660w" width="435"/>Lack of fund has negative implications </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Delayed payment</strong>: Due to this, payments for MGNREGA workers as well as material costs will be delayed, unless States dip into their own funds.</li>
<li><strong>Livelihood loss:</strong> MGNREGA data shows that 13% of households who demanded work under the scheme were not provided work.</li>
<li><strong>Halt of work</strong>: Many workers are simply turned away by officials when they demand work, without their demand being registered at all.</li>
<li><strong>Fall in demands</strong>: This has led to stop the generation of work. There is an artificial squeezing of demand.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done according to rural development committee?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Utilization of funds</strong>: A large amount of funds allocated for MGNREGA have remained un-utilised. For example, in 2010-11, 27.31% of the funds remained unutilised. The Committee recommends that the Department of Rural Development should analyse reasons for poor utilisation of funds and take steps to improve the same. In addition, it should initiate action against officers found guilty of misappropriating funds under MGNREGA.</li>
<li><strong>Context specific projects and convergence</strong>: Since states are at various stages of socio-economic development, they have varied requirements for development. Therefore, state governments should be allowed to undertake works that are pertinent to their context. There should be more emphasis on skilled and semi-skilled work under MGNREGA. In addition, the Committee recommends a greater emphasis on convergence with other schemes such as the National Rural Livelihoods Mission, National Rural Health Mission, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Regulation of job cards</strong>: Offences such as not recording employment related information in job cards and unlawful possession of job cards with elected PRI representatives and MGNREGA functionaries should be made punishable under the Act.</li>
<li><strong>Participation of people with disabilities</strong>: Special works (projects) must be identified for people with disabilities and special job cards must be issued and personnel must be employed to ensure their participation.</li>
<li><strong>Payment of unemployment allowance</strong>: Dated receipts for demanded work should be issued so that workers can claim unemployment allowance. Funds for unemployment allowance should be met by the central government.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Some innovation in MGNREGA can address the challenges </strong></h4>
<p><strong>1) Looping in the skilled worker</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>First, there is a suggestion to use it to meet the wage cost of their employment in small and medium enterprises (SMEs).</li>
<li>Accordingly, skilled migrant workers may be placed in SMEs and their wages would be charged to MGNREGA.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2) Including farm related works</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In the last few years, un-remunerative prices of several crops have been the root cause of widespread agrarian distress.</li>
<li>The suggestion is to allow farmers to employ MGNREGA workers in agricultural operations like land preparation, sowing, transplantation of paddy, plucking of cotton, intercultural operations and harvesting of crops etc. so as to reduce the cost of cultivation.</li>
<li>The idea is to pay part of the wages of labour in agricultural operations from MGNREGA.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>3) Increasing the number of Work Schemes</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Currently, there are only 2-3 work schemes (say PMAY) running per panchayat, which is leading to the crowding of workers at worksites.</li>
<li>To prevent this and to ensure that all willing households are able to access employment through NREGA, the number of schemes needs to be increased, and 6-8 schemes must be introduced in each village.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>4) Paying Workers Immediately</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Rural households urgently need cash-in-hand, and so the emerging demand is for immediate payment to workers. NREGA payments are frequently delayed by weeks or months.</li>
<li>Given the circumstances, such delays will be entirely counterproductive.</li>
<li>It is recommended that in remote areas, wage payments should be made in cash, and paid on the same day.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Government and NGOs must study the impact of MGNREGA in rural areas so as to ensure that this massive anti-poverty scheme is not getting diluted from its actual path.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Large scale social security programmes like MGNREGA are subjected to undergo several stumbling blocks in the times to come due to lack of fund. Analyse these roadblocks and give some innovative measures to tackle these roadblocks.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mgnrega/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Cybercrime needs immediate revamp in response</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cybercrime/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Indian evidence act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Cybersecurity</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="cybercrime" class="alignnone wp-image-629933" height="200" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 382px) 100vw, 382px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Cybersecurity-Awareness-Month-Types-of-Cybercrime-300x157.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Cybersecurity-Awareness-Month-Types-of-Cybercrime-300x157.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Cybersecurity-Awareness-Month-Types-of-Cybercrime-1024x536.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Cybersecurity-Awareness-Month-Types-of-Cybercrime-768x402.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Cybersecurity-Awareness-Month-Types-of-Cybercrime.jpg 1201w" width="382"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There has been a steady spike in cases of cybercrime in the last five years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/cyber-security/"><strong>What is a cybercrime?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cybercrime is any criminal activity that involves a computer, networked device or a network. While most cybercrimes are carried out in order to generate profit for the cybercriminals, some cybercrimes are carried out against computers or devices directly to damage or disable them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What data states?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India reported 52,974 cases of cybercrime in 2021, an increase of over 5 per cent from 2020 (50,035 cases) and over 15 per cent from 2019 (44,735 cases), according to latest government data.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>How many cyber criminals are caught in India?</strong></p>
<p>In 2020, over 18.4 thousand people were arrested on account of cyber-crimes across India.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Who is responsible for cyber security centre or state?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>With ‘police’ and ‘public order’ being in the State List, the primary obligation to check crime and create the necessary cyberinfrastructure lies with States.</li>
<li>At the same time, with the IT Act and major laws being central legislations, the central government is no less responsible to evolve uniform statutory procedures for the enforcement agencies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="cybercrime" class="alignnone wp-image-629935" height="302" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 482px) 100vw, 482px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/surge-1024x640-1-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/surge-1024x640-1-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/surge-1024x640-1-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/surge-1024x640-1-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/surge-1024x640-1.jpg 1024w" width="482"/>Status of cyber investigation</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is no separate procedural code for the investigation of cyber or computer-related offences.</li>
<li>As electronic evidence is entirely different in nature when compared with evidence of traditional crime, laying down standard and uniform procedures to deal with electronic evidence is essential.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are general guidelines for cyber investigation? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The broad ‘guidelines for the identification, collection, acquisition and preservation of digital evidence’ are given in the Indian Standard IS/ISO/ IEC 27037: 2012, issued by the Bureau of Indian Standards (BIS).</li>
<li>This document is fairly comprehensive and easy to comprehend for both the first responder (who could be an authorised and trained police officer of a police station) as well as the specialist (who has specialised knowledge, skills and the abilities to handle a wide range of technical issues).</li>
<li>The guidelines, if followed meticulously, may ensure that electronic evidence is neither tampered with nor subject to spoliation during investigation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="cybercrime" class="alignnone wp-image-629938" height="397" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 529px) 100vw, 529px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-logs-40-per-cent-annual-increase-in-cyber-crime-cases-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-logs-40-per-cent-annual-increase-in-cyber-crime-cases-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-logs-40-per-cent-annual-increase-in-cyber-crime-cases-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-logs-40-per-cent-annual-increase-in-cyber-crime-cases-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-logs-40-per-cent-annual-increase-in-cyber-crime-cases.jpg 1200w" width="529"/><br/>
What is the meaning of digital evidence or electronic evidence?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Digital evidence is information stored or transmitted in binary form that may be relied on in court. It can be found on a computer hard drive, a mobile phone, among other places. Digital evidence is commonly associated with electronic crime, or e-crime, such as child pornography or credit card fraud.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Arjun Khotkar vs Kailash Gorantyal Judgement </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Court held that a certificate under Section 65B(4) of the Indian Evidence (IE) Act was a mandatory pre-requisite for the admissibility of (secondary) electronic record if the original record could not be produced.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Indian evidence act?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian Evidence Act, originally passed in India by the Imperial Legislative Council in 1872, during the British Raj, contains a set of rules and allied issues governing admissibility of evidence in the Indian courts of law.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Judicial activism for cyber security</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A significant attempt has been made by the higher judiciary in this field also. As resolved in the Conference of the Chief Justices of the High Court in April 2016, a five judge committee was constituted in July 2018 to frame the draft rules which could serve as a model for the reception of digital evidence by courts.</li>
<li>The committee, after extensive deliberations with experts, the police and investigation agencies, finalised its report in November 2018, but the suggested Draft Rules for the Reception, Retrieval, Authentication and Preservation of Electronic Records are yet to be given a statutory force.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What needs to be done?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Upgrade cyber labs</strong>: The cyber forensic laboratories of States must be upgraded with the advent of new technologies.</li>
<li><strong>Digital rupee</strong>: Offences related to cryptocurrency remain under-reported as the capacity to solve such crimes remains limited. The central government has proposed launching a digital rupee using block-chain technology soon.</li>
<li><strong>Empowering states</strong>: State enforcement agencies need to be ready for new technologies. The Centre helps in upgrading the State laboratories by providing modernisation funds, though the corpus has gradually shrunk over the years.</li>
<li><strong>Need for localisation of data</strong>: Most cybercrimes are trans-national in nature with extra-territorial jurisdiction. The collection of evidence from foreign territories is not only a difficult but also a tardy process.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Centre and States must not only work in tandem and frame statutory guidelines to facilitate investigation of cybercrime but also need to commit sufficient funds to develop much-awaited and required cyber infrastructure.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains questio</strong><strong>n </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>With the increasing use of computers in society, cybercrime has become a major issue. Analyse the loopholes in cyber security regime of India by giving suggestions to rectify the same.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cybercrime/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Energy self reliance for good future</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/energy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>energy secure India</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Energy" class="alignnone wp-image-630999" height="304" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 380px) 100vw, 380px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-s-quest-for-energy-security-2020-02-23-300x240.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-s-quest-for-energy-security-2020-02-23-300x240.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-s-quest-for-energy-security-2020-02-23-768x614.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/india-s-quest-for-energy-security-2020-02-23.jpg 1000w" width="380"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Prime Minister has called for “Energy Atmanirbharta” by 2040.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Atmanirbharta?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Atmanirbharta translates literally to self-reliance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the main purpose of Atmanirbhar Bharat?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The aim is to make the country and its citizens independent and self-reliant in all senses. Five pillars of Aatma Nirbhar Bharat are – Economy, Infrastructure, System, Vibrant Demography and Demand.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How to achieve energy self-reliance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Definitional clarity</strong>: Atmanirbharta translates literally to self-reliance. Many interpret it to mean self-sufficiency. That should not be our goal. <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/yojana-archive-energy-security-nuclear-power/">Energy self-sufficiency</a> is infeasible and uneconomic. A better statement of intent would be “strategic autonomy”.</li>
<li><strong>Affordable access to fuel</strong>: Our policy must continue to emphasise affordable and secure access to oil and gas. Part of this objective could be met by intensifying domestic exploration.</li>
<li><strong>Prioritise access to the building blocks of green energy: </strong>The sine qua non for realising this forecast will be cost-competitive access to minerals/components (copper, cobalt, lithium, semiconductor chips etc) required to build EVs, solar panels, wind turbines and batteries.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure development: </strong>We must expand our strategic petroleum reserves to cover at least 30 days of consumption and upgrade the transmission grid and battery storage systems to scale up renewables and smoothen its supplies. We will need to develop innovative financing mechanisms to fund green infrastructure. It should be emphasised that all such investments will get impaired if state discoms are financially insolvent.</li>
<li><strong>Green incentives</strong>: The government’s production-linked incentive scheme (PLI) offers benefits for investment in green energy.</li>
<li><strong>Demand conservation and efficiency: </strong>Energy usage norms must be standardised and tightened. Legislation should be contemplated to ensure compliance.</li>
<li><strong>Energy diplomacy</strong>: Our diplomats should add the arrows of energy diplomacy to their quiver. This is because of our dependence on the international energy supply chains. Success in navigating the cross-currents of economic and geopolitical uncertainties will rest greatly on skilful diplomacy.</li>
<li><strong>Holistic governance</strong>: The current siloed structures of energy governance are suboptimal. A root and branch administrative overall is required. Institutions should be created to facilitate integrated energy planning and implementation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-631000" height="219" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1644938879phpp5StKZ-300x219.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1644938879phpp5StKZ-300x219.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1644938879phpp5StKZ.jpeg 600w" width="300"/>Case study for value addition </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><em>Costa Rica lasted 300 consecutive days on renewable energy alone. Costa Rica set the record in 2017 for most consecutive days with renewable energy. The previous record for this feat was in 2015 when Costa Rica lasted 299 consecutive days on pure, clean energy.</em></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges ahead </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Anti-nuclear public sentiment</strong>: The Fukushima-Daiichi accident resulted in growing concern over the safety of nuclear plants in India .The construction of a nuclear plant in Kudankulam, Tamil Nadu, brought the issue directly into the public domain in 2012.</li>
<li><strong>Management autonomy</strong>: Power sector is dominated by public sector companies or PSUs (owned by the central and state government). Some parts of the energy sector have made very little progress in attracting private investment since 2007.</li>
<li><strong>Pricing</strong>: is the key to ensure the commercial viability of business entities and to attract investment into each fuel sector.</li>
<li><strong>Rigid tariff setting mechanism</strong>: Theoretically,  prices should be supervised and adjusted in a timely manner and adequately by independent regulators to reflect changing costs. However, in India, regulators including CERC and SERCs operate in a very rigid way due to political considerations. This jeopardises the operational profitability of companies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Energy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-631001" height="223" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images.jpeg" width="226"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>We need leadership that can reconcile temporal differences and balance the short-term pressures of elections with the longer-term imperatives of sustainability in energy security which calls for bold and pragmatic decision making by the leadership.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. How India can achieve “Energy Atmanirbharta” by 2040 an ambitious target stated by prime minister? What are the challenges in achieving this goal?.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/energy/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Teacher concerns should be addressed immediately</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/teacher/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>teacher concerns and issues</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="teacher " class="alignnone wp-image-631018" height="362" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 362px) 100vw, 362px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/28teachers1-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/28teachers1.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/28teachers1-150x150.jpg 150w" width="362"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>5 September is teacher’s day. Teachers’ Day or Shikshak Divas marks the birthday of the country’s first Vice President (1952–1962) who went on to become the second President of India (1962-1967), a scholar, philosopher, Bharat Ratna awardee, a highly-respected teacher and prolific statesman – Dr Sarvapalli Radhakrishnan.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="teacher " class="alignnone wp-image-631022" height="216" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 383px) 100vw, 383px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/917409a0-f9d2-11eb-a6fe-32d1c824c5de_1628597000407-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/917409a0-f9d2-11eb-a6fe-32d1c824c5de_1628597000407-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/917409a0-f9d2-11eb-a6fe-32d1c824c5de_1628597000407.jpg 550w" width="383"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/teaching-the-teacher/">What are the issue with teachers?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Less attractive career</strong>: It seems that teaching the young is no longer an attractive profession because systemic conditions are so discouraging. It points towards the reforms that education now requires.</li>
<li><strong>Diversion from teaching:</strong> Teaching children is not regarded as a serious profession. Non-teaching duties are routinely assigned, and now the digital regime has washed away the few traces of professional autonomy even in the best of private schools.</li>
<li><strong>Bureaucratic over vigilance:</strong> So deep is official suspicion of their integrity that many states have installed CCTV cameras in classrooms. That is not the only form of insult teacher’s face. They have little power to assert their professional dignity in the face of bureaucratic or managerial authority.</li>
<li><strong>Marginalisation by coaching institutes: </strong>The Indian school teacher now faces new social and economic forces. Coaching institutions have marginalised the secondary-level science teacher. All over the country, children are allowed to bunk school to attend NEET and JEE coaching classes. Science and math teachers were, in any case, aware that their pedagogic effectiveness would be measured by an unreformed examination system<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Reliability issue due to internet overuse: </strong>Social Science teachers are coping with a different kind of challenge to justify their knowledge and interpretation. Children’s access to the internet exposes them to a wilderness of socio-political ideas and information. It is not easy for social science teachers to convince children that they are more reliable than a YouTube video or a WhatsApp message.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Catchy line in this context for value addition</strong></p>
<p><em>Jinke jiwan me guru nahi, unka jiwan abhi shuru nahi.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>How to address these challenges </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Supporting teacher control over curriculum and instruction: </strong>Classical top-down school leadership needs to be re-examined, and teachers must be recognized as professionals who have expertise to make good learning decisions for their students.</li>
<li><strong>Establish adequate pay scales and financial incentives: </strong>Compensation systems signal what skills and attributes are valued and what kinds of contributions are rewarded.</li>
<li><strong>Establish and conduct personnel evaluation systems: </strong>Teachers need regular feedback and accurate information on job expectations.</li>
<li><strong>Provide adequate planning time for teachers: </strong>While all teachers work under tremendous time constraints, experienced teachers generally are able to complete their planning more quickly. For new teachers, adequate planning time can allay feelings of being overwhelmed.</li>
<li><strong>Provide a structure for team planning and teaching: </strong>Teachers often report feeling isolated in their classrooms. Team planning and teaching can be an important step in retaining a high quality teaching force.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="teacher " class="alignnone wp-image-631020" height="195" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ded-300x130.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ded-300x130.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ded.jpg 305w" width="449"/>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Since the teacher is the pivot of the entire educational system and is the main catalytic agent for introducing desirable changes in the teaching learning process, all attempts need be made for motivating teachers to become innovative and creative. It goes without saying that a self-motivated and really industrious teacher can utilise his own resources to keep themselves abreast of new knowledge and skills.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. It seems that teaching the young is no longer an attractive profession because systemic conditions are so discouraging. Critically analyse.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/teacher/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India Bangladesh bilateral ties has strong future</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bangladesh/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>bilateral ties</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="bangladesh" class="alignnone wp-image-631044" height="150" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 344px) 100vw, 344px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960X420-11-300x131.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960X420-11-300x131.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960X420-11-768x336.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960X420-11.jpg 960w" width="344"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bangladesh PM Sheikh Hasina’s four-day visit to India to boost bilateral ties.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/foreign-policy-watch-india-bangladesh/"><strong>India-Bangladesh ties background </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s links with Bangladesh are civilization, cultural, social and economic.</li>
<li>There is much that unites the two countries – a shared history and common heritage, linguistic and cultural ties, passion for music, literature and the arts.</li>
<li>India was one of the first countries, along with Bhutan, to recognise Bangladesh as a sovereign state on 6 December 1971.</li>
<li>It is also worth recalling that India shares its longest border of 4,096.7 kilometres with Bangladesh, which is also the fifth-longest border in the contemporary world.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="bangladesh" class="alignnone wp-image-631046" height="209" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 371px) 100vw, 371px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sheikh_Hasina_1662288566031_1662288566150_1662288566150-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sheikh_Hasina_1662288566031_1662288566150_1662288566150-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sheikh_Hasina_1662288566031_1662288566150_1662288566150.jpeg 600w" width="371"/>Trade between two</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>CEPA:</strong> Trade will be a focal point during Ms. Hasina’s visit as the two countries gear up to sign a Comprehensive Economic Partnership Agreement.</li>
<li><strong>Bangladesh dependency:</strong> Bangladesh imports critical industrial raw material from India on which its exports are reliant.</li>
<li><strong>Leveraging Indian support:</strong> Bangladesh also could improve several manufacturing industries by leveraging Indian expertise in service sectors.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="bangladesh" class="alignnone wp-image-631047" height="216" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-1.jpeg" width="376"/>Connectivity </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>IMT highway</strong>: Bangladesh has expressed its interest in joining the India-Myanmar-Thailand highway project.</li>
<li><strong>Waterway</strong>: India-Bangladesh bilateral waterway trade will get boosted as India can now use the Mongla and Chittagong ports.</li>
<li><strong>Logistics</strong>: India’s Northeast and Bangladesh is important for bilateral cooperation. Currently, three express trains and international bus services operate between Indian and Bangladesh.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Key data to remember </strong></h4>
<p>Bangladesh is India’s sixth largest trade partner with bilateral trade rising from $2.4 billion in 2009 to $10.8 billion in 2020-21.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Regional geopolitics</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Chinese influence: </strong>Chinese inroads into the neighbourhood have been a cause of worry for India. China has been actively pursuing bilateral ties with Bangladesh. Bangladesh had successfully approached China for a mega project to enhance Teesta river water flow.</li>
<li><strong>Strategic location</strong>: From the perspective of India’s Northeast, Bangladesh is India’s most strategic neighbour, whom New Delhi cannot ever afford to ignore.</li>
<li><strong>Cooperation needed</strong>: India’s dream of ‘Act East Policy’ can only be materialized with the helping hands of Dhaka.</li>
<li><strong>Gateway to northeast</strong>: The bridge ‘Maitri Setu’ has been built over the Feni River which flows between the Indian boundary in Tripura State and Bangladesh. It is set to become the ‘Gateway of North East’ with access to Chittagong Port of Bangladesh, which is just 80 kms from Sabroom.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The future will present itself with an abundance of opportunities to help the two countries to reach a new plane of bilateral relations higher than ever before.</li>
<li>Both nations should play their diplomatic cards with more maturity and pragmatism, keeping the regional aspirations and nuances of both countries in mind.</li>
<li>A judicious aggregation of regional expectations on both sides of the border will help in achieving their mutual national objectives.</li>
<li>To make the recent gains irreversible, both countries need to continue working on the three Cs — cooperation, collaboration, and consolidation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>For India it will take more than cosy relations with one particular government to have long-term stable relations with its most trusted friend in the neighbourhood.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Do you think Bangladesh is most trusted friend in the neighbourhood? Discuss bilateral relations between two in terms of trade, connectivity and geopolitics.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bangladesh/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Scientists remain sceptical about how Liquid Nano Urea benefits crops</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/scientists-sceptical-liquid-nano-urea/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Liquid Nano Urea (LNU)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-631401" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lnu-253x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lnu-253x300.jpg 253w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lnu-865x1024.jpg 865w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lnu-768x909.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lnu-760x900.jpg 760w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lnu.jpg 1081w" width="253"/></strong></p>
<p>Liquid Nano Urea, a fertilizer patented and sold by the Indian Farmers Fertiliser Cooperative Ltd. (IFFCO), has been approved by the government for commercial use because of its potential to substantially reduce the import bill, but several experts have questioned the science underlying its efficacy.</p>
<h4>What is Liquid Nano Urea (LNU)?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Urea is chemical nitrogen fertiliser, white in colour, which artificially provides nitrogen, a major nutrient required by plants.</li>
<li>LNU is essentially urea in the form of a nanoparticle.</li>
<li>It is sprayed directly on the leaves and gets absorbed by the plant.</li>
<li>Fertilisers in nano form provide a targeted supply of nutrients to crops, as they are absorbed by the stomata, pores found on the epidermis of leaves.</li>
<li>According to IFFCO, liquid nano urea contains 4 per cent total nitrogen (w/v) evenly dispersed in water.</li>
<li>The size of a nano nitrogen particle varies from 20-50 nm. (A nanometre is equal to a billionth of a metre.)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Using <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-liquid-nano-urea/">LNU</a></h4>
<ul>
<li>The liquid nano urea produced by IFFCO Limited comes in a half-litre bottle priced at Rs 240, and carries no burden of subsidy currently.</li>
<li>By contrast, a farmer pays around Rs 300 for a 50-kg bag of heavily subsidised urea.</li>
<li>According to IFFCO, a bottle of the nano urea can effectively replace at least one bag of urea.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How efficient is LNU?</h4>
<ul>
<li>While conventional urea has an efficiency of about 25 per cent, the efficiency of liquid nano urea can be as high as 85-90 per cent.</li>
<li>Conventional urea fails to have the desired impact on crops as it is often applied incorrectly, and the nitrogen in it is vaporized or lost as a gas.</li>
<li>A lot of nitrogen is also washed away during irrigation.</li>
<li>Liquid nano urea has a shelf life of a year, and farmers need not be worried about “caking” when it comes in contact with moisture.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of LNU</h4>
<ul>
<li>This patented product is expected to not only <strong><u>substitute imported urea</u></strong>, but to also <strong><u>produce better results in farms.</u></strong></li>
<li>Apart from <strong><u>reducing the country’s subsidy bill</u></strong>, it is aimed at <strong><u>reducing the unbalanced and indiscriminate use of conventional urea</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It will help <strong><u>increase crop productivity</u></strong>, and reduce soil, water, and air pollution.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Plants need nitrogen to make protein and they source almost all of it from soil bacteria which live in a plant’s roots and have the ability to break down atmospheric nitrogen, or that from chemicals such as urea into a form usable by plants.</li>
<li>Chemically packaged urea is 46% nitrogen, which means a 45-kg sack contains about 20 kg of nitrogen.</li>
<li>Contrastingly, nano urea sold in 500-ml bottles has only 4% nitrogen (or around 20 g).</li>
<li>How this can compensate for the kilograms of nitrogen normally required puzzles scientists.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/scientists-sceptical-liquid-nano-urea/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Exercise Vostok-22</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-navy-exercise-vostok-22/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Vostok 2022</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India-Russia Relations</p></div></div><p>Russia is holding Vostok exercises. However, India has only sent its army contingent of the 7/8 Gorkha Rifles, and will not take part in the maritime section of the two-part event.</p>
<h4>Vostok-2022</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is an annual, multilateral, strategic and command exercise hosted by Russia.</li>
<li>This year it will see the participation of more than <strong><u>50,000 troops</u></strong> from <strong><u>13 countries</u></strong> such as India, China, Algeria, India, Laos, Mongolia, Nicaragua, Syria and many more.</li>
<li>While the exercises in Vostok-2022 are routine, they are the first such multilateral exercises to be held since the Russian war in Ukraine began.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has only sent its army contingent and will not take part in the maritime section of the two-part event.</li>
<li>This is because the maritime part of the exercises would be held in the Sea of Okhotsk and the Sea of Japan.</li>
<li>These are near the disputed <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-kuril-islands/">South Kuril Islands</a>.</li>
<li>India’s decision not to take part in the naval exercises is believed to be in deference to Tokyo’s sensitivities.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What does India’s participation mean?</h4>
<p>By sending an army contingent to join Russian and Chinese troops in the exercises at this time, New Delhi is aiming to send a four-pronged message:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Continuing relationship with Russia despite the Ukraine war:</strong> The Modi government has decided not to join the Western sanctions regime, or to curb oil imports and other economic engagement with Moscow.</li>
<li><strong>Signal balance and non-alignment in the current crisis:</strong> India has mostly abstained from votes at the United Nations seeking to criticise Russia.</li>
<li><strong>India also takes part in routine Indo-Pacific exercises:</strong> This is with its Western partners including the Quad, as well as in bilateral exercises, like the India-US Ex. Yudh Abhyas.</li>
<li><strong>Willingness to conditional engagement with China:</strong> The message the government continues to give is that it is willing to engage with China on a number of fronts, even as military talks at LAC (Line of Actual Control) remain stuck.</li>
</ol>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>There might be some discomfort for Indian soldiers in dealing with their counterparts at a time when they are facing each other off along the LAC.</li>
<li>But that’s a small price to pay if it means keeping India-Russia ties on an even keel.</li>
<li>India needs to start communicating its intent better.</li>
<li>Strategic communication is an art. It’s time to master it.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-navy-exercise-vostok-22/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Explained: Bail for Women</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-bail-for-women/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Bails</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Different bail provisions</p></div></div><p>An activist recently walked out of a prison, a day after the Supreme Court granted her <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mudda-aapka-supreme-court-suggests-bail-act/">interim bail</a> in a case of allegedly fabricating evidence related to the 2002 Gujarat riots.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>Here we get to know that bail laws in India are not gender neutral. They somewhat favor women due to certain disprivileged social backgrounds.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>What is Bail?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bail is the conditional release of a defendant with the promise to appear in court when required.</li>
<li>The term also means the security that is deposited in order to secure the release of the accused.</li>
<li>In India’s legal world, the term offense has been categorized as bailable offenses and non-bailable under the Code of Criminal Procedure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need Bail?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bail is a <strong><u>fundamental aspect</u></strong> of any criminal justice system.</li>
<li>The practice of bail grew out of the need <strong><u>to safeguard the fundamental right to liberty</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Liberty is the right of one whose <strong><u>guilt has not yet been proven</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Types of Bail in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Depending upon the sage of the criminal matter, there are commonly three types of bail in India:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Regular bail:</strong> Regular bail is generally granted to a person who has been arrested or is in police custody. A bail application can be filed for regular bail under sections 437 and 439 of CrPC.</li>
<li><strong>Interim bail:</strong> This type of bail is granted for a short period of time and it is granted before the hearing for the grant of regular bail or anticipatory bail.</li>
<li><strong>Anticipatory bail:</strong> Anticipatory bail is granted under section 438 of CrPC either by session court or High Court. An application for the grant of anticipatory bail can be filed by the person who discerns that he may be arrested by the police for a non-bailable offense.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<p>Ans. <strong><u>Favorable treatment for Women</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>During the hearing, the Supreme Court of India has made an oral observation that under Section 437 of the Code of Criminal Procedure (CrPC), a woman is entitled to favourable treatment.</li>
<li>The provision says that, being a woman is a possible ground for granting bail, even when otherwise it cannot be considered.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does the bail provision say in favor of Women? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Section 437</u></strong> of the CrPC deals with bail in case of non-bailable offences.</li>
<li>It says a person shall not be released on bail if there is reasonable ground to believe that he has committed an offence punishable with <strong><u>death or life imprisonment</u></strong>.</li>
<li>However, it also contains exceptions in a provision that says the court may grant bail even in these cases, “<strong><u>if such person is under the age of 16 or is a woman or is sick or infirm</u></strong>”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Are there other provisions favourable to women accused? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There are several provisions in criminal law that give special consideration to women, of any age, when they are victims of offences, including sexual offences, in the way they are treated as witnesses and victims of crimes.</li>
<li>There are also some provisions relating to women when they are made an accused, and arrested.</li>
<li>For instance, when a police officer requires the attendance of any person who he believes is acquainted with a case under investigation, the person has to appear before the officer (Section 160).</li>
<li>However, no woman shall be required to do so at any place other than the place in which she resides.</li>
<li>This is understood to mean that the officer has to visit the place of residence to make enquiries.</li>
<li>This benefit is also available to boys under 15, men above 65 and any mentally or physically disabled person.</li>
<li>In its 84th and 135th Report in 1980 and 1989, the Law Commission suggested that the word ‘place’ is ambiguous, and it would be better to amend it to ‘dwelling place’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does the CrPC say on the arrest of a woman? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A police officer <strong><u>may arrest a person who has committed a cognisable offence without a judicial order</u></strong> or a warrant (Section 41).</li>
<li>If the person does not submit to custody based on the word or action of the police, Section 46 enables the police officer to confine the person physically to effect the arrest.</li>
<li>A proviso was introduced in the CrPC in 2009 to the effect that where a woman is to be arrested, <strong><u>only a female police officer may touch the woman’s person</u></strong>, unless circumstances otherwise require.</li>
<li>Earlier, through a 2005 amendment, a subsection was added to Section 46 to <strong><u>prohibit the arrest of a woman after sunset or before sunrise. </u></strong></li>
<li>However, in exceptional circumstances, a woman police officer can obtain the prior permission of a judicial magistrate to make the arrest.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does it say on women who don’t appear in public? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The police <strong><u>may seek entry into any premises</u></strong> where they suspect that a person who is required to be arrested is present.</li>
<li>In a situation where any such place is an apartment in the occupancy of a female (who is not the person to be arrested) and if the woman is one who, by custom, does not appear in public, <strong><u>the police have to give notice to her</u></strong> so that she may withdraw before they enter it (Proviso to Section 47).</li>
<li>It adds that they shall afford her every reasonable facility for withdrawing before they break open and enter the place.</li>
<li>In yet another exception, a woman who intends to file a defamation case, but is one who does not appear in public according to custom, can ask someone else to file the complaint on her behalf.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="KJzf6BcJX5"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mudda-aapka-supreme-court-suggests-bail-act/">[Sansad TV] Mudda AapKa: Supreme Court Suggests “Bail Act”</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="KJzf6BcJX5" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mudda-aapka-supreme-court-suggests-bail-act/embed/#?secret=Q38Uhz229F#?secret=KJzf6BcJX5" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Sansad TV] Mudda AapKa: Supreme Court Suggests “Bail Act”” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-bail-for-women/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was Ramon Magsaysay of Philippines?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-ramon-magsaysay-of-philippines/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ramon Magsaysay</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-631406" height="237" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 350px) 100vw, 350px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay-300x203.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay-300x203.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay.jpg 637w" width="350"/></p>
<p>A leftist leader and former Kerala health minister has declined to receive the Ramon Magsaysay Award as the late President of the Philippines was known for his alleged brutality against the Communists.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lunched in 1958, the Ramon Magsaysay Award, widely considered to be Asia’s equivalent to the Nobel Prize, recognises outstanding leadership and communitarian contributions in Asia.</li>
<li>This year’s annual list of awardees was announced last week.</li>
<li>Shailaja was considered for the award for her performance as state health minister from 2016 to 2021, a period which saw Kerala fight against the Nipah virus and Covid-19.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who was Ramon Magsaysay?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Born on August 31, 1907 to a father who worked as a blacksmith and a mother who was a teacher, Ramon Del Fierro Magsaysay Senior was the seventh president of the Philippines, from 1953 until his death in an air crash in 1957.</li>
<li>Magsaysay started out as an automobile mechanic before being drafted into the Pacific War (1941-1945), during World War II.</li>
<li>The Pacific War would see the Japanese occupation of the Philippines — then a colony of the US — for nearly four years.</li>
<li>The US formally recognised the Philippines as an independent nation in 1946.</li>
</ul>
<h4>His legacy</h4>
<ul>
<li>As a guerrilla leader resisting the Japanese occupation, Magsaysay’s bravery and leadership saw his appointment as a military governor.</li>
<li>In 1946, he would be elected under the Liberal Party to the Philippine House of Representatives, where he would serve two terms as a Congressman before being appointed secretary of National Defence in 1950.</li>
<li>On December 30, 1953, he would be elected president from the Nationalist Party, the oldest political party in the Philippines.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Communism and Magsaysay</h4>
<ul>
<li>Founded in 1902, the Unión Obrera Democrática is considered the first modern trade federation in the Philippines.</li>
<li>The Communist Party of the Philippines or the Partido Komunista ng Pilipinas (PKP) was formed in 1930.</li>
<li>The Hukbong Bayan Laban sa Hapon or the People’s Army Against the Japanese, popularly known as the Hukbalahap (Huk), was a prominent guerrilla outfit that fought the Japanese.</li>
<li>As the country plunged into post-war chaos after 1946, the fortunes of the Hukbalahaps, too, changed dramatically.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How he rose to his fame?</h4>
<ul>
<li>With the expansion of capitalism, the gap between the rich and poor widened and the farmers continued to languish.</li>
<li>Huk leaders were viewed with suspicion over their declaration of commitment to communism and the demand for peasant rights.</li>
<li>With the US as its close ally, the Philippine government cracked down on the Huks, who formed an alliance with the PKP to take their struggle to a parliamentary platform.</li>
<li>The severe crackdown against the Huks continued until Magsaysay became the National Defence Secretary under President Elpidio Quirino.</li>
<li>Magsaysay drew upon his own experience of guerrilla warfare to initiate a two-pronged system of reforms and military campaigns.</li>
<li>It was under his administrative and military policies that the Huk threat was considered to be neutralised.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Ramon Magsaysay Award</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 1957, the Ramon Magsaysay award was set up by trustees of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund and the Philippine government to carry forward Magsaysay’s legacy of service to the people, good governance, and pragmatic idealism.</li>
<li>In the six decades since 1958 — the first year the Award was given out — over 300 organisations and individuals have been recognised for their developmental endeavours crucial to Asia, and, consequently, to the world.</li>
<li>The award is given out every year on August 31, on Magsaysay’s birth anniversary.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Indian winners on the list</h4>
<ul>
<li>Prominent Indians who have won the award include Vinoba Bhave in 1958, Mother Teresa in 1962, Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay in 1966, Satyajit Ray in 1967, Mahasweta Devi in 1997.</li>
<li>In recent years, Arvind Kejriwal (2006), Anshu Gupta of Goonj (2015), human rights activist Bezwada Wilson (2016), and journalist Ravish Kumar (2019) have won the award.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-ramon-magsaysay-of-philippines/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Kurki, and why is it a big issue in Punjab?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-kurki-in-punjab/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Kurki</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>A farmer in Punjab has committed suicide outside the office of the Muktsar DC against kurki orders for his land based on a court case filed against him by the local moneylender for defaulting on loan payment.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Kurki?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Kurki means attachment of a farmer’s land, already pledged to the money lending institution or individual, in case of a loan default.</li>
<li>Apart from banks, private moneylenders, commission agents also get these decrees against farmers from time to time.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How is kurki executed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Kurki orders are executed under Section 60 of Civil Procedure Code, 1908.</li>
<li>The land which is pledged by the farmer to the bank or money lender gets registered in their name. In some cases, the land is auctioned as well.</li>
<li>The process begins after the money lender moves court to get kurki orders in case the farmer is unable to pay back his loan.</li>
<li>In kurki, attachment of farmer’s land as well as his tractor can be done as per the Section 60.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Was kurki not banned in Punjab?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Both Akali Dal and Congress governments of the past have claimed to have banned kurki.</li>
<li>Congress fought the 2017 Assembly polls on the slogan ‘karza kurki khatam, fasal di poori rakam’.</li>
<li>Soon after winning polls in 2017, the then government abolished Section 67-A of Punjab Cooperative Societies Act that enabled cooperatives to recover unpaid loans through auctioning of land mortgaged by farmers.</li>
<li>However, Section 63-B, 63-C of the Act were not dropped to prevent attachment of land.</li>
<li>Former Punjab CM has also claimed that kurki was abolished by his government. Activists accuses governments of issuing vague orders on the matter.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why has a total ban on the century-old kurki law not been achieved?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A plea filed in the Punjab and Haryana High Court in 2018 sought complete ban on kurki.</li>
<li>However, the Punjab government in its affidavit stated that there was no need to ban kurki as relief was being given to farmers in terms of loan waiver, compensation etc.</li>
<li>Moreover, it stated that Section 60 of Civil Procedure Code, 1908 – under which kurki takes place — was over 110 years old and needed complete revision.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the ground reality?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Farmers point out that they are made to give post-dated cheques for loan, which are then used to get arrest orders issued in cheque bounce cases.</li>
<li>They have also accused money lenders of using pronotes signed by them to get kurki orders.</li>
<li>“Pro-notes” (promissory notes) are written documents taken from farmers, and signed by them at the time of giving the loan.</li>
<li>In April 2022, over 2,000 arrest warrants were issued against farmers for non-payment of loans to cooperative societies and Punjab agriculture development banks.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-kurki-in-punjab/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Martand Temple in Kashmir</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/martand-temple-in-kashmir/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Martand Sun Temple</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-539806" height="295" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 436px) 100vw, 436px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/mart-300x203.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/mart-300x203.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/mart.jpg 636w" width="436"/></p>
<p>In May this year, some pilgrims offered prayers inside the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-martand-sun-temple/">Martand Temple</a>, an Archaeological Survey of India-protected (ASI) monument</p>
<h4>About Martand Sun Temple</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Martand Sun Temple is a Hindu temple located near the city of Anantnag in the Kashmir Valley.</li>
<li>It dates back to the eighth century AD and was dedicated to Surya, the chief solar deity.</li>
<li>The temple was destroyed by Sikandar Shah Miri in a bid to undertake mass conversion and execution of Hindus in the valley.</li>
<li>According to Kalhana, the Temple was commissioned by Lalitaditya Muktapida in the eighth century AD.</li>
<li>The temple is built on top of a plateau from where one can view whole of the Kashmir Valley.</li>
<li>From the ruins the visible architecture seems to be blended with the Gandharan, Gupta and Chinese forms of architecture.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>According to ASI, prayers are allowed at its protected sites only if they were “functioning places of worship” at the time it took charge of them.</li>
<li>No religious rituals can be conducted at non-living monuments where there has been no continuity of worship when it became an ASI-protected site.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the living/non-living monument?</h4>
<ul>
<li>If some activity, like any kind of worship, has been going on for years in the structure, then it is taken over as a living monument.</li>
<li>But where no activity has taken place, say an abandoned building, then it is declared a dead monument.</li>
<li>The latter is difficult to restore because it is generally covered by a lot of overgrowth.</li>
<li>The best-known example of a living ASI monument is the Taj Mahal in Agra, where namaz is held every Friday.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/martand-temple-in-kashmir/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>History and debates about ‘socialist’ and ‘secular’ in the Preamble</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/socialist-and-secular-in-the-preamble/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Preamble to the Constitution</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-631405" height="477" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 348px) 100vw, 348px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/preamble-219x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/preamble-219x300.jpg 219w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/preamble.jpg 551w" width="348"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court will hear a petition filed by former MP Dr Subramanian Swamy, seeking the removal of the words “Socialist” and “Secular” from the preamble of the Indian Constitution.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The petitioners in two similar cases have argued that these words were never intended to be in the Constitution and that such insertion is beyond the amending power of the Parliament under Article 368.</li>
<li>Similar petitions have been filed earlier too and given rise to debates around the preamble and the role it plays in the Constitution.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did these words come?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The two terms were inserted into the preamble as part of the <strong><u>42nd Amendment</u> </strong>of the Constitution in<strong> <u>1976</u></strong> <strong><u>during the Emergency</u></strong> imposed by then PM Indira Gandhi.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the purpose of the Preamble?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A preamble serves as an introduction to a document and contains its basic principles and goals.</li>
<li>When the Indian Constitution was being drafted, the ideals behind the preamble were first laid down in the Objectives Resolution, <strong><u>adopted by the Constituent Assembly in 1947</u></strong>.</li>
<li>These ideals emerged out of the numerous debates that took place during the drafting of the Constitution.</li>
</ul>
<p>Initially, the Preamble said:</p>
<p>“WE, THE PEOPLE OF INDIA, having solemnly resolved to constitute India into a SOVEREIGN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC and to secure to all its citizens:</p>
<p>JUSTICE, social, economic and political;</p>
<p>LIBERTY of thought, expression, belief, faith and worship;</p>
<p>EQUALITY of status and of opportunity;</p>
<p>And to promote among them all</p>
<p>FRATERNITY assuring the dignity of the individual and the unity of the Nation;</p>
<p>IN OUR CONSTITUENT ASSEMBLY this twenty-sixth day of November, 1949, do HEREBY ADOPT, ENACT AND GIVE TO OURSELVES THIS CONSTITUTION.”</p>
<h4>Nature of the preamble</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Constitution was the product of democratic deliberations and decided upon by the people of India themselves in the wake of freedom from colonial rule.</li>
<li>The ideals mentioned here were at the core of the newly democratic nation.</li>
<li>During the Constituent Assembly debates, many suggestions were put forth — including that God should be invoked in the preamble as in the Irish constitution, that Mahatma Gandhi’s name should be included, etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Is it a part of the Constitution?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The question of whether the preamble is a part of the Constitution or simply an introduction has been deliberated upon by the highest court.</li>
<li>This is because the meaning and weight of the objectives mentioned in it, such as equality of status and opportunity, remained unclear from the perspective of law.</li>
<li>However, in its judgment in the famous LIC case of 1995, the Supreme Court said and the Preamble of the Constitution which is an <strong><u>integral part and scheme of the Constitution</u></strong>, affirming its position as part of the Constitution.</li>
<li>Additionally, the violation of any principle mentioned in the preamble cannot be a reason to go to court, meaning the preamble is “<strong><u>non-justiciable</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>However, judgments of courts can cite it as an additional factor in their reasoning, given that it <strong><u>constitutes the spirit of the Constitution</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How else has the preamble been debated earlier?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2020 a ruling MP has moved a resolution in Rajya Sabha seeking to remove the word socialism from the preamble.</li>
<li>It said, that the earlier party which ruled the country for seven decades has changed its direction from being socialist to welfare to neo-liberalism.</li>
<li>Its new liberal policies adopted in the 1990s have negated its own earlier positions.</li>
<li>Earlier in 2015, the Ministry of Information and Broadcasting used an image of the preamble of the Indian Constitution without the words “socialist” and “secular”, leading to some criticism.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the right-wing narrative?</h4>
<ul>
<li>These words were added during the Emergency. Now what is the harm if there is a debate on it?</li>
<li>In 2008, the Supreme Court rejected a plea demanding the removal of ‘socialist’.</li>
<li>The apex court asked-Why do you take socialism in a narrow sense defined by Communists?</li>
<li>In a broader sense, it means welfare measures for the citizens. It is a facet of democracy, said the Court.</li>
<li>It hasn’t got any definite meaning. It gets different meanings in different times.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Under what circumstances was the preamble amended?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Over her years in government, Indira Gandhi had attempted to cement her approval among the masses on the basis of a socialist and pro-poor image with slogans such as “garibi hatao” (Eradicate poverty).</li>
<li>The 42nd Amendment to the Constitution, passed in 1976 when the Emergency was in place, replaced the words “sovereign democratic republic” with “sovereign socialist secular democratic republic”.</li>
<li>It also changed “unity of the nation” to “unity and integrity of the nation”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Were ‘Secular’ and ‘Socialist’ debated before Independence?</h4>
<ul>
<li>During the debates in the Constituent Assembly, members such as K T Shah and Brajeshwar Prasad had raised the demand to add these words to the preamble.</li>
<li>However, Dr B R Ambedkar argued: What should be the policy of the State, how the Society should be organised in its social and economic side are matters which must be decided by the people themselves according to time and circumstances.</li>
<li>It cannot be laid down in the Constitution itself because that is destroying democracy altogether.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Is it inclusive of the Constitution?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Indeed, many principles affirming secularism and socialism were contained in the Constitution originally, such as in the Directive Principles of State Policy that is meant to guide the government in its actions.</li>
<li>Some examples are provisions related to the “equitable distribution of material resources of the community for the common good”, and protecting the rights of workers.</li>
<li>Similarly, in the fundamental rights that allow the freedom to profess and propagate one’s religion, as well as in the government policies that recognize religious occasions across communities, an Indian version of secularism is followed.</li>
<li>Unlike western secularism which strictly separates the state and religion, the Indian state has over the years acknowledged and involved itself in matters related to all religions.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/socialist-and-secular-in-the-preamble/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>TN reiterates plea for a Bench of Supreme Court in Chennai</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/plea-for-bench-of-supreme-court-chennai/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Article 130, Circuit Court</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Judicial accessibility</p></div></div><p>TN Chief Minister yet again reiterated the State’s request for establishing a <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/the-idea-of-regional-supreme-court-benches/">Regional Bench of the Supreme Court</a> in Chennai and allowing Tamil to be used in the Madras High Court as one of its official languages.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Outgoing Vice President, M Venkaiah Naidu suggested bifurcation of the Supreme Court into four regional benches for speedy disposal of cases.</li>
<li>However, the Supreme Court has maintained on previous occasions that there is no need for such benches outside Delhi.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why the Supreme Court is located in New Delhi?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Article 130</u></strong> of the Constitution of India reads- The <strong><u>Supreme Court shall sit in Delhi or in such other place or places</u></strong>, as the <strong><u>Chief Justice of India</u></strong> may, with the approval of the President, from time to time, appoint.</li>
<li>The law thus provides scope for setting up the Supreme Court in multiple places, subject to the concurrence of the CJI and the President.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who can establish the SC benches outside New Delhi?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court in <strong><u>Union of India v. S.P. Anand Verdict</u></strong><u> (2009)</u>, held that the Article vests exclusive discretionary powers on the matter with the Chief Justice of India.</li>
<li>It is an enabling provision and if the Chief Justice (after taking relevant factors into account) feels that the Court should sit elsewhere, s/he can seek the President’s approval for it.</li>
<li>No authority can compel the <strong><u>Chief Justice of India</u></strong> to act in a particular way under the Article.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Voices for circuit benches</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Law Commission in its 229th Report</u></strong> had suggested setting up a Constitution Bench of the Court in New Delhi and four other benches in different regions i.e., Northern region in Delhi, Southern region in Chennai/Hyderabad, Easter region in Kolkata and Western region in Mumbai.</li>
<li>However, this idea did not find favour with the Judges of the Supreme Court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Reasons for having Regional/Circuit Benches</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Access to Justice:</strong> Many litigants are discouraged to travel to Delhi from far away locations like south or northeast India.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Geographical Constraints:</strong> A disproportionately high number of cases filed in the Supreme Court originated in High Courts closer to Delhi. Hence coming up with regional benches will remove this constraint.</li>
<li><strong>Huge pendency of cases: </strong>Increased workload on the Supreme Court and at present more than 65,000 cases are pending in the Supreme Court, and disposal of appeals takes many years.</li>
<li><strong>Reducing Cost of Justice: </strong>It is observed that besides travelling to New Delhi, engaging expensive Supreme Court counsel to pursue a case is beyond the means of most litigants.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Advantages of having circuit courts</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Promotes Article 39A:</strong> It has been pointed out that Article 39A says that the state shall secure that the operation of the legal system promotes justice, on a basis of equal opportunity.</li>
<li><strong>Remove Geographical Constraints:</strong> It is high time we had more benches because in a country as vast as India the litigants have to travel long distances and spend a huge amount of money and energy.</li>
<li><strong>Upholding the spirit of the constitution:</strong> Setting up Benches outside Delhi would neither impair unity and integrity nor undermine the importance of the Supreme Court.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/plea-for-bench-of-supreme-court-chennai/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India’s first Dark Sky Reserve to come up in Ladakh</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-first-dark-sky-reserve-in-ladakh/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Dark Sky Reserve</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-631404" height="262" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 528px) 100vw, 528px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dark-sky-300x149.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dark-sky-300x149.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dark-sky.jpg 668w" width="528"/></p>
<p>In a first-of-its-kind initiative, the Department of Science &amp; Technology (DST) has announced the setting up of India’s first dark sky reserve at Hanle in Ladakh in the next three months.</p>
<h4>What is a Dark Sky Reserve?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A dark-sky reserve is an area, usually surrounding a park or observatory that is kept free of artificial light pollution.</li>
<li>The purpose of a dark sky preserve is generally to promote astronomy.</li>
<li>Because different national organizations have worked independently to create their programs, different terms have been used to describe the areas.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How is it designated?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A dark sky reserve is a designation given to a place that has policies in place to ensure that a tract of land or region has minimal artificial light interference.</li>
<li>The International Dark Sky Association is a US-based non-profit that designates sites as international dark sky places, parks, sanctuaries and reserves, depending on the criteria they meet.</li>
<li>Several such reserves exist around the world but none so far in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Dark Sky Reserve at Hanle</h4>
<ul>
<li>Hanle, which is about 4,500 metres above sea level, hosts telescopes and is regarded as one of the world’s most optimal sites for astronomical observations.</li>
<li>However, ensuring that the site remains well-suited for astronomy implies keeping the night sky pristine, or ensuring minimal interference to the telescopes from artificial light sources such as electric lights and vehicular lights from the ground.</li>
<li>The site will have activities to help in boosting local tourism and economy through interventions of science and technology.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em>The Himalayan Chandra Telescope, High Energy Gamma Ray Telescope, Major Atmospheric Cherenkov Experiment Telescope and GROWTH-India are the prominent telescopes located at the Hanle observatory.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4>Ideal conditions in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian Astronomical Observatory, the high-altitude station of the IIA, is situated to the north of Western Himalayas, at an altitude of 4,500 metres above mean sea level.</li>
<li>Located atop Mt. Saraswati in the Nilamkhul Plain in the Hanle Valley of Changthang, it is a dry, cold desert with sparse human population.</li>
<li>The cloudless skies and low atmospheric water vapour make it one of the best sites in the world for optical, infrared, sub-millimetre, and millimetre wavelengths.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-first-dark-sky-reserve-in-ladakh/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>ISRO tests system recoverable rocket ‘Inflatable Aerodynamic Decelerator (IAD)’</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/isro-tests-system-recoverable-rocket/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Inflatable Aerodynamic Decelerator (IAD)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-631403" height="208" sizes="(max-width: 422px) 100vw, 422px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reusable-300x148.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reusable-300x148.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reusable-768x378.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reusable.jpg 984w" width="422"/></p>
<p>The Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO) has successfully tested a technology that could aid the cost-effective recovery of spent rocket stages and safely land payloads on other planets.</p>
<h4>What is IAD?</h4>
<ul>
<li>IAD is a technique used for an <strong><u>atmospheric entry payload</u></strong>.</li>
<li>An <strong><u>inflatable envelope and an inflatant</u></strong> (anything that inflates the envelope, like air or helium) make up the inflatable aerodynamic decelerator.</li>
<li>While entering the atmosphere, it <strong><u>inflates like a balloon and decelerates the lander. </u></strong></li>
<li>The inflatant is designed to fill the inflatable envelope to a condition such that it surrounds the payload meant to enter the atmosphere of a planet or satellite and causes aerodynamic forces to slow it down.</li>
<li>In simpler words, IAD is designed to increase drag upon entering the atmosphere of any planetary body, like Earth, Mars, or even Moon.</li>
<li>Its shape is maintained by a closed, gas-pressured body and the inflatant gas is also generated internally. Some versions also use ram air or both.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How significant is this IAD?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Some space agencies, including NASA, have already successfully tested advanced versions of the technology, including the supersonic and hypersonic variants.</li>
<li>However, for near future missions of ISRO, the current version that it tested is perfect.</li>
<li>Its use was first proposed by NASA more than 50 years ago for planetary entries.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Minuscule of ISRO’s IAD</h4>
<ul>
<li>The IAD tested by ISRO was inflated at an <strong><u>altitude of around 84 km</u></strong> and the sounding rocket’s cargo dropped through the atmosphere on it.</li>
<li>It is fitted with a <strong><u>booster motor</u></strong>. It also has a <strong><u>spin rocket</u></strong> that is ejectable.</li>
<li>The inflatable structure is made out of <strong><u>Kevlar fabric</u></strong>, which is a very strong synthetic fibre and also heat resistant to withstand atmospheric pressure and temperature changes.</li>
<li>On top of it, it’s coated with <strong><u>polychloroprene</u></strong>, an oil and wax resistant rubber, to <strong><u>withstand extreme temperatures. </u></strong></li>
<li>In the inflation system, it <strong><u>uses compressed nitrogen</u></strong> stored in a bottle.</li>
<li>It has consistently <strong><u>decreased the payload’s velocity</u></strong> through <strong><u>aerodynamic drag</u></strong> while maintaining the expected trajectory during the test flight.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where does ISRO intend to use it?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The IAD will help ISRO in performing many space tasks effectively including recovery of spent stages of rockets, for landing payloads on missions to other planetary bodies.</li>
<li>This is the first instance where an IAD has been specially created for spent stage recovery.</li>
<li>So inter-planetary missions are certainly one aspect that ISRO wishes to explore.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/isro-tests-system-recoverable-rocket/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Untangling Kerala’s Lokayukta Amendment Controversy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/untangling-keralas-lokayukta-amendment-controversy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Lokpal and Lokayukta</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The Kerala Legislative Assembly passed the Kerala Lok Ayukta (Amendment) Bill on August 30, amid a boycott.</p>
<h4>Who are Lokpal-Lokayuktas?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Lokpal-Lokayukta issue has always generated intense debate in the country.</li>
<li>In fact, this term was <strong><u>first used</u></strong> in a report of the <strong><u>Administrative Reforms Commission </u></strong>headed by <strong><u>Morarji Desai</u></strong> as far back as in <strong><u>1966</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Political corruption had become rampant by then and it was thought that a credible system of an ombudsman should be established to redress public grievances against the leaders and public officials.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>first Bill on Lokpal</u></strong> was <strong><u>introduced in the Lok Sabha in 1968</u></strong> which <strong><u>lapsed</u></strong> with the dissolution of the House.</li>
<li><strong><u>Anna Hazare’s movement</u></strong> and the active involvement of civil society generated a lot of moral pressure on the Government which ultimately led to the <strong><u>passing of the Bill in 2013</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Composition of Lokpal</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Lokpal is no ordinary investigative body.</li>
<li>It is headed by the incumbent Chief Justice of India or a retired judge.</li>
<li>It has eight members, four of whom are judicial members.</li>
<li>Thus the whole system is studded with judges or judicial men.</li>
<li>The Lokpal has an inquiry wing and a prosecution wing to deal with investigation and prosecution, respectively.</li>
<li>The director of prosecution files the case in the special court based on the findings of the Lokpal.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who falls under the ambit of Lokpal?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Lokpal has jurisdiction to inquire into allegations of corruption against the Prime Minister, Ministers, Members of Parliament, Group A, B, C and D officers and officials of the central government.</li>
<li>After the conclusion of the investigation, the Lokpal may file a case in the special court in case the findings disclose the commission of offence under the Prevention of Corruption Act by the PM, Ministers or MPs.</li>
<li>However, the Lokpal does not have the power to ask the President to remove the Prime Minister or a Minister from office.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What about the states?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Lokpal and Lokayukta Act delegates the power to States to establish by law the Lokayukta to deal with complaints relating to corruption against public functionaries.</li>
<li>Some States already have established Lokayuktas. For example, Maharashtra in 1971, and Kerala in 1999.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the Keralan controversy?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In order to get a clearer perspective on the Kerala Lokayukta controversy, it is necessary to understand the scheme of the Lokpal and Lokayuktas Act enacted by Parliament.</li>
<li>The long title of the Act says: “An Act to provide for the establishment of a body of Lokpal for the Union and Lokayukta for States to inquire into allegations of corruption against certain public functionaries….”</li>
<li>Thus, the Lokpal is conceived of as a body which will inquire into allegations of corruption.</li>
<li>It is basically an investigative body whose task is to conduct prompt and fair investigation and the prosecution of cases of corruption.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with the Amendment</h4>
<ul>
<li>The amendments were related to the competent authority to consider Lok Ayukta recommendations.</li>
<li>In the case of any unfavourable <strong><u>decision from the Lok Ayukta against the CM, the competent authority will now be the Legislative Assembly instead of the Governor</u></strong> as is prescribed in the existing Act.</li>
<li>The amendment tries to <strong><u>take away at the powers of the Governor</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Lokayukta has indirectly expressed its resentment</u></strong> over the attempt to take away some of its powers.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Arguments by Kerala Government</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Government, on the other hand, claims that through the amendment, a provision in the original Act which is unconstitutional has been excised.</li>
<li>Earlier it gave power to the <strong><u>Lokayukta to give directions to the Governor to remove a CM</u></strong> or a Minister on being found guilty of corruption.</li>
<li>This meant that the Lokayukta was to be over and above the office of Governor.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Legal and constitutional implications</h4>
<p>Two important points need to be made here:</p>
<p><strong>(A) Overpowering the Lokpal</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>One, an investigative body does not have the legal authority to direct the public servant to resign his post on the basis of its findings.</li>
<li>It can only submit its findings to the competent authority or, as is provided in the Lokpal Act, file a case in the special court.</li>
<li>The Lokayukta is basically an investigative body with certain powers to carry out an investigation into cases relating to the Prevention of Corruption Act.</li>
<li>The only special feature of this body is that it is headed by a retired judge of the Supreme Court or a retired Chief Justice of a High Court.</li>
<li>But that does not alter the basic character of the Lokayukta as an investigative body.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(B) Compulsion on Governor</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Chief Minister or a Minister holds office during the pleasure of the Governor (Article 164).</li>
<li>The Constitution of India does not contemplate any external pressure on the Governor to withdraw his pleasure.</li>
<li>The Sarkaria Commission had suggested that the Governor can dismiss a Chief Minister only when he loses his majority in the Assembly and refuses to step down.</li>
<li>The Supreme Court has accepted this recommendation of the Sarkaria Commission.</li>
<li>Another occasion when the Governor could withdraw his pleasure is on account of CM having been convicted in a criminal case and sentenced to not less than two years of imprisonment.</li>
<li>In other words, a Chief Minister cannot be asked to resign when he enjoys a majority in the House.</li>
<li>The Governor, being a high constitutional authority, cannot be compelled by a law to act in a particular manner so far as his constitutional duties and functions are concerned.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Other contentious provisions</h4>
<p><strong>(1) Undue burden on Political Parties</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There are some other provisions as well which may not stand legal scrutiny.</li>
<li>For example, this law includes the office bearers of political parties within its definition of ‘public servant’.</li>
<li>Basically, the Prevention of Corruption Act deals with corruption in the government and allied agencies, statutory bodies, elected bodies, etc.</li>
<li>The functionaries of political parties do not come within the mischief of this law. So, it is difficult to understand how they can be brought within the sweep of the Lokayukta Act.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Reports of Lokayukta</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Another problematic provision in this law is the one which deals with the reports of Lokayukta (Section 12).</li>
<li>It says that the Lokayukta shall, on the allegation of corruption being substantiated, send the findings along with recommendation of action to the competent authority who is required to take action as recommended by the Lokayukta.</li>
<li>It further says that if the Lokayukta is satisfied by the action taken by the competent authority, he shall close the case.</li>
<li>The question is how the Lokayukta can close a corruption case which is a criminal case and which invites imprisonment for three to seven years.</li>
<li>The Lokpal files the case in the court after the investigation. There is no provision in the central law under which the Lokpal can close the case before it reaches the court.</li>
<li>The Lokayukta not being a court does not have the legal capacity to close the corruption case under any circumstances.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Kerala Lokayukta Act should be re-examined by a committee of the Assembly and should be brought on a par with the Lokpal Act.</li>
<li>Legislation that seeks to punish corrupt functionaries should be placed above controversies.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4><strong>Back2Basics: Lokpal Movement</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Lokpal, the apex body to inquire and investigate graft complaints against public functionaries, came into being with the appointment of its chairperson and members in March 2019.</li>
<li>In March 2019, former SC judge Justice Pinaki Chandra Ghose was selected as the first head of the Lokpal.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Lokpal and Lokayuktas Act, 2013</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Lokpal Act 2013 is anti-corruption legislation that seeks to provide for the establishment of the institution of Lokpal.</li>
<li>It seeks to inquire into allegations of corruption against certain important public functionaries including the PM, cabinet ministers, MPs, Group A officials of the Central Government, etc.</li>
<li>The Bill was introduced in the parliament following massive public protests led by anti-corruption crusader Anna Hazare and his associates.</li>
<li>The Bill is one of the most widely discussed and debated Bills in India in recent times.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Its history</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The term Lokpal was coined in 1963 by Laxmi Mall Singhvi, a member of parliament during a parliamentary debate about grievance mechanisms.</li>
<li>The Administrative Reforms Commission (ARC) headed by Morarji Desai submitted an interim report on “Problems of Redressal of Citizen’s Grievances” in 1966.</li>
<li>In this report, ARC recommended the creation of two special authorities designated as ‘Lokpal’ and ‘Lokayukta’ for a redress of citizens’ grievances.</li>
<li>Maharashtra was the first state to introduce Lokayukta through The Maharashtra Lokayukta and Upa-Lokayuktas Act in 1971.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/untangling-keralas-lokayukta-amendment-controversy/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>