<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 11:09:38 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Fruit Fly: Novel method to study Nuclear Matrix</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nuclear Matrix</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627770" height="489" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 566px) 100vw, 566px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly.jpg 665w" width="566"/></p>
<p>Now, using a novel method, Indian researchers have established a way of studying the nuclear matrix of the fruit fly (Drosophila melanogaster) without removing the nucleus from the embryo.</p>
<h4>Nuclear Matrix of fruit flies</h4>
<ul>
<li>Every cell that makes up an organism contains a copy of its genome.</li>
<li>This genome is packaged in special ways with the help of a structure known as the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>The nuclear matrix gives an organisation and architecture to the nucleus.</li>
<li>A familiar figure, the nuclear matrix of fruit flies, for instance, has been studied for many years, mainly by isolating it in nuclei that have been taken out from fruit fly embryos.</li>
<li>This allows comparative study of nuclear matrix in different cells within the embryo, giving a boost for fruit fly genetics.</li>
<li>Two of the most recent papers on this work have been published in the journals Nucleus and Molecular and Cell Proteomics.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What exactly is Nuclear Matrix?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The nuclear matrix is like a scaffolding.</li>
<li>Using biochemical means, if the nucleus is taken out and treated with an enzyme that digests all the DNA.</li>
<li>It is then washed with a solution of high salt concentration so that viable DNA proteins or protein-protein interactions are removed.</li>
<li>What is then left is a fibrous meshwork of proteins called the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>This is like a building from which all movables have been sucked out, leaving only the beams, ceiling, and walls, plug points, etc.</li>
<li>Analogous to the building, the nuclear matrix creates the architecture in which the genome is packaged.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why study them?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Studying the nuclear matrix is, therefore, very important to get a better picture of how precisely development progresses every time a new individual is born.</li>
<li>We have 220 different types of cells in the body, but all contain identical genomes.</li>
<li>The same genome sequence is present in neurons, where it works for thinking; in the liver, the same sequence enacts metabolism; and in the intestine, it works to digest.</li>
<li>So, this information is packaged differently in different cell types.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was Ramon Magsaysay of Philippines?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-ramon-magsaysay-of-philippines/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ramon Magsaysay</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-631406" height="237" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 350px) 100vw, 350px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay-300x203.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay-300x203.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay.jpg 637w" width="350"/></p>
<p>A leftist leader and former Kerala health minister has declined to receive the Ramon Magsaysay Award as the late President of the Philippines was known for his alleged brutality against the Communists.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lunched in 1958, the Ramon Magsaysay Award, widely considered to be Asia’s equivalent to the Nobel Prize, recognises outstanding leadership and communitarian contributions in Asia.</li>
<li>This year’s annual list of awardees was announced last week.</li>
<li>Shailaja was considered for the award for her performance as state health minister from 2016 to 2021, a period which saw Kerala fight against the Nipah virus and Covid-19.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who was Ramon Magsaysay?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Born on August 31, 1907 to a father who worked as a blacksmith and a mother who was a teacher, Ramon Del Fierro Magsaysay Senior was the seventh president of the Philippines, from 1953 until his death in an air crash in 1957.</li>
<li>Magsaysay started out as an automobile mechanic before being drafted into the Pacific War (1941-1945), during World War II.</li>
<li>The Pacific War would see the Japanese occupation of the Philippines — then a colony of the US — for nearly four years.</li>
<li>The US formally recognised the Philippines as an independent nation in 1946.</li>
</ul>
<h4>His legacy</h4>
<ul>
<li>As a guerrilla leader resisting the Japanese occupation, Magsaysay’s bravery and leadership saw his appointment as a military governor.</li>
<li>In 1946, he would be elected under the Liberal Party to the Philippine House of Representatives, where he would serve two terms as a Congressman before being appointed secretary of National Defence in 1950.</li>
<li>On December 30, 1953, he would be elected president from the Nationalist Party, the oldest political party in the Philippines.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Communism and Magsaysay</h4>
<ul>
<li>Founded in 1902, the Unión Obrera Democrática is considered the first modern trade federation in the Philippines.</li>
<li>The Communist Party of the Philippines or the Partido Komunista ng Pilipinas (PKP) was formed in 1930.</li>
<li>The Hukbong Bayan Laban sa Hapon or the People’s Army Against the Japanese, popularly known as the Hukbalahap (Huk), was a prominent guerrilla outfit that fought the Japanese.</li>
<li>As the country plunged into post-war chaos after 1946, the fortunes of the Hukbalahaps, too, changed dramatically.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How he rose to his fame?</h4>
<ul>
<li>With the expansion of capitalism, the gap between the rich and poor widened and the farmers continued to languish.</li>
<li>Huk leaders were viewed with suspicion over their declaration of commitment to communism and the demand for peasant rights.</li>
<li>With the US as its close ally, the Philippine government cracked down on the Huks, who formed an alliance with the PKP to take their struggle to a parliamentary platform.</li>
<li>The severe crackdown against the Huks continued until Magsaysay became the National Defence Secretary under President Elpidio Quirino.</li>
<li>Magsaysay drew upon his own experience of guerrilla warfare to initiate a two-pronged system of reforms and military campaigns.</li>
<li>It was under his administrative and military policies that the Huk threat was considered to be neutralised.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Ramon Magsaysay Award</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 1957, the Ramon Magsaysay award was set up by trustees of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund and the Philippine government to carry forward Magsaysay’s legacy of service to the people, good governance, and pragmatic idealism.</li>
<li>In the six decades since 1958 — the first year the Award was given out — over 300 organisations and individuals have been recognised for their developmental endeavours crucial to Asia, and, consequently, to the world.</li>
<li>The award is given out every year on August 31, on Magsaysay’s birth anniversary.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Indian winners on the list</h4>
<ul>
<li>Prominent Indians who have won the award include Vinoba Bhave in 1958, Mother Teresa in 1962, Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay in 1966, Satyajit Ray in 1967, Mahasweta Devi in 1997.</li>
<li>In recent years, Arvind Kejriwal (2006), Anshu Gupta of Goonj (2015), human rights activist Bezwada Wilson (2016), and journalist Ravish Kumar (2019) have won the award.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-ramon-magsaysay-of-philippines/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is a Triple-Dip La Nina?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-triple-dip-la-nina/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Triple Dip La-Nina</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="nina" class="alignnone wp-image-356942" height="197" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 444px) 100vw, 444px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/enso-300x133.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/enso-300x133.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/enso.jpg 708w" width="444"/></p>
<p>Parts of the world are expected to experience severe weather for the rest of the year and into 2023, as part of a rare “triple dip La Nina” event, according to the World Meteorological Organization (WMO).</p>
<h4><strong>El Nino and La Nina</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While El Niño (Spanish for ‘little boy’), the more common expression, is the abnormal surface warming observed along the eastern and central regions of the Pacific Ocean (the region between Peru and Papua New Guinea).</li>
<li>The La Niña (Spanish for ‘little girl’) is an abnormal cooling of these surface waters.</li>
<li>Together, the El Niño (Warm Phase) and La Niña (Cool Phase) phenomena are termed as El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO).</li>
<li>These are large-scale ocean phenomena which influence the global weather — winds, temperature and rainfall. They have the ability to trigger extreme weather events like droughts, floods, hot and cold conditions, globally.</li>
<li>Each cycle can last anywhere between 9 to 12 months, at times extendable to 18 months — and re-occur after every three to five years.</li>
<li>Meteorologists record the sea surface temperatures for four different regions, known as Niño regions, along this equatorial belt.</li>
<li>Depending on the temperatures, they forecast either as an El Niño, an ENSO neutral phase, or a La Niña.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> What is the “Triple-Dip” La Nina? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A “triple-dip” La Nina is a <strong><u>multiyear cooling of the surface temperature of the equatorial Pacific Ocean</u></strong>, which can cause droughts, fierce winds and heavy rainfall.</li>
<li>According to WMO, the current La Nina is projected to span three consecutive northern hemisphere winters. It began in September 2020.</li>
<li>If it continues for the next six months, it will be the first “triple-dip” La Nina event of the 21st century, WMO says.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How rare is this triple-dip?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is exceptional to have three consecutive years with a la Nina event.</li>
<li>Its cooling influence is temporarily slowing the rise in global temperatures – but it will not halt or reverse the long-term warming trend.</li>
<li>La Nina’s are usually preceded by El Nino, a weather pattern that warms the surface of the eastern tropical Pacific Ocean.</li>
<li>However, an El Nino event did not occur before the current La Nina.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Has it happened before? Will it happen again?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>La Nina’s occurred several times between 1903 to 2010 and 2010 to 2012.</li>
<li>This would be the first “triple-dip” La Nina this century.</li>
<li>However, it is not unprecedented for the weather pattern to last more than nine months to a year, which is typical for a La Nina.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Evaluating the likely impact</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the Indian context, La Nina is associated with good rainfall during the monsoon season.</li>
<li>This is the opposite of El Nino which is known to suppress monsoon rainfall.</li>
<li>Thus, a continued spell of La Nina could lead to expectation of another year of good, or normal, rainfall during the monsoon.</li>
<li>Until now, the monsoon season this year has produced 7% more rain compared to normal. Last year, the seasonal rainfall was almost 100%.</li>
<li>But, even though powerful, ENSO condition is only one of the several factors affecting monsoon rainfall in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Impact on rainfall</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is no one-on-one correlation between the ENSO condition and the amount of rainfall.</li>
<li>Also, the influence of ENSO is at a macro level.</li>
<li>There are wide variations in rainfall at the local level, which are getting exacerbated by climate change.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Differential impacts of this triple-dip event</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The continuance of La Nina further into 2023 is not bad news from the Indian standpoint. But it is not the same for many other regions where La Nina has very different impacts.</li>
<li>In most parts of the <strong><u>United States</u></strong>, for example, La Nina is associated with <strong><u>very dry winters</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In <strong><u>Australia and Indonesia</u></strong>, and generally in the tropical region, La Nina is expected to bring <strong><u>more rainfall.</u></strong></li>
<li>The <strong><u>excessive rainfall in Pakistan</u></strong>, which is experiencing its worst flooding disaster, can also be blamed in part on La Nina.</li>
<li>It said that the persistence of La Nina was most likely to result in a worsening of the <strong><u>drought in Africa</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is its climate change link?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Every</u></strong><u> <strong>unusual weather event these days is attributed to climate change</strong></u>, but science is not conclusive right now.</li>
<li>The occurrences of El Nino or La Nina are not very regular.</li>
<li>Sometimes they emerge every two years, at other times there has been a gap of even seven years.</li>
<li>Historical records do not go very far in the past.</li>
<li>As a result, the natural variability of ENSO is not understood very clearly.</li>
<li>And when the natural variability itself is not clear, the influence of global warming is difficult to quantify.</li>
<li>But there is clearer evidence of another kind of linkage with global warming.</li>
<li>During La Nina years, the colder surfaces allow the oceans to absorb more heat from the atmosphere.</li>
<li>Consequently, the air temperatures tend to go down, producing a cooling effect.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-triple-dip-la-nina/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Southwest Monsoon begins early Withdrawal/Retreat</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/monsoon-begins-early-withdrawal-retreat/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Retreat of Monsoon</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The southwest monsoon rainfall, 7% more than normal, has started to withdraw.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Monsoon Withdrawal/Retreat?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In India, retreating <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/various-terms-related-to-indian-monsoon/">monsoon</a> is the withdrawal of south-west monsoon winds from North India.</li>
<li>The withdrawal is gradual and takes about three months.</li>
<li>With the retreat of the monsoons, the clouds disappear and the sky becomes clear. The day temperature starts falling steeply.</li>
<li>Monsoon rains weaken all over India except few southeastern states.</li>
<li>It is helpful in Rabi crop cultivation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Factors affecting the retreat</strong></h4>
<p>Two predominant factors cause the phenomenon:</p>
<p><strong>(1) Land topography</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>First, the low mountain range in each region runs from north to south, shielding it from west-bound winds that trigger summer monsoon.</li>
<li>After summer, the range aids in the ‘orographic lift’ or rising of east-bound air mass from a lower to higher elevation, forming clouds and resulting in rain.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Atmospheric convection</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The second factor is atmospheric convection or vertical movement of air.</li>
<li>As the earth is heated by the sun, different surfaces absorb different amounts of energy and convection may occur where the surface heats up very rapidly.</li>
<li>As the surface warms, it heats the overlying air, which gradually becomes less dense than the surrounding air and begins to rise.</li>
<li>This condition is more favorable from September to February because of the role played by sea surface temperature or water temperature.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Immediate factors influencing withdrawal</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The withdrawal of the monsoon is based on meteorological conditions such as-</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Anti-cyclonic circulation (dry air that is the opposite of a cyclone)</li>
<li>Absence of rain in the past five days and</li>
<li>Dry weather conditions over the region</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>When does it occur?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The monsoon withdrawal is a long-drawn process and extends into mid-October, though the <strong><u>IMD considers September 30 to be the final day</u></strong> of the season over India.</li>
<li>The rain after that is categorised as “<strong><u>post-monsoon</u></strong>” rainfall.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ:</h4>
<p><strong>Q.The seasonal reversal of winds is the typical characteristic of:</strong></p>
<p>(a) Equatorial climate</p>
<p>(b) Mediterranean climate</p>
<p>(c) Monsoon climate</p>
<p>(d) All of the above climates</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="I4EHflyfgs"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/various-terms-related-to-indian-monsoon/">Various terms related to Indian Monsoon</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="I4EHflyfgs" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/various-terms-related-to-indian-monsoon/embed/#?secret=U6HYHuUCWH#?secret=I4EHflyfgs" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“Various terms related to Indian Monsoon” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/monsoon-begins-early-withdrawal-retreat/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Explained: Lumpy Skin Disease in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-lumpy-skin-disease-in-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Lumpy Skin Disease</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="lumpy" class="alignnone wp-image-638582 size-medium" height="251" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lumpy-300x251.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lumpy-300x251.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lumpy.jpg 523w" width="300"/></strong></p>
<p>The Mumbai Police have ordered the prohibition of cattle transportation in the city to prevent the spread of the lumpy skin disease (LSD).</p>
<h4><strong>What is the Lumpy Skin Disease?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Lumpy skin disease is caused by the lumpy skin disease <strong><u>virus</u></strong> (LSDV), which belongs to the genus capripoxvirus, a part of the poxviridae family.</li>
<li>Smallpox and monkeypox viruses are also a part of the same family.</li>
<li>The LSDV shares antigenic similarities with the sheeppox virus (SPPV) and the goatpox virus (GTPV) or is similar in the immune response to those viruses.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does it spread?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is <strong><u>not a zoonotic virus</u></strong>, meaning the disease <strong><u>cannot spread to humans</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It is a <strong><u>contagious vector-borne disease</u></strong> spread by vectors like mosquitoes, some biting flies, and ticks and usually affects host animals like cows and water buffaloes.</li>
<li>Infected animals shed the virus through oral and nasal secretions which may contaminate common feeding and water troughs.</li>
<li>Thus, the disease <strong><u>can either spread through direct contact</u></strong> with the vectors or through contaminated fodder and water.</li>
<li>Studies have also shown that it can spread through animal semen during artificial insemination.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does it affect the animal?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>LSD affects the lymph nodes of the infected animal, causing the nodes to enlarge and appear like lumps on the skin, which is where it derives its name from.</li>
<li>The cutaneous nodules, 2–5 cm in diameter, appear on the infected cattle’s head, neck, limbs, udder, genitalia, and perineum.</li>
<li>The nodules may later turn into ulcers and eventually develop scabs over the skin.</li>
<li>The other symptoms include high fever, sharp drop in milk yield, discharge from the eyes and nose, salivation, loss of appetite, depression, damaged hides, wasting of animals, infertility and abortions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Do it kills the animal?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The incubation period or the time between infection and symptoms is about 28 days according to the FAO, and 4 to 14 days according to some other estimates.</li>
<li>The morbidity of the disease varies between two to 45% and mortality or rate of date is less than 10%.</li>
<li>However, the reported mortality of the current outbreak in India is up to 15%, particularly in cases being reported in the western part (Rajasthan) of the country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the geographical distribution and how did it spread to India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The disease was <strong><u>first observed in Zambia</u></strong> in 1929.</li>
<li>Subsequently it got spread to most African countries, followed by West Asia, Southeastern Europe, and Central Asia, and more recently spreading to South Asia and China in 2019.</li>
<li>As per the FAO, the LSD disease is currently endemic in several countries across Africa, parts of the West Asia (Iraq, Saudi Arabia, Syrian Arab Republic), and Turkey.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Lumpy in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The spread in South Asia first affected Bangladesh in July 2019 and then reached India in August that year, with initial cases being detected in Odisha and West Bengal.</li>
<li>The long porous borders between India, Nepal and Bangladesh allow for a significant amount of bilateral and informal animal trade, including cattle and buffaloes.</li>
<li>This may have contributed to the spread of LSD in July-August 2019 between Bangladesh and India.</li>
<li>While the 2019 outbreak later subsided, the recent spread in India began in June this year.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Is it safe to consume the milk of affected cattle?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Studies say that it has <strong><u>not been possible to ascertain</u></strong> the presence of viable and infectious LSDV virus in milk derived from the infected animal.</li>
<li>However, that a large portion of the milk in Asia is <strong><u>processed</u></strong> after collection and is either <strong><u>pasteurised</u></strong> or boiled or dried in order to make milk powder.</li>
<li>This process ensures that the <strong><u>virus is inactivated</u></strong> or destroyed.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Economic implications of Lumpy on Dairy Sector</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Milk reduction:</strong> Lumpy leads to reduced milk production as the animal becomes weak and also loses appetite due to mouth ulceration.</li>
<li><strong>Animal wasting:</strong> The income losses can also be due to poor growth, reduced draught power capacity and reproductive problems associated with abortions, infertility and lack of semen for artificial insemination.</li>
<li><strong>Impact of trade ban:</strong> Movement and trade bans after infection also put an economic strain on the whole value chain.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why India is at higher risk?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India is the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/making-india-a-major-milk-exporting-nation/"><strong>world’s largest milk producer</strong></a> at about 210 million tonnes annually.</li>
<li>India also has the <strong><u>largest headcount of bovines</u></strong></li>
<li>In Rajasthan, which is witnessing the worst impact of LSD, it has led to reduced milk production, which lessened by about three to six lakh litres a day.</li>
<li>Reports indicate that milk production has also gone down in Punjab owing to the spread of the disease.</li>
<li>According to FAO, the disease threatens the livelihoods of smaller poultry farmers significantly.</li>
<li>Notably, farmers in Uttar Pradesh and Punjab have incurred losses due to cattle deaths and are seeking compensation from their State governments.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How bad is the current spread in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Lumpy has <strong><u>infected over 16 lakh cattle</u></strong> in 197 districts as of September 11.</li>
<li>Of the nearly 75,000 cattle that the disease has killed, more than 50,000 deaths, mostly cows, have been reported from Rajasthan.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Remedies available in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Union Ministry of Fisheries, Animal Husbandry and Dairying informed that the ‘<strong><u>Goat Pox Vaccine</u></strong>’ is very effective against LSD.</li>
<li>It is being used across affected States to contain the spread.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<p>The FAO has suggested a set of spread-control measures for LSD, which involves:</p>
<ul>
<li>Vaccination of susceptible populations with more than 80% coverage</li>
<li>Movement control of bovine animals and quarantining</li>
<li>Implementing biosecurity through vector control by sanitising sheds and spraying insecticides</li>
<li>Strengthening active and passive surveillance</li>
<li>Spreading awareness on risk mitigation among all stakeholders involved, and</li>
<li>Creating large protection and surveillance zones and vaccination zones</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-lumpy-skin-disease-in-india/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why only 2 firms chose Pre-Pack IBC resolution in a year?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pre-pack-ibc-resolution/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Pre-Packs, IBC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="pre-pack" class="alignnone wp-image-638581" height="335" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 574px) 100vw, 574px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pre-pack-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pre-pack-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pre-pack.jpg 652w" width="574"/></strong></p>
<p>India introduced the pre-packaged insolvency resolution process (PPIRP) in April 2021, as an alternative resolution process for micro, small and medium enterprises (MSMEs). However, it has only two cases admitted under it so far.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code (IBC)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The IBC was enacted in 2016 to simplify insolvency and bankruptcy proceedings, safeguard interests of all stakeholders (the firm, employees, debtors and especially creditors), and resolve non-performing assets.</li>
<li>From a ‘debtor in possession’ regime, it was a shift to a ‘creditor in control’ one.</li>
<li>IBC provides for a time-bound process for resolving insolvencies.</li>
<li>The Insolvency and Bankruptcy Board of India (IBBI) is the regulator implementing the code and overseeing the functioning of stakeholders.</li>
<li>The IBBI last week allowed payment of performance-linked incentives to resolution professionals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Pre-packs?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A pre-pack is the resolution of the debt of a distressed company through an agreement between secured creditors and investors instead of a public bidding process.</li>
<li>This system of insolvency proceedings has become an increasingly popular mechanism for insolvency resolution in the UK and Europe over the past decade.</li>
<li>Under the pre-pack system, financial creditors will agree to terms with a potential investor and seek approval of the resolution plan from the National Company Law Tribunal (NCLT).</li>
<li>The approval of a minimum of 66 percent of financial creditors that are unrelated to the corporate debtor would be required before a resolution plan is submitted to the NCLT.</li>
<li>Further NCLTs are also required to either accept or reject any application for a pre-pack insolvency proceeding before considering a petition for a corporate insolvency resolution process (CIRP).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does it work?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Unlike the CIRP, an informal understanding is reached with creditors before the application is filed.</li>
<li>PPIRP begins only after 66% of financial creditors approve the proposal and the name of resolution professional.</li>
<li>Debt resolution agreement between financial creditor and a potential investor is arrived at in consultation with the corporate debtor for which subsequent approval of the resolution plan is sought from the NCLT.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What were the objectives behind introducing PPIRP?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>MSMEs greatly contribute to the economy, and employ a wide section of the population.</li>
<li>The pandemic severely impacted their operations.</li>
<li>This alternative insolvency resolution process was designed to ensure quicker, cost-effective and value-maximizing outcomes for all.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the progress in PPIRP so far?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Only two insolvency cases have been initiated under PPIRP since it was introduced.</li>
<li>The poor response has been attributed to the hesitancy on the part of financial institutions.</li>
<li>In the case of CIRP, the haircut involved is a last resort, against a voluntary one in case of PPIRP.</li>
<li>Data shows that between December 2016 and June 2022, a total of 5,636 CIRPs commenced, of which 3,637 have been closed.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Does PPIRP defeat the purpose of IBC?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The IBC’s objective is to facilitate exit from failed units so that capital can be reallocated to better ones.</li>
<li>However, banks are not comfortable initiating PPIRP due to voluntary haircuts.</li>
<li>There is a fear that such a decision might be scrutinized later.</li>
<li>This means capital will remain locked up in failed units, defeating the purpose of IBC.</li>
<li>Voluntary haircuts mean fewer resources from the winding-up process and greater scope for corrupt practices.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pre-pack-ibc-resolution/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>More teeth and bigger muscles: ED’s lengthening arm</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/more-teeth-and-bigger-muscles-ed-lengthening-arm/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Enforcement Directorate (ED)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>Since the advent of the Modi government, the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-enforcement-directorate-ed-dreaded-nightmare-of-indian-politicians-businessmen/">ED – Enforcement Directorate</a> has gone after politicians/celebrities suspected of corruption with far greater prowess than other central law enforcement agencies.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Enforcement Directorate (ED)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It goes back to May 1, 1956, when an ‘<strong><u>Enforcement Unit</u>’</strong> was formed in the Department of Economic Affairs.</li>
<li>It then aimed for handling Exchange Control Laws violations under the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act (FERA).</li>
<li>The ED today is a <strong><u>multi-dimensional organisation</u></strong> investigating economic offences under the Prevention of Money Laundering Act (PMLA), Fugitive Economic Offenders Act, Foreign Exchange Management Act and FERA.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>From where does the ED get its powers?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When proceeds of crime (property/money) are generated, the best way to save that money is by parking it somewhere, so one is not answerable to anyone in the country.</li>
<li>Therefore, there was a need to control and prevent the laundering of money.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>PMLA</u></strong> was brought in for this exact reason in 2002, but was enacted only in 2005.</li>
<li>The objective was to prevent parking of the money outside India and to trace out the layering and the trail of money.</li>
<li>So as per the Act, the ED got its power to investigate under Sections 48 (authorities under act) and 49 (appointment and powers of authorities and other officers).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Roles and functions of the ED</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Summon, Search and seizure:</strong> The ED carries out search (property) and seizure (money/documents) after it has decided that the money has been laundered, under Section 16 (power of survey) and Section 17 (search and seizure) of the PMLA.</li>
<li><strong>Arrest and detentions:</strong> On the basis of that, the authorities will decide if an arrest is needed as per Section 19 (power of arrest).</li>
<li><strong>Attachment of property:</strong> Under Section 50, the ED can also directly carry out search and seizure without calling the person for questioning. It is not necessary to summon the person first and then start with the search and seizure.</li>
<li><strong>Filing of chargesheet:</strong> If the person is arrested, the ED gets 60 days to file the prosecution complaint (chargesheet) as the punishment under PMLA doesn’t go beyond seven years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>At what stage does the ED step in when a crime is committed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Whenever any offence is registered by a local police station, which has generated proceeds of crime <strong><u>over and above ₹1 crore</u></strong>, the investigating police officer forwards the details to the ED.</li>
<li>Alternately, <strong><u>if the offence comes under the knowledge of the Central agency</u></strong>, they can then call for the First Information Report (FIR) or the chargesheet if it has been filed directly by police officials.</li>
<li>This will be done to find out if any laundering has taken place.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>PMLA, the ED’s sword arm</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ED’s aggression has been largely on leveraging the massive powers bestowed on the agency by the Prevention of Money Laundering Act (PMLA), 2002.</li>
<li>PMLA, 2002 is an Act of the Parliament of India enacted by the NDA government to prevent money laundering and to provide for the confiscation of property derived from money laundering.</li>
<li>It was enacted in response to India’s global commitment (including the Vienna Convention) to combat the menace of money laundering.</li>
<li>PMLA and the Rules notified there under came into force with effect from July 1, 2005.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How is PMLA going increasingly stringent?</strong></h4>
<p>The PMLA’s ambit was widened through amendments in 2009, 2013, 2015, and 2019, giving the ED the teeth it now has.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Broader jurisdiction for investigation:</strong> In 2009, ‘criminal conspiracy’ under Section 120B of the Indian Penal Code was added to the PMLA’s schedule among various other offences. This has, over the years, allowed the ED to enter any case where a conspiracy is alleged — even if the principal offence is not part of the PMLA schedule. In 2009, the ED also got international jurisdiction as far as tracking laundered money was concerned.</li>
<li><strong>Immediate attachment of property:</strong> Following amendments in 2015 and 2018, the ED was allowed to attach properties in India equivalent to properties acquired abroad through laundered money. Through certain “explanations” inserted into the PMLA in 2019, the government allowed the ED to attach properties earned directly or indirectly through alleged criminal activity that was even “relatable” to a scheduled offence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why ED mostly grips Politicians?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Exposing rampant corruption:</strong> It is not always ironic to say that most politicians are never corrupt. We have a very inglorious past of political corruption.</li>
<li><strong>Selective witch-hunt:</strong> The ED has often been attacked for initiating investigations, raiding and questioning leaders of opposition parties, be it under the current regime or under past governments.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues with PMLA</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Misuse of central agencies:</strong> PMLA is being pulled into the investigation of even ordinary crimes by the Enforcement Directorate.</li>
<li><strong>Seizing of assets:</strong> Assets of genuine victims have been attached. The ED could just walk into anybody’s house.</li>
<li><strong>Politically motivated raids:</strong> In all this, the fundamental purpose of PMLA to investigate the conversion of “illegitimate money into legitimate money” was lost.</li>
<li><strong>Opacity of charges:</strong> Petitioners pointed out that even the Enforcement Case Information Report (ECIR) – an equivalent of the FIR – is considered an “internal document” and not given to the accused.</li>
<li><strong>Vagueness over evidence:</strong> The accused is called upon to make statements that are treated as admissible in evidence.</li>
<li><strong>Harassment:</strong> The ED begins to summon accused persons and seeks details of all their financial transactions and of their family members.</li>
<li><strong>Against individual liberty:</strong> The initiation of an investigation by the ED has consequences that have the potential of curtailing the liberty of an individual.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Allegations against ED</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Huge discretions:</strong> The ED is the only Central agency in the country that does not require permission from the government to summon or prosecute politicians or government functionaries for committing economic offences like money laundering.</li>
<li><strong>Used for petty crimes:</strong> PMLA is pulled into the investigation of even “ordinary” crimes and assets of genuine victims have been attached.</li>
<li><strong>Actual purpose denigrated: </strong>PMLA was a comprehensive penal statute to counter the threat of money laundering, specifically stemming from the trade in narcotics.</li>
<li><strong>Violations of Rights:</strong> PMLA was enacted in response to India’s global commitment to combat the menace of money laundering. Instead, rights have been “cribbed, cabined and confined”.</li>
<li><strong>Functional opacity:</strong> There is also a lack of clarity about ED’s selection of cases to investigate. We often see ED raiding houses of opposition parties suddenly.</li>
<li><strong>Poor rate of conviction:</strong> We have hardly read the conclusion of cases by ED. Meantime media-trial tears off the accused person’s credibility which is the most desired intent.</li>
<li><strong>Under-trials and slower prosecution</strong>: ED has been focusing on keeping the accused in custody rather than actually proving the charges against them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges to ED</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>ED being dragged to court:</strong> The petitions against the ED had the effect of slowing down the investigations, as officers have to defend themselves in court.</li>
<li><strong>Foul crying politicians:</strong> There are attempts to cover up unexplained, high-value transactions that fall within the PMLA’s ambit</li>
<li><strong>Investigation of foreign transactions:</strong> Getting information on accounts and money stashed abroad to establish a trail is the biggest challenge they face.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The fight against corruption is intimately linked with the reform of the investigations.</li>
<li>Therefore the adjudicating authorities must work in cooperation and ensure the highest standards of transparency and fairness.</li>
<li>ED has been walking a tightrope to safeguard its integrity by speeding up investigations and court procedures.</li>
<li>The need of the hour could be systemic fixes—and not shrill calls to throw the baby out with the bathwater.</li>
<li>It is unlikely that corruption can be substantially reduced without modifying the way government agencies operate.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/more-teeth-and-bigger-muscles-ed-lengthening-arm/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Donations to recognised Political Parties come under EC lens</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/donations-recognised-political-parties-come-under-ec-lens/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with Political Funding</p></div></div><p>The Election Commission’s ongoing drive to clean up the electoral space has now gone beyond RUPPs (<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vacant-offices-unaware-office-bearers-curious-case-of-delisted-parties/">registered unrecognised political parties</a>) to cover recognised national and State parties.</p>
<h4>What is Political Funding?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Political Funding implies the methods that political parties use to raise funds to finance their campaign and routine activities.</li>
<li>A political party needs money to pitch itself, its objectives, and its intended actions to get votes for itself. (<a href="http://www.drbrambedkarcollege.ac.in/sites/default/files/UNIT-2_PART-5_CORPORATE%20FUNDING%20OF%20POLITICAL%20PARTIES.pdf" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Reference</a>)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why need political funding?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Across the world, political parties need access to money in order to reach out to the electorate, explain their policies and receive inputs from people.</li>
<li>And in order to do the same, parties resort to political party funding.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Generally who makes these funding?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Individuals:</strong> One of the primary sources of this funding is voluntary contributions made by individuals.</li>
<li><strong>Corporates:</strong> Besides this, corporates pay hefty donations to parties in different forms.</li>
<li><strong>Foreign aid:</strong> This is yet another source but highly controversial.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Statutory Provisions</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Section 29B of the Representation of the People Act (RPA)</u></strong> entitles parties to accept voluntary contributions by any person or company, except a Government Company.</li>
<li><strong><u>Section 29C of the RPA mandates political parties to declare donations</u></strong> that exceed 20,000 rupees. Such a declaration is made by making a report and submitting the same to the EC. Failure to do so on time disentitles a party from tax relief under the Income Tax Act, 1961.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Methods used by Indian Political Parties</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li><strong>Individual Persons:</strong> Section 29B of RPA allows political parties to receive donations from individual persons.</li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<ol start="2">
<li><strong>State/Public Funding:</strong> Here, the government provides funds to parties for election related purposes. State Funding is of two types:</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>Direct Funding:</strong> The government provides funds directly to the political parties. Direct funding by tax is prohibited in India.</li>
<li><strong>Indirect Funding:</strong> It includes other methods except direct funding, like free access to media, free access to public places for rallies, free or subsidized transport facilities. It is allowed in India in a regulated manner.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<ol start="3">
<li><strong>Corporate Funding:</strong> In India, donations by corporate bodies are governed under the Companies Act, 2013. Section 182 of the Act provides that:</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>A company needs to be at least three years old to be able to donate to a political party.</li>
<li>Companies can donate up to 7.5% of average net profits made during three simultaneous preceding financial years. (Now removed after Finance Act, 2017)</li>
<li>Such contributions must be disclosed in the company’s profit and loss account. (Removed)</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<ol start="4">
<li><strong>Electoral Trusts:</strong> A non-profit company created in India for orderly receipt of voluntary contributions from any person like an individual or a domestic company.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>According to the Election Commission Guidelines, all electoral trusts formed after January 2013 are required to declare details of the money received and disbursed.</li>
<li>The Central Government rules mandate these firms to donate 95% of their total income to registered political parties in a financial year.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with Political Funding</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Money laundering:</strong> One of the biggest disadvantages of the corporate funding is the use of fake companies to route black money.</li>
<li><strong>Influence of contributor:</strong> Influence of people and companies over political parties to which they provide funds.</li>
<li><strong>Election malpractices:</strong> There are various gaps in Indian rules, the benefit of which political parties take to avoid any kind of reporting.</li>
<li><strong>Money politics:</strong> Hidden sources of funding lead to more spending of funds in election campaigns, thus impacting the economy of the country.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Recent steps taken</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>FCRA Reforms:</strong> In March, 2018, the government passed a key amendment to the Foreign Contribution Regulation Act, 2010 allowing foreign companies to fund political parties in India.</li>
<li><strong>Electoral Bonds Schemes:</strong> The government notified the Electoral Bond Scheme on 2nd January, 2018 to establish and cleanse the system of political funding in the country.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Electoral Bond Scheme?</h4>
<ul>
<li>An electoral bond is a bearer instrument like a Promissory Note.</li>
<li>It can be purchased by any citizen of India or a body incorporated in India to donate to the political party of their choice.</li>
<li>Donor’s name is not there on the bond.</li>
<li>These bonds can be used for making donations to the political parties registered under Section 29A of the RP Act, 1951.</li>
<li>The party should have secured not less than one per cent of the votes polled in the last general election to the Lok Sabha or a Legislative Assembly.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with the scheme</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Opaque funding:</strong> While the identity of the donor is captured, it is not revealed to the party or public. So transparency is not enhanced for the voter.</li>
<li><strong>No IT break:</strong> Also income tax breaks may not be available for donations through electoral bonds. This pushes the donor to choose between remaining anonymous and saving on taxes.</li>
<li><strong>No anonymity for donors:</strong> The privacy of the donor is compromised as the bank will know their identity.</li>
<li><strong>Differential benefits:</strong> These bonds will help any party that is in power because the government can know who donated what money and to whom.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<p>Former Chief Election Commissioner SY Quraishi has suggested an alternative worth exploring:</p>
<ul>
<li>A National Electoral Fund to which all donors can contribute.</li>
<li>The funds would be allocated to political parties in proportion to the votes they get.</li>
<li>Not only would this protect the identity of donors, it would also weed out black money from political funding.</li>
<li>There can be a tax benefit for those who donate to the fund.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4>Try this question from our AWE Initiative</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="ihyxvccakT"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/q-2-examine-the-issues-with-political-funding-in-india-how-far-has-the-introduction-of-electoral-bonds-succeeded-in-dealing-with-the-issues-with-political-funding-10-marks/">Q.2) Examine the issues with political funding in India. How far has the introduction of electoral bonds succeeded in dealing with the issues with political funding? (10 marks)</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="ihyxvccakT" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/q-2-examine-the-issues-with-political-funding-in-india-how-far-has-the-introduction-of-electoral-bonds-succeeded-in-dealing-with-the-issues-with-political-funding-10-marks/embed/#?secret=Wm8HVXEafF#?secret=ihyxvccakT" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“Q.2) Examine the issues with political funding in India. How far has the introduction of electoral bonds succeeded in dealing with the issues with political funding? (10 marks)” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/donations-recognised-political-parties-come-under-ec-lens/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The heavy rainfall and the crazy Banglore flood: A case to study</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/flood/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>urban floods mitigation</p></div></div><h4><img alt="flood" class="alignnone wp-image-638490" height="321" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734.jpg 1600w" width="570"/>Context</h4>
<ul>
<li>The recent events of heavy downpours in short period of time and the recent example of Banglore flood, highlights how cities in India and elsewhere need to adapt to climate change as it brings more extreme rainfall in the future.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is heavy downpour?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A downpour or cloudburst is a sudden and unexpected heavy fall of rain.</li>
<li>It is usually local in nature and of brief duration. Most so-called cloudbursts occur in connection with thunderstorms.</li>
<li>Heavy downpour in short period causes flood, damage to buildings and infrastructure can disrupt transport, communications and connectivity, loss of crops and livestock.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The heavy rainfall and the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/floods/">Banglore flood</a> causes </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rise in built up area: </strong>Lakes and natural depressions may not always fill up during many monsoons so the people who are unaware of hydrology tempts to build and buy in the catchment areas of water-bodies, which will be disastrous when it rains heavily as there is rise in the quantity.</li>
<li><strong>Water-logging: </strong>rainwater and sewage water are forced to build up, which results in water-logging. The highway acts as a dam for the water ,Garbage frequently clogs drains, which limits the flow of sewage, and they are too small to support the weight of the expanding population.</li>
<li><strong>Physical shrinkage of water-bodies</strong>: Destruction of lakes is a major issue .lakes can store the excess water and regulate the flow of water however the pollution of natural water bodies and converting them for development purposes has increased the risks of floods<strong>. </strong>Unplanned growth, Rise in population<strong>, </strong>rise in the built up areas along streams, canals, around the lakes, leaving no storage capacity.</li>
<li><strong>Compromised runoff potential and health hazards</strong>: Choked and encroached drains and lakes, ill designed infrastructure and missing pipes compromising run off potential. Not only the physical quantity of the runoff that poses a hazard. When polluted drains and lakes overflow, the flood can pose a health hazard especially to vulnerable and exposed marginal communities living in informal settlements.</li>
<li><strong>Zero or limited ability to allow infiltration of water: </strong>Encroachments in and around wetlands and green lands harming the natural way of water infiltration and ground water recharge.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of vision in rain water harvesting: </strong>Ignorance towards the tradition rain water harvesting techniques and no or limited vision for creating new systems of rain water harvesting. Exceptionally heavy monsoon rains have been exacerbated by poor urban planning in the Indian tech hub, showing the need for improved water systems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="flood" class="alignnone wp-image-638492" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 641px) 100vw, 641px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/deccan-Herald-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/deccan-Herald-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/deccan-Herald.jpg 708w" width="641"/>What are the reasons behind the frequent floods in urban areas?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Meteorological factors</strong>: change in the weather patterns, increase in the temperature leading to heavy rainfall, sudden downpour, cloudburst, thunderstorms, hailstorms etc.</li>
<li><strong>Hydrological factors</strong>: Natural surface infiltration rate, soil moisture level, presence or absence of Overbank flows, Presence of impervious cover, the occurrence of high tides impeding the drainage in coastal cities.</li>
<li><strong>Man-Made factors: </strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Unplanned urbanization: </strong>Unplanned settlement is one of the main cause of urban flooding. Blocking of natural drainage pathways through construction activity and encroachment on catchment areas, streams, rivers, lakebeds. Reduced infiltration and ground water recharge of water, destruction of lakes, Land-use changes (e.g. surface sealing due to urbanization, deforestation) increase runoff and sedimentation. Inefficiency or non-maintenance of infrastructure etc.</li>
<li><strong>Outdated Drainage systems</strong>: The old and ill-maintained drainage system is one of the main factor making cities in India vulnerable to flooding</li>
<li><strong>Encroachments on and around water-bodies: </strong>Illegal Habitations started growing into towns and cities alongside rivers and watercourses. As a result of this, the capacity of the natural drains has decreased, resulting in flooding.</li>
<li><strong>Climate Change: </strong>Climate change due to various anthropogenic events has led to extreme weather events, increasing temperature which resulting in heavy rainfall in one part while drought and dry spells in other.</li>
<li><strong>Poor Solid Waste Management System:</strong> Indiscriminate disposal of solid waste, poor waste management system, clogging drains because of accumulation of non-biodegradable wastes are major concerns. Domestic, commercial and industrial waste and dumping of it into the drains also contribute significantly to reducing their capacities.</li>
<li><strong>Reduced Seepage:</strong> use of hard and non-porous construction material making the soil impervious, reducing the seepage capability in no of cities in India.</li>
<li><strong>Weak Implementation and lack of awareness:</strong>Even with provisions of rainwater harvesting, sustainable urban drainage systems, etc, in regulatory mechanisms like the Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA), adoption at user end as well as enforcement agencies remains weak.</li>
<li><strong>No Community Participation:</strong>Flood control measures planned without participation of the affected community are unsustainable as they do not meet the needs of relevant stakeholders.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to prevent the urban floods and prevent losses?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Developing climate Resilient Infrastructure:</strong> using permeable material for roads and pavement, green roofs and harvesting systems in buildings. To reduce the burden of road infrastructure in cities Outer Ring Road should be explored. Innovative approaches like Sponge Cities wetland restoration, flushing systems using collected rooftop water, public spaces as flexible water retention facilities can be applied to Indian urban areas.</li>
<li><strong>Use of technology in Early Warning Systems and Communication: </strong>Early-warning systems using sensors across waterbodies and drains, and a network of communication for hotspots of emerging flood risk in the wet-season should be put in place. Providing real-time data where traditional systems fail. Tools such as predictive precipitation modelingcan help do that and are also able to link it with the adaptive capacity of urban land use.</li>
<li><strong>Proper management and regular upgrade of Urban Drainage System:</strong> drains need to be cleaned on a regular basis to permit the free flow of water .Proper management of the drainage system is necessary to ensure that the water does not get stored in one place. Watershed management and emergency drainage plan should be clearly enunciated in policy.</li>
<li><strong>Rainwater Harvesting</strong>: It will serve the twin purposes of lowering the peak runoff and raising the groundwater table. Many municipal corporations in India have already made rainwater harvesting compulsory<strong>. </strong></li>
<li><strong>Conservation of Water Bodies: </strong>Urban water bodies like lakes, tanks, and ponds also play a very important role in the management of urban flooding by reducing the flood water run-off by capturing it.</li>
<li><strong>Holistic approach: </strong>Improved monitoring, forecasting, and decision-support systems. Find out the different method for improving the preparedness for urban flooding.</li>
<li><strong>Responsibility on every stakeholder: </strong>Locally, citizens, local ward officials and staff will need to work together to minimize dumping of solid waste and garbage in storm-water drains. As this is a socio –political problem, public participation awareness and responsibility of citizen is the need of the hour. To develop a long-lasting solution, all parties must acknowledge the issues and adopt a thorough strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What we as citizens can do on a personal level to prevent the urban environment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Raising voice at all available forums and platforms</li>
<li>Making politicians and bureaucrats accountable</li>
<li>Refuse to buy a house in the encroached lands.</li>
<li>Applying methods of rain water harvesting on individual level.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Exceptionally heavy monsoon rains have been exacerbated by poor urban planning in the Indian tech hub, showing the need for improved water systems.</li>
<li>Urbanization is a global and inevitable process, and with cities as engines of the economy, built-up areas will continue to grow. But we need to draw upon these experiences and the growing perils of climate change and extreme rain events and change course.</li>
<li>According to UN projections, by 2050 more than 68% of the world’s population could be concentrated in urban areas.</li>
<li>In this context, resilience-based strategies should be adopted to improve the capacity to handle the crisis arising out of climate change.</li>
<li>Wetlands are the kidneys of the earth, let’s keep it healthy.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What are the factors causing flood in the urban cities? What are the measures to prevent the urban flooding keeping in mind the sustainable development? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/flood/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Multilateralism will open pandora of opportunities for India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/multilateralism/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>SCO and QUAD</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>multilateralism</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="multilateralism" class="alignnone wp-image-638494" height="399" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 599px) 100vw, 599px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/brics-621x414-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/brics-621x414-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/brics-621x414-1.jpg 621w" width="599"/>Context</strong></h4>
<p>India may give up its strategic balancing of China and West if the Ukraine war weakens Russia. Because for major defence supplies India is dependent on Russia.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/growing-salience-of-multilateralism/"><strong>What is the concept of multilateralism?</strong></a></p>
<ul>
<li>Process of organizing relations between groups of three or more states. Beyond that basic quantitative aspect, multilateralism is generally considered to comprise certain qualitative elements or principles that shape the character of the arrangement or institution.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is SCO?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Shanghai Cooperation Organization (SCO) is a Eurasian political, economic and security organization.</li>
<li><strong>Global share:</strong> In terms of geographic scope and population, it is the world’s largest regional organization, covering approximately 60% of the area of Eurasia, 40% of the world population, and more than 30% of global GDP.</li>
<li><strong>Members</strong>: The SCO currently comprises eight Member States. They are- China, India, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Russia, Pakistan, Tajikistan and Uzbekistan.</li>
<li><strong>Headquarters</strong>: Beijing, China.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is QUAD?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (QSD), commonly known as the Quad.</li>
<li>It is a strategic security dialogue.</li>
<li><strong>Members</strong>: Australia, India, Japan, and the United States.</li>
<li><strong>Origin</strong>: The dialogue was initiated in 2007.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="multilateralism" class="alignnone wp-image-638498" height="562" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 538px) 100vw, 538px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-287x300.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-287x300.jpeg 287w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-978x1024.jpeg 978w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-768x804.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-860x900.jpeg 860w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2.jpeg 1200w" width="538"/>Which factors forced India to have more engagements with QUAD?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Chinese threat has been largely responsible in shaping New Delhi’s Indo Pacific Policy.</li>
<li>The China’s Belt and Road initiative and the growing China’s presence in India’s neighborhood- as evident from China’s investment not only in Pakistan and Myanmar, but also in Nepal and Sri Lanka. Because of such activities India felt encircled.</li>
<li>The very launch of the QUAD initiative was the reaction to China’s assertiveness in the Indo Pacific region.</li>
<li>India agreed to upgrade the quad meeting at the ministerial level only after the gunmen attack of 2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How India is maintaining balance between the West and China-Russia Alliance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Plurilateralism</strong>: India continued to believe in <strong>plurilateralism</strong>, a doctrine elucidated by external affairs Minister S Jaishankar in his book <strong>‘The Indian Way</strong>’.</li>
<li><strong>Member of both QUAD and SCO</strong>: Along with QUAD, India also took membership of SCO. It means India dealing with the USA and Japan on one side and Russia and China on the other.</li>
<li><strong>Simultaneously dealing with many powers: </strong>India is engaging with competing powers like the USA, China, the EU or Russia at the same time.</li>
<li><strong>Multipolar world: </strong>India stands in favor of a <strong>multipolar world</strong> where the plurality of power centers would allow her to play one pole against the other. In this context, New Delhi wants Russia to remain an important player.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="multilateralism" class="alignnone wp-image-638500" height="353" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 602px) 100vw, 602px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-300x176.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-300x176.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1.jpg 637w" width="602"/><br/>
What are India’s concerns regarding the West created world order?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The stand on Multilateralism goes together with India’s reservations (not being completely satisfied) against the West’s past hegemony and the international orders that were established after 1945.</li>
<li>MEA S Jaishankar emphasises that the West has imposed norms on the world that need to be dismantled. He says, “The key of western durability till now is the set of institutions and practices that it progressively but firmly established in the period of its dominance”.</li>
<li>The world order and the institutions are created and supported by the West by narratives that serve the West well, while diminishing its competitors.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the steps taken by India to deal with the West created world order and institutions ?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s engagement with the other regional organizations like BRICS, SCO, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Doctrine of Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam: </strong>India’s foreign policy has been based on the philosophy of Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam.</li>
<li><strong>UN Reforms:</strong> Efforts towards bringing reforms in the UNs.</li>
<li><strong>Shift from Non-Alignment to Multi-Alignment:</strong> Multi-alignment is the very essence of India’s foreign policy and the economic policy of India today. Promotion of multilateralism by engaging with many poles simultaneously.</li>
<li><strong>Various Multilateral initiatives: </strong>India has taken the lead in promoting various multilateral initiatives like International Solar Alliance, proposing CCIT for combating terrorism, Asia-Africa Growth corridor.</li>
<li><strong>Collaborating with Like-minded Countries: </strong>India could work closely with the <strong>Alliance for Multilateralism </strong>(an initiative launched by Germany and France) to shape both the alliance itself and the reform agenda at large.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is Russia important for India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Military supplies</strong>: India is heavily dependent on Russia for its military supplies with more than two-third of its weapons coming from Russia. For example: S-400 is the recent supply to India by Russia.</li>
<li><strong>Balancing China:</strong> Russia is important for India to balance China. More isolation of Russia may push Russia closer to China.</li>
<li><strong>To promote multilateralism</strong>: To maintain multilateral world order Russia is a major player or partner for India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A multilateral world order with power decentralized between all the regions and all the economic strata is critical for any sustainable model of peace and prosperity to be gained. The UN and similar bodies must recognize the need of the hour and must reform or else they will perish in yet another set of protectionism, distrust, and possible large-scale military conflicts like Russia- Ukraine.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What are the concerns of India regarding the present world order created by the West? </strong><strong>How can India promote multilateralism by playing a balancing role between the QUAD and the SCO?  What is the importance of Russia for India in the present global situation? Explain.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/multilateralism/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>On reservations for disempowered Dalit Christians and Muslims, a question of government’s intent</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dalit/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>social justice</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="dalit" class="alignnone wp-image-638560" height="367" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 551px) 100vw, 551px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1457603210-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1457603210-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1457603210.jpeg 555w" width="551"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Union government intends to appoint a national commission to study the status of Dalits (ex “untouchable” castes) belonging to the Muslim and Christian communities. Aim of study to check the socio-economic condition of Muslims and Christian Dalits on par with Hindu, Sikh, Buddhist Dalits.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Current reservation policy</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At present, scheduled caste reservation is applicable only to schedule caste (Dalit) belongs to Hindu, Sikh, Buddhist. Currently it is unavailable for schedule caste belongs to Muslims and Christians.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why Muslim and Christian Dalit needs reservation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2008 review-study commissioned by the National Commission of Minorities (NCM) and housed in the Sociology Department of <a href="https://indianexpress.com/section/cities/delhi/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Delhi</a> The remit of the study was to conduct a comprehensive review of already existing social-scientific evidence that might offer answers to three questions.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>What is the contemporary status of Dalit Muslims (DMs) and Dalit Christians (DCs) in terms of their material well-being and social status?</li>
<li>How does their situation compare with that of: a) non-Dalits of their own communities, and b) Dalits of other communities?</li>
<li>Do the caste disabilities suffered by these groups justify state intervention?</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong><img alt="dalit" class="alignnone wp-image-638564" height="308" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 547px) 100vw, 547px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537.jpg 777w" width="547"/>What were the findings of study?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The study reviewed two main kinds of available evidence, ethnographic-descriptive and macro-statistical, in addition to semi-academic NGO reports and publications.</li>
<li>The survey of ethnographic materials began with the finding that the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-caste-system/">existence of caste divisions</a> – including the presence of ex-untouchable castes recognised as such – among both Muslims and Christians – was beyond dispute.</li>
<li>DMs and DCs were identified and segregated much like their counterparts in the Hindu or Sikh communities.</li>
<li>Evidence was tabulated on five forms of caste-based social discrimination – the practice untouchability; enforced ban on inter-marriage; occupational segregation; social and cultural segregation and finally, economic discrimination.</li>
<li>The most common instances were separate mosques or churches (or hierarchically segregated seating); separate burial grounds; strict prohibition on inter-marriage with very severe punishments (sometimes extending to murder) for breaking this taboo; and general avoidance of social interaction and cooperation.</li>
<li>The main findings were that DMs are clearly the worst off among all Dalits, while DCs are somewhat better off than other Dalits except Sikh Dalits (who are by far the best off, especially in the rural sector).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why DMs and DCs doesn’t have reservation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The courts accept that “caste survives conversion” but complain about the lack of reliable data. No recognition, no data; no data, no recognition.</li>
<li>Informal guesstimates (based on the 2001 Census and the 2004-05 NSSO survey) place the proportion of DMs at 1 per cent or less of the Muslim population, and DCs as anything between 40-50 per cent of the Christian population of India.</li>
<li>As per the 2011 Census, Muslims are 14.2 per cent and Christians 2.3 per cent of our population. Taken together, DMs and DCs are likely to form less than 2 per cent of the total Dalit population of India, more than 90 per cent of which is Hindu.</li>
<li>According to experts Adding DMs and DCs will not rock the boat of reservation, since the increment will be roughly one-fifth of the 10 per cent reservation readily granted to the upper castes as the Economically Weaker Sections.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What efforts have been made to include Muslims and Christians of Dalit origin among SCs?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>After 1990, a number of Private Member’s Bills were brought in Parliament for this purpose.</li>
<li>In 1996, a government Bill called The Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Orders (Amendment) Bill was drafted, but in view of a divergence of opinions, the Bill was not introduced in Parliament.</li>
<li>Then government headed by PM Manmohan Singh set up two important panels:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Ranganath Misra Commission:</strong> The National Commission for Religious and Linguistic Minorities, popularly known as the Ranganath Misra Commission, in October 2004 and</li>
<li><strong>Sachar Committee:</strong> A seven-member high-level committee headed by former Chief Justice of Delhi High Court Rajinder Sachar to study the social, economic, and educational condition of Muslims in March 2005.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What did they recommend?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Sachar Committee Report</u></strong> observed that the social and economic situation of Dalit Muslims and Dalit Christians did not improve after conversion.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Ranganath Misra Commission</u></strong>, which submitted its report in May 2007, recommended that SC status should be completely de-linked from religion and Scheduled Castes should be made fully religion-neutral like Scheduled Tribes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="dalit" class="alignnone wp-image-638566" height="321" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 609px) 100vw, 609px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244.jpg 1200w" width="609"/>Reception to these recommendations</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The report was tabled in Parliament in 2009, but its recommendation was <strong><u>not accepted</u></strong> in view of inadequate field data and corroboration with the actual situation on the ground.</li>
<li>Few studies, commissioned by the National Commission for Minorities, was also <strong><u>not considered reliable due to insufficient data.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Schedule caste community from all religion India suffers from same fate of untouchability. Change of religion unfortunately, have change their social status. If 70+ year of reservation of Dalit in Hindu haven’t substantially change their social destiny, we have to think beyond reservation for social dignity and economic empowerment of schedule castes in India.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Reservation policy in India is religion based and not based on overall social discrimination. Comment in the context of demand for Dalit reservation extension to Christians and Muslims Dalits.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dalit/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the Dharavi Redevelopment Project?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dharavi-redevelopment-project/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Dharavi</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Slum rehabilitation</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-638844" height="424" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 563px) 100vw, 563px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dharavi-300x226.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dharavi-300x226.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dharavi.jpg 635w" width="563"/></p>
<p>The Maharashtra government gave the go-ahead for fresh tenders in the Dharavi redevelopment project, almost two decades after it was first proposed.</p>
<h4>About Dharavi</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dharavi, infamous as one of the world’s largest slums, is located in the heart of India’s financial capital – Mumbai.</li>
<li>A city within a city, it is one unending stretch of narrow dirty lanes, open sewers and cramped huts.</li>
<li>While the land (area of 535 acres) is owned by the government, the houses are maintained by individuals.</li>
<li>The Dharavi slum came into being in 1884. It was originally inhibited by fisherfolk when the area was still creeks, swamps.</li>
<li>It became attractive to migrant workers from South Mumbai and others when the swamp began to fill in due to natural and artificial causes.</li>
<li>The area grew as poor rural Indians migrated to urban Mumbai.</li>
<li>Today, an estimated 600,000 to 1 million people live crammed in Dharavi.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Economic significance of Dharavi</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dharavi stands near to India’s richest business district, the Bandra-Kurla Complex, where commercial office premiums are among the highest in the country.</li>
<li>The slum sprawl, spread over 2.8 sq.km. is home to an informal leather and pottery industry which employs over a lakh people.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the Dharavi Redevelopment Project all about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The state had envisaged this sprawl be transformed into a cluster of high-rises with improved urban infrastructure.</li>
<li>It entailed resettling 68,000 people, including slum dwellers and those with commercial establishments.</li>
<li>The state was to provide 300-sqft houses for free to residents with proof that their slum structure was in existence before January 1, 2000.</li>
<li>The project was initially mooted in 2004, but never got off the ground due to various reasons.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When redevelopment was first proposed?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 1999, the government first proposed to redevelop Dharavi.</li>
<li>Thereafter, the government of Maharashtra in the year 2003-04 decided to redevelop Dharavi as an integrated planned township.</li>
<li>An action plan for redevelopment was approved by issuing a government resolution.</li>
<li>It was decided to develop Dharavi by using land as a resource to cross-subsidie the cost of development through a sale component on the basis of the Slum Rehabilitation Scheme.</li>
<li>The government also decided to notify the whole of Dharavi as an undeveloped area and to appoint a Special Planning Authority for its development.</li>
<li>In 2011, the government cancelled all tenders and drew up a master plan.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dharavi-redevelopment-project/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Government approves 50% incentive of project cost for setting up Semiconductor Units</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/50-incentive-of-project-cost-for-setting-up-semiconductor-units/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Programme for Development of Semiconductors and Display Manufacturing Ecosystem</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The Union Cabinet has approved a uniform incentive of 50% of the project cost for setting up semiconductor, display and compound semiconductor fabrication units.</p>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="incentive" class="alignnone wp-image-638846" height="290" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 426px) 100vw, 426px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vedanta-300x204.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vedanta-300x204.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vedanta.jpg 640w" width="426"/></p>
<ul>
<li>Maharashtra is witnessing a political firestorm.</li>
<li>The Vedanta Limited shifted its decision to set up a $20 billion Vedanta-Foxconn semiconductor manufacturing facility in neighbouring Gujarat, despite finalising its location near Pune (Mh).</li>
<li>Foxconn is a major chip supplier to Apple. It has suspended its operations in the Chinese tech hub of Shenzhen and is now shifting to India.</li>
<li>Bigger companies, such as Intel, TSMC, Samsung, etc., have announced such plans.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em>Spats between states over the location of critical industries display the grim picture of competitive bidding in India. This portrays India’s negative image as against ease of doing business.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>About the Incentive Scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme has been named the “<strong><u>Programme for Development of Semiconductors and Display Manufacturing Ecosystem</u></strong>.”</li>
<li>Previously, the three schemes had an incentive range of 30-50%.</li>
<li>While incentives for setting up semiconductor fabrication were based on the size of the chip, for display fabrication and compound semiconductor fabs, the incentives were largely 30% of the total cost of the project.</li>
<li>This scheme aims to <strong><u>project India’s position as global hub for electronics manufacturing</u></strong> with semiconductors as the foundational building block.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need such an incentive?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Huge Investments involved: </strong>Semiconductor Fabrication facility requires many expensive devices to function. Complex tools and equipment are required to test quality and move silicon from location to location within the ultra-clean confines of the plant.</li>
<li><strong>Economy of scale:  </strong> In semiconductor fabrication, a high volume production is required to be maintain so as to meet the increasing demand of the marketplace, at the same time, a strong financial backing as Indian market is very much uncertain about financial fluctuations.</li>
<li><strong>Requirement highly skilled labour:</strong>   Semiconductor fabrication is a multiple-step sequence of photolithographic and chemical processing steps during which electronic circuits are gradually created on a wafer made of pure semiconducting material. This actually requires high skills.</li>
<li><strong>Scarcity of raw materials</strong>: From a value-chain perspective, it needs silicon, Germanium &amp; Gallium arsenide and Silicon carbide which are not available in India and needs to be imported.</li>
<li><strong>Uncertain Indian market</strong>: A semiconductor fabrication facility in India cannot independently rely on Indian customers for their entire sales structure. They have to maintain overseas customer base to balance inflections from Indian market due to market trends, government policies etc.</li>
<li><strong>Disposal of hazardous waste</strong>: Many toxic materials are used in the fabrication process such as arsenic, antimony, and phosphorus. Hazardous impact on the environment by the industry may act as an impediment to India’s commitment to mitigate climate change.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other supportive initiatives in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>India Semiconductor Mission (ISM):</strong> It was announced with the aim to attract large-scale investments for manufacturing facilities in the midst of a global chip crisis.</li>
<li><strong>Make in India:</strong> This aims to transform India into a global hub for Electronic System Design and Manufacturing (ESDM).</li>
<li><strong>PLI scheme:</strong> In December 2021 the Centre sanctioned ₹76,000 crore under the production-linked incentive (PLI) scheme to encourage the manufacturing of various semiconductor goods within India.</li>
<li><strong>DLI scheme:</strong> It offers financial incentives, design infrastructure support across various stages of development and deployment of semiconductor design for Integrated Circuits (ICs), Chipsets, System on Chips (SoCs), Systems &amp; IP Cores and semiconductor linked design.</li>
<li><strong>Digital RISC-V (DIR-V) program: </strong>It intends to enable the production of microprocessors in India in the upcoming days achieving industry-grade silicon and design wins by December 2023.</li>
<li><strong>India Semiconductor Mission (ISM):</strong> The vision is to build a vibrant semiconductor and display design and innovation ecosystem to enable India’s emergence as a global hub for electronics manufacturing and design</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Policy framework</strong>: As foundry setup is highly Capital intensive, it must be supported with a solid long term plan and financial backing. This backing is required from the entrepreneur &amp; the government both.</li>
<li><strong>Fiscal sustenance:</strong> In text of Indian Government as tax holiday, subsidy, zero duty, financial investment etc. will play an important role in promoting the Fab along with the semiconductor industry in India; this will put further pressure on already large Fiscal Deficit.</li>
<li><strong>Support Infrastructure:</strong> World class, sustainable infrastructure, as required by a modern Fab be provided, with swift transportation, large quantity of pure water, uninterrupted electricity, communication, pollutant free environment etc.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/50-incentive-of-project-cost-for-setting-up-semiconductor-units/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Recession unlikely to hit India: S&amp;P</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/recession-unlikely-to-hit-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Recessions, Depression</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="recession" class="aligncenter wp-image-638845" height="312" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 532px) 100vw, 532px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-1-300x176.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-1-300x176.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-1.jpg 670w" width="532"/></strong></p>
<p>Global rating agency S&amp;P has said that even though the US and the Euro zone are headed towards recession, India is unlikely to face the impact given the not-so-coupled nature of its economy with the global economy.</p>
<h4><strong>How is India immune to global recession?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian economy is a lot decoupled from the global economy than we normally think of, given its large domestic demand.</li>
<li>India has enough forex reserves on one hand and domestic companies have managed to maintain healthy balance sheets.</li>
<li>In fact, India was never coupled fully with the global economy and so is relatively independent of global markets.</li>
<li>Elsewhere, a lot depends on how global fund flows behave if there is a recession in the U.S. and Europe.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Recession?</strong></h4>
<p><strong><img alt="recession" class="alignnone wp-image-631660" height="240" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 442px) 100vw, 442px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-300x163.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-300x163.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-1024x555.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-768x416.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession.jpg 1026w" width="442"/></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>A recession is a significant decline in economic activity that lasts for months or even years.</li>
<li>Experts declare a recession when a nation’s economy experiences negative GDP, rising levels of unemployment, falling retail sales, and contracting measures of income and manufacturing for an extended period of time.</li>
<li>Recessions are considered an unavoidable part of the business cycle—or the regular cadence of expansion and contraction that occurs in a nation’s economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What causes Recessions?</strong></h4>
<p>These phenomena are some of the main drivers of a recession:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>A sudden economic shock:</strong> An economic shock is a surprise problem that creates serious financial damage. The coronavirus outbreak, which shut down economies worldwide, is a more recent example of a sudden economic shock.</li>
<li><strong>Excessive debt:</strong> When individuals or businesses take on too much debt, the cost of servicing the debt can grow to the point where they can’t pay their bills. Growing debt defaults and bankruptcies then capsize the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Asset bubbles:</strong> When investing decisions are driven by emotion, bad economic outcomes aren’t far behind. Investors can become too optimistic during a strong economy.</li>
<li><strong>Too much inflation:</strong> Inflation is the steady, upward trend in prices over time. Inflation isn’t a bad thing per se, but excessive inflation is a dangerous phenomenon. Central banks control inflation by raising interest rates, and higher interest rates depress economic activity.</li>
<li><strong>Too much deflation:</strong> While runaway inflation can create a recession, deflation can be even worse. Deflation is when prices decline over time, which causes wages to contract, which further depresses prices. When a deflationary feedback loop gets out of hand, people and business stop spending, which undermines the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Technological change:</strong> New inventions increase productivity and help the economy over the long term, but there can be short-term periods of adjustment to technological breakthroughs. In the 19th century, there were waves of labour-saving technological improvements.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What’s the difference between Recession and Depression?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Recessions and depressions have similar causes, but the overall impact of a depression is much, much worse.</li>
<li>There are greater job losses, higher unemployment and steeper declines in GDP.</li>
<li>Most of all, a depression lasts longer—years, not months—and it takes more time for the economy to recover.</li>
<li>Economists do not have a set definition or fixed measurements to show what counts as a depression. Suffice to say, all the impacts of a depression are deeper and last longer.</li>
<li>In the past century, the US has faced just one depression: The Great Depression.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The Great Depression</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Great Depression started in 1929 and lasted through 1933, although the economy didn’t really recover until World War II, nearly a decade later.</li>
<li>During the Great Depression, unemployment rose to 25% and the GDP fell by 30%.</li>
<li>It was the most unprecedented economic collapse in modern US history.</li>
<li>By way of comparison, the Great Recession was the worst recession since the Great Depression.</li>
<li>During the Great Recession, unemployment peaked around 10% and the recession officially lasted from December 2007 to June 2009, about a year and a half.</li>
<li>Some economists fear that the coronavirus recession could morph into a depression, depending how long it lasts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How long do recessions last?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Gulf War Recession (July 1990 to March 1991):</strong> At the start of the 1990s, the U.S. went through a short, eight-month recession, partly caused by spiking oil prices during the First Gulf War.</li>
<li><strong>The Great Recession (2008-2009):</strong> As mentioned, the Great Recession was caused in part by a bubble in the real estate market.</li>
<li><strong>Covid-19 Recession:</strong> The most recent recession began in February 2020 and lasted only two months, making it the shortest US recession in history.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Can we predict a recession?</strong></h4>
<p>Given that economic forecasting is uncertain, predicting future recessions is far from easy. However, the following warning signs can give you more time to figure out how to prepare for a recession before it happens:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>An inverted yield curve:</strong> The yield curve is a graph that plots the market value—or the yield—of a range. When long-term yields are lower than short-term yields, it shows that investors are worried about a recession. This phenomenon is known as a yield curve inversion, and it has predicted past recessions.</li>
<li><strong>Declines in consumer confidence:</strong> Consumer spending is the main driver of the US economy. If surveys show a sustained drop in consumer confidence, it could be a sign of impending trouble for the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Drop in the Leading Economic Index (LEI):</strong> Published monthly by the Conference Board, the LEI strives to predict future economic trends. It looks at factors like applications for unemployment insurance, new orders for manufacturing and stock market performance.</li>
<li><strong>Sudden stock market declines:</strong> A large, sudden decline in stock markets could be a sign of a recession coming on, since investors sell off parts and sometimes all of their holdings in anticipation of an economic slowdown.</li>
<li><strong>Rising unemployment:</strong> It goes without saying that if people are losing their jobs, it’s a bad sign for the economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does a recession affect individuals?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>We may lose your job during a recession, as unemployment levels rise. It becomes much harder to find a job replacement since more people are out of work.</li>
<li>People who keep their jobs may see cuts to pay and benefits, and struggle to negotiate future pay raises.</li>
<li>Investments in stocks, bonds, real estate and other assets can lose money in a recession, reducing your savings and upsetting your plans for retirement.</li>
<li>Business owners make fewer sales during a recession, and may even be forced into bankruptcy.</li>
<li>With more people unable to pay their bills during a recession, lenders tighten standards for mortgages, car loans, and other types of financing.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/recession-unlikely-to-hit-india/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Ratan Tata, KT Thomas appointed trustees of PM CARES</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ratan-tata-appointed-trustee-pm-cares/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PM CARES</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with PM CARES</p></div></div><p>The Union government has appointed veteran industrialist Ratan Tata, former Supreme Court judge K.T. Thomas, and former Lok Sabha Deputy Speaker Kariya Munda as trustees of the PM CARES Fund.</p>
<h4><strong>PM CARES Fund</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PM CARES Fund was created on 28 March 2020 following the COVID-19 pandemic in India.</li>
<li>The fund will be used for combat, containment and relief efforts against the coronavirus outbreak and similar pandemic like situations in the future.</li>
<li>The PM is the chairman of the trust. Members will include the defence, home and finance ministers.</li>
<li>The fund will also enable micro-donations. The minimum donation accepted is ₹10 (14¢ US).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Some intriguing facts about PM-CARES fund</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>PM CARES has been created not by law, not by notification, but by the mere creation of a webpage, and set up last year in March to raise funds for those affected by the COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
<li>The page lists its structure, functions and duties in an arbitrary manner.</li>
<li>The official appeals for funds are made under the national emblem.</li>
<li>The most significant lie of this sworn statement is that the Government has no control over the Fund.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The other funds</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) National Disaster Response Fund (NDRF)</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The statutorily constituted NDRF was established under the Disaster Management (DM) Act of 2005.</li>
<li>The NDRF is mandated to be accountable, and answerable under the RTI Act, being a public authority, and auditable by the Comptroller and Auditor General of India.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Disaster Response Fund</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The DM Act also provided for a Disaster Response Fund — state and district level funds (besides the national level).</li>
<li>It also collects and uses the donations at the local level, with mandatory transparency and audit provisions.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Prime Minister’s National Relief Fund</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is the PMNRF operative since the days of Jawaharlal Nehru. It was established with public contributions to assist displaced persons from Pakistan.</li>
<li>The resources are now utilised primarily to render immediate relief to families of those killed in natural calamities and to the victims of the major accidents and riots.</li>
<li>However, it has the President of India and the Leader of Opposition also as trustees.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues over PM-CARES Fund</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>No defined purpose:</strong> It is deliberately ignored while a new, controversial, unanswerable, and ‘non-accountable vehicle is created; its character is not spelt out till today.</li>
<li><strong>Non-accountable:</strong> The government seems to consider statutory provisions for enquiry and information seeking to be embarrassing obstacles.</li>
<li><strong>Centralization of donations:</strong> It centralises the collection of donations and its utility, which is not only against the federal character but also practically inconvenient. The issue is seeming, the trusteeship of the fund.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Questions and gaps</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Law/statute:</strong> The PM CARES Fund was neither created by the Constitution of India nor by any statute.</li>
<li><strong>Authority:</strong> If that is the case, under what authority does it use the designation of the Prime Minister, designated symbols of the nation, the tricolour and the official (gov.in) website of the PMO, and grant tax concessions through an ordinance.</li>
<li><strong>Collection and dispensation:</strong> The amount received by the Fund does not go to the Consolidated Fund of India. If it goes to the CFI, it could have been audited by the CAG.</li>
<li><strong>Uncontrolled:</strong> The This Trust is neither intended to be or is in fact owned, controlled or substantially financed by any instrumentality of the any govt even being chaired by the PM.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issue over tax benefits</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Income tax:</strong> An ordinance was promulgated to amend Income Tax Act, 1961 and declare that the donations to the PM CARES Fund “would qualify for 80G benefits for 100% exemption”.</li>
<li><strong>CSR Funds:</strong> It will also qualify to be counted as Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) expenditure under the Companies Act, 2013.</li>
<li><strong>Foreign donations:</strong> It has also got exemption under the FCRA [Foreign Contribution Regulation Act] and a separate account for receiving foreign donations has been opened.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be inferred from all these?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Centre now considers it as another obstacle and has created a new trust with the Prime Minister and his Ministers only.</li>
<li>The manner in which the PM CARES Fund was set up — with its acronym created to publicise the point that the PM cares for people — shows a bypassing of the statutory obligations of a public authority.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Query and response: Again ironical</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>After initial denials, the Government has conceded it to be a public charitable trust, but still maintains that it is not a ‘public authority’.</li>
<li>The point is that the PMO operates the Fund, but says it cannot supply any information about the PM CARES Fund because it is not a public authority.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Severe interpretations: Is it an Office of Profit?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>If the PM CARES Fund is unconnected with the Government, then the Fund could become an office of profit.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In order to uphold transparency, the PM CARES Fund should be declared as a Public Authority under the RTI Act, and all RTI queries answered truthfully.</li>
<li>The fund should be designated as a “public authority” under Section 2(h) of the RTI Act.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ratan-tata-appointed-trustee-pm-cares/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Rules for Identifying Criminals now notified</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rules-for-identifying-criminal-now-notified/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-638847" height="525" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 525px) 100vw, 525px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/criminal-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/criminal-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/criminal-150x150.jpg 150w" width="525"/></strong></p>
<p>On September 19, the Ministry of Home Affairs (MHA) notified the rules governing The Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022. The Act was passed in March by the Parliament.</p>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Until rules are notified, an Act cannot be implemented or come into force.</li>
<li>The legislation would enable police and central investigating agencies to collect, store and analyse physical and biological samples including retina and iris scan of arrested persons.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Ans.</strong> It is about critical measurements of Criminals.</p>
<ul>
<li>This act provides legal sanction to law enforcement agencies for taking measurements of convicts and other persons for the purposes of identification and investigation of criminal matters.</li>
<li>The Minister of Home Affairs has observed that with advancements in forensics, there was a need to recognise more kinds of “measurements” that can be used by law enforcement agencies for investigation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the use of identification details in criminal trials?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Measurements and photographs for identification have three main purposes:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>To establish the identity of the culprit against the person being arrested</li>
<li>To identify suspected repetition of similar offences by the same person and third</li>
<li>To establish a previous conviction</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What was the previous Identification of Prisoners Act, 1920 about?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Even though the police has powers of arrest, mere <strong><u>arrest does not give Police the right to search a person</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The police requires <strong><u>legal sanction to search the person</u></strong> and collect evidence.</li>
<li>These legal sanctions are designed so as <strong><u>to maintain a balance between the rights of an individual and the interests of society</u></strong> in prosecution and prevention of offences.</li>
<li>The Identification of Prisoners Act, 1920 became a necessity when the <strong><u>recording of newer forms of evidence such as fingerprints, footprints and measurements started</u></strong> becoming more accurate and reliable.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the need to replace this Act?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Ans. </strong>Changing nature of Crime</p>
<ul>
<li>Over the years, the need to amend/update the Identification of Prisoners Act, 1920 has been voiced several times.</li>
<li>In 1980, the <strong><u>87th Report of the Law Commission of India</u></strong> undertook a review of this legislation and recommended several amendments.</li>
<li>This was done in the backdrop of the <strong><u>State of UP vs. Ram Babu Misra case</u></strong>, where the Supreme Court had highlighted the need for amending this law.</li>
<li>The first set of recommendations laid out the need to amend the Act to expand the scope of measurements <strong><u>to include “palm impressions”, “specimen of signature or writing” and “specimen of voice”. </u></strong></li>
<li>The second set of recommendations raised the <strong><u>need of allowing measurements to be taken for proceedings</u></strong> other than those under the Code of Criminal Procedure (CrPC).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the main highlights and differences in both the legislations?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Both provide legal sanction:</strong> Like the 1920 Law, the new Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022 provides for legal sanction to law enforcement agencies for the collection of measurements.</li>
<li><strong>Creating usable database of evidences:</strong> The purpose is to create a useable database of these measurements.</li>
<li><strong>Notifying designated state agencies:</strong> At the State level, each State is required to notify an appropriate agency to collect and preserve this database of measurements.</li>
<li><strong>NCRB at centre stage:</strong> At the national level, the National Crime Records Bureau (NCRB) is the designated agency to manage, process, share and disseminate the records collected at the State level.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are some of the concerns with the present legislation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Striking a balance:</strong> The new legislation has raised some concerns related to the protection of fundamental rights.</li>
<li><strong>Unresolved right to Privacy debate:</strong> The legislation comes in the backdrop of the right to privacy being recognised as a fundamental right.</li>
<li><strong>Notion of physical privacy:</strong> A fundamental facet of the right to privacy is protection from the invasion of one’s physical privacy.</li>
<li><strong>Justifying necessity:</strong> As per the Puttaswamy judgment, there is a need for the measure to be taken in pursuance of a legitimate aim of the state, be backed by the law and be “necessary and proportionate” to the aim being sought to be achieved.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(1) Various tests behind</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In this case, while the first two tests are satisfied, as:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>“<strong><u>prevention and investigation of crime</u></strong>” is a legitimate aim of the state</li>
<li>“<strong><u>measurements</u></strong>” are being taken under a valid legislation,</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Satisfaction of the third test of “<strong><u>necessity and proportionality</u></strong>” has been challenged on multiple counts.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) A probable police state in making</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Analysis and measurement of behavioural attributes have raised concerns that data processing may go beyond recording of core “measurements”.</li>
<li>That is some of these measurements could be processed for <strong><u>predictive policing</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Includes petty offences</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The current law allows for “measurements” to be taken if a person has been convicted/arrested for any offence, including petty offences.</li>
<li>The necessity of taking measurements of such persons for investigation of offences is unclear, and such discretion is likely to result in abuse of the law at lower levels.</li>
<li>This would definitely overburden the systems used for collection and storage of these measurements.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Period of storage of data</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Given that these records will be stored for 75 years from the time of collection, the law has been criticised as being disproportionate.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Surveillance state</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Such collection can also result in mass surveillance, with the database under this law being combined with other databases such as those of the Crime and Criminal Tracking Network and Systems (CCTNS).</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Promotes self-incrimination</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Concerns are being raised that the <strong><u>present law violates the right against self-incrimination</u></strong> enshrined in Article 20(3) of the Constitution of India.</li>
<li>However, this argument is nebulous since the Supreme Court has already settled this point.</li>
<li>In the State of Bombay vs Kathi Kalu Oghad, the Supreme Court had conclusively held that “non-communicative” evidence i.e. evidence which does not convey information within the personal knowledge of the accused cannot be understood to be leading to self-incrimination.</li>
<li>Therefore, no challenge lies to the law on this ground.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Extensive pre-legislative consultation is must for any sensitive law as such.</li>
<li>Privacy and data protection-related concerns must be addressed in the Rules formulated under the legislation and through model Prison Manuals that States can refer to.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rules-for-identifying-criminal-now-notified/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Live Streaming of SC proceedings: the rationale and the concerns</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/live-streaming-of-sc-proceedings/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Live streaming of courts proceedings</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-638849" height="141" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/live-streaming-300x141.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/live-streaming-300x141.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/live-streaming-768x361.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/live-streaming.jpg 905w" width="300"/></p>
<p>From September 27 onward, all proceedings of Supreme Court Constitution Benches will be live-streamed, a full court meeting of the top court has decided.</p>
<h4><strong>Background of the move</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>History was made on August 26 (2022) when the proceedings from the Chief Justice’s Court in the Supreme Court (SC) were live streamed.</li>
<li>In the <strong><u>‘Swapnil Tripathi’ judgment</u></strong>, in September 2018, the SC had cleared the deck for live streaming of cases of national and constitutional importance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Immediate triggers for live streaming</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>They had agreed to hear a public interest litigation seeking live streaming of judicial proceedings <strong><u>on matters of constitutional and national importance.</u></strong></li>
<li>Prime considerations cited are:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>De-congestion of courts and</li>
<li>Improving physical access to courts for litigants who have to otherwise travel long distances</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Recommended by A-G</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court approved a set of guidelines suggested by the A-G, which included allowing transcripts and archiving the proceedings.</li>
<li>However, the A-G suggested that the court must retain the <strong><u>power to withhold broadcasting</u></strong>, and to also NOT permit it in cases involving:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Matrimonial matters,</li>
<li>Matters involving interests of juveniles or the protection and safety of the private life of the young offenders,</li>
<li>Matters of National security,</li>
<li>To ensure that victims, witnesses or defendants can depose truthfully and without any fear.</li>
<li>To protect confidential or sensitive information, including all matters relating to sexual assault and rape,</li>
<li>Matters where publicity would be antithetical to the administration of justice, and</li>
<li>Cases which may provoke sentiments and arouse passion and provoke enmity among communities.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Live streaming in HCs</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Following the SC’s decision, Gujarat High Court began live streaming its proceedings in July 2021.</li>
<li>Currently, the Jharkhand, Karnataka, Madhya Pradesh, Orissa, and Patna High Courts live stream their proceedings.</li>
<li>Allahabad High Court is learnt to be considering doing the same.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Global examples of live streaming</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>United States of America:</strong> While the US Supreme Court has rejected pleas for broadcast of its proceedings, it has <u>since 1955</u> allowed audio recording and transcripts of oral arguments.</li>
<li><strong>United Kingdom:</strong> In 2005, the law was amended to remove contempt of court charges for recording proceedings of the Supreme Court.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need live streaming of court?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Improved accountability:</strong> Live-streaming of court proceedings would serve as an instrument for greater accountability and formed part of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.</li>
<li><strong>Living up the expectation of Constitution:</strong> Live Streaming of Court proceedings is manifested in public interest. Public interest has always been preserved through the Constitution article 19 and 21</li>
<li><strong>Empowering the masses: </strong>It will enable the legal system to deliver on its promise of empowering the masses.</li>
<li><strong>More transparency: </strong>It will encourage the principle of open court and reduce dependence on second-hand views. It will effectuate the public’s right to know.</li>
<li>This would inspire confidence in the functioning of the judiciary as an institution and help maintain the respect that it deserved as a co-equal organ of the state.</li>
<li><strong>Academic help:</strong> Live streaming may also be a help for academic purposes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Concerns around live streaming</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Contempt of court:</strong> Video clips of proceedings from Indian courts are already on YouTube and other social media platforms with sensational titles and little context, such as “HIGH COURT super angry on army officer”.</li>
<li><strong>Disinformation and sensationalism:</strong> There are fears that irresponsible or motivated use of content could spread disinformation among the public.</li>
<li><strong>Unnecessary activism:</strong> With the advent of social media, every citizen became a potential journalist. Study shows that justices behave like politicians when given free television time, they act to maximize their individual exposure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues to judicial functioning</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Decency of questions:</strong> During hearings judges may not ask questions or make comments that could be perceived as unpopular.</li>
<li><strong>Triggers for oral observations:</strong> There is an increasing trend of oral observations of the court, which are not binding on parties replacing reasoned judgment and orders that are consequential.</li>
<li><strong>Dignity of court may be compromised:</strong> Similarly, lawyers, aware of their new audience, may choose to grandstand and play to the gallery, especially in a case they expect to lose.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Selective broadcast:</strong> The solution may lie in carefully determining how the live streaming proceeds.</li>
<li><strong>Careful selection of cases:</strong> Not uploading archived stream on the SC website until it is legally/technologically possible to ensure that such videos cannot be spliced.</li>
<li><strong>Understanding public perception and sentiments:</strong> Other similar measures that reflect an understanding of how the public consumes (dis)information will ensure that live streaming enriches constitutionalism across the country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A hasty and wholesale introduction on the other hand is likely to land the SC right in the middle of the majoritarian and toxic information swamp that prevails in the country.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/live-streaming-of-sc-proceedings/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why the India China Border situation is still risky?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-china-border/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>border security</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="india china border" class="alignnone wp-image-638843" height="304" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 540px) 100vw, 540px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/117159998_gettyimages-1231271682-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/117159998_gettyimages-1231271682-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/117159998_gettyimages-1231271682-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/117159998_gettyimages-1231271682.jpg 976w" width="540"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to the consensus reached in the 16th round of India China Corps Commander Level Meeting, the Indian and Chinese troops in the area of Gogra-Hotsprings (PP-15) have begun to disengage in a coordinated and planned way. With disengagement at PP 15 India China border, forces of the two countries have disengaged at all friction points in the region which included the North and South banks of the <a href="https://indianexpress.com/article/explained/india-china-conflict-in-ladakh-the-importance-of-the-pangong-tso-lake-6419377/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Pangong Tso</a>, PP 14, PP 15 and PP 17A.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="India china border" class="alignnone wp-image-638858" height="305" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 467px) 100vw, 467px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dispute-300x196.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dispute-300x196.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dispute-768x502.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dispute.jpg 966w" width="467"/>Why the India-China Border situation is still risky?</strong></h4>
<p>The tentative conciliatory steps between two nuclear-armed rivals are important; but they also carry risks, especially for India. The risks are as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Uneasy peace: </strong>Despite the latest round of disengagement, the LAC remains deeply unsettled. Observers have pointed out that the buﬀer zones produced by the crisis inhibit India’s ability to patrol its own territory.</li>
<li><strong>Un-resolve areas: </strong>India and China have tacitly agreed to postpone settlement at two other confrontation sites, particularly tactically valuable area known as Depsangand Charding Nala regions.</li>
<li><strong>Persisting threat: </strong>The reinforcements that each side deployed since 2020 have not returned to garrison. Even if future rounds of talks continue “disengagement and de-escalation,” and reduce those forces, returning to the status quo ante is now impossible.</li>
<li><strong>Border infrastructure: </strong>Both sides on India China border are racing towards building permanent military infrastructure near the border, to help them surge forces to the border. Unsurprisingly, China seems to have outpaced India in building these roads, helipads, and communications nodes.</li>
<li><strong>Possibility of conflict: </strong>The increasing capabilities and mobility on both sides of the border means that a crisis can more quickly escalate to a large military stand-oﬀ anywhere on the LAC, and possibly even trigger a conflict</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-china-border-dispute-a-conflict-years-in-the-making/"><strong><img alt="india china border" class="alignnone wp-image-638848" height="528" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 793px) 100vw, 793px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/file7ejeq84moxlfs3ppjoa-952973-1613730158-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/file7ejeq84moxlfs3ppjoa-952973-1613730158-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/file7ejeq84moxlfs3ppjoa-952973-1613730158-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/file7ejeq84moxlfs3ppjoa-952973-1613730158-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/file7ejeq84moxlfs3ppjoa-952973-1613730158.jpg 1200w" width="793"/>What are the Strategic implications?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Changing priorities: </strong>India has reassigned one of three originally Pakistan-facing Strike Corps to the China front. It has deployed its newest artillery, jets, and drones to the China border.</li>
<li><strong>Unattended Indian Ocean: </strong>India has not yet improved its capabilities or posture in the Indian Ocean region significantly.</li>
<li><strong>Diversion from real threat: </strong>With the border crisis, China seems to have successfully ﬁxed India’s gaze to the land border, at the expense of that more consequential competition over the Indian Ocean.</li>
<li><strong>Loss of grazing</strong>: Ladakh’s elected representatives said the disengagement has caused loss of huge grazing land as it would now be converted into no man’s land.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="india china border" class="alignnone wp-image-638851" height="326" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 579px) 100vw, 579px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811.jpg 1600w" width="579"/>Steps taken by India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increasing capability: </strong>from cruise missile-equipped ﬁghter jets and U.S.-origin naval helicopters to a brand-new indigenously-built aircraft carrier.</li>
<li><strong>Atmanirbhar Bharat: </strong>India undertook several structural economic reforms for strengthening domestic capability and reducing the economic parity between two nations. Defence ministry has decided to increase CAB (capital acquisition budget), around 64% of modernization fund around 70000 cr. has been allocated for purchasing from domestic market. Atma Nirbhar Bharat and Make in India mission will also include Defence sector, we can see the local or private companies can also participate in procurement of defence equipment</li>
<li><strong>Defence India Start-up Challenge (DISC): </strong>Started by the defence ministry and over 1200 MSMEs participated in the fourth edition of the DISC in 2020. The government has prepared a negative list, it include light combat helicopters, artillery guns; these items will not be imported by anyone thus encouraging self-reliant India.</li>
<li><strong>The SRIJAN</strong> <strong>portal: </strong>Launched to facilitate the two initiatives, Atmanirbhar Bharat and make in India</li>
<li><strong>Sagarmala project</strong>: The sagarmala project has been started to revamp port Infrastructure which is a welcome step in modernization.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>For china Deception is diplomacy. Time and again China tries a deception strategy from its Confucius doctrine to defeat its enemy. From 1962 to 2022 India has made a lot of progress in military and economic sphere but China is way ahead than us. Strategic competition between two Asian giants will continue foreseeable future. So as long as India doesn’t gain domestic capabilities it would be prudent step to undertake strategic balancing.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. India has decided to maintain a strategic balance with china rather than being subsidiary to china. Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-china-border/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Domestic violence needs to stop for true women empowerment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/domestic-violence/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>women empowerment</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="domestic violence" class="alignnone wp-image-638948" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 501px) 100vw, 501px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101-1024x681.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101-768x511.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101.jpg 1200w" width="501"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Due to prevalence of patriarchy women have been discriminated not only in India but in most parts of the world. According to The United Nations, one out of every three women experience domestic violence. The same UN report suggests that the most dangerous place for women is their home. Gender equality and women’s empowerment are essential for the development and well-being of families, communities and nations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How UN women defines Violence against women and girls</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Any act of gender-based violence that results in, or is likely to result in, physical, sexual or mental harm or suffering to women and girls, including threats of such acts, coercion or arbitrary deprivation of liberty, whether occurring in public or in private life.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why Women are the victim</strong>?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Domestic violence is one of the most common forms of violence experienced by women globally.</li>
<li>Women are usually the victim of domestic violence that derives from unequal power relationships between men and women.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="domestic violence" class="alignnone wp-image-638960" height="443" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 575px) 100vw, 575px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/76064761-300x231.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/76064761-300x231.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/76064761.jpg 635w" width="575"/>Why there is recent spike in violence against women?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to UN, Violence against women and girls is one of the world’s most prevalent human rights violations, taking place every day, many times over, in every corner of the world.</li>
<li><strong>Conditions created by the pandemic</strong> – including lockdowns, reduced mobility, heightened isolation, stress and economic uncertainty have led to an alarming spike in domestic violence and have further exposed women and girls to other forms of violence, from child marriage to sexual harassment online.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Domestic violence?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Domestic violence is any pattern of behavior that is used to gain or maintain power and control over an intimate partner. It encompasses all physical, sexual, emotional, economic and psychological actions or threats of actions that influence another person.</li>
<li><strong>Domestic violence</strong> <strong>can include the following.</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Psychological violence: </strong>Psychological violence involves causing fear, threatening physical harm or forcing isolation from friends, family, school or work<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Economic violence: </strong>Making or attempting to make a person financially dependent by maintaining total control over financial resources.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Emotional violence: </strong>Undermining a person’s sense of self-worth through constant criticism; belittling one’s abilities; verbal abuse.</li>
<li><strong>Physical violence: </strong>Use of Physical force or hurting or trying to hurt a partner .it also includes denying medical care.</li>
<li><strong>Sexual violence: </strong>Forcing a partner to take part in a sex act when the partner does not consent</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the current Status in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Nearly one-third of women in India have experienced physical or sexual violence</li>
<li>The most common type of spousal violence is physical violence (28%), followed by emotional violence and sexual violence</li>
<li>While domestic violence against women has declined from 31.2% to 29.3% in the country, 30% women between the age of 18 and 49 have experienced physical violence since the age of 15 years, while 6% have experienced sexual violence in their lifetime,.</li>
<li>Only 14% of women who have experienced physical or sexual violence by anyone have brought the issue up.</li>
<li>32% of married women (18-49 years) have experienced physical, sexual, or emotional spousal violence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Recent findings from National Family health Survey Report-5</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Status</strong>: Domestic violence against women is highest in Karnataka at 48%, followed by Bihar, Telangana, Manipur and Tamil Nadu. Lakshawdeep has the least domestic violence at 2.1%.</li>
<li><strong>Rural</strong>–<strong>urban difference</strong>: Physical violence is more common among women in rural areas (32%) as compared to their urban areas (24%).</li>
<li><strong>Impact of schooling and education: </strong>40% women with no schooling are subject to physical violence compared to 18% who completed their schooling.</li>
<li><strong>Impact of employment and wealth:</strong> The experience of physical violence ranges between 39% among women in the lowest wealth quintile and 17% in the highest wealth quintile.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> </strong><strong>Why women left behind as compared to men in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Patriarchal structure: </strong>Patriarchal structures and ideologies and the mindset lead to women subordination and gender inequalities</li>
<li><strong>Low sex ratio: </strong>Sex ratios for women in India Is not good comparatively. It was even bad at the time of independence.</li>
<li><strong>Life expectancy</strong>: Women’s life expectancy, health, nutritional levels are significantly lower than that of men.</li>
<li><strong>Education: </strong>low investment on girl education, Girl children are kept out of schools, or made drop out of school at early age, girl is considered as burden on family in many societies.</li>
<li><strong>Employment</strong>: even if they are educated they are not allowed to work by their families Discrimination at the workplaces, lower wages for the work of equal value<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Decision making: </strong>The have little say in the families, socio economic, legal and political rules and policy formulations. Very limited or no decision making power.</li>
<li><strong>Political participation: </strong>The participation of women in political and social decision making power is abysmally low. Their number in parliament has never exceeded more than 10%.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-empowerment/"><strong>What can be done for empowering women?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Recognition: </strong>Recognition of women as productive, vital agents of family and environment should be a precondition for addressing their social needs. We need to change the way they are perceived.</li>
<li><strong>Treatment: </strong>They must not be only treated only as objects of welfare but needed to be treated as those who are contributing to the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Health: </strong>To provide quality and affordable healthcare and must be easily accessible.</li>
<li><strong>Education: </strong>Education of women is the most important component for women’s empowerment.</li>
<li><strong>Safe and secure environment: </strong>providing safety and security is the precondition for empowerment and social justice.</li>
<li><strong>Economic Independence: </strong>Helping women to stand on their legs, become independent and also to earn for their family is necessary to empowering women and to raise their hand in decision making process of family, society and nation</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="domestic violence" class="alignnone wp-image-638986" height="349" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 537px) 100vw, 537px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Downloads2-300x195.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Downloads2-300x195.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Downloads2.jpg 620w" width="537"/>Woman as the foundation stone of every family, society and nation</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has an ancient woman worship tradition.</li>
<li>In India we see woman as a mother goddess. There are no of evidences to support this idea</li>
<li>For instance the Sanskrit text “Yatra naryastu pujyante ramante tatra Devata”which means where women are honored, there gods resides.</li>
<li>Which means there is a overall development if the women of the family is happy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="domestic violence" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-639056" height="158" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India.jpg 1200w" width="300"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Domestic violence against women is major obstacle on progress on achieving development targets. Without addressing it, anybody have little chance of meeting millennium development. Recognition of women as productive, vital agents of family and environment should be a precondition for addressing their social needs. Gender equality and women’s empowerment are essential for the development and well-being of families, communities and nations.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Empowering women on every front is the pre-condition for the overall development of the nation. Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/domestic-violence/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The problem of fly ash generation and its proper disposal and usage</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fly-ash/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>composition of fly ash</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>environmental pollution</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="fly ash" class="alignnone wp-image-639139" height="352" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 100vw, 542px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.28841000_1663768775_0-300x195.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.28841000_1663768775_0-300x195.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.28841000_1663768775_0-768x498.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.28841000_1663768775_0.jpg 1024w" width="542"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India depends heavily on coal for power generation. This creates the problem of fly-ash generation and its proper disposal, usage.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/national-green-tribunal-ngt/">National Green Tribunal (NGT)</a> noted September 19, 2022 that there was an urgent need to augment the utilisation and disposal of fly ash in Chhattisgarh.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is fly ash?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fly ash is a by-product of coal combustion. It contains Aluminium Silicate, SiO2, CaO, oxides of iron, magnesium and toxic metals like lead, arsenic, cobalt, and copper.</li>
<li>It can travel to far places. India is growing to double its power generation in the next decade and with coal being the biggest source of fuel for power generation, the problem of fly ash is going to increase too.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fly ash " class="alignnone wp-image-639140" height="623" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 467px) 100vw, 467px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-225x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-225x300.jpg 225w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-1535x2048.jpg 1535w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-675x900.jpg 675w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-1200x1601.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-1980x2641.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-scaled.jpg 1919w" width="467"/>Environmental Problems with fly ash </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A large quantity of fly ash dumped into poorly designed and maintained ash ponds. About a billion tonnes of this toxic ash lie dumped in these ponds, polluting land, air, and water.</li>
<li>All the heavy metals found in fly ash—nickel, cadmium, arsenic, chromium, lead, etc—are toxic in nature. They leech into the surrounding soil and can enter food-chains.</li>
<li>Fly ash gets easily ingested through respiration, which causes many diseases such as asthma, neurological disorders.</li>
<li>Suspended fly ash in the air acts as a global warming agent and heats the earth’s surface.</li>
<li>Fly ash settles on leaves and crops and reduces crop productivity.</li>
<li>It pollutes the groundwater.</li>
<li>There is a reduction in recharging of groundwater due to fly ash filled mine voids.</li>
<li>Reduces visibility by creating dense fog in the winter season.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fly ash" class="alignnone wp-image-639144" height="339" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/flyash-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/flyash-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/flyash-768x449.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/flyash.jpg 900w" width="581"/>Issues with fly ash management</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The government mandates that all coal power plants (CPPs) reach 100% utilization of fly ash.</li>
<li>Along with it, CPPs should give a certain amount of fly ash free of cost for MSMEs to manufacture bricks, tiles and rest of the fly ash should be sold to other industries.</li>
<li>CPPs will have to maintain fly ash ponds to reduce its suspension in air.</li>
<li>But all these steps for utilization areas are problematic as they do little to mitigate these risks.</li>
<li>The pricing of fly ash is increasingly becoming a contentious issue that is hampering its gainful utilization.</li>
<li>The current approaches to evaluating risks with fly ash disposal are very limited, and they may underestimate the true risks</li>
<li>In spite of initiatives taken by the government, several nongovernmental and research and development organizations for fly ash utilization, the level of fly ash utilization in the country is quite low at only 38% which is less than the global standards.</li>
<li>Hence, rather than being utilized, fly ash is being stored despite warnings from regulators.</li>
<li>Deposition in storage places has negative influences on water and soil because of their mineral composition as well as morphology and filtration properties.</li>
<li>Ash-handling units are the biggest consumers of water in CPPs. The government advocates the designed ash-to-water ratios as approximately 1:5 for fly ash, but the observed ratios have been around 1:20.</li>
<li>Certain states have discouraged the use of blended cement and fly ash bricks in public works.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fly ash" class="alignnone wp-image-639142" height="353" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-4.jpeg" width="630"/>The above issues can be addressed by</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Greater regulatory oversight and price control,</li>
<li>Revision of cement blending standards,</li>
<li>Research in improving fly ash quality,</li>
<li>Reducing the cost of transportation,</li>
<li>Provisions for overcoming information asymmetries,</li>
<li>Incentivising use in brick kilns for producing fly ash bricks,</li>
<li>Overall sensitization of key decision-makers on the matter.</li>
<li>Instead of dumping it on ash ponds, can be used for construction due to its reuse as pozzolan, and replacement of portland cement by hydraulic cement</li>
<li>Due to its grain size distribution, enhanced strength permeability, it can be used to construct embankments at road construction, concrete dams like GHATGHAR DAM</li>
<li>Strong penalties for those production units who do not use proper filtration devices</li>
<li>Moving to renewable energy production away from coal-based thermal production.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Utilization of Fly Ash is not only possible but also essential. In this context “Fly Ash Mission of Government of India” is a slow but steady start, the pace of which needs to be ramped up. An honest effort is required by the concerned stakeholders to improve the perceptions of fly ash-based cement or concrete; increase its use, particularly for government works; and impart scientific knowledge about fly ash, its uses, and possible impacts.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What is fly ash? Discuss the environmental challenges it poses. Suggest how to address the situation. </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fly-ash/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>