<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 20:12:26 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>SC takes up pleas against Places of Worship Act</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-takes-up-pleas-against-places-of-worship-act/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Places of Worship Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with the Act</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has set the ball rolling on a series of petitions challenging the validity of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-places-of-worship-act/">Places of Worship Act of 1991</a>, a parliamentary law that protects the identity and character of religious places as on August 15, 1947.</p>
<h4>What are the petitions about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A slew of petitions has been filed against the Act.</li>
<li>The Act has fixed a retrospective cut-off date illegally barring Hindus, Jains, Buddhists and Sikhs from approaching courts to re-claim their places of worship which were invaded and encroached.</li>
<li>The main objective of these petitions is to set right a historical wrong committed by barbaric invaders.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Places of Worship Act, 1991</h4>
<ul>
<li>It was passed in 1991 by the P V Narasimha Rao-led government.</li>
<li>The law seeks to maintain the “religious character” of places of worship as it was in 1947 — except in the case of the Ram Janmabhoomi-Babri Masjid dispute, which was already in court.</li>
<li>The law was brought in at the peak of the Ram Mandir movement, exactly a year before the demolition of the Babri Masjid.</li>
<li>Introducing the law, then Home Minister S B Chavan said in Parliament that it was adopted to curb communal tension.</li>
</ul>
<p>What are its provisions?</p>
<h4>What are its provisions?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Anti-conversion:</strong> Section 3 of the Act bars the conversion, in full or part, of a place of worship of any religious denomination into a place of worship of a different religious denomination — or even a different segment of the same religious denomination.</li>
<li><strong>Holiness of a place:</strong> Section 4(1) declares that the religious character of a place of worship “shall continue to be the same as it existed” on August 15, 1947.</li>
<li><strong>Litigation:</strong> Section 4(2) says any suit or legal proceeding with respect to the conversion of the religious character of any place existing on August 15, 1947, pending before any court, shall abate — and no fresh suit or legal proceedings shall be instituted.</li>
<li><strong>Exception for Ayodhya:</strong> Section 5 stipulates that the Act shall not apply to the Ramjanmabhoomi-Babri Masjid case, and to any suit, appeal or proceeding relating to it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the law under challenge?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>cut-off date of August 15, 1947, is “arbitrary, irrational and retrospective</u></strong>” and prohibits Hindus, Jains, Buddhists, and Sikhs from approaching courts to “reclaim” their places of worship.</li>
<li>Such places, he argued, were “<strong><u>invaded” and “encroached” upon by “fundamentalist barbaric invaders</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The right-wing politicians have opposed the law even when it was introduced, arguing that the Centre has no power to legislate on “pilgrimages” or “burial grounds” which is under the state list.</li>
<li>Another criticism against the law is that the cut-off is the date of Independence, which means that the status quo determined by a colonial power is considered final.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-takes-up-pleas-against-places-of-worship-act/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Uttarakhand panel seeks inputs on UCC</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/uttarakhand-panel-seeks-inputs-on-uniform-civil-code/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UCC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Need for UCC</p></div></div><p><img alt="uniform civil code" class="alignnone wp-image-211041" height="697" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 495px) 100vw, 495px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/UCC-213x300.png" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/UCC-213x300.png 213w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/UCC.png 479w" width="495"/></p>
<p>The expert committee formed by the Uttarakhand government to examine ways for the implementation of a Uniform Civil Code (UCC) has launched a website, seeking public opinion on the plan.</p>
<h4><strong>What is a Uniform Civil Code?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-uniform-civil-code/">Uniform Civil Code</a> (UCC) is one that would provide for <strong><u>one personal civil law for the entire country</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This would be <strong><u>applicable to all religious communities</u></strong> in their personal matters such as marriage, divorce, inheritance, adoption etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Basis for Uniform Civil Code<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Article 44</u></strong>, one of the <strong><u>Directive Principles</u></strong> of the Constitution lays down that the state shall endeavour to secure a UCC for the citizens throughout the territory of India.</li>
<li>These, as defined in <strong><u>Article 37</u></strong>, <strong>are not justiciable</strong> (<strong><u>not enforceable by any court</u></strong>) but the principles laid down therein are fundamental in governance.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Personal Laws And Uniform Civil Code: Timeline</strong></h4>
<p><strong># British period<br/>
</strong>During the British Raj, Personal laws were first framed mainly for Hindu and Muslims citizens.</p>
<p><strong># Start of 20th Century</strong><br/>
In the beginning of the twentieth century, the demand for a uniform civil code was first put forward by the women activists. The objective behind this demand was the women’s rights, equality and secularism.</p>
<p><strong># 1940 – The Idea of Uniform Civil Code is born</strong><br/>
The idea of Uniform Civil Code was tabled by the National Planning Commission (NPC) appointed by the Congress. There was a subcommittee who was to examine women’s status and recommends reforms of personal law for gender equality.</p>
<p><strong># 1947 – Question of UCC as a Fundamental Right<br/>
</strong>UCC was sought to be enshrined in the Constitution of India as a fundamental right by Minoo Masani, Hansa Mehta, Amrit Kaur and Dr. B.R Ambedkar.</p>
<p><strong># 1948 – Constitution Assembly debated UCC</strong><br/>
Article 44 of the Indian Constitution i.e. Directive Principles of State Policy sets implementation of uniform civil laws which is the duty of the state under Part IV.</p>
<p><strong># 1950 – Reformist Bill passed</strong><br/>
Reformist bills were passed which gave the Hindu women the right to divorce and inherit property. Bigamy and child marriages are outlawed. Such reforms were resisted by Dr. Rajendra Prasad.</p>
<p><strong># 1951 – Dr. Ambedkar Resigns</strong><br/>
Dr. Ambedkar resigned from the cabinet in 1951 when his draft of the Hindu Code Bill was stalled by the Parliament.</p>
<p><strong># 1985 – Shah Bano Case</strong><br/>
In this case, a divorced Muslim woman was brought within the ambit of Section 125 of Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 by the Supreme Court in which it was declared by the Apex court that she was entitled for maintenance even after the completion ofiddatperiod.</p>
<p><strong># 1995- Sarla Mudgal v. Union of India<br/>
</strong>In this case, Justice Kuldip Singh reiterated the need for the Parliament to frame a Uniform Civil Code, which would help the cause of national integration by removing contradictions based on ideologies. Therefore, the responsibility entrusted on the State under Article 44 of the Constitution whereby a Uniform Civil Code must be secured has been urged by the Supreme Court repeatedly as a matter of urgency.</p>
<p><strong># 2000 – Supreme Court advocates UCC<br/>
</strong>The case of Lily Thomas v. Union of India (2000),where the Supreme Court said it could not direct the centre to introduce a UCC.</p>
<p><strong># 2015 – The Debate lives through</strong><br/>
The apex court refused to direct the government to take a decision on having a UCC.</p>
<p><strong># 2016 – Triple Talaq Debate<br/>
</strong>When PM asked the Law Commission to examine the issue.</p>
<p><strong># 2017 – Ruling of the Triple Talaq case</strong><br/>
Triple Talaq (Talaq -e- biddat) was declared unconstitutional on August 22, 2017.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>UCC vs. Right to Freedom of Religion</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li><strong><u>Article 25</u></strong> lays down an individual’s fundamental right to religion</li>
<li><strong><u>Article 26(b)</u></strong> upholds the right of each religious denomination or any section thereof to “manage its own affairs in matters of religion”</li>
<li><strong><u>Article 29</u></strong> defines the right to conserve distinctive culture</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Reasonable restrictions on the Freedom of Religion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An individual’s freedom of religion under <strong><u>Article 25 is</u></strong> <strong>subject to “public order, health, morality”</strong> and other provisions relating to FRs, but a group’s freedom under Article 26 has not been subjected to other FRs.</li>
<li>In the Constituent Assembly, there was division on the issue of putting UCC in the fundamental rights chapter. The matter was settled by a vote.</li>
<li>By a 5:4 majority, the fundamental rights sub-committee headed by Sardar Patel held that the provision was outside the scope of FRs and therefore the UCC was made less important.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Minority Opinion in the Constituent Assembly</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Some members sought to <strong><u>immunize Muslim Personal Law from state regulation</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Mohammed Ismail, who thrice tried unsuccessfully to get Muslim Personal Law exempted from Article 44, said <strong><u>a secular state should not interfere with the personal law of people</u></strong>.</li>
<li>B Pocker Saheb said he had received representations against a common civil code from various organisations, including Hindu organisations.</li>
<li>Hussain Imam questioned <strong><u>whether there could ever be uniformity of personal laws in a diverse country like India.</u></strong></li>
<li>B R Ambedkar said “no government can use its provisions in a way that would force the Muslims to revolt”.</li>
<li>Alladi Krishnaswami, who was in favour of a UCC, conceded that it would be unwise to enact UCC ignoring strong opposition from any community.</li>
<li><strong><em><u>Gender justice was never discussed in these debates.</u></em></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Enacting and Enforcing UCC</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fundamental rights are enforceable in a court of law.</li>
<li>While Article 44 uses the words “state shall endeavour”, other Articles in the ‘Directive Principles’ chapter use words such as “in particular strive”; “shall in particular direct its policy”; “shall be obligation of the state” etc.</li>
<li>Article 43 mentions “state shall endeavour by suitable legislation” while the phrase “by suitable legislation” is absent in Article 44.</li>
<li>All this implies that <strong><u>the duty of the state is greater in other directive principles than in Article 44</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are more important — fundamental rights or directive principles?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is no doubt that <strong><u>fundamental rights are more important</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Supreme Court held in Minerva Mills (1980): Indian Constitution is founded on the bed-rock of the balance between Parts III (Fundamental Rights) and IV (Directive Principles).</li>
<li>To give absolute primacy to one over the other is to disturb the harmony of the Constitution.</li>
<li>Article 31C inserted by the 42nd Amendment in 1976, however, lays down that if a law is made to implement any directive principle, it cannot be challenged on the ground of being violative of the FRs under Articles 14 and 19.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What about Personal Laws?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Citizens belonging to different religions and denominations follow different property and matrimonial laws which <strong><u>are an affront to the nation’s unity</u></strong>.</li>
<li>If the framers of the Constitution had intended to have a UCC, they would have given exclusive jurisdiction to Parliament in respect of personal laws, by including this subject in the Union List.</li>
<li><strong><u>“Personal Laws” are mentioned in the Concurrent List.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Various customary laws</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>All Hindus of the country are not governed by one law, nor are all Muslims or all Christians.</li>
<li>Muslims of Kashmir were governed by a customary law, which in many ways was at variance with Muslim Personal Law in the rest of the country and was, in fact, closer to Hindu law.</li>
<li>Even on the registration of marriage among Muslims, laws differ from place to place.</li>
<li>In the Northeast, there are more than 200 tribes with their own varied customary laws.</li>
<li>The Constitution itself protects local customs in Nagaland. Similar protections are enjoyed by Meghalaya and Mizoram.</li>
<li>Even reformed Hindu law, in spite of codification, protects customary practices.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> Why need UCC?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>UCC would provide <strong><u>equal status to all citizens</u></strong></li>
<li>It would promote <strong><u>gender parity</u></strong> in Indian society.</li>
<li>UCC would accommodate the <strong><u>aspirations of the young population</u></strong> who imbibe liberal ideology.</li>
<li>Its implementation would thus support the <strong><u>national integration</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Hurdles to UCC implementation</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There are practical difficulties due to <strong><u>religious and cultural diversity</u></strong> in India.</li>
<li>The UCC is often perceived by minorities as an <strong><u>encroachment of religious freedom.</u></strong></li>
<li>It is often regarded as <strong><u>interference of the state in personal matters</u></strong> of the minorities.</li>
<li>Experts often argue that the <strong><u>time is not ripe for Indian society</u></strong> to embrace such UCC.</li>
</ul>
<p>These questions need to be addressed which are being completely ignored in the present din around UCC.</p>
<ol>
<li>Firstly, how can uniformity in personal laws are brought without disturbing the distinct essence of each and every component of the society.</li>
<li>Secondly, what makes us believe that practices of one community are backward and unjust?</li>
<li>Thirdly, has other uniformities been able to eradicate inequalities that diminish the status of our society as a whole?</li>
</ol>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>It should be the duty of the religious intelligentia to educate the community about its rights and obligations based on modern liberal interpretations.</li>
<li>A good environment for the UCC must be prepared by the government by explaining the contents and significance of Article 44 taking all into confidence.</li>
<li>Social reforms are not overnight but gradual phenomena. They are often vulnerable to media evils such as fake news and disinformation.</li>
<li>Social harmony and the cultural fabric of our nation must be the priority.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/uttarakhand-panel-seeks-inputs-on-uniform-civil-code/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Karoo-Ferrar Large Igneous Province?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/karoo-ferrar-large-igneous-province/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Karoo-Ferrar Large Igneous Province</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="karoo" class="alignnone wp-image-635036" height="276" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 508px) 100vw, 508px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/karoo-300x163.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/karoo-300x163.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/karoo.jpg 749w" width="508"/></p>
<p>A new study shows that a decline in <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/in-news-continental-drift-theory/">continental plate movement</a> likely controlled the onset and duration of many of the major volcanic events throughout Earth’s history.</p>
<h4>Why is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Previous studies have linked major volcanic eruptions with past mass extinctions and disturbances in the global climatic, environmental and the carbon cycle.</li>
<li>Large igneous province volcanism, formations due to major volcanic eruptions occurring throughout Earth’s history, released large quantities of greenhouse gasses and toxic compounds into the atmosphere.</li>
<li>The sea warmed up by 4°C to 10°C, even at low- to mid-latitudes, the study noted.</li>
<li>Increased acidic levels and a lack of oxygen drove major ocean extinctions.</li>
<li>Large-scale volcanism took place in southern Africa, Antarctica and Australia. This is known as the Karoo-Ferrar Large Igneous Province.</li>
</ul>
<h4>About Karoo-Ferrar Large Igneous Province</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Karoo and Ferrar Large Igneous Provinces (LIPs) are two large igneous provinces in Southern Africa and Antarctica respectively, collectively known as the Karoo-Ferrar, Gondwana, or Southeast African LIP associated with the initial break-up of the Gondwana supercontinent.</li>
<li>Its flood basalt mostly covers South Africa and Antarctica but portions extend further into southern Africa and into South America, India, Australia and New Zealand.</li>
<li>Karoo-Ferrar formed just prior to the breakup of Gondwana in the Lower Jurassic epoch, about 183 million years ago.</li>
<li>This time corresponds to the early Toarcian anoxic event and the Pliensbachian-Toarcian extinction.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/karoo-ferrar-large-igneous-province/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>PM Modi to attend SCO meet</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pm-modi-to-attend-sco-meet/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>SCO</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="sco" class="alignnone wp-image-635038" height="424" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 416px) 100vw, 416px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/sco-0-294x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/sco-0-294x300.jpg 294w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/sco-0-768x782.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/sco-0.jpg 800w" width="416"/></p>
<p>PM Modi will travel to Samarkand in Uzbekistan to attend the first in-person summit of the SCO (Shanghai Cooperation Organisation) countries since the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
<h4>What is SCO?</h4>
<ul>
<li>After the collapse of the Soviet Union in 1991, the then security and economic architecture in the Eurasian region dissolved and new structures had to come up.</li>
<li>The original Shanghai Five were China, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Russia and Tajikistan.</li>
<li>The SCO was formed in 2001, with Uzbekistan included. It expanded in 2017 to include India and Pakistan.</li>
<li>Since its formation, the SCO has focused on regional non-traditional security, with counter-terrorism as a priority.</li>
<li>The fight against the “three evils” of terrorism, separatism and extremism has become its mantra. Today, areas of cooperation include themes such as economics and culture.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s entry to the SCO</h4>
<ul>
<li>India and Pakistan both were observer countries.</li>
<li>While Central Asian countries and China were not in favor of expansion initially, the main supporter — of India’s entry in particular — was Russia.</li>
<li>A widely held view is that Russia’s growing unease about an increasingly powerful China prompted it to push for its expansion.</li>
<li>From 2009 onwards, Russia officially supported India’s ambition to join the SCO in 2017.</li>
<li>China then asked for its all-weather friend Pakistan’s entry.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Changing the narrative of SCO</h4>
<p><img alt="sco" class="wp-image-635037 aligncenter" height="775" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/sco-125x300.jpg" width="323"/></p>
<ul>
<li>There has been discussion in the international arena that the trend of non-alignment is back.</li>
<li>NATO is based on Cold War thinking.</li>
<li>The logic of NATO is creating new enemies to sustain its own existence.</li>
<li>However, SCO is a cooperative organisation based on non-alignment and not targeting a third party.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India and SCO: Present status</h4>
<ul>
<li>India will host the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/shanghai-cooperation-organisation-sco/">SCO</a> summit next year, and Varanasi has been selected as the SCO region’s first “Tourism and Cultural Capital”.</li>
<li>India will also be chairing the summit.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pm-modi-to-attend-sco-meet/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India stays out of ‘Trade Pillar’ of IPEF</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-out-of-trade-pillar-of-ipef/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Indo-Pacific Economic Framework for Prosperity (IPEF)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>India stayed out of the joint declaration on the trade pillar of the US-led Indo-Pacific Economic Framework (IPEF) ministerial meet in Los Angeles, with Union Commerce Minister citing concerns over possible discrimination against developing economies.</p>
<h4><strong>Why did India opt out of the trade pillar?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>One of the reasons for staying out of the trade pillar was that the contours of the framework had not emerged yet.</li>
<li>This is particularly about the kind of commitment each country would have to make on “environment, labour, digital trade and public procurement”.</li>
<li>India’s decision also mirrors the decision to walk out after seven years of negotiations from the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-indias-exit-from-rcep-2/">Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership (RCEP)</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is IPEF?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is a US-led framework for participating countries to solidify their relationships and engage in crucial economic and trade matters that concern the region, such as building resilient supply chains battered by the pandemic.</li>
<li>It is not a free trade agreement. No market access or tariff reductions have been outlined, although experts say it can pave the way to trade deals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Members of IPEF</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The member nations include Australia, Brunei, India, Indonesia, Japan, South Korea, Malaysia, New Zealand, the Philippines, Singapore, Thailand and Vietnam.</li>
<li>It includes seven out of 10 members of the Association of South East Asian Nations (ASEAN), all four Quad countries, and New Zealand.</li>
<li>Together, these countries account for 40 per cent of the global GDP.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Four pillars of IPEF</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li><strong><u>Trade</u></strong> that will include digital economy and emerging technology, labor commitments, the environment, trade facilitation, transparency and good regulatory practices, and corporate accountability, standards on cross-border data flow and data localisations;</li>
<li><strong><u>Supply chain resilience</u></strong> to develop “a first-of-its-kind supply chain agreement” that would anticipate and prevent disruptions;</li>
<li><strong><u>Clean energy and decarbonization</u></strong> that will include agreements on “high-ambition commitments” such as renewable energy targets, carbon removal purchasing commitments, energy efficiency standards, and new measures to combat methane emissions; and</li>
<li><strong><u>Tax and anti-corruption</u></strong>, with commitments to enact and enforce “effective tax, anti-money laundering, anti-bribery schemes in line with [American] values”.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>How do members participate?  </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Countries are free to join</u></strong> (or not join) initiatives <strong><u>under any of the stipulated pillars</u></strong> but are expected to adhere to all commitments once they enrol.</li>
<li><strong><u>Negotiations are meant to determine and list the provisions</u></strong> under each pillar and open the floor for countries to choose their ‘commitments’.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>framework would be open to other countries willing to join in the future</u></strong> provided they are willing to adhere to the stipulated goals and other necessary obligations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reasons for the creation of IPEF</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>US regaining lost credibility:</strong> IPEF is also seen as a means by which the US is trying to regain credibility in the region after Trump pulled out of the Trans Pacific Partnership TPP).</li>
<li><strong>Rising Chinese influence:</strong> Since then, there has been concern over the absence of a credible US economic and trade strategy to counter China’s economic influence in the region.</li>
<li><strong>Competing RCEP:</strong> It is also in the 14-member Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership, of which the US is not a member (India withdrew from RCEP).</li>
<li><strong>“Pivot to Asia” strategy:</strong> US has intensified its engagement with the wider Asia-Pacific region to advance its economic and geopolitical interests.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>India’s perception of IPEF</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>PM Modi described the grouping as born from a collective desire to make the Indo-Pacific region an engine of global economic growth.</li>
<li>India has called for common and creative solutions to tackle economic challenges in the Indo-Pacific region.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does it have to do with China?  </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The US strategists believe the <strong><u>US lacks an economic and trade strategy to counter China</u></strong>’s increasing economic influence in the region since 2017.</li>
<li>US <strong><u>companies are looking to move away from manufacturing in China</u></strong>.</li>
<li>IPEF would therefore offer an advantage to participating countries, allowing them <strong><u>to bring those businesses into their territory.</u></strong></li>
<li>However, it <strong><u>officially excluded Taiwan</u></strong> despite its <strong><u>willingness and economic merit to join</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This exhibits <strong><u>Washington’s geopolitical caution</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reactions from the opponents</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi criticized the initiative as an attempt to further <strong><u>economic decoupling from China.</u></strong></li>
<li>He argued that the initiative, and the US Indo-Pacific strategy as a whole, <strong><u>created divisions and incited confrontation</u></strong>. It is destined to be <strong><u>ultimately be a failure</u></strong>.</li>
<li><strong><u>Taiwan was excluded</u></strong> in order <strong><u>to appease key “fence-sitter” countries such as Indonesia</u></strong> whose governments feared angering China.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues with IPEF framework</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>IPEF would <strong><u>neither constitute a ‘free trade agreement,’ nor a forum to discuss tariff</u></strong> reductions or increasing market access.</li>
<li>Unlike a traditional trade agreement, the <strong><u>US administration will not need congressional approval</u></strong> to act under the IPEF. Hence its <strong><u>legal status is</u></strong> <strong>questionable</strong>.</li>
<li>This also raises doubts among potential participants about their <strong><u>reluctance to offer significant concessions under the agreement.</u></strong></li>
<li>The <strong><u>volatility of US domestic politics</u></strong> has raised concerns about IPEF’s durability.</li>
<li>Unlike traditional FTAs, the <strong><u>IPEF does not subscribe to the single undertaking principle</u></strong>, where all items on the agenda are negotiated simultaneously.</li>
</ul>
<p>Given the divisive nature of American politics, it is unclear whether the IPEF will survive past the Biden administration.</p>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The IPEF’s launch in Tokyo was symbolic in nature; bringing the IPEF to fruition will involve significant domestic and international challenges.</li>
<li>Without ratification by Congress, the IPEF’s fortunes will remain in limbo.</li>
<li>Going forward, the US and the founding partners need to develop the process and criteria by which other countries from the region will be invited to join the negotiations on the IPEF.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-out-of-trade-pillar-of-ipef/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>New adoption rules create confusion</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/new-adoption-rules-create-confusion/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CARA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Child Adoption</p></div></div><p><img alt="adoption" class="alignnone wp-image-635040" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 436px) 100vw, 436px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/adoption-300x230.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/adoption-300x230.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/adoption.jpg 500w" width="436"/></p>
<p>There is confusion over the implementation of new adoption rules that require the transfer of adoption petitions from courts to District Magistrates (DMs).</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>From September 1, DMs have been empowered to give adoption orders instead of courts.</li>
<li>All cases pending before courts have to be now transferred.</li>
<li>Hundreds of adoptive parents in the country are now concerned that the transfer process will further delay what is already a long and tedious process.</li>
<li>There are questions whether an order passed by the executive will pass muster when an adopted child’s entitlements on succession and inheritance are contested before a court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Adoption in India: A backgrounder</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2015, the then Minister for Women and Child Development centralised the entire adoption system by empowering <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/panel-moots-district-level-survey-to-bring-more-children-into-adoption-ambit/">Central Adoption Resource Authority (CARA</a>).</li>
<li>It was empowered to maintain in various specialised adoption agencies, a registry of children, prospective adoptive parents as well as match them before adoption.</li>
<li>This was aimed at checking rampant corruption and trafficking as child care institutions and NGOs could directly give children for adoption after obtaining a no-objection certificate from CARA.</li>
</ul>
<h4>DMs to issue Adoption Orders</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Parliament passed the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) Amendment Bill, 2021 in order to amend the Juvenile Justice Act (JJ Act), 2015.</li>
<li>The key changes include authorising District Magistrates and Additional District Magistrates to issue adoption orders under Section 61 of the JJ Act by striking out the word “court”.</li>
<li>This was done “in order to ensure speedy disposal of cases and enhance accountability,” according to a government statement.</li>
<li>The DMs have also been empowered under the Act to inspect child care institutions as well as evaluate the functioning of district child protection units, child welfare committees, juvenile justice boards, specialised juvenile police units, child care institutions etc.</li>
</ul>
<p>Why is there concern over the revised rules?</p>
<ul>
<li>Parents, activists, lawyers and adoption agencies will have to be transferred and the <strong><u>process will have to start afresh</u></strong>.</li>
<li>A <strong><u>delay</u></strong> in such an order can often mean that a <strong><u>child can’t get admission into a school</u></strong> because parents don’t yet have a birth certificate.</li>
<li>Parents and lawyers also state that <strong><u>neither judges, nor DMs are aware about the change in the JJ Act</u></strong> leading to confusion in the system and delays.</li>
<li><strong><u>DMs don’t handle civil matters</u></strong> that bestow inheritance and succession rights on a child.</li>
<li>If these rights are contested when a child turns 18, a judicial order is far more tenable to ensure the child is not <strong><u>deprived of his or her entitlements</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Is it such a big issue?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Central Adoption Resource Authority (CARA) says there are <strong><u>nearly 1,000 adoption cases pending</u></strong> before various courts in the country.</li>
<li>This is not such a huge burden.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What is the adoption procedure in India?  </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Adoptions in India are governed by two laws:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Hindu Adoption and Maintenance Act, 1956 (HAMA):</strong> It is a parent-centric law that provides son to the son-less for reasons of succession, inheritance, continuance of family name and for funeral rights and later adoption of daughters was incorporated because kanyadaan is considered an important part of dharma in Hindu tradition.</li>
<li><strong>Juvenile Justice Act, 2015:</strong> It handles issues of children in conflict with law as well as those who are in need of care and protection and only has a small chapter on adoptions.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Both laws have their separate eligibility criteria for adoptive parents.</li>
<li>Those applying under the JJ Act have to register on CARA’s portal after which a specialised adoption agency carries out a home study report.</li>
<li>After it finds the candidate eligible for adoption, a child declared legally free for adoption is referred to the applicant.</li>
<li>Under HAMA, a “<strong><u>dattaka hom</u></strong>” ceremony or an adoption deed or a court order is sufficient to obtain irrevocable adoption rights.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with child adoption in India</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Parent-centrism:</strong> The current adoption approach is very parent-centred, but parents must make it child-centred.</li>
<li><strong>Age of child:</strong> Most Indian parents also want a child between the ages of zero and two, believing that this is when the parent-child bond is formed.</li>
<li><strong>Institutional issues:</strong> Because the ratio of abandoned children to children in institutionalised care is lopsided, there are not enough children available for adoption.</li>
<li><strong>Lineage discrimination:</strong> Most Indians have a distorted view of adoption because they want their genes, blood, and lineage to be passed down to their children.</li>
<li><strong>Red-tapism:</strong> Child adoption is also not so easy task after the Juvenile Justice Rules of 2016 and the Adoption Regulations of 2017 were launched.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Practical issues in adoption </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There are <strong><u>no rules for monitoring adoptions</u></strong> and verifying sourcing of children and determining whether parents are fit to adopt.</li>
<li>There are many problems with the adoption system under CARA but at the heart of it is the fact that <strong><u>there are very few children in its registry. </u></strong></li>
<li>According to the latest figures there are only 2,188 children in the adoption pool, while there are more than 31,000 parents waiting to adopt a child.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/new-adoption-rules-create-confusion/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the Kushiyara River Treaty?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-kushiyara-river-treaty/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Kushiyara River</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="Kushiyara" class="alignnone wp-image-635035" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 401px) 100vw, 401px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kushi-300x250.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kushi-300x250.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kushi-1024x852.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kushi-768x639.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kushi-1082x900.jpg 1082w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kushi.jpg 1200w" width="401"/></strong></p>
<p>For the first time in 26 years, India and Bangladesh agreed to share the waters of a significant transboundary river, the Kushiyara, while negotiations over a long-delayed agreement to share the Teesta River’s waters, which are politically sensitive are still ongoing.</p>
<h4>India-Bangla water disputes: A backgrounder</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Teesta River and the Ganges River</u></strong> dispute are the two main long-standing water conflicts between India and Bangladesh.</li>
<li>Both rivers are important supplies of water for fishermen, farmers, and boatmen in both nations.</li>
<li>Since the sacred river flows from India to Bangladesh, the Ganga river dispute has been a source of contention between the two countries for the past 35 years.</li>
<li>There <strong><u>hasn’t been a long-term solution for sharing water</u></strong> offered despite several rounds of bilateral negotiations failing.</li>
<li>In order to establish a water sharing arrangement for the following 30 years, a treaty was signed in 1996. This deal is about to expire.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the Kushiyara River Treaty?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The first such deal since the 1996 signing of the Ganga water treaty, India and Bangladesh reached an interim agreement on water sharing for the Kushiyara River.</li>
<li><strong><u>India withdrew its objection</u></strong> to withdrawal of Kushiyara’s waters by Bangladesh through the Rahimpur Canal.</li>
<li>Over the last century, the flow of the Barak river has changed in such a way that the bulk of the river’s water flows into Kushiyara while the rest goes into Surma.</li>
<li>The agreement is aimed at addressing part of the problem that the changing nature of the river has posed before Bangladesh as it unleashes floods during the monsoon.</li>
<li>It goes dry during the winter when demand of water goes up because of a crop cycle in Sylhet.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Terms of the treaty</h4>
<ul>
<li>Under this MoU, <strong><u>Bangladesh will be able to withdraw 153 cusecs</u></strong> (cubic feet per second) of water from the Kushiyara out of the approximately 2,500 cusecs of water that is there in the river during the winter season.</li>
<li>The agreement <strong><u>addresses Bangladesh’s concern over water supply</u></strong> along the river, during the winter months but <strong><u>flood control</u></strong> in the basin of Kushiyara is expected to require much more work.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How will Bangladesh use the water?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The water of Kushiyara will be channelled through the <strong><u>Rahimpur Canal project</u></strong> in Sylhet.</li>
<li>The eight km long canal is the only supplier of water from the Kushiyara to the region and Bangladesh has built a pump house and other facilities for withdrawal of water that can now be utilised.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Benefits to Bangladesh</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is generally understood that approximately <strong><u>10,000 hectares of land and millions of people will benefit</u></strong> from the water that will flow through a network of canals in Sylhet.</li>
<li>It will benefit the farmers involved in Boro rice, which is basically the rice cultivated during the dry season of December to February and harvested in early summer.</li>
<li>Bangladesh has been complaining that the <strong><u>Boro rice cultivation</u></strong> in the region had been suffering as India did not allow it to withdraw the required water from the Kushiyara.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the water from the Kushiyara so important for Rahimpur Canal?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The water of the <strong><u>Kushiyara has been used for centuries</u></strong> in Sylhet’s subdivisions like the Zakiganj, Kanaighat and Beanibazar areas.</li>
<li>But Bangladesh has witnessed that the <strong><u>flow and volume of water in the canal has reduced</u></strong> during the lean season.</li>
<li>The utility of the river and the canal during the lean/winter season had gone down, affecting cultivation of rice as well as a wide variety of vegetables for which Sylhet is famous.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What was India’s objection to the Rahimpur Canal?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India objected to the <strong><u>clearing and dredging</u></strong> of canal.</li>
<li>It claimed that the <strong><u>dyke and other infrastructure interfered in border security</u></strong> as Kushiyara itself forms part of the border between the two sides.</li>
<li>However, the agreement indicates that the <strong><u>economic benefits possible from the river outweighed the security</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the hurdles to the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/teesta-water-sharing-issue/">Teesta agreement</a>?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Kushiyara agreement is relatively smaller in scale in comparison to Teesta that <strong><u>involves West Bengal</u></strong>, which has problems with the proposal.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Kushiyara agreement did not require a nod from any of the States</u></strong> like Assam from which the Barak emerges and branches into Kushiyara and Surma.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-kushiyara-river-treaty/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Our apple farmers should be supported enthusiastically</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/apple-farmers/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>farmers welfare</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="apple farmers" class="alignnone wp-image-634926" height="348" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 464px) 100vw, 464px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/apple-cultivation-on-encroached-forest-land-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/apple-cultivation-on-encroached-forest-land-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/apple-cultivation-on-encroached-forest-land-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/apple-cultivation-on-encroached-forest-land.jpg 800w" width="464"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The increasing cost of production and the increase in GST on apple cartons has triggered protests in Himachal Pradesh’s apple farmers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the issue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The cost of production of agricultural items increased substantially, denying remunerative prices to the poor and marginal apple farmers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reason for crisis in apple farming</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increase in cost of production: </strong>The input cost of fertilizers, insecticides, and fungicides has risen in the last decade by 300%, as per some estimates. The cost of apple cartons and trays and packaging has also seen a dramatic rise. In the last decade, the cost of a carton, for instance, has risen from about ₹30 to ₹ The cost borne to market the Produce has also risen.</li>
<li><strong>High taxation: </strong>The increase in the Goods and Services Tax on cartons from 12% to 18%. This was done to ensure that farmers are forced to sell their produce to big buyers instead of selling it in the open market. Just as the three farm laws were designed on the pretext of getting rid of the middlemen, the argument here was that commission agents, who fleece the apple farmers, will be forced to exit the picture. But this leaves the apple growers at the mercy of large giants in procurement, who have precedence of even deciding the procurement price.</li>
<li><strong>No MSP in Himachal: </strong>Unlike in Jammu and Kashmir, where there is a minimum rate for procurement, there is no such law in Himachal. The government also does not seem prepared to bring in such a law. The farmers are demanding that legally guaranteed procurement at a <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/back-in-news-minimum-support-price-msp/">Minimum Support Price</a> (C2+50%) should be ensured to improve apple farmers condition.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="apple farmers" class="alignnone wp-image-634928" height="366" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 552px) 100vw, 552px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_3largeimg_782680985-300x199.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_3largeimg_782680985-300x199.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_3largeimg_782680985.jpeg 660w" width="552"/>How to address this issue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Need for a regulator: </strong>What is required is an independent body that is duly supported and trusted by the farmers. Such a body should have representatives of apple growers, market players, commission agents and the government. This must be a statutory body that is also given the task of conducting research in the apple economy.</li>
<li><strong>Directional efforts: </strong>Issues such as high input cost, lack of fair price and unavailability of infrastructure such as cold chains should be addressed.</li>
<li><strong>Required research to support improvements in apple farming systems</strong>: Over the past few decades, the priorities in research projects and government policies on apple production were focused on the improvement of tree productivity and product quality. This was important to enhance the net incomes and living standards of apple producers in India. This research should be further enhanced by introducing European varieties in India.</li>
<li><strong>Focussing on Alternative Market Channels: </strong>The alternative market channel works on the principles of decentralisation and direct-to-home delivery. The idea is to create smaller, less congested markets in urban areas with the participation of farmers’ groups and Farmer Producer Companies (FPCs) so that farmers have direct access to consumers.</li>
<li><strong>Logistics transformation: </strong>To sustain the demand for agricultural commodities, investments in key logistics must be enhanced. Moreover, e-commerce and delivery companies and start-ups need to be encouraged with suitable policies and incentives. The small and medium enterprises, running with raw materials from the agriculture and allied sector or otherwise, also need special attention so that the rural economy doesn’t collapse.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="apple farmers" class="alignnone wp-image-634929" height="333" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/apple1-1598518281-lb-300x172.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/apple1-1598518281-lb-300x172.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/apple1-1598518281-lb.jpg 740w" width="581"/>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Agriculture is dying, not as in the production of food but as a desirable profession. One bad yield, whether due to errant rains, pests, etc., and most farmers have no buffer available. The last point worth considering is that food and agriculture are not the same. Expenditures on food span the value-add, including processing, preparation, service in restaurants, etc. Farmers in India merely get paid for their product and not for the food we eat.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Do you think there is urgent need to extend MSP to horticulture sector also? Discuss what can be done to solve the apple farmer crisis in Himachal Pradesh.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/apple-farmers/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Kashmiri pandits  should be heard to deliver justice .</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/kashmiri-pandits/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>national integration</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Kashmiri pandits" class="alignnone wp-image-634941" height="223" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 423px) 100vw, 423px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/856145-72550-hryioskhjb-1509453250-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/856145-72550-hryioskhjb-1509453250-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/856145-72550-hryioskhjb-1509453250-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/856145-72550-hryioskhjb-1509453250-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/856145-72550-hryioskhjb-1509453250.jpg 1200w" width="423"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Recent events of targeted killings of Kashmiri pandits and other Hindus by the militants in the valley lead to the protests which once again brought forward the question of their right to return and the safety of minorities living in the valley</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who are the Kashmiri pandits?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Kashmiri Pandits are one of the highest ranked Brahman castes who are the natives of the valley, locally known as pundits.</li>
<li>They were the minority in the valley comprising only 5% of the total population.</li>
<li>Traditionally dependent on agriculture and small-scale business and one of the favored sections in the administration.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-kashmiri-pandit-exodus/"><strong>What is the conflict?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Radical Islamists and militants started targeting the Kashmiri pundits putting in front the option of either of conversion or persecution.</li>
<li>The Growth of militancy in the 1990s forced Kashmiri pandits to leave the valley in greater numbers. They started migrating to the other states, leaving every belonging behind and seeking refuge in other parts.</li>
<li>While many of them started migrating some decided to stay back in their homeland.</li>
<li>Conflict arose between radical Islamists organization and the Hindus leading to the mass killings of the Kashmiri Hindus in waves which is termed as exodus.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="kashmiri pandit" class="alignnone wp-image-634946" height="260" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 462px) 100vw, 462px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/412983-full-2-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/412983-full-2-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/412983-full-2-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/412983-full-2-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/412983-full-2-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/412983-full-2-1200x676.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/412983-full-2.jpg 1819w" width="462"/>What has been done so far?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>After the Pandit exodus from the Valley in the 1990s, the first few years of this century saw government efforts to send Pandits back to the Valley.</li>
<li>Under the Prime Minister’s return and rehabilitation of Kashmir migrants scheme, created government postings in the Valley for Kashmiri Pandit “migrant” youth.</li>
<li>Mostly, teachers and these government employees have lived in protected high security enclaves, but their work requires them to leave these enclaves and mingle with the rest of the population. Another segment, known as “non-migrant” Pandits because they never left the Valley, has lived in their own homes, without state-provided protection.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is CDR?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Centre for dialogue and reconciliation (CDR) is a Delhi-based think-tank incorporated in March 2001, aims to be a catalyst for peace in South Asia.</li>
<li>CDR working for the peace-building process in Jammu Kashmir, supported the initiative of dialogue between the two communities as a part of self-assessment, acknowledging the mistakes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="kashmiri pandits" class="alignnone wp-image-634947" height="324" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 506px) 100vw, 506px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kashmiri-pandits-pti2-1654090920-300x192.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kashmiri-pandits-pti2-1654090920-300x192.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kashmiri-pandits-pti2-1654090920.jpg 715w" width="506"/>What did CDR do in Kashmir?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>CDR supported the initiative for a dialogue proposed by two prominent young Kashmiris one a Muslim and the other a Pandit both who have witnessed the violence of 1990 and the subsequent years.</li>
<li>They believe in the principle of talking could lead to healing.</li>
<li>It led to CDR’s ‘Shared Witness’, a Pandit-Muslim dialogue series, in December 2010.</li>
<li>Public intellectuals and other influential persons from both communities were participants</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Observations of the dialogue </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The dialogue series coincided with the launching of the Prime Minister’s job scheme.</li>
<li>Dialogues created a social environment that enabled Kashmiri Pandits to take up government postings in the Valley.</li>
<li>They focused on the events in and around 1990, and the incidents that triggered the displacement of the Pandit community.</li>
<li>By the third dialogue, participants were sharing individual experiences that did not fit into the narrative that each community had built about the other.</li>
<li>The process of the conversation lead them to think on the actual reason behind the conflict, was it communal differences, or was it only religion?</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>From the eyes of the pandits</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Pandits were aggrieved that the Muslims did not protest the Pandit killings, not even when the killers claimed them. That greater responsibility lay with the Muslims as they were the majority.</li>
<li>If some social organizations had acted quickly, the exodus could have been stopped.</li>
<li>They observed that the Pandit community too had suffered from a lack of leadership.</li>
<li>They demand an apology and to set up of possible “Truth commission”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What do the Muslims say?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Muslim participants felt the Pandits were in denial of the struggle of the Muslims in the Valley, who were facing violence from the system.</li>
<li>The Kashmiri Muslim was always portrayed as being misguided, aided, and abetted by Pakistan.</li>
<li>The protest in Kashmir was not against religion but against structures of power and oppression.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Current situation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The fresh spate of targeted killings of Kashmir pandits created an environment of fear and provided a major setback to their rehabilitation in the Kashmir valley.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>We need urgent civil society engagement between communities in Kashmir once again.</li>
<li>The government can enable it, but individuals and civil society will need to create conditions on the ground. They will have to encourage people to give up the blame game.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Dialogue can bring peace in Kashmir valley. Critically examine.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/kashmiri-pandits/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Sustainable and green tourism is strong sunrise sector for our promising hospitality</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tourism/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>tourism as economic driver</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-634949" height="284" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 453px) 100vw, 453px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Career-in-Travel-and-Tourism-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Career-in-Travel-and-Tourism-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Career-in-Travel-and-Tourism-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Career-in-Travel-and-Tourism-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Career-in-Travel-and-Tourism.jpg 880w" width="453"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Ministry of Tourism identified Tourism Industry’s potential as a Sunrise Industry.</li>
<li>There is a need for tourism analysts to hold tourism planners accountable.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism is travel for pleasure or business; also the theory and practice of touring, the business of attracting, accommodating, and entertaining tourists, and the business of operating tours.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Types of tourism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Domestic tourism</strong>: Refers to activities of a visitor within their country of residence and outside of their home (e.g. a Indian visiting other parts of India)</li>
<li><strong>Inbound tourism</strong>: Refers to the activities of a visitor from outside of country of residence (e.g. a Spaniard visiting Britain).</li>
<li><strong>Outbound tourism</strong>: Refers to the activities of a resident visitor outside of their country of residence (e.g. an Indian visiting an overseas country).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does sustainable tourism mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sustainable tourism is defined by the UN Environment Program and UN World Tourism Organization as “tourism that takes full account of its current and future economic, social and environmental impacts, addressing the needs of visitors, the industry, the environment and host communities.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-634950" height="331" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 497px) 100vw, 497px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pexels-asad-photo-maldives-1268855-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pexels-asad-photo-maldives-1268855-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pexels-asad-photo-maldives-1268855-1024x681.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pexels-asad-photo-maldives-1268855-768x511.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pexels-asad-photo-maldives-1268855-1536x1022.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pexels-asad-photo-maldives-1268855-2048x1363.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pexels-asad-photo-maldives-1268855-1200x798.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pexels-asad-photo-maldives-1268855-1980x1317.jpg 1980w" width="497"/>What is the main importance of tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism boosts the revenue of the economy, creates thousands of jobs, develops the infrastructures of a country, and plants a sense of cultural exchange between foreigners and citizens.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why tourism is needed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism is not a fad. It is a compulsion driven by the urge to discover new places. Because we have this compulsion to venture into the unknown, we need each other. When humans travel, meet and exchange ideas, civilisation flourishes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What should be done to promote tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>National Tourism Authority</strong>: A separate National Tourism Authority (NTA) should be established for executing and operationalizing various tourism related initiatives. Simple, flexible and elegant processes will be laid down to allow for nimbleness.</li>
<li><strong>National Tourism Advisory Board</strong>: A National Tourism Advisory Board (NTAB) should be set up to provide overall vision, guidance and direction to the Development of Tourism Sector in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Creating Synergy in Tourism Eco System</strong>: In order to ensure synergy at various levels of Government and with the Private Sector, it is important to have a well-defined framework in place.</li>
<li><strong>Quality Tourism Framework</strong>: A robust framework for quality certification of products and services across all segments like accommodation providers, tour operators, adventure tour operators, service providers like spa and wellness, guides, restaurants etc. should be laid down.</li>
<li><strong>Enhancing the existing luxury tourism products:</strong> The existing tourism products such as Nilgiri Mountain Railway, Palace on Wheels etc. should be enhanced and their numbers will also be increased. Haulage charges will be rationalised to make luxury trains viable.</li>
<li><strong>Railways can be a game changer:</strong> For tourism Railways have presence in most parts of the country. Most of the tourist destinations in the country are connected by rail. Railways is also in the process of connecting more places especially the strategic locations that also are tourist places with limited connectivity at present. Indian Railways is working towards promoting tourism in the country by operating more trains connecting tourists’ destinations and also by providing an array of products starting from luxury tourist trains to budget catering tourist trains</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-634951" height="219" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 389px) 100vw, 389px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital_Communication__Tourism_EWM_Digital_Agency_Geneva-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital_Communication__Tourism_EWM_Digital_Agency_Geneva-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital_Communication__Tourism_EWM_Digital_Agency_Geneva-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital_Communication__Tourism_EWM_Digital_Agency_Geneva-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital_Communication__Tourism_EWM_Digital_Agency_Geneva-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital_Communication__Tourism_EWM_Digital_Agency_Geneva-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital_Communication__Tourism_EWM_Digital_Agency_Geneva.jpg 1920w" width="389"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gujarats-mice-tourism-policy/">What is MICE tourism of Gujarat?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The acronym “MICE” stands for “Meetings, Incentives, Conferences and Exhibitions”, and is essentially a version of business tourism that draws domestic and international tourists to a destination.</li>
<li>The policy aims to make Gujarat one of the top five MICE tourism destinations in the country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Enhance the contribution of tourism in Indian economy by increasing the visitation, stay and spend</li>
<li>Create jobs and entrepreneurial opportunities in tourism sector and ensure supply of skilled work force</li>
<li>Enhance the competitiveness of tourism sector and attract private sector investment</li>
<li>Preserve and enhance the cultural and natural resources of the country</li>
<li>To ensure sustainable, responsible and inclusive development of tourism in the country</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>We know that India has the highest tourism potential of any country. That is because we have every terrain and climate zone, and a range of customs, traditions, cuisines, crafts, art forms and festivals unmatched by any other nation. We should monetize our potential through putting comprehensive National tourism policy in place.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What should be done to transform our tourist destinations to provide world class visitor experience making India one of the topmost destinations for sustainable and responsible tourism?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tourism/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Cloudbursts forecast in India still remains elusive?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cloudbursts-forecast-in-india-still-remains-elusive/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Cloudburst</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Flash floods and cloudbursts</p></div></div><p><img alt="cloudbursts" class="alignnone wp-image-635041" height="444" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 420px) 100vw, 420px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloudburst-284x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloudburst-284x300.jpg 284w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cloudburst.jpg 509w" width="420"/></p>
<p>The characteristics of cloud burst events remain elusive, and our efforts in monitoring and forecasting them is at an embryonic stage.</p>
<p>Cyclones can be predicted about one week in advance. However, <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-cloudbursts/">cloudburst</a> forecasts still remain elusive.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Cloudbursts?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A cloudburst is a localised but intense rainfall activity.</li>
<li>Short spells of very heavy rainfall over a small geographical area can cause widespread destruction, especially in hilly regions where this phenomenon is the most common.</li>
<li>Not all instances of very heavy rainfall, however, are cloudbursts.</li>
<li>A cloudburst has a very specific definition: Rainfall of 10 cm or more in an hour over a roughly 10 km x 10-km area is classified as a cloudburst event.</li>
<li>By this definition, 5 cm of rainfall in a half-hour period over the same area would also be categorized as a cloudburst.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Which clouds do burst?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cloudburst events are often associated with <strong><u>cumulonimbus clouds</u></strong> that cause thunderstorms and occasionally due to monsoon wind surges and other weather phenomena.</li>
<li>Cumulonimbus clouds can grow up to <strong><u>12-15 km in height</u></strong> through the entire troposphere (occasionally up to 21 km) and can hold huge amounts of water.</li>
<li>Tall cumulonimbus clouds can develop in about half an hour as the moisture updraft happens rapidly, at a pace of 60 to 120 km/hr.</li>
<li>A single-cell cloud may last for an hour and <strong><u>dump all the rain in the last 20 to 30 minutes</u></strong>, while some of these clouds merge to form multi-cell storms and last for several hours.</li>
<li>However, cloudbursts are not defined based on cloud characteristics and do not indicate clouds exploding. Cloudbursts are defined by the amount of rainfall.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How is it different from normal rainfall?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to the India Meteorological Department (IMD), 100 mm of rain in an hour is called a cloudburst.</li>
<li>Usually, cloudbursts occur over a small geographical region of 20 to 30 sq. km.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>When do they occur? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In India, cloudbursts often occur during the monsoon season, when the southwesterly monsoon winds bring in copious amounts of moisture inland.</li>
<li>The moist air that converges over land gets lifted as they encounter the hills.</li>
<li>The moist air reaches an altitude and gets saturated, and the water starts condensing out of the air forming clouds.</li>
<li>This is how clouds usually form, but such an orographic lifting together with a strong moisture convergence can lead to intense cumulonimbus clouds taking in huge volumes of moisture that is dumped during cloudbursts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How common are cloudbursts?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cloudbursts are not uncommon events, particularly during the monsoon months.</li>
<li>Most of these happen in the Himalayan states where the local topology, wind systems, and temperature gradients between the lower and upper atmosphere facilitate the occurrence of such events.</li>
<li>However, not every event that is described as a cloudburst is actually, by definition, a cloudburst.</li>
<li>That is because these events are highly localized.</li>
<li>They take place in very small areas which are often devoid of rainfall measuring instruments.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Climate change and cloudbursts: How are they related?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Climate change is projected to increase the frequency and intensity of cloudbursts worldwide.</li>
<li>As the air gets warmer, it can hold more moisture and for a longer time. We call this the <strong><u>Clausius Clapeyron relationship. </u></strong></li>
<li>A <strong><u>1-degree Celsius rise in temperature may correspond to a 7-10% increase in moisture and rainfall</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This increase in <strong><u>rainfall amount does not get spread moderately</u></strong> throughout the season.</li>
<li>As the moisture holding <strong><u>capacity of air increases</u></strong>, it results in prolonged dry periods intermittent with short spells of extreme rains.</li>
<li><strong><u>Deeper cumulonimbus clouds will form</u></strong> and the chances of cloudbursts also increase.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why are they so destructive?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The consequences of these events, however, <strong><u>are not confined to small areas</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Because of the nature of terrain, the heavy rainfall events often <strong><u>trigger landslides and flash floods</u></strong>, causing extensive destruction downstream.</li>
<li>This is the reason why every sudden downpour that leads to destruction of life and property in the hilly areas gets described as a “cloudburst”, irrespective of whether the amount of rainfall meets the defining criteria.</li>
<li>At the same time, it is also possible that actual cloudburst events in remote locations aren’t recorded.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Detecting cloudbursts</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Satellites are extensively useful in detecting large-scale monsoon weather systems.</li>
<li>However the <strong><u>resolution of the precipitation radars of these satellites can be much smaller</u></strong> than the area of individual cloudburst events, and hence they go undetected.</li>
<li>Weather <strong><u>forecast models also face a similar challenge</u></strong> in simulating the clouds at a high resolution.</li>
<li>The skillful forecasting of rainfall in hilly regions remains challenging due to the uncertainties in the interaction between the <strong><u>moisture convergence and the hilly terrain</u></strong>.</li>
<li>There also involves the <strong><u>cloud microphysics, and the heating-cooling mechanisms</u></strong> at different atmospheric levels.</li>
<li><strong><u>Multiple radars</u></strong> can be a quick measure for providing warnings, but radars <strong><u>are an expensive affair</u></strong>, and installing them across the country may not be practically feasible.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Solutions to cloudbursts forecast</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Multiple doppler weather radars</u></strong> can be used to monitor moving cloud droplets and help to provide nowcasts (forecasts for the next three hours).</li>
<li>A long-term measure would be <strong><u>mapping the cloudburst-prone regions</u></strong> using automatic rain gauges.</li>
<li>If cloudburst-prone regions are <strong><u>co-located with landslide-prone regions</u></strong>, these locations can be designated as hazardous.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cloudbursts-forecast-in-india-still-remains-elusive/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Supreme Court to take up CAA Challenge</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/supreme-court-to-take-up-caa-challenge/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CAA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>A three-judge Bench of the Supreme Court led by Chief Justice of India (CJI) U U Lalit will hear the challenge to the contentious Citizenship (Amendment) Act.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Citizenship Amendment Act (CAA), 2019?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The act is sought <strong>to</strong> <strong>amend the Citizenship Act, 1955</strong> to make Hindu, Sikh, Buddhist, Jain, Parsi, and Christian illegal migrants from Afghanistan, Bangladesh, and Pakistan, eligible for citizenship of India.</li>
<li>In other words, it intends to make it easier for non-Muslim immigrants from India’s three Muslim-majority neighbours to become citizens of India.</li>
<li>Under The Citizenship Act, 1955, one of the requirements for citizenship by naturalization is that the applicant must have resided in India during the last 12 months, as well as for 11 of the previous 14 years.</li>
<li>The amendment relaxes the second requirement from 11 years to 6 years as a specific condition for applicants belonging to these six religions, and the aforementioned three countries.</li>
<li>It exempts the members of the six communities from any criminal case under the Foreigners Act, 1946 and the Passport Act, 1920 if they entered India before December 31, 2014.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Key feature: Defining illegal migrants</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Illegal migrants cannot become Indian citizens in accordance with the present laws.</li>
<li>Under the CAA, an illegal migrant is a foreigner who: (i) enters the country without valid travel documents like a passport and visa, or (ii) enters with valid documents, but stays beyond the permitted time period.</li>
<li>Illegal migrants may be put in jail or deported under the Foreigners Act, 1946 and The Passport (Entry into India) Act, 1920.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Exceptions</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Bill provides that illegal migrants who fulfil four conditions will not be treated as illegal migrants under the Act.  The conditions are:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>they are Hindus, Sikhs, Buddhists, Jains, Parsis or Christians;</li>
<li>they are from Afghanistan, Bangladesh or Pakistan;</li>
<li>they entered India on or before December 31, 2014;</li>
<li>they are not in certain tribal areas of Assam, Meghalaya, Mizoram, or Tripura included in the Sixth Schedule to the Constitution, or areas under the “Inner Line” permit, i.e., Arunachal Pradesh, Mizoram, and Nagaland.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Controversy with the Act</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Country of Origin:</strong> The Act classifies migrants based on their country of origin to include only Afghanistan, Pakistan and Bangladesh.</li>
<li><strong>Other religious minorities ignored:</strong> It is unclear why illegal migrants from only six specified religious minorities have been included in the Act.</li>
<li><strong>Defiance of purpose:</strong> India shares a border with Myanmar, which has had a history of persecution of a religious minority, the Rohingya Muslims.</li>
<li><strong>Date of Entry:</strong> It is also unclear why there is a differential treatment of migrants based on their date of entry into India, i.e., whether they entered India before or after December 31, 2014.</li>
<li><strong>Against the spirit of Secularism:</strong> Further, granting citizenship on the grounds of religion is seen to be against the secular nature of the Constitution which has been recognised as part of the basic structure that cannot be altered by Parliament.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Basis of challenging in Supreme Court</h4>
<ul>
<li>The challenge rests primarily on the grounds that the <strong><u>law violates Article 14 of the Constitution</u></strong> that guarantees that no person shall be denied the right to equality before law or the equal protection of law in the territory of India.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Supreme Court has developed a <strong><u>two-pronged test to examine a law</u></strong> on the grounds of Article 14.</p>
<ol>
<li>First, any <strong><u>differentiation between groups</u></strong> of persons must be founded on “intelligible differentia”</li>
<li>Second, that <strong><u>differentia must have a rational nexus</u></strong> to the object sought to be achieved by the Act</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Simply put, for a law to satisfy the conditions under Article 14, it has to first create a <strong><u>“reasonable class” of subjects</u></strong> that it seeks to govern under the law.</li>
<li>Even <strong><u>if the classification is reasonable</u></strong>, any person who falls in that category has to be treated alike.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What happens next?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The listing of the CAA challenge indicates that the <strong><u>hearing will be fast-tracked</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The court will have to ensure that all pleadings, written submissions are filed and served to the opposite party before it is listed for final hearing.</li>
<li>Some petitioners could also seek a <strong><u>referral to a larger Constitution Bench</u></strong>.</li>
<li>However, the challenge is to a statute and does not directly involve interpretation of the Constitution.</li>
<li>These issues are also likely to be debated before the court allots time for the final hearing.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India is a constitutional democracy with a basic structure that assures a secure and spacious home for all Indians.</li>
<li>Being partitioned on religious grounds, India has to undertake a balancing act for protecting the religious minorities in its neighbourhood.</li>
<li>These minorities are under constant threat of persecution and vandalism.</li>
<li>India needs to balance its civilization duties to protect those who are prosecuted in the neighbourhood.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/supreme-court-to-take-up-caa-challenge/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Cheetah reintroduction is right step for biodiversity conservation here is why</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cheetah/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>environment conservation</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Cheetah" class="alignnone wp-image-635348" height="378" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 668px) 100vw, 668px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cheeta-300x170.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cheeta-300x170.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cheeta.jpg 609w" width="668"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>African cheetahs from Namibia will arrive in India September 17, 2022. This is the world’s first intercontinental translocation of a carnivore. It is even more unique because this is the first time cheetahs will be reintroduced in an unfenced protected area (PA).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>About Asiatic Cheetah</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Feature:</strong> Cheetah, the world’s fastest land animal was declared extinct in India in 1952.</li>
<li><strong>Status</strong>: The Asiatic cheetah is classified as a “critically endangered” species by the IUCN Red List, and is believed to survive only in Iran.</li>
<li><strong>Reintroduction</strong>: It was expected to be re-introduced into the country after the Supreme Court lifted curbs for its re-introduction.</li>
<li><strong>Extinction: </strong>From 400 in the 1990s, their numbers are estimated to have reached to 50-70 today, because of poaching, hunting of their main prey (gazelles) and encroachment on their habitat.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Cheetah" class="alignnone wp-image-635349" height="332" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 394px) 100vw, 394px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cheeta-1-300x253.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cheeta-1-300x253.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cheeta-1.jpg 751w" width="394"/>Distribution of cheetahs in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Historically, Asiatic cheetahs had a very wide distribution in India.</li>
<li>There are authentic reports of their occurrence from as far north as Punjab to Tirunelveli district in southern Tamil Nadu, from Gujarat and Rajasthan in the west to Bengal in the east.</li>
<li>Most of the records are from a belt extending from Gujarat passing through Maharashtra, Madhya Pradesh, Uttar Pradesh, Chhattisgarh, Jharkhand and Odisha.</li>
<li>There is also a cluster of reports from southern Maharashtra extending to parts of Karnataka, Telangana, Kerala and Tamil Nadu.</li>
<li>The distribution range of the cheetah was wide and spread all over the subcontinent. They occurred in substantial numbers.</li>
<li>The cheetah’s habitat was also diverse, favouring the more open habitats: scrub forests, dry grasslands, savannahs and other arid and semi-arid open habitats.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Cheetah" class="alignnone wp-image-635350" height="352" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 100vw, 542px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.36804400_1524563822_threee_cheetahs_with_handlers_in_baroda_in_the_1890s-300x195.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.36804400_1524563822_threee_cheetahs_with_handlers_in_baroda_in_the_1890s-300x195.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.36804400_1524563822_threee_cheetahs_with_handlers_in_baroda_in_the_1890s-768x498.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.36804400_1524563822_threee_cheetahs_with_handlers_in_baroda_in_the_1890s.jpg 1024w" width="542"/>What caused the extinction of cheetahs in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Reduced fecundity and high infant mortality in the wild</li>
<li>Inability to breed in captivity</li>
<li>Sport hunting and</li>
<li>Bounty killings</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/reintroduction-of-african-cheetahs-in-indian-forests/"><strong>Historic data on cheetah</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is reported that the Mughal Emperor Akbar had kept 1,000 cheetahs in his menagerie and collected as many as 9,000 cats during his half-century reign from 1556 to 1605.</li>
<li>The cheetah numbers were fast depleting by the end of the 18th century even though their prey base and habitat survived till much later.</li>
<li>It is recorded that the last cheetahs were shot in India in 1947, but there are credible reports of sightings of the cat till about 1967.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Cheetah" class="alignnone wp-image-635351" height="309" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 498px) 100vw, 498px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.50639200_1662987037_cheetah-300x186.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.50639200_1662987037_cheetah-300x186.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.50639200_1662987037_cheetah-768x476.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.50639200_1662987037_cheetah.jpg 1024w" width="498"/>Issues in re-introduction</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Experts find it difficult whether the African cheetahs would find the sanctuary a favourable climate as far as the abundance of prey is concerned.</li>
<li>The habitat of cheetahs is needed to support a genetically viable population.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why reintroduce Cheetahs?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Reintroductions of large carnivores have increasingly been recognized as a strategy to conserve threatened species and restore ecosystem functions.</li>
<li>The cheetah is the only large carnivore that has been extirpated, mainly by over-hunting in India in historical times.</li>
<li>India now has the economic ability to consider restoring its lost natural heritage for ethical as well as ecological reasons.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains questions</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. Reintroductions of large carnivores have increasingly been recognized as a strategy to conserve threatened species and restore ecosystem functions. Discuss in context of cheetah reintroduction in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cheetah/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>G20 summit will open pandora of opportunities</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/g20-summit/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>members of G20</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>opportunities for India</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="G20 summit" class="alignnone wp-image-635366" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 528px) 100vw, 528px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/G20-1-300x205.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/G20-1-300x205.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/G20-1.jpg 660w" width="528"/>Context</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India is going to be at the centre stage of geopolitical spectrum as India will be hosting G20 summit presidency from December 2022. As Harsh V. Shringla, India’s chief G20 coordinator and former Foreign Secretary, (Amitabh kant is G20 Sherpa of India) recently said, “Our G20 Presidency would place India on the global stage, and provide an opportunity for India to place its priorities and narratives on the global agenda.”</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What is G20 (Group of Twenty)?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Composed of most of the world’s largest economies: </strong>19 countries plus European Union, including both industrialized and developing nations. Together, its members represent more than 80% of the world’s GDP, 75% of international trade and 60% of the world’s population.</li>
<li><strong>Role: </strong>To address major issues related to the global economy such as international financial stability, climate change mitigation, and sustainable development.</li>
<li><strong>It is an Intergovernmental forum.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Strategic role</strong>: The G20 holds a strategic role in securing global economic growth and prosperity.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="G20 summit" class="alignnone wp-image-635368" height="253" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/modi_g20_summit_first_session_covid_fight_1635610509535_1635610509767-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/modi_g20_summit_first_session_covid_fight_1635610509535_1635610509767-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/modi_g20_summit_first_session_covid_fight_1635610509535_1635610509767-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/modi_g20_summit_first_session_covid_fight_1635610509535_1635610509767-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/modi_g20_summit_first_session_covid_fight_1635610509535_1635610509767-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/modi_g20_summit_first_session_covid_fight_1635610509535_1635610509767-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/modi_g20_summit_first_session_covid_fight_1635610509535_1635610509767.jpg 1600w" width="449"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/g20/">India and the presidency of G20 summit</a></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In November this year, the 17th G20 Heads of State and Government Summit will take place in Bali.</li>
<li>After Indonesia, India will assume the presidency of the G20 from December 1, 2022 to November 30, 2023.</li>
<li>By hosting the summit of the G20, India will have the opportunity to assume centre stage in proposing and setting the global agenda and discourse.</li>
<li>India can assert its political, economic and intellectual leadership while hosting the G20 presidency.</li>
<li>Further it Provides India an opportunity to also champion the causes of developing and least developed countries.</li>
<li>India could invite and engage countries from Africa and South America to ensure better and more balanced representation at the G20.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="G20 summit" class="alignnone wp-image-635370" height="296" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 475px) 100vw, 475px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/VBK-MODITRILATERAL-REUTERS-1-300x187.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/VBK-MODITRILATERAL-REUTERS-1-300x187.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/VBK-MODITRILATERAL-REUTERS-1-1024x639.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/VBK-MODITRILATERAL-REUTERS-1-768x479.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/VBK-MODITRILATERAL-REUTERS-1-400x250.jpeg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/VBK-MODITRILATERAL-REUTERS-1.jpeg 1200w" width="475"/>Challenges before India:</strong></p>
<p><strong>         Global </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>World affected by the pandemic:</strong> Uneven vaccine availability has been flagged by many countries. Vaccine issue upset some countries<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Ukraine conflict: </strong>According to external affairs ministers Dr.S.Jaishankar due to Ukraine  conflict world is divided and this poses the challenge for India to bring rival camp on same stage</li>
<li><strong>Climate change: </strong>Divergent view of developed and developing countries on climate change can be the bone of contention between west and the rest.</li>
<li><strong>The rise of an assertive China: </strong>To maintain the delicate balance between NATO, G7 on the on hand while Russia and china on the other (as India is part of both QUAD and SCO).</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>     Domestic</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Economic challenges: </strong>Such as stagflation, unemployment, exchange rate, declining prospects for exports and rising trade deficit.</li>
<li><strong>Terrorism:</strong> Cross border terrorism emanating from Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Indonesia has focused on three key pillars in its presidency of G20 presidency:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Global health architecture</strong>: president of Indonesia Joko Widodo talked about a global contingency fund for medical supplies, building capacity in developing countries to manufacture vaccines and the creation of global health protocols and standards.</li>
<li><strong>Sustainable energy transition:</strong> as part of its roadmap to reach net zero by 2060, Indonesia had slashed the coverage area of forest fires sevenfold. The country has restored peatlands and rehabilitated 50,000 hectares of mangrove forests.</li>
<li><strong>Digital transformation</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What India can address?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Issues of global concern:</strong> Terrorism, climate change, stagflation etc.</li>
<li><strong>Domestic and regional</strong>: economic recovery, trade and investment, unemployment, patent waivers on diagnostics, therapeutics, vaccines etc.</li>
<li><strong>Greater co-operation and co-ordination: </strong>free trade agreements, supply chain resilience mechanism, stressing on green and digital transformations in the economy and its impact on societal well-being.</li>
<li><strong>Other important Areas</strong> :such as technology transfer, assistance towards green economy, greater access to trade for developing countries, addressing debt distress of countries by offering sustainable aid and loan programmes, tackling food and energy prices/security for vulnerable economies etc.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Why G20 summit presidency is an opportunity for India?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India exchange the G20 presidency with Indonesia and chose 2023 instead of 2022 to host the G20 countries.</li>
<li>India wanted to showcase its prowess in its 75<sup>th</sup> year of independence as cornerstone of new emerging world order. As India is part of Quad and SCO BRICS -the warring factions at world stage, it’s an opportunity in crisis to become the bridge of the divided world.</li>
<li>India is hosting the summit in Kashmir. World media will be in the Kashmir. In the direct message to world India will again assert that Kashmir is an integral part of India.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Way ahead</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>As India will be hosting G20 and SCO summits, India will be central in outlining key priority areas. India can assert its political, economic and intellectual leadership which will have to address issues that help in cement the Fault-line in the world order.</li>
<li>India’s leadership could define the coming years and decades of global discourse and avenues of cooperation.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Other related Information</strong></p>
<p><strong>SCO (Shanghai Co-operation Organization):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Shanghai Cooperation Organization (SCO) is a Eurasian political, economic and security organization. It is the world’s largest regional organization, 40% of the world population, and more than 30% of global GDP.</li>
<li><strong>Members:</strong> The Shanghai Five group was created on 26 April 1996; China, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Russia and Tajikistan, Uzbekistan<u>,</u> India and Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>QUAD:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Known as the ‘Quadrilateral Security Dialogue’ (QSD), the Quad is an informal strategic forum comprising four nations, namely – United States of America (USA), India, Australia and Japan.</li>
<li>One of the primary objectives of the Quad is to work for a free, open, prosperous and inclusive Indo-Pacific region.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>G7:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Group of Seven (G7) is an inter-governmental political forum consisting of Canada, France Germany, Italy, Japan, the United Kingdom and the United States. In addition, the European Union is a ‘non-enumerated member.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. India can take advantage of G20 for its economic growth and security architecture. Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/g20-summit/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>IIP gives us true health of our economy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/iip/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of IIP</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>economic indicator</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="IIP" class="alignnone wp-image-635380" height="297" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 528px) 100vw, 528px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5e933a6963c04d30bf78f58c09750441-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5e933a6963c04d30bf78f58c09750441-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5e933a6963c04d30bf78f58c09750441-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5e933a6963c04d30bf78f58c09750441-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5e933a6963c04d30bf78f58c09750441.jpeg 1080w" width="528"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s statistics ministry generates only one high-frequency gauge of economic activity. And that lone barometer, the index of industrial production (IIP), is completely broken.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is IIP?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Index of Industrial Production (IIP) is an index that indicates the performance of various industrial sectors of the Indian economy. It is a composite indicator of the general level of industrial activity in the economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="IIP" class="alignnone wp-image-635381" height="261" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 463px) 100vw, 463px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/73818-factory-output-reuters-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/73818-factory-output-reuters-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/73818-factory-output-reuters-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/73818-factory-output-reuters.jpg 850w" width="463"/>How is IIP calculated?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>IIP is calculated as the weighted average of production relatives of all the industrial activities. In the mathematical calculation Laspeyre’s fixed base formula is used.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the Core Industries in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The main or the key industries constitute the core sectors of an economy.</li>
<li>In India, there are eight sectors that are considered the core sectors.</li>
<li>They are electricity, steel, refinery products, crude oil, coal, cement, natural gas and fertilizers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Which has highest weightage in IIP?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The eight core sector industries in decreasing order of their weightage: Refinery Products&gt; Electricity&gt; Steel&gt; Coal&gt; Crude Oil&gt; Natural Gas&gt; Cement&gt; Fertilizers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="IIP" class="alignnone wp-image-635383" height="312" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 478px) 100vw, 478px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/linh-vuc-san-xuat-cua-viet-nam-300x196.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/linh-vuc-san-xuat-cua-viet-nam-300x196.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/linh-vuc-san-xuat-cua-viet-nam-768x501.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/linh-vuc-san-xuat-cua-viet-nam.jpg 800w" width="478"/>Why is IIP important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>IIP is the only measure on the physical volume of production. It is used by government agencies including the Ministry of Finance, the Reserve Bank of India, etc. for policy-making purposes. IIP remains extremely relevant for the calculation of the quarterly and advance GDP estimates.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who releases IIP data?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The IIP data is compiled and published by CSO every month.</li>
<li>CSO or Central Statistical Organisation operates under the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-the-first-advance-estimates-of-gdp/">Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation (MoSPI).</a></li>
<li>The IIP index data, once released, is also available on the PIB website.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How useful are monthly IIP figures to draw a conclusion about India’s growth?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>IIP figures are monthly data and as such it keeps going up and down.</li>
<li>In fact, the release calls them “quick estimates” because they tend to get revised after a month or two.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>IIP Index Components</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Mining, manufacturing, and electricity are the three broad sectors in which IIP constituents fall.</li>
<li>The relative weights of these three sectors are 77.6% (manufacturing), 14.4% (mining) and 8% (electricity).</li>
<li>Electricity, crude oil, coal, cement, steel, refinery products, natural gas, and fertilizers are the eight core industries that comprise about 40 per cent of the weight of items included in the IIP.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Basket of products</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Primary Goods (consisting of mining, electricity, fuels and fertilisers)</li>
<li>Capital Goods (e.g. machinery items)</li>
<li>Intermediate Goods (e.g. yarns, chemicals, semi-finished steel items, etc)</li>
<li>Infrastructure Goods (e.g. paints, cement, cables, bricks and tiles, rail materials, etc)</li>
<li>Consumer Durables (e.g. garments, telephones, passenger vehicles, etc)</li>
<li>Consumer Non-durables (e.g. food items, medicines, toiletries, etc)</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>IIP base year change</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The base year was changed to 2011-12 from 2004-05 in the year 2017.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>IIP remains extremely relevant for the calculation of the quarterly and advance GDP (Gross Domestic Product) estimates.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you understand by IIP? How it helps us to understand economic health?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/iip/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>GPS-based toll system to replace FASTag</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gps-based-toll-to-replace-fastag-ias/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>FASTags, GPS</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-635419" height="261" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 522px) 100vw, 522px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gps-toll-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gps-toll-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gps-toll-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gps-toll.jpg 900w" width="522"/></p>
<p>The government plans to start a GPS-based toll system in place of FASTag to ensure seamless payment and vehicle movement on national highways.</p>
<p><strong>Why in news?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The move would end the role of toll plazas across the country.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How will a GPS-based tolling system work?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Vehicles will be fitted with an electronic device that can track their movement.</li>
<li>Highways will be geo-fenced, creating virtual boundaries. The system will use GPS or radio frequency identification technologies.</li>
<li>The software will recognize when a mobile device enters or leaves a particular area, and toll will be charged based on the distance travelled at the highway’s exit point.</li>
<li>As the system is based on sensors, there will be no need to stop at toll plazas.</li>
<li>Vehicles and users must be registered with the GPS toll system, linked to bank accounts that will be used to transfer toll payments.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are FASTags?</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-implementation-of-fastags/">FASTags</a> are stickers that are affixed to the windscreen of vehicles and use Radio Frequency Identification (RFID) technology to enable digital, contactless payment of tolls without having to stop at toll gates.</li>
<li>RFID uses electromagnetic fields to automatically identify and track tags attached to objects.</li>
<li>The tags are linked to bank accounts and other payment methods.</li>
<li>As a car crosses a toll plaza, the amount is automatically deducted, and a notification is sent to the registered mobile phone number.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with FASTags</h4>
<ul>
<li>Since the card is affixed to the windscreen, it can be easily <strong><u>misplaced, damaged or stolen</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The existing FASTag system, though faster than cash payments, <strong><u>still requires vehicles to stop at toll booths to enable reading of tags. </u></strong></li>
<li>Also, the <strong><u>vehicle must wait till the gate is opened</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It has been observed that sometimes the <strong><u>toll fee is deducted twice</u></strong> from user account. Mostly, this happens due to a technical glitch.</li>
<li>Some card readers take <strong><u>longer time to read and register</u></strong>. Hence the <strong><u>purpose of saving time is itself defied.</u></strong></li>
<li>Still, the <strong><u>wait time at toll booths is much more than the 30 seconds</u></strong> that was promised earlier.</li>
<li>Also, it has <strong><u>not helped reduce the number of toll booths</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Hence the benefits of using FASTag far outweigh the challenges.</p>
<h4>Is FASTags a total failure?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Usage has increased</u></strong> since FASTag was made mandatory in 2021 after its launch in 2015.</li>
<li><strong><u>Penetration has grown</u></strong> from nearly 16% in FY18 to 96.3% in FY22.</li>
<li>Total toll collection in FY18 was ₹21,948 crore, including ₹3,532 crore collected through FASTags.</li>
<li>In FY22, <strong><u>toll collection through FASTags increased</u></strong> sharply to ₹33,274 crore out of total toll collection of ₹34,535 crore.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How will GPS benefit highway users?</h4>
<ul>
<li>GPS tolling uses satellite-based navigation and <strong><u>requires no halting</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Also, <strong><u>vehicles can be charged only for their actual travel</u></strong> on a highway stretch.</li>
<li>Currently, toll is paid at toll booths which is <strong><u>fixed between two points of tolling</u></strong> and a <strong><u>user does not get any concession even if he/she exits before completing the full run</u></strong> between two toll plazas.</li>
<li>The new system should <strong><u>reduce the toll amount charged</u></strong> for travel on highways.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the progress so far on GPS tolling?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Union road ministry has <strong><u>amended</u></strong> the <strong><u>National Highways Fee (Determination of Rates and Collection) Rules, 2008</u></strong>, allowing for the collection of toll based on distance travelled on national highways.</li>
<li>This will facilitate the introduction of GPS tolling.</li>
<li>First trials may be done on the under-construction Mumbai-Delhi expressway which will be geo-fenced.</li>
<li>Also the <strong><u>cost of GPS devices</u></strong> needs to be considered at very beginning.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>The system needs <strong><u>a proper legislative framework</u></strong>, and a full launch is still years away. The government intends to introduce it in phases.</li>
<li>The road ministry is expected to amend the Motor Vehicles Act and create rules to facilitate GPS tolling as well as to <strong><u>penalize offenders</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Moreover, <strong><u>GPS will come with its own set of complications on calculating differential tolls</u></strong>.</li>
<li><strong><u>Regulations and framework</u></strong> for these need to be developed first.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gps-based-toll-to-replace-fastag-ias/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SC Collegium approves names for appointments in three High Courts</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-collegium-approves-names-for-appointments-in-three-high-courts/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Collegium system, NJAC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court Collegium led by Chief Justice of India (CJI) U.U. Lalit has recommended eight names for appointment to the Bombay High Court.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Collegium System?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-collegium-system/">Collegium</a> of judges is the Indian Supreme Court’s invention.</li>
<li>It does not figure in the Constitution, which says judges of the Supreme Court and High Courts are appointed by the President and speaks of a process of consultation.</li>
<li>In effect, it is a system under which judges are appointed by an institution comprising judges.</li>
<li>After some judges were superseded in the appointment of the CJI in the 1970s, and attempts made subsequently to effect a mass transfer of High Court judges across the country.</li>
<li>Hence there was a perception that the independence of the judiciary was under threat. This resulted in a series of cases over the years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Evolution: The Judges Cases</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>First Judges Case (1981)</strong> ruled that the “consultation” with the CJI in the matter of appointments must be full and effective.</li>
<li>However, it rejected the idea that the CJI’s opinion, albeit carrying great weight, should have primacy.</li>
<li><strong>Second Judges Case (1993)</strong> introduced the Collegium system, holding that “consultation” really meant “concurrence”.</li>
<li>It added that it was not the CJI’s individual opinion, but an institutional opinion formed in consultation with the two senior-most judges in the Supreme Court.</li>
<li><strong>Third Judges Case (1998):</strong> On a Presidential Reference for its opinion, the Supreme Court, in the Third Judges Case (1998) expanded the Collegium to a five-member body, comprising the CJI and four of his senior-most colleagues.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The procedure followed by the Collegium</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Appointment of CJI</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The President of India appoints the CJI and the other SC judges.</li>
<li>As far as the CJI is concerned, the outgoing CJI recommends his successor.</li>
<li>In practice, it has been strictly by seniority ever since the supersession controversy of the 1970s.</li>
<li>The Union Law Minister forwards the recommendation to the PM who, in turn, advises the President.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Other SC Judges</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>For other judges of the top court, the proposal is initiated by the CJI.</li>
<li>The CJI consults the rest of the Collegium members, as well as the senior-most judge of the court hailing from the High Court to which the recommended person belongs.</li>
<li>The consultees must record their opinions in writing and it should form part of the file.</li>
<li>The Collegium sends the recommendation to the Law Minister, who forwards it to the Prime Minister to advise the President.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>For High Courts</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The CJs of High Courts are appointed as per the policy of having Chief Justices from outside the respective States. The Collegium takes the call on the elevation.</li>
<li>High Court judges are recommended by a Collegium comprising the CJI and two senior-most judges.</li>
<li>The proposal, however, is initiated by the Chief Justice of the High Court concerned in consultation with two senior-most colleagues.</li>
<li>The recommendation is sent to the Chief Minister, who advises the Governor to send the proposal to the Union Law Minister.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Does the Collegium recommend transfers too?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Yes, the Collegium also recommends the transfer of Chief Justices and other judges.</li>
<li>Article 222 of the Constitution provides for the transfer of a judge from one High Court to another.</li>
<li>When a CJ is transferred, a replacement must also be simultaneously found for the High Court concerned. There can be an acting CJ in a High Court for not more than a month.</li>
<li>In matters of transfers, the opinion of the CJI “is determinative”, and the consent of the judge concerned is not required.</li>
<li>However, the CJI should take into account the views of the CJ of the High Court concerned and the views of one or more SC judges who are in a position to do so.</li>
<li>All transfers must be made in the public interest, that is, “for the betterment of the administration of justice”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Loopholes in the Collegium system</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of Transparency:</strong> Opaqueness and a lack of transparency, and the scope for nepotism are cited often.</li>
<li><strong>Judges appointing Judge:</strong> The attempt made to replace it with a ‘National Judicial Appointments Commission’ was struck down by the court in 2015 on the ground that it posed a threat to the independence of the judiciary.</li>
<li><strong>Criteria:</strong> Some do not believe in full disclosure of reasons for transfers, as it may make lawyers in the destination court chary of the transferred judge.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In respect of appointments, there has been an acknowledgment that the “zone of consideration” must be expanded to avoid criticism that many appointees hail from families of retired judges.</li>
<li>The status of a proposed new memorandum of procedure, to infuse greater accountability, is also unclear.</li>
<li>Even the majority opinions admitted the need for transparency, now Collegiums’ resolutions are now posted online, but reasons are not given.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-collegium-approves-names-for-appointments-in-three-high-courts/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Supreme Court’s Three-Question Test for Validity of 10% EWS quota</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/supreme-courts-three-question-test-for-validity-of-ews-quota/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>EWS Quota , 103rd Amendment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court will today examine whether The Constitution (103rd Amendment) Act, which introduced a 10 per cent quota for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/economically-weaker-sections-ews-as-defined-by-govt-panel/">Economically Weaker Sections (EWS)</a> in government jobs and admissions, violates the basic structure of the Constitution.</p>
<p><strong>What is the news?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Constitution Bench has decided to examine three key issues to ascertain the validity of the amendment.</li>
<li>The challenge to the EWS quota was referred to a five-judge Bench in August 2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>EWS Quota: A backgrounder</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The 10% reservation was introduced through the 103rd Constitution Amendment and enforced in January 2019.</li>
<li>It added Clause (6) to Article 15 to empower the Government to introduce special provisions for the EWS among citizens except those in the classes that already enjoy reservation.</li>
<li>It allows reservation in educational institutions, both public and private, whether aided or unaided, excluding those run by minority institutions, up to a maximum of 10%.</li>
<li>It also added Clause (6) to Article 16 to facilitate reservation in employment.</li>
<li>The new clauses make it clear that the EWS reservation will be in addition to the existing reservation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>EWS quota: What are the issues fixed by the Supreme Court?</h4>
<p>Attorney General K K Venugopal had drafted <strong><u>four issues related to </u></strong><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/the-basic-structure-and-essential-feature-govern-now-the-political-and-juristic-destiny-of-indian-constitutional-development-comment-10-marks/"><strong>Basic Structure</strong></a> for the consideration of the Bench.  On September 8, the court decided to take up three of them:</p>
<ol>
<li>Whether the 103rd Constitution Amendment can be said to breach the basic structure of the Constitution <strong><u>by permitting the state to make special provisions, including reservation, based on economic criteria</u></strong>”;</li>
<li>Whether the amendment can be said to breach the basic structure <strong><u>by permitting the state to make special provisions in relation to admission to private unaided institutions</u></strong></li>
<li>Whether the basic structure is violated by excluding the SEBCs (Socially and Educationally Backward Classes)/ OBCs (Other Backward Classes)/ SCs (Scheduled Castes)/ STs (Scheduled Tribes) from the scope of EWS reservation.</li>
</ol>
<h4>What is the 103rd Amendment?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 103rd Amendment inserted Articles 15(6) and 16(6) in the Constitution to provide up to 10 per cent reservation to EWS other than backward classes, SCs, and STs in higher educational institutions and initial recruitment in government jobs.</li>
<li>The amendment empowered state governments to provide reservation on the basis of economic backwardness.</li>
<li>Article 15 prohibits discrimination on grounds of religion, race, caste, sex, or place of birth.</li>
<li>Article 16 guarantees equal opportunity in matters of public employment.</li>
<li>The additional clauses gave Parliament the power to make special laws for EWS like it does for SCs, STs, and OBCs.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Basis of EWS reservation: Sinho Commission</h4>
<ul>
<li>The EWS reservation was granted based on the recommendations of a commission headed by <strong><u>Major General (retd) S R Sinho. </u></strong></li>
<li>The commission, which was <strong><u>constituted in March 2005</u></strong> by the UPA government, <strong><u>submitted its report in July 2010.</u></strong></li>
<li>It recommended that <strong><u>all below-poverty-line (BPL) families</u></strong> <strong><u>within the general category</u></strong> and also all families <strong><u>whose annual family income from all sources is below the taxable limit</u></strong>, should be identified as EBCs (economically backward classes).</li>
</ul>
<h4>How is EWS status determined under the law?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The EWS criteria for employment and admission was notified on January 31, 2019 by the Department of Personnel and Training (DoPT) based on the 103rd Amendment.</li>
<li>Under the 2019 notification:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>A person who was not covered under the scheme of reservation for SCs, STs, and OBCs, and</li>
<li>Whose family had a gross annual income below Rs 8 lakh, was to be identified as EWS for the benefit of reservation.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The notification specified what constituted “income”, and excluded some persons from the EWS category if their families possessed certain specified assets.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Debate over the criteria</h4>
<ul>
<li>In October 2021, <strong><u>the Supreme Court</u></strong> <strong><u>asked the government how the threshold of Rs 8 lakh had been reached</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Centre told the court that it would <strong><u>revisit the income criterion</u></strong>, and set up a three-member panel for this purpose.</li>
<li>In January this year, the government accepted the committee’s report, which said that the threshold of <strong><u>Rs 8 lakh of annual family income seems reasonable</u></strong> for determining EWS and may be retained.</li>
<li>However, the committee said, EWS may exclude, irrespective of income, a person whose family has <strong><u>5 acres of agricultural land and above. </u></strong></li>
<li>Also, the committee recommended, the <strong><u>residential asset criteria may altogether be removed</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the basis of the challenge to the amendment?</h4>
<h4>(1) Vagueness of Basic Structure</h4>
<ul>
<li>The primary argument in this case is that the amendment violates the basic structure of the Constitution.</li>
<li>Although there is <strong><u>no clear definition of basic structure</u></strong>, any law that violates it is understood to be unconstitutional.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(2) Burden of Proof</h4>
<ul>
<li>When a law is challenged, the <strong><u>burden of proving it is unconstitutional lies on the petitioners</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(3) Sole economic criteria</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 103rd Amendment departs from this by promising special <strong><u>protections on the sole basis of economic status</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(4) Violating 50% cap</h4>
<ul>
<li>The petitioners have also challenged the amendment on the ground that it violates the Supreme Court’s 1992 ruling in <strong><u>Indra Sawhney &amp; Ors v Union of India</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This has <strong><u>upheld the Mandal report</u></strong> and capped reservations at 50 per cent.</li>
<li>The court had held that <strong><u>economic backwardness cannot be the sole criterion</u></strong> for identifying a backward class.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(5) Rights of educational institutions</h4>
<ul>
<li>Another challenge is on behalf of private, unaided educational institutions.</li>
<li>They have argued that their fundamental right to practise a trade/ profession is violated when the <strong><u>state compels them to implement its reservation policy</u></strong> and admit students on any criteria other than merit.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What has been the government’s stand in this matter so far?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In counter-affidavits, the govt has said that <strong><u>the state has a duty</u></strong> to protect the interests of economically weaker sections.</li>
<li>Against the argument of violation of the basic structure, the government said that the <strong><u>very identity of the Constitution has NOT been altered</u></strong>.</li>
<li>On the Indra Sawhney principle, the government has relied on the <strong><u>SC’s 2008 ruling in Ashoka Kumar Thakur v Union of India</u></strong>, in which the court upheld the 27 per cent quota for OBCs.</li>
<li>The argument is that the co<strong><u>urt accepted that the definition of OBCs was not made on the sole criterion of caste but a mix of caste and economic factors</u></strong>; thus, there need not be a sole criterion for according reservation.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/supreme-courts-three-question-test-for-validity-of-ews-quota/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India raises Sri Lankan Tamil issue in UN</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-raises-sri-lankan-tamil-issue-in-un/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="gyanvapi" class="alignnone wp-image-635418" height="389" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 318px) 100vw, 318px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tamil-245x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tamil-245x300.jpg 245w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tamil.jpg 420w" width="318"/></strong></p>
<p>India voiced concern over the “lack of measurable progress” in Sri Lanka’s promised political solution to the long-pending Tamil national question.</p>
<h4><strong>Back in news: Tamil Issue<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has made an unexpected (for SL) reference to the crisis-hit island nation’s “debt-driven” economy in the context of its current crisis.</li>
<li>Indian delegation noted the lack of measurable progress by Government of Sri Lanka on their commitments of a political solution to the ethnic issue.</li>
<li>It sought for full implementation of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-13th-amendment-to-the-sri-lankan-constitution-and-why-is-it-contentious/">13th Amendment</a> of the Constitution, delegation of powers to Provincial Councils and holding of Provincial Council elections at the earliest.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Has India retreated from supporting Sri Lanka?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s statement comes ahead of a resolution on Sri Lanka that will likely face a vote at the Council.</li>
<li>Since 2009, India has voted thrice in favour of the UN resolution on Sri Lanka — two were critical — and abstained twice, in 2014 and 2021.</li>
<li>Irrespective of its vote, India has consistently underscored the need for a political settlement within the framework of a united Sri Lanka, ensuring justice, peace, equality and dignity for the Tamils of Sri Lanka.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues faced by Tamils in Sri Lanka</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to Freedom House’s Freedom in the World 2016 report on Sri Lanka, Tamils report systematic discrimination in areas including government employment, university education, and access to justice.</li>
<li>A large portion of the Tamil population still remains displaced.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Tamil issue in Sri Lanka?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Violent persecution against the Tamil population erupted in the form of the 1956, 1958, 1977, 1981 and 1983 anti-Tamil pogroms in Sri Lanka.</li>
<li>Over 13 years since the end of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-india-sri-lanka-relations-in-recent-times/">Sri Lanka’s civil war</a>, in which tens of thousands of civilians were killed and disappeared, survivors continue demanding justice and accountability for war-time crimes.</li>
<li>In the post-war years, Sri Lanka’s human rights defenders have frequently flagged concerns over persisting militarisation, especially in the Tamil-majority north and east; repression, and the shrinking space for dissent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the 13<sup>th</sup> Amendment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is an outcome of the Indo-Lanka Accord of <strong><u>July 1987</u></strong>, <strong><u>signed by the then PM Rajiv Gandhi</u></strong> and President J.R. Jayawardene, in an attempt to resolve the ethnic conflict and civil war.</li>
<li>The 13th Amendment led to the creation of Provincial Councils and assured a power-sharing arrangement to enable all nine provinces in the country, including Sinhala majority areas, to self-govern.</li>
<li>Subjects such as education, health, agriculture, housing, land and police are devolved to the provincial administrations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is it contentious?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The 13th Amendment carries considerable <strong><u>baggage from the country’s civil war years</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It was opposed vociferously by both Sinhala nationalist parties and the LTTE.</li>
<li>The opposition within Sri Lanka saw the Accord and the consequent legislation as an imprint of Indian intervention.</li>
<li>It was widely perceived as an imposition by a <strong><u>neighbour wielding hegemonic influence</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Tamil polity, especially its dominant nationalist strain, does not find the 13th Amendment sufficient in its ambit or substance.</li>
<li>However, some find it as an important starting point, something to build upon.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why India objects over this?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Because of restrictions on financial powers and <strong><u>overriding powers given to the President</u></strong>, the provincial administrations have not made much headway.</li>
<li>In particular, the <strong><u>provisions relating to police and land have never been implemented</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is it significant?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Till date, the Amendment represents the only <strong><u>constitutional provision on the settlement of the long-pending Tamil question.</u></strong></li>
<li>In addition to assuring a measure of devolution, it is considered part of the few significant gains since the 1980s, in the face of <strong><u>growing Sinhala-Buddhist majoritarianism</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-raises-sri-lankan-tamil-issue-in-un/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Gyanvapi -Kashi Vishwanath Temple Complex Dispute</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gyanvapi-kashi-vishwanath-temple-complex-dispute/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Religious places issues in India</p></div></div><p><img alt="gyanvapi" class="alignnone wp-image-635417" height="231" sizes="(max-width: 462px) 100vw, 462px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gyanvapi-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gyanvapi-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gyanvapi-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gyanvapi.jpg 900w" width="462"/></p>
<p>The Varanasi District and Sessions Court has rejected the plea of the organization which manages the Gyanvapi mosque complex, challenging the maintainability of the civil suits filed by some women seeking the right to worship Goddesses on the outer wall of the complex.</p>
<h4>About Gyanvapi Mosque</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Gyanvapi Mosque was built in 1669 during the reign of the Mughal emperor Aurangzeb, who ordered the demolition of the existing Vishweshwar temple at the site, and its replacement by a mosque.</li>
<li>The plinth of the temple was left untouched, and served as the courtyard of the mosque.</li>
<li>One of the walls too was spared, and it became the qibla wall, the most important wall in a mosque that faces Mecca.</li>
<li>Material from the destroyed temple was used to build the mosque, evidence of which can be seen today.</li>
<li>The name of the mosque is said to have derived from an adjoining well, the Gyanvapi, or Well of Knowledge.</li>
<li>An old sculpture of the Nandi bull inside the compound of the present Kashi Vishwanath Temple faces the wall of the mosque instead of the sanctum sanctorum of the temple.</li>
<li>It is believed that Nandi is in fact, facing the sanctum sanctorum of the original Vishweshwar temple.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The temple to Lord Shiva</h4>
<ul>
<li>For more than 100 years after the mosque was built, there was no temple at the site.</li>
<li>The present Kashi Vishwanath Temple was built in the 18th century by Rani Ahilyabai Holkar of Indore, immediately to the south of the mosque.</li>
<li>Over the decades it emerged as one of the most prominent and revered centres of the Hindu religion.</li>
<li>Many Hindus have long believed that the original deity of the erstwhile Vishweshwar temple was hidden by the priests inside the Gyanvapi well during Aurangzeb’s raid.</li>
<li>This has fired the desire to conduct puja and rituals at the sacred place where the mosque now stands.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Longstanding claims</h4>
<ul>
<li>From time to time, petitioners have laid claim to the mosque, saying it remains the original sacred place of Hindu worship.</li>
<li>The Ayodhya movement also aimed to “liberate” the Kashi-Vishwanath Temple-Gyanvapi mosque site and the Shri Krishna Janmabhoomi in Mathura as well.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What laws restrict such acts?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Places of Worship (Special Provisions) Act, 1991 — which mandates that the nature of all places of worship, except the one in Ayodhya that was then under litigation, shall be maintained as it was on August 15, 1947.</li>
<li>It maintains that no encroachment of any such place prior to the date can be challenged in courts — applies to the disputed complex in Varanasi.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What was the case before the Court?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The temple worshipers side had argued that the mosque was built on the site of an older temple, while the another side pleaded that the mosque was built on Wakf premises.</li>
<li>The plea also said that <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-takes-up-pleas-against-places-of-worship-act/">The Places of Worship Act of 1991</a> barred the changing of the character of the mosque.</li>
<li>The case was initially heard by the Civil Judge (Senior Division), Varanasi, but it was transferred by the Supreme Court to the District Judge on grounds of the “complexity of the issues involved in the civil suit”.</li>
<li>The Supreme Court said it would wait for the district court’s decision on the mosque committee’s application before intervening in the matter.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issue in Limelight</h4>
<ul>
<li>In April 2021, Fast Track Court Civil Judge ordered the Archaeological Survey of India to get a comprehensive archaeological physical survey” done of the Kashi Vishwanath Temple-Gyanvapi Mosque complex.</li>
<li>It was tasked to find out as to whether the religious structure standing at present at the disputed site is a superimposition, alteration or addition or there is a structural overlapping of any kind, with or over, any religious structure.</li>
<li>The mosque is not an ASI-protected site, and the ASI has no role in its maintenance or upkeep.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the people seeking now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Worshippers find the <strong><u>cut-off date of August 15, 1947, is “arbitrary, irrational and retrospective</u></strong>” and prohibits Hindus, Jains, Buddhists, and Sikhs from approaching courts to “reclaim” their places of worship.</li>
<li>Such places, they argue, were “<strong><u>invaded” and “encroached” upon by “fundamentalist barbaric invaders</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>Certain groups have opposed the law even when it was introduced, arguing that the Centre has no power to legislate on “pilgrimages” or “burial grounds” which are under the state list.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gyanvapi-kashi-vishwanath-temple-complex-dispute/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>