<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 05:55:21 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Europe heading for Recession</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/europe-heading-for-recession/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Recessions, Depression</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-631660" height="272" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 501px) 100vw, 501px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-300x163.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-300x163.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-1024x555.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-768x416.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession.jpg 1026w" width="501"/></p>
<p>The Eurozone is almost certainly entering a recession, with surveys showing a deepening cost-of-living crisis and a gloomy outlook that is keeping consumers wary of spending.</p>
<h4>What is Recession?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/imf-flags-recession-risk/">recession</a> is a significant decline in economic activity that lasts for months or even years.</li>
<li>Experts declare a recession when a nation’s economy experiences negative GDP, rising levels of unemployment, falling retail sales, and contracting measures of income and manufacturing for an extended period of time.</li>
<li>Recessions are considered an unavoidable part of the business cycle—or the regular cadence of expansion and contraction that occurs in a nation’s economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What causes Recessions?</h4>
<p>These phenomena are some of the main drivers of a recession:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>A sudden economic shock:</strong> An economic shock is a surprise problem that creates serious financial damage. The coronavirus outbreak, which shut down economies worldwide, is a more recent example of a sudden economic shock.</li>
<li><strong>Excessive debt:</strong> When individuals or businesses take on too much debt, the cost of servicing the debt can grow to the point where they can’t pay their bills. Growing debt defaults and bankruptcies then capsize the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Asset bubbles:</strong> When investing decisions are driven by emotion, bad economic outcomes aren’t far behind. Investors can become too optimistic during a strong economy.</li>
<li><strong>Too much inflation:</strong> Inflation is the steady, upward trend in prices over time. Inflation isn’t a bad thing per se, but excessive inflation is a dangerous phenomenon. Central banks control inflation by raising interest rates, and higher interest rates depress economic activity.</li>
<li><strong>Too much deflation:</strong> While runaway inflation can create a recession, deflation can be even worse. Deflation is when prices decline over time, which causes wages to contract, which further depresses prices. When a deflationary feedback loop gets out of hand, people and business stop spending, which undermines the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Technological change:</strong> New inventions increase productivity and help the economy over the long term, but there can be short-term periods of adjustment to technological breakthroughs. In the 19th century, there were waves of labour-saving technological improvements.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What’s the difference between <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/imf-flags-recession-risk/">Recession</a> and Depression?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Recessions and depressions have similar causes, but the overall impact of a depression is much, much worse.</li>
<li>There are greater job losses, higher unemployment and steeper declines in GDP.</li>
<li>Most of all, a depression lasts longer—years, not months—and it takes more time for the economy to recover.</li>
<li>Economists do not have a set definition or fixed measurements to show what counts as a depression. Suffice to say, all the impacts of a depression are deeper and last longer.</li>
<li>In the past century, the US has faced just one depression: The Great Depression.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Great Depression</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Great Depression started in 1929 and lasted through 1933, although the economy didn’t really recover until World War II, nearly a decade later.</li>
<li>During the Great Depression, unemployment rose to 25% and the GDP fell by 30%.</li>
<li>It was the most unprecedented economic collapse in modern US history.</li>
<li>By way of comparison, the Great Recession was the worst recession since the Great Depression.</li>
<li>During the Great Recession, unemployment peaked around 10% and the recession officially lasted from December 2007 to June 2009, about a year and a half.</li>
<li>Some economists fear that the coronavirus recession could morph into a depression, depending how long it lasts.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How long do recessions last?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Gulf War Recession (July 1990 to March 1991):</strong> At the start of the 1990s, the U.S. went through a short, eight-month recession, partly caused by spiking oil prices during the First Gulf War.</li>
<li><strong>The Great Recession (2008-2009):</strong> As mentioned, the Great Recession was caused in part by a bubble in the real estate market.</li>
<li><strong>Covid-19 Recession:</strong> The most recent recession began in February 2020 and lasted only two months, making it the shortest US recession in history.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Can we predict a recession?</h4>
<p>Given that economic forecasting is uncertain, predicting future recessions is far from easy. However, the following warning signs can give you more time to figure out how to prepare for a recession before it happens:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>An inverted yield curve:</strong> The yield curve is a graph that plots the market value—or the yield—of a range. When long-term yields are lower than short-term yields, it shows that investors are worried about a recession. This phenomenon is known as a yield curve inversion, and it has predicted past recessions.</li>
<li><strong>Declines in consumer confidence:</strong> Consumer spending is the main driver of the US economy. If surveys show a sustained drop in consumer confidence, it could be a sign of impending trouble for the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Drop in the Leading Economic Index (LEI):</strong> Published monthly by the Conference Board, the LEI strives to predict future economic trends. It looks at factors like applications for unemployment insurance, new orders for manufacturing and stock market performance.</li>
<li><strong>Sudden stock market declines:</strong> A large, sudden decline in stock markets could be a sign of a recession coming on, since investors sell off parts and sometimes all of their holdings in anticipation of an economic slowdown.</li>
<li><strong>Rising unemployment:</strong> It goes without saying that if people are losing their jobs, it’s a bad sign for the economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How does a recession affect individuals?</h4>
<ul>
<li>We may lose your job during a recession, as unemployment levels rise. It becomes much harder to find a job replacement since more people are out of work.</li>
<li>People who keep their jobs may see cuts to pay and benefits, and struggle to negotiate future pay raises.</li>
<li>Investments in stocks, bonds, real estate and other assets can lose money in a recession, reducing your savings and upsetting your plans for retirement.</li>
<li>Business owners make fewer sales during a recession, and may even be forced into bankruptcy.</li>
<li>With more people unable to pay their bills during a recession, lenders tighten standards for mortgages, car loans, and other types of financing.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/europe-heading-for-recession/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Preventive Detentions rose in 2021</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/preventive-detention-rose-in-2021/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Article 22</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with preventive detentions</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-631658" height="261" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 399px) 100vw, 399px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/preventive-detention-300x196.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/preventive-detention-300x196.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/preventive-detention.jpg 507w" width="399"/></p>
<p>Preventive detentions in 2021 saw a rise by over 23.7% compared with the year before, with over 1.1 lakh people being placed under preventive detention, according to statistics released by the National Crime Records Bureau (NCRB).</p>
<h4>What does NCRB report say on Preventive Detention?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Over 24,500 people placed under preventive detention were either in custody or still detained as of 2021-end — the highest since 2017 when the NCRB started recording this data.</li>
<li>Over 483 were detentions under the National Security Act, of which almost half (241) were either in custody or still detained as of 2021-end.</li>
<li>In 2017, the NCRB’s Crime in India report found that 67,084 persons had been detained as a preventive measure that year.</li>
<li>Of these, 48,815 were released between one and six months of their detention and 18,269 were either in custody or still in preventive detention as of the end of the year.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Various provisions invoked for Preventive Detention</h4>
<ul>
<li>Among other laws under which the NCRB has recorded data on preventive detentions are the:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Goonda Act (State and Central) (29,306),</li>
<li>Prevention of Illicit Traffic in Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1988 (1,331), and</li>
<li>A category classified as “Other Detention Acts”, under which most of the detentions were registered (79,514).</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Since 2017, the highest number of persons to be placed under preventive detention has consistently been under the “Other Detention Acts” category.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Concerns over the report</h4>
<ul>
<li>The number of persons placed under detention has been increasing since 2017 — to over 98,700 in 2018 and over 1.06 lakh in 2019 — before dipping to 89,405 in 2020 (due to lockdowns).</li>
<li>The number of persons placed under preventive detention has seen an increase in 2021.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Preventive Detention?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Preventive detention means detaining a person so that to prevent that person from commenting on any possible crime.</li>
<li>In other words, preventive detention is an action taken by the administration on the grounds of the suspicion that some wrong actions may be done by the person concerned which will be prejudicial to the state.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Preventive Detention in India</h4>
<p>A police officer can arrest an individual without orders from a Magistrate and without any warrant if he gets any information that such an individual can commit any offense.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Preventive Detention Law, 1950:</strong> According to this law any person could be arrested and detained if his freedom would endanger the security of the country, foreign relations, public interests, or otherwise necessary for the country.</li>
<li><strong>Unlawful Activities Prevention Act (UAPA) 1968:</strong> Within the ambit of UAPA law the Indian State could declare any organization illegal and could imprison anyone for interrogation if the said organization or person critiqued/questioned Indian sovereignty territorially.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the difference between Preventive Detention and an Arrest?</h4>
<ul>
<li>An ‘arrest’ is done when a person is charged with a crime.</li>
<li>In the case of preventive detention, a person is detained as he/she is simply restricted from doing something that might deteriorate the law-and-order situation.</li>
<li>Article 22 of the Indian Constitution provides protection against arrest and detention in certain cases.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Rights of an Arrested Person in India</h4>
<p>A/c to Article 22(1) and 22(2) of the Indian constitution:</p>
<ul>
<li>A person cannot be arrested and detained without being informed why he is being arrested.</li>
<li>A person who is arrested cannot be denied to be defended by a legal practitioner of his choice. This means that the arrested person has right to hire a legal practitioner to defend himself/ herself.</li>
<li>Every person who has been arrested would be produced before the nearest magistrate within 24 hours.</li>
<li>The custody of the detained person cannot be beyond the said period by the authority of magistrate.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Exceptions for Preventive Detention</h4>
<p>Article 22(3) says that the above safeguards are not available to the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>If the person is at the time being an enemy alien</li>
<li>If the person is arrested under certain law made for the purpose of “Preventive Detention”</li>
</ul>
<h4>Constitutional provision</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is extraordinary that the framers of the Indian Constitution, who suffered most because of the Preventive Detention Laws, did not hesitate to give Constitutional sanctity.</li>
<li>B.R. Ambedkar was of the opinion that the freedom of the individual should not supersede the interests of the state.</li>
<li>He had also stated that the independence of the country was in a state of inflancy and in order to save it, preventive detention was essential.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with preventive detention</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Arbitrariness:</strong> The police determinations of whether a person poses a threat are not tested at a trial by leading evidence or examined by legally trained persons.</li>
<li><strong>Rights violation:</strong> Quiet often, there is no trial (upto 3 months), no periodic review, and no legal assistance for the detained person.</li>
<li><strong>Abuse:</strong> It does not provide any procedural protections such as to reduce detainees’ vulnerability to torture and discriminatory treatment, and to prevent officials’ misusing preventive detention for subversive activities.</li>
<li><strong>Tool for suppression:</strong> In the absence of proper safeguards, preventive detention has been misused, particularly against the Dalits and the minorities.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What has the apex court recently rule?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Preventive detention is a <strong><u>necessary evil</u></strong> only to prevent public disorder, ruled the Supreme Court in 2021.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>State should not arbitrarily resort to “preventive detention</u></strong>” to deal with <strong><u>all sundry “law and order” problems</u></strong>, which could be <strong><u>dealt with by the ordinary laws</u></strong> of the country.</li>
<li>Whenever an order under a preventive detention law is challenged, one of the questions the court must ask in deciding its legality is: <strong><u>was the ordinary law of the land sufficient</u></strong> to deal with the situation?</li>
<li>If the answer is in the affirmative, the detention order will be illegal.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Upholding the Article 21</h4>
<ul>
<li>Preventive detention must fall within the four corners of Article 21 (due process of law) read with Article 22 (safeguards against arbitrary arrest and detention) and the statute in question, Justice Nariman ruled.</li>
<li>The Liberty of a citizen is a most important right won by our forefathers after long, historical, and arduous struggles.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>Having such kind of acts has a restraining influence on the anti-social and subversive elements.</li>
<li>India is a large country and many separatist tendencies against the national security and integrity existed and existing and a strict law is required to counter the subversive activities.</li>
<li>The number of persons detained in these acts is not a very large and due attention is made before preventive detention.</li>
<li>The state should have very effective powers to deal with the acts in which the citizens involve in hostile activities, espionage, coercion, terrorism, etc.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/preventive-detention-rose-in-2021/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Backsliding on climate action</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/backsliding-on-climate-action/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Paris agreement</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Climate change</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>Europe is staring at a recession and its appetite for climate action is waning.</p>
<h4>Developed countries moving away from commitment</h4>
<ul>
<li>Countries in Europe led by Germany, Austria and the Netherlands are cranking up their coal plants again.</li>
<li>Fossil fuels are making a comeback and countries are rejecting the European Union (EU)’s plan to reduce natural gas consumption by 15%. Dutch, Polish and other European farmers are protesting against emission cuts from agriculture.</li>
<li>In the U.S. too, the Senate and the Supreme Court have struck blows to climate action.</li>
<li>And in the U.S. too, prices of fuel started increasing last year, not just this year.</li>
<li>Fossil fuels are making a quiet comeback, since the strength of the U.S. is its oil and gas industry.</li>
<li>That is why we have just witnessed a ‘re-calibration’ of U.S. policy towards the Gulf.</li>
<li>Coal, oil and gas are not going anywhere in the developed world; they are, in fact, making a comeback.</li>
<li>The West had rushed to draw down on fossil fuels even before technology for renewables were in place.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Global peaking issue</h4>
<ul>
<li>Article 4 of the Paris Agreement defines ‘Global Peaking’ thus: “In order to achieve the long-term temperature goal set out in Article 2, Parties aim <strong>to reach global peaking</strong> of greenhouse gas emissions as soon as possible, recognizing that peaking will take longer for developing country Parties.”</li>
<li>The developed countries, given their historical emissions, will have to peak first.</li>
<li>That’s why the reference is to<strong> ‘global peaking’</strong> and not ‘individual peaking’.</li>
<li>From this, it logically follows that when developing country parties peak later than developed countries, they will also achieve net zero later than developed countries.</li>
<li>Consequently, it is the logical conclusion of the Article 4 of the Paris Agreement that when we consider net zero, we should only consider ‘global net zero’ and not ‘individual net zero’ for 2050.</li>
<li>The statement calls on developed countries to do a net negative on mitigation by 2050 rather than just “net zero”, if they are serious about fighting climate change.</li>
<li>In effect, the West needs to do a net minus and not just net zero.</li>
<li>Thanks to the efforts of India, the phrase used in the 2021 summit-level declarations at both G-20 and Quad is ‘global net zero’. We need to build on this understanding.</li>
<li>India stands as beacon of hope in renewables.</li>
<li>It is time for all developing countries, especially the small island developing states, to make sure that the developed world doesn’t backslide on its commitments on mitigation yet again.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward for developing countries</h4>
<ul>
<li>With countries of the developed world almost sure to renege on their 2030 Paris Agreement commitments, countries of the developing world must do everything to hold the countries of the developed world to their commitments.</li>
<li>The Western nations have already started reinterpreting the Paris Agreement and look to downgrade their commitments.</li>
<li>The concept of net zero is being cleverly misinterpreted.</li>
<li> To bring this to the attention of the Global South, India, China and eight other countries from Africa, Asia and Latin America made a cross-regional statement on ‘global net zero’ on June 7 at the UN on World Environment Day.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>COP 27 in Egypt gives us that opportunity to hold their feet to the fire. It is time for the developed world to make net minus pledges. If we don’t collectively push for it, we will be collectively pushed back.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/backsliding-on-climate-action/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How India adopted its military flags and badges based on Lord Mountbatten’s suggestions?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/how-india-adopted-its-military-flags-and-badges-mountbattens/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Flags and defence insignia</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-629568" height="152" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/navy-300x152.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/navy-300x152.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/navy.jpg 621w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The new Naval Ensign (flag), which will be unveiled by PM in Kochi, has brought into focus the flags and ranks adopted by the Indian military after Independence.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Do you know?</strong></p>
<p>The octagonal shape with twin golden borders draws inspiration from the seal of the great Indian emperor, Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj, whose visionary maritime outlook established a credible naval fleet</p></blockquote>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Documents accessed from <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-national-archives-of-india/">National Archives of India</a> show that Lord Mountbatten, former Viceroy and Governor General of India, played a major role in suggesting new flags and rank badges.</li>
<li>This was when India was about to become a Republic on January 26, 1950.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When did India switch from British-era flags and ranks?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The switch from British-era flags and ranks took place when India became a Republic (26<sup>th</sup> Jan, 1950).</li>
<li>Prior to that the flags and badges of ranks of the military were of the British pattern.</li>
<li>The new, Indian pattern of flags of Army, Navy and Air Force, and also the Regimental Flags of the Army and badges of ranks of all three services were adopted on January 26, 1950.</li>
<li>The ‘Kings Commission’ granted to Indian military officers was also changed to ‘Indian Commission’ on the same date.</li>
<li>And at a subsequent date the King’s Colours of the various Regiments were laid to rest in Indian Military Academy (IMA), Dehradun.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When did Lord Mountbatten come into the picture?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The national archives have files, dated 1949, that include a detailed note from Lord Mountbatten regarding names, flags and ranks of the armed forces, and then PM Nehru’s letter to the then Defence Minister Baldev Singh regarding Mountbatten’s suggestions.</li>
<li>The note, archives reveal, was given to Nehru by Lord Mountbatten when the two met in London.</li>
<li>The note was forwarded from the PM’s office to the office of then Governor General C Rajagopalachari on May 24, 1949, stating that it is on the issue of ‘Names and Insignia of Indian Armed Forces’ after India becomes a Republic.</li>
<li>The letter also stated that the note should be placed before the Governor General.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What did Lord Mountbatten say in the note?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The note begins by saying that consequent to becoming a Republic the word ‘Royal’ shall be dropped from India’s Army, Navy and Air Force.</li>
<li>Mountbatten strongly recommended that no other word like ‘State’ of ‘Republican’ should replace the word ‘Royal’.</li>
<li>This was because it would have the effect of separating the forces of India psychologically from the other services in the Commonwealth.</li>
<li>He further suggested in the letter that the Crown should be replaced from the insignias and replaced by the “three lions of Ashoka”.</li>
<li>Regarding the Naval Ensign, he said that all Commonwealth navies fly the same flag which consists of a large white flag with a red-cross and Union Jack in the upper corner nearer the staff and is known as the ‘White Ensign’.</li>
<li>The new Ensign, the note suggested, should continue to have the red-cross but the Indian national flag should replace the Union Jack.</li>
<li>He suggested this to maintain commonality with the Commonwealth flags.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What changes did Mountbatten suggest for uniforms?</h4>
<ul>
<li>He strongly urged that existing uniforms should be changed as little as possible.</li>
<li>He added that the Crown worn on badges of ranks of Majors and above should be replaced by the “three lions of Ashoka”.</li>
<li>The Star of the Order of the Bath should be replaced by Star of India or another form of star.</li>
<li>He also suggested that the crossed sword and baton on the badges of ranks of Generals should be retained.</li>
<li>The former Viceroy advocated retaining the stripes of rank in Navy and Air Force saying these were internationally almost the same.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did the Indian government react to Mountbatten’s suggestions?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Nehru wrote to the then defence minister in September 1949 saying that he agreed with the suggestions made by the former Governor General that there should be as little change as possible.</li>
<li>The then PM particularly mentioned the changes suggested by Mountbatten for the Navy.</li>
<li>Then Governor General C Rajagopalachari also wrote back to Nehru in May 1949 itself agreeing to Mountbatten’s suggestions.</li>
<li>In the end, Mountbatten’s suggestions were virtually all accepted and implemented with effect from January 26, 1950.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/how-india-adopted-its-military-flags-and-badges-mountbattens/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Public health should be led by doctor alone</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/public-health/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Health care sector reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="public health" class="alignnone wp-image-631766" height="284" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 426px) 100vw, 426px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/a-group-of-women-frontline-workers-smiling-and-looking-at-the-camera-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/a-group-of-women-frontline-workers-smiling-and-looking-at-the-camera-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/a-group-of-women-frontline-workers-smiling-and-looking-at-the-camera-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/a-group-of-women-frontline-workers-smiling-and-looking-at-the-camera-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/a-group-of-women-frontline-workers-smiling-and-looking-at-the-camera-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/a-group-of-women-frontline-workers-smiling-and-looking-at-the-camera.jpg 1250w" width="426"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Doctor shortages are creating hurdles in health emergency response</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the crux of the article in simple words?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Medical qualification and expertise is necessary to deliver quality health services by medical professionals unlike by general health care workers who lack competency.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is public health?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Public health has been defined as “the science and art of preventing disease, prolonging life and promoting health through the organized efforts and informed choices of society, organizations, public and private, communities and individuals”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why there is need of qualification?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of training</strong>: Health workers have no training in public health; they are grassroots-level service providers. Asking them to be part of public health cadre trivialises the profession of public health.</li>
<li><strong>Separate profession</strong>: It is important to understand that public health is a separate profession with a specific set of competencies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="public health" class="alignnone wp-image-631767" height="280" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-2.jpeg" width="339"/>What are 4 pillars of public health? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Academics: </strong>Academics refers to a good understanding of evidence generation and synthesis by having a good grounding in epidemiology and biostatistics. These competencies are also critical for monitoring and evaluating programmes, conducting surveillance, and interpreting data and routine reporting.</li>
<li><strong>Activism</strong>: Public health is inherently linked to ‘social change’ and an element of activism is core to public health. Public health requires social mobilisation at the grassroots level by understanding community needs, community organisation, etc. This requires grounding in social and behavioural sciences.</li>
<li><strong>Administration:</strong> Administration refers to administering health systems at different levels from a primary health centre to the district, State, and national level. This includes implementing and managing health programmes, addressing human resource issues, supply and logistical issues, etc. It includes microplanning of programme delivery, team building, leadership as well as financial management to some extent.</li>
<li><strong>Advocacy:</strong> In public health, there is little that one can do at an individual level; there must be communication with key stakeholders to change the status quo at different levels of government. This requires clear enunciation of the need, analysis of alternative set of actions and the cost of implementation or non-implementation. Good communication and negotiation skills are critical to perform this function. The related subjects are health policy, health economics, health advocacy and global health.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="public health" class="alignnone wp-image-631768" height="276" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-1-1.jpeg" width="415"/>What are the hurdles in absorbing others as public health professionals?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of skill</strong>: Many doctors and other health professionals work at the grassroots level and develop a good sense of public health due to their inclination. But they do not become public health professionals as they may not have the necessary skills. Nevertheless, they are valuable.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of critical expertise</strong>: Clinicians with training in epidemiology and biostatistics would not qualify to be public health professionals as they lack not only other essential and critical expertise but also an appropriate perspective.</li>
<li><strong>Compromise on quality</strong>:</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/healthcare-in-india-is-ailing-here-is-how-to-fix-it/"><strong>Current challenges faced by public healthcare in India</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Deficiency: </strong>The doctor-patient ratio of 1:1655 in India as against WHO norm of 1:1000 clearly shows the deficit of MBBS. While the government is working towards a solution and targeting to reach the required ratio, there is a need to relook at the overall medical education.</li>
<li><strong>Post pandemic scenario: </strong>The lag in formal medical education has come up evidently post-pandemic when the nation saw the medical fraternity struggling to fill the doctor deficit.</li>
<li><strong>Limited government seats:</strong> The number of seats available for medical education in India is far less than the number of aspirants who leave school with the dream of becoming doctors.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of skills:</strong> Though the institutes are managing to hire professors and lecturers, there is a lack of technical skills. Finding faculties in clinical and non-clinical disciplines is difficult and there are very few faculty development programs for upskilling the existing lot.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of infrastructure</strong>: The gap in digital learning infrastructure is currently the biggest challenge the sector is facing. There is an urgent need to adopt technology and have resources available to facilitate e-learning.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of research and innovation:</strong> The medical research and innovation needs an added push as there haven’t been many ground-breaking research here. The education system needs to focus more on increasing the quality of research. Additionally since industry academia partnership is not available, hence innovation also takes a back-seat.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>By establishing new medical colleges, the government can increase student intake as well as enhance equitable access to public health as separate profession. This will attract the best and the brightest people into this discipline, which is very important for the nation’s health. This is one lesson that we should learn from the pandemic.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you understand by public health? Do you think it is a separate profession requiring a specific set of competencies? Examine.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/public-health/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The strategic partnership between India and Japan in solving their common security challenges</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/japan/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>QUAD</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Bilateral relations</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Japan" class="alignnone wp-image-631852" height="252" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 378px) 100vw, 378px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/QT-India-Japan-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/QT-India-Japan-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/QT-India-Japan-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/QT-India-Japan-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/QT-India-Japan.jpg 1200w" width="378"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is much that India and Japan could do together in meeting their common security challenges.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>China’s growing military capabilities and assertiveness on territorial disputes are at the heart of the deteriorating environment of India and Japan.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is 2+2 talks between India and allies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The 2+2 dialogue is a format of meeting of the foreign and defence ministers of India and its allies on strategic and security issues.</li>
<li>A 2+2 ministerial dialogue enables the partners to better understand and appreciate each other’s strategic concerns and sensitivities taking into account political factors on both sides.</li>
<li>This helps to build a stronger, more integrated strategic relationship in a rapidly changing global environment.</li>
<li>India has 2+2 dialogues with four key strategic partners: <strong>US, Australia, Japan, and RUSSIA</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Japan" class="alignnone wp-image-631853" height="237" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 356px) 100vw, 356px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/EKoDl3CWsAE-qb1-scaled-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/EKoDl3CWsAE-qb1-scaled-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/EKoDl3CWsAE-qb1-scaled-1.jpg 675w" width="356"/>Recent developments in India-Japan Relationship</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Supply Chain Resilience Initiative</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Recently India, Australia and Japan formally launched the Supply Chain Resilience Initiative. The initiative was launched to counter the dominance of China in the Global Supply Chain.</li>
<li>It aims to prevent disruptions in the supply chain as seen during COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
<li>The initiative will mainly focus on diversification of investment and digital technology adoption.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Other MEA led-bilateral dialogues</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Act East Forum</strong>, established in 2017, aims to provide a platform for India-Japan collaboration under the rubric of India’s <strong>“Act East Policy”</strong> and Japan’s <strong>“Free and Open Indo-Pacific Vision”</strong>.</li>
<li>At the Second meeting of the Act East forum, both sides agreed to focus on expanding of Japanese language in North East, training of caregivers under <strong>Technical Intern Training Program</strong> (<strong>TITP</strong>), capacity building in area of bamboo value chain development and Disaster Management.</li>
<li><strong>The inaugural India-Japan Space Dialogue</strong> was held in Delhi for enhancing bilateral cooperation in outer space and information exchange on the respective space policies.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Currency Swap Agreement</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Japan and India have entered into a $75-billion currency swap arrangement that will bolster the country’s firepower as it battles a steep drop in the rupee’s value.</li>
<li>A currency swap is an agreement between two parties to exchange a series of cash flows denominated in one currency for those denominated in another for a predetermined period of time.</li>
<li>The deal will help the two countries to swap their currencies for U.S. dollars to stabilise the rupee which has witnessed the steepest fall in recent years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Japan" class="alignnone wp-image-631854" height="292" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 371px) 100vw, 371px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/02indo-japan-1-300x236.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/02indo-japan-1-300x236.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/02indo-japan-1.jpg 670w" width="371"/>Japan’s new strategy</strong>:</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Capacity building</strong>: To cope with Chinese power involves three broad elements reorienting Japan’s diplomacy, boosting national capabilities to deter aggression and deepening defence partnerships.</li>
<li><strong>Realism diplomacy</strong>: In his address to the annual Shangri La Dialogue in Singapore this June, Japanese PM Fumio Kishida talked of a new “realism diplomacy” that will allow Japan to meet the new security challenges through pragmatism and firmness.</li>
<li><strong>Increase in budget</strong>: On the question of deterrence, Kishida declared his commitment to “fundamentally reinforce Japan’s defence capabilities within the next five years and secure substantial increase of Japan’s defence budget needed to effect it”.</li>
<li><strong>No apology</strong>: Japan is no longer apologetic about its new determination to protect itself. For different reasons, both Tokyo and Delhi had tended to be far too deferential to China and hesitant to call out Beijing’s unacceptable actions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Security and defence cooperation </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>QUAD</strong>:Formed in 2007 and revived in 2017 The Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (QSD, also known as the Quad) is an informal strategic dialogue between the United States, Japan, Australia and India.</li>
<li><strong>Exercise Malabar</strong>:The dialogue was paralleled by joint military exercises of an unprecedented scale, titled Exercise Malabar.</li>
<li><strong>JIMEX</strong>: In spite of the pandemic, complex exercises in all domains were conducted including Japan India maritime exercise (JIMEX 2020)and PASSEX, showcasing the trust and interoperability between the navies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-india-japan-ties-in-recent-times/"><strong>Challenges in ties </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Geographical limitations</strong>:The two countries are too far apart to be meaningful partners in any confrontation between one of them and China.</li>
<li><strong>China is too big to defeat</strong>:No partnership have the military muscle or diplomatic heft to achieve its objectives in countering China.</li>
<li><strong>Lesser say at UNSC</strong>:At the diplomatic level, neither pulls the kind of power that can counter Beijing and this is not just because they are not UNSC members, unlike China.</li>
<li><strong>Japan lacks military technology</strong>:Japan obviously has a very advanced high-technology industrial sector, its military industry is insignificant. It’s better not to invoke the DRDO.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Key fact to remember </strong></p>
<p>Japanese economy is the third-largest in the world</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>People to people contact:</strong> Although the Covid-19 situation remains challenging, people-to-people exchanges between two countries are also being advanced.</li>
<li><strong>Cooperation in security:</strong> Cooperation has also taken great strides in the area of security, including joint exercises between the Japan Self-Defence Forces and the Indian Armed Forces.</li>
<li><strong>Reaping the benefits of natural alliance:</strong> Taking advantage of its considerable assets — the world’s third-largest economy, substantial high-tech skills, Japan is largely perceived as a natural ally to India.</li>
<li><strong>Looking East:</strong> If Japan and India continue to add concrete security content to their relationship, their strategic partnership could potentially be a game-changer in Asia.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Both should inject substantive military content into the strategic partnership between India and Japan. For there is much that Delhi and Tokyo could do together in meeting their common security challenges.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>China’s growing military capabilities and assertiveness on territorial disputes are at the heart of the deteriorating environment of India and Japan. Critically examine bilateral ties between both.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/japan/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>LGBTQ leap forward for positive future growth of human rights</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/lgbtq/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>various judgments</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>human rights</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="LGBTQ" class="alignnone wp-image-631871" height="248" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 372px) 100vw, 372px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gp-kZ7E-621x414%40LiveMint-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gp-kZ7E-621x414%40LiveMint-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gp-kZ7E-621x414%40LiveMint.jpg 621w" width="372"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Four years after landmark LGBTQ verdict: The march to full citizenship.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>On September 6, 2018, exactly four years ago, in Navtej Singh Johar and Ors v Union of India, a five-judge constitution bench of the Supreme Court, in a beautifully elaborate decision, liberated LGBTQI Indians from the darkness of Section 377 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/lgbt-rights/"><strong>What is LGBTQ?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>LGBTQ is an initialism that stands for lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender. In use since the 1990s, the initialism, as well as some of its common variants, functions as an umbrella term for sexuality and gender identity.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Section 377 of the IPC?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It reads – Unnatural offences: Whoever voluntarily has <strong>carnal intercourse against the order of nature </strong>with any man, woman or animal shall be punished with imprisonment for life, or with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to ten years, and shall also be liable to fine.</li>
<li>The terms “carnal intercourse” and “against the order of nature” are not defined precisely anywhere in the code.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="LGBTQ" class="alignnone wp-image-631872" height="254" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 451px) 100vw, 451px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/48561589_101-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/48561589_101-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/48561589_101-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/48561589_101.jpg 1024w" width="451"/>Role played by the judiciary hitherto</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Delhi High Court’s verdict in Naz Foundation vs Government of NCT of Delhi (2009) was a landmark in the law of sexuality and equality jurisprudence in India.</li>
<li>The court held that Section 377 offended the guarantee of equality enshrined in Article 14 of the Constitution, because it creates an unreasonable classification and targets homosexuals as a class.</li>
<li>In a retrograde step, the Supreme Court, in Suresh Kumar Koushal vs Naz Foundation (2013), reinstated Section 377 to the IPC.</li>
<li>However, the Supreme Court in Navtej Singh Johar &amp; Ors. vs Union of India (2018) declared that the application of Section 377 IPC to consensual homosexual behaviour was “unconstitutional”.</li>
<li>This Supreme Court judgment has been a great victory to the Indian individual in his quest for identity and dignity.</li>
<li>It also underscored the doctrine of progressive realisation of rights.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="LGBTQ" class="alignnone wp-image-631876" height="325" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 488px) 100vw, 488px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Section377-621x414-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Section377-621x414-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Section377-621x414-1.jpg 621w" width="488"/>What’s next?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Overarching legislation is needed to guarantee equality to all persons on the basis of sexual orientation, gender identity and expression, sex, caste, religion, age, disability, marital status, pregnancy, nationality, and other grounds.</li>
<li>The law should impose obligations of equality and non-discrimination on all persons, public and private, and in the areas of education, employment, healthcare, land and housing and access to public places.</li>
<li>It should provide for civil remedies to stop discriminatory behaviour, costs and damages, and positive action to make reparations.</li>
<li>We need an equality law to define what equality would encompass.</li>
<li>Supreme Court comes held in its privacy judgment in K.S. Puttuswamy v. Union of India (2017) that equality and liberty cannot be separated, and equality encompasses the inclusion of dignity and basic freedoms.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Schools and colleges must effect changes in curricula for a better understanding of the community.</li>
<li>People of a different sexual orientation or gender identity often narrate harrowing tales of bullying, discrimination, stigma and ostracization.</li>
<li>Gender-neutral restrooms should be compulsory in educational institutes and other places.</li>
<li>Parents too need to be sensitised, because the first point of misunderstanding and abuse often begins at home, with teenagers being forced to opt for “conversion” therapies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Justice Chandrachud, speaking on the fourth anniversary of Johar and the journey ahead, while quoting the Beatles classic “All you need is love”, notes that “simply love is not enough”. Rights are necessary. Which will enhance dignity of the community.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. “Silent segregation” on the grounds of gender, sexual orientation preferences are followed in several houses. Elucidate in context of LGBTQ issues. What Legal remedies are needed for its victims?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/lgbtq/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Sustainable port development promises blue economy to bloom</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/port-development/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Sustainable coast management</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is politically hard, but developmentally critical, to run port development projects with coastal management sustainably.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="port" class="alignnone wp-image-632083" height="314" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 419px) 100vw, 419px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler.jpg 1200w" width="419"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-ports-development/">What is a port?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A port is a maritime facility comprising one or more wharves or loading areas, where ships load and discharge cargo and passengers. Although usually situated on a sea coast or estuary, ports can also be found far inland, such as Hamburg, Manchester and Duluth; these access the sea via rivers or canals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is meant by port management?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A port management analysis involves an understanding of the port conditions, including intra-port distribution, and routes and hinterland connections outside the port.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why ports are important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Ports infrastructure is key to the development of any nation. India has a coastline spanning about 7,500 km. around 90 percent of India’s external trade by volume and 70 percent by value are handled by ports.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="port" class="alignnone wp-image-632085" height="303" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 502px) 100vw, 502px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Jawaharlal_Nehru_Trust_Port-300x181.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Jawaharlal_Nehru_Trust_Port-300x181.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Jawaharlal_Nehru_Trust_Port.jpg 640w" width="502"/>What are concerns with port projects?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Displacement: </strong>Some 350 families that have lost homes to coastal erosion last year, and those living in makeshift schools and camps are just a foretaste of things to come if coastal erosion and extreme cyclones continue unabated.</li>
<li><strong>Ecological impact</strong>: A further danger is an irreversibly destroyed ecology, triggering deadlier hazards of nature. Ports without adequate safeguards in a highly delicate ecology unleash destruction on marine life and the livelihoods of the local population.</li>
<li><strong>Coastal erosion</strong>: Visakhapatnam and Chennai show how siltation, coastal erosion and accretion can be exacerbated by deepening of harbour channels in ecologically sensitive areas.</li>
<li><strong>Oil spills:</strong> During the operation of ports, spillage or leakages from the loading and unloading of cargo and pollution from oil spills are common due to poor adherence to environmental laws and standards.</li>
<li><strong>Ecosystem threat</strong>: The water discharged during the cleaning of a ship and the discharge of ballast water is a threat to marine ecosystems</li>
<li><strong>Impact on fisheries: </strong>Dredging cause’s environmental problems (increased sedimentation) affecting local productivity of the local waters and its fisheries</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Value addition example </strong></p>
<p>A just published study shows that during 2006-20, the sea gobbled some 2.62 square kilometres or close to 650 acres from the Thiruvananthapuram coast alone.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="port" class="alignnone wp-image-632086" height="291" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 455px) 100vw, 455px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1953413479_27757193ef_o-800x512-1-300x192.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1953413479_27757193ef_o-800x512-1-300x192.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1953413479_27757193ef_o-800x512-1-768x492.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1953413479_27757193ef_o-800x512-1.jpg 800w" width="455"/>Steps to take</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Compensation:</strong> The first order of business, as in infrastructure projects worldwide, is that the project provides compensation to the displaced people and restores their rights.</li>
<li><strong>Reversing marine damage:</strong> Second, the gross neglect of the damage to invaluable marine biodiversity must be redressed with an acceptable EIA, including inputs from experts in biology, ecology, and oceanography.</li>
<li><strong>Safeguard to place:</strong> Third, there needs to be an independent assessment of safeguards that port authorities must put in place as a precondition for any further construction.</li>
<li><strong>Blue Economy:</strong>Blue Economy as a concept includes all the economic activities related to oceans, seas, and coastal areas and emerges from a need for integrated conservation and sustainability in the management of the maritime domain.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Master plan</strong>: Countries should adopt a National Long-term Mater plan addressing the aspects of smarter, greener, safer sustainable port development and productivity improvement.</li>
<li><strong>Planning:</strong> Port development and investment should be driven by setting specific and realistic goals, such as building a stable infrastructure focused on reducing trade costs and contribute to achieving sustainable transport.</li>
<li><strong>Cooperation of multiple sectors</strong>: In order to establish a comprehensive port development master plan, cooperation with financial, environmental, technical, energy, transportation and urban development authorities is essential and must reflect the needs of users, including shippers and shipping lines.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To address existing challenges, we should provide research, analysis and technical assistance to help ports and the maritime transport sector especially in developing countries to improve operations and become more sustainable and resilient to crises, including climate change.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. What do you understand by sustainable port development and port productivity? Discuss the challenges in achieving the same along with way forward.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/port-development/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Planned sand mining could save the deteriorating rivers</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sand-mining-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>environment impact of sand mining</p></div></div><p> </p>
<h4><strong><img alt="sand mining" class="alignnone wp-image-632091" height="264" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 528px) 100vw, 528px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_1-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_1-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_1-1024x512.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_1-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_1-1536x768.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_1-1200x600.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_1.jpg 1600w" width="528"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>From flora and fauna to human residents, no one has been left untouched due to the wanton extraction of sand mining from Yamuna River.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is sand?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sand is a granular material made up of finely divided rock and mineral fragments. According to The Mines and Minerals (Development and Regulations) Act of 1957, sand is classified as a “minor mineral”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Sand mining?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sand mining is the extraction of sand, mainly through an open pit but sometimes mined from beaches and inland dunes or dredged from ocean and river beds. Sand is often used in manufacturing, for example as an abrasive or in concrete.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Sand Mining overview</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Least regulated</strong>: Sand and gravel are the second largest natural resources extracted and traded by volume after water, but among the least regulated.</li>
<li><strong>Uneven distribution</strong>: Sand is created by slow geological processes, and its distribution is not even.</li>
<li><strong>Desert sand: </strong>Available in plenty, is not suited for construction use because it is wind-smoothed, and therefore non-adherent.</li>
<li><strong>Environmental impact</strong>: While 85% to 90% of global sand demand is met from quarries, and sand and gravel pits, the 10% to 15% extracted from rivers and sea shores is a severe concern due the environmental and social impacts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="sand mining" class="alignnone wp-image-632092" height="301" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 534px) 100vw, 534px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/aadfff77-5ff6-41cc-b59c-c6d422ba1052_w1080_h608_s-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/aadfff77-5ff6-41cc-b59c-c6d422ba1052_w1080_h608_s-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/aadfff77-5ff6-41cc-b59c-c6d422ba1052_w1080_h608_s-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/aadfff77-5ff6-41cc-b59c-c6d422ba1052_w1080_h608_s-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/aadfff77-5ff6-41cc-b59c-c6d422ba1052_w1080_h608_s.jpg 1080w" width="534"/>Concerns of excessive mining</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Deteriorating river banks</strong>: Their extraction often results in river and coastal erosion and threats to freshwater and marine fisheries and aquatic ecosystems, instability of river banks leading to increased flooding, and lowering of ground water levels.</li>
<li><strong>Critical hotspot:</strong> The report notes that China and India head the list of critical hotspots for sand extraction impacts in rivers, lakes and on coastlines.</li>
<li><strong>Broken replenishment</strong>: system exacerbates pressures on beaches already threatened by sea level rise and intensity of storm-waves induced by climate change, as well as coastal developments.</li>
<li><strong>Aesthetic sense is reduced</strong>: There are also indirect consequences, like loss of local livelihoods an ironic example is that construction in tourist destinations can lead to depletion of natural sand in the area, thereby making those very places unattractive and safety risks for workers where the industry is not regulated.</li>
<li><strong>No comprehensive assessment</strong>: Despite this, there is no comprehensive assessment available to evaluate the scale of sand mining in India.</li>
<li><strong>Damage to the environment</strong>: Regional studies such as those by the Centre for Science and Environment of the Yamuna riverbed in Uttar Pradesh have observed that increasing demand for soil has severely affected soil formation and the soil holding ability of the land, leading to a loss in marine life, an increase in flood frequency, droughts, and also degradation of water quality.</li>
<li><strong>Loss to exchequer:</strong> It is not just damage to the environment. Illegal mining causes copious losses to the state exchequer.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Innovative use of technology </strong></p>
<p>State governments such as Gujarat have employed satellite imagery to monitor the volume of sand extraction and transportation from the riverbeds.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="sand mining" class="alignnone wp-image-632093" height="345" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 612px) 100vw, 612px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_3_oQzaCxR-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_3_oQzaCxR-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_3_oQzaCxR-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_3_oQzaCxR-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_3_oQzaCxR-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_3_oQzaCxR-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Image_3_oQzaCxR.jpg 1600w" width="612"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-the-mineral-laws-amendment-bill-2020/">Sustainable Sand and Minor Mineral Mining – Guidelines</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Where to mine and where to prohibit mining: </strong>District Survey Report for each district in the country, focusing on the river as a single ecological system. ISRO, remote sensing data, and ground truthing are all used.</li>
<li><strong>Sustainable mining: </strong>It involves extracting only the amount of material that is deposited each year.</li>
<li><strong>District authorities’ participation in the process: </strong>The District Collector chairs the District Environment Impact Assessment Authority (DEIAA). The District Collector will be assisted by the District Level Expert Appraisal Committee (DEAC), which is led by the Executive Engineer (Irrigation Department) and is tasked with granting environmental clearance for up to 5 hectares of mine lease area for minor minerals, primarily sand.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Protecting sand mineral requires investment in production and consumption measurement and also monitoring and planning tools. To this end, technology has to be used to provide a sustainable solution.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question  </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. </strong><strong>A growing global population increasingly living in cities has led to a spiralling rise in the extraction of sand and aggregates, with serious environmental, political and social consequences. Examine.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sand-mining-2/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Mental wellness for stress free life</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mental-wellness/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>manodarpan initiative</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>mental health</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="mental wellness" class="alignnone wp-image-632098" height="331" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-3.jpeg" width="372"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>How to deal with mental wellness challenges in the uniformed forces</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is stress?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Stress is a feeling of emotional or physical tension. It can come from any event or thought that makes you feel frustrated, angry, or nervous. Stress is your body’s reaction to a challenge or demand.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is mental wellness?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Mental wellness encompasses emotional, psychological, and social well-being. It influences cognition, perception, and behaviour. It also determines how an individual handles stress, interpersonal relationships, and decision-making.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is Mental Health Important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Mental health is more important now than ever before; it impacts every area of our lives. The importance of good mental health ripples into everything we do, think, or say.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="mental wellness" class="alignnone wp-image-632099" height="304" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 537px) 100vw, 537px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/clusters-img-4-300x170.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/clusters-img-4-300x170.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/clusters-img-4.jpg 741w" width="537"/>Reasons for Persistence of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/mental-illness-is-a-critical-health-concern-in-india-which-also-faces-social-stigma-in-context-of-this-analyze-the-importance-of-new-mental-health-care-act-which-came-into-force-in-july-2018-also-di/">Mental Illness</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Stigma to seek help</strong>: The staggering figures are void of millions of others directly, or indirectly impacted by the challenge and those who face deep-rooted stigma, many times rendering them unable to seek help.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of awareness</strong>: This growing challenge in dealing with mental health issues is further compounded by a lack of information and awareness, self-diagnosis, and stigma.</li>
<li><strong>Psycho-social factors:</strong> Institutions like gender, race and ethnicity, are also responsible for mental health conditions.</li>
<li><strong>Post-Treatment gap</strong>: There is a need for proper rehabilitation of the mentally ill persons post/her treatment which is currently not present.</li>
<li><strong>Rise in Severity</strong>: Mental health problems tend to increase during economic downturns, therefore special attention is needed during times of economic distress.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="mental wellness" class="alignnone wp-image-632100" height="234" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 401px) 100vw, 401px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mental-health-wellness-during-covid-19-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mental-health-wellness-during-covid-19-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mental-health-wellness-during-covid-19-768x449.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/mental-health-wellness-during-covid-19.jpg 1000w" width="401"/>Ongoing challenges in mental wellness regime </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is a need to expand understanding of the full scope of what uniformed Services and other mental health experts can achieve.</li>
<li>Stigma regarding mental health both domestically and around the world remains strong.</li>
<li>There is a lack of trained personnel and healthcare and public health systems in many areas of the world.</li>
<li>Training needs are broad and reach beyond direct patient care, especially regarding cultural competence, crisis communication, and consultation.</li>
<li>There is a need for expanded support for the value of multi-professional and multi-organizational integration and collaboration.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Government Policy initiatives</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>National Mental Health Program (NMHP): </strong>To address the huge burden of mental disorders and shortage of qualified professionals in the field of mental health, the government has been implementing the NMHP since 1982.</li>
<li><strong>Mental HealthCare Act 2017</strong>: It guarantees every affected person access to mental healthcare and treatment from services run or funded by the government.</li>
<li><strong>Rights of Persons with Disabilities Act, 2017:</strong> The Act acknowledges mental illness as a disability and seeks to enhance the Rights and Entitlements of the Disabled and provide an effective mechanism for ensuring their empowerment and inclusion in the society</li>
<li><strong>Manodarpan Initiative</strong>: An initiative under Atmanirbhar Bharat Abhiyan aims to provide psycho-social support to students for their mental health and well-being.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What needs to be done?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Open dialogue: </strong>The practice of open dialogue, a therapeutic practice that originated in Finland, runs through many programmes in the Guidance. This approach trains the therapist in de-escalation of distress and breaks power differentials that allow for free expression.</li>
<li><strong>Increase investment</strong>: With emphasis on social care components such as work force participation, pensions and housing, increased investments in health and social care seem imperative.</li>
<li><strong>Network of services</strong>: For those homeless and who opt not to enter mental health establishments, we can provide a network of services ranging from soup kitchens at vantage points to mobile mental health and social care clinics.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Persons with mental health conditions need a responsive care system that inspires hope and participation without which their lives are empty. We should endeavour to provide them with such a responsive care system.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Mental disorders are now among the top leading causes of health burden worldwide, with no evidence of global reduction since 1990. Examine.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mental-wellness/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>5G revolution and challenges</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/5g-revolution/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of 5G</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>scientific achievements and issues with it</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="5G revolution " class="alignnone wp-image-625615" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful.jpeg 1200w" width="581"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Prime Minister Narendra Modi recently announced that 5G revolution deployment in India will commence sooner than expected.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is 5G technology?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>5G or fifth generation revolution  is the latest upgrade in the long-term evolution (LTE) mobile broadband networks.</li>
<li>5G enables a new kind of network that is designed to connect virtually everyone and everything together including machines, objects, and devices.</li>
<li>It’s a unified platform which is much more capable than previous mobile services with more capacity, lower latency, faster data delivery rate and better utilisation of spectrum.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How it evolved from 1G to 5G?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>1G: </strong>Launched in the 1980s. Analog radio signals and supported only voice calls.</li>
<li><strong>2G:</strong> Launched in the 1990s. Uses digital radio signals and supported both voice and data transmission with a Bandwidth (BW) of 64 Kbps.</li>
<li><strong>3G:</strong> Launched in the 2000s. With a speed of 1 Mbps to 2 Mbps it has the ability to transmit telephone signal including digitized voice, video calls and conferencing.</li>
<li><strong>4G</strong>: With a peak speed of 100 Mbps-1 Gbps it also enables 3D virtual reality.</li>
<li><strong>5G:</strong> with a speed of more than 1Gbps, it is capable of connecting entire world without limits.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="5G revolution" class="alignnone wp-image-625641" height="291" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 552px) 100vw, 552px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g1-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g1-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g1.jpg 392w" width="552"/>Salient features</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Capability:</strong> 5G will provide much faster mobile broadband service as compared to the previous versions and will provide support to previous services like mission critical communication and the massive Internet Of Things (IoT).</li>
<li><strong>Upgraded LTE</strong>: 5G is the latest upgrade in the long-term evolution (LTE) mobile broadband networks.</li>
<li><strong>Speed:</strong> With peak delivering rate of up to 20 Gbps and an average of 100Mbps, it will be much faster as compared to its predecessors. The speed increment is partly achieved partly by using higher-frequency radio waves than previous networks.</li>
<li><strong>Capacity</strong>: There will be up to 100 x increase in traffic capacity and network efficiency.</li>
<li><strong>Spectrum usage</strong>: Will provide better usage for every bit of spectrum, from low bands below 1 GHz to high bands.</li>
<li><strong>Latency</strong>: It’s expected to have lower latency with better instantaneous, real-time access of the data. The 5G, like 4G LTE, also uses Orthogonal Frequency Division Multiplexing (OFDM) but the new 5G NR (New Radio) air interface will enhance OFDM and provide better flexibility in data delivery.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><br/>
<img alt="5G revolution" class="alignnone wp-image-625634" height="176" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-300x81.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-300x81.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g.jpg 718w" width="650"/>Applications of 5G technology</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>High-Speed mobile network</strong>: 5G will revolutionize the mobile experience with supercharged wireless network. Compared to conventional mobile transmission technologies, voice and high-speed data can be simultaneously transferred efficiently in 5G.</li>
<li><strong>Entertainment and multimedia</strong>: 5G can provide 120 frames per second, high resolution and higher dynamic range video streaming without interruption. Audiovisual experience will be rewritten after the implementation of the latest technologies powered by 5G wireless. Augmented Reality and virtual Reality services will be better experienced over 5G.</li>
<li><strong>Internet of Things</strong>: IoT applications collects huge amount of data from millions of devices and sensors and thus requires an efficient network for data collection, processing, transmission, control and real-time analytics which 5G network is a better candidate.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Interesting facts about 5G</strong></h4>
<p><strong>According to researchers, about 1.5 billion people will have access to 5G by 2024. </strong></p>
<p><strong>It may not seem like it at present, however, 5G will cover about 40% of the world.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>The security risks introduced BY 5G</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increased attack surface</strong>: With millions and even billions more connected devices, 5G makes it possible for larger and more dangerous attacks. Current and future vulnerabilities of the existing internet infrastructure are only exacerbated. The risk of more sophisticated botnets, privacy violations, and faster data extraction can escalate with 5G.</li>
<li><strong>More IoT, more problems</strong>: IoT devices are inherently insecure; security is often not built-in by design. Each insecure IoT device on an organization’s networks represents another potential hole that an attacker can expose.</li>
<li><strong>Decreased network visibility</strong>: With 5G, our networks will only expand and become more usable by mobile users and devices. This means much more network traffic to manage. But without a robust wide area network (WAN) security solution like Secure Access Service Edge (SASE) in place, companies may not be able to gain the network traffic visibility required to identify abnormalities or attacks.</li>
<li><strong>Increased supply chain and software vulnerabilities</strong>: Currently and for the foreseeable future, 5G supply chains are limited. Vulnerabilities exist — particularly as devices are rushed to market — increasing the potential for faulty and insecure components. Compared to traditional mobile networks, 5G is also more reliant on software, which elevates the risk of exploitation of the network infrastructure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges in rolling out 5G</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enabling critical infrastructures</strong>: 5G will require a fundamental change to the core architecture of the communication system. The major flaw of data transfer using 5G is that it can’t carry data over longer distances. Hence, even 5G technology needs to be augmented to enable infrastructure.</li>
<li><strong>Financial liability on consumers</strong>: For transition from 4G to 5G technology, one has to upgrade to the latest cellular technology, thereby creating financial liability on consumers.</li>
<li><strong>Capital Inadequacy</strong>: Lack of flow of cash and adequate capital with the suitable telecom companies (like Bharti Airtel and Vodafone Idea) is delaying the 5G spectrum allocation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India should not miss the opportunity and should proactively work to deploy 5G technology. We should focus on strengthening our cyber infrastructure.</li>
<li>5G start-ups that enable this design and manufacturing capabilities should be promoted. This will spur leaps in the coverage, capacity and density of wireless networks.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">Conclusion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The recent recommendation of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India to the government to develop a national road map for India to implement 5G in the best possible manner should include cyber security concerns.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. 5G is already transforming and enhancing connectivity. In this context Discuss India’s preparedness and cybersecurity challenges that needs to be taken care of for earlier roll out of 5G.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/5g-revolution/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>UN slams Sri Lanka’s rights record</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/un-slams-sri-lanka-rights-record/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UNHRC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economic crisis in Sri Lanka</p></div></div><p>Linking Sri Lanka’s past on human rights record to its current economic crisis, the UN Human Rights Chief on said “impunity” for human rights abuses, economic crimes, and corruption was the underlying reason for the country’s collapse.</p>
<h4>UNHRC report on Sri Lanka</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/united-nations-human-rights-council-unhrc/">UNHRC</a> report warned that Sri Lanka’s failure to address human rights violations and war crimes committed in the past had put the country on a “dangerous path”.</li>
<li>It rose that this could lead to a “recurrence” of policies and practices that gave rise to the earlier situation.</li>
<li>It flagged the accelerating militarization of civilian governmental functions, a reversal of important constitutional safeguards, political obstruction of accountability, intimidation of civil society, and the use of anti-terrorism laws.</li>
<li>The shrinking space for independent media and civil society and human rights organizations are also themes in the report.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Resolution 30/1</h4>
<ul>
<li>The resolution 30/1 launched in 2015 deals with promoting reconciliation, accountability and human rights in Sri Lanka.</li>
<li>It extended an opportunity to make good on its promises for justice and offered extensive support to accomplish that objective.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Sri Lanka’s intention</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is more than Sri Lanka has failed to – and doesn’t intend to — take the necessary, decisive, and sustainable steps necessary to achieve domestic justice and reconciliation.</li>
<li>Sri Lanka has officially sought India’s help to muster support against the resolution, which it has described as “unwanted interference by powerful countries”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where India comes in</h4>
<ul>
<li>The UNHRC is scheduled to hold an “interactive” session on Sri Lanka where the report was to be discussed, and member countries were to make statements.</li>
<li>Country-specific resolutions against Sri Lanka have regularly come up at the UNHRC in the last decade.</li>
<li>New Delhi voted against Sri Lanka in 2012 and abstained in 2014. It was spared the dilemma in 2015 when Sri Lanka joined resolution 30/1.</li>
<li>With elections coming up in Tamil Nadu, and PM declaring on a recent visit that he was the first Indian leader to visit Jaffna, Sri Lanka has begun reading the tea leaves.</li>
<li>Whichever way it goes, the resolution is likely to resonate in India-Sri Lanka Relations and for India internally, in the run-up to the Assembly elections in Tamil Nadu.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/un-slams-sri-lanka-rights-record/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the PM SHRI Scheme?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-pm-shri-scheme/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PM Shri Schools</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632164" height="398" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 394px) 100vw, 394px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pmshri-297x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pmshri-297x300.jpg 297w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pmshri.jpg 630w" width="394"/></p>
<p>Prime Minister has announced that under the PM SHRI Scheme, as many as 14,500 schools will be “upgraded” across India to showcase the components of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-national-education-policy-2020-higher-education-and-regional-languages/">National Education Policy, 2020</a>.</p>
<h4>What is the PM SHRI scheme?</h4>
<ul>
<li>According to the Ministry of Education, the <strong><u>centrally sponsored scheme</u></strong> will be called PM SHRI Schools (PM Schools for Rising India).</li>
<li>Under it, as many as 14,500 schools across states and Union Territories will be redeveloped to reflect the key features of the NEP, 2020.</li>
<li>The plan was first discussed with the education ministers of states and UTs during a conference organised by the Ministry of Education in June at Gandhinagar in Gujarat.</li>
<li>While there are exemplary schools like Navodaya Vidyalayas, Kendriya Vidyalayas, the PM SHRI will act as “NEP labs”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the key features of NEP in school education?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The NEP envisages a curricular structure and teaching style divided into various stages – foundational, preparatory, middle and secondary.</li>
<li>The foundational years (pre-school and grades I, II) will involve play-based learning.</li>
<li>At the preparatory level (III-V), light textbooks are to be introduced along with some formal classroom teaching. Subject teachers are to be introduced at the middle level (VI-VIII).</li>
<li>The secondary stage (IX-XII) will be multidisciplinary in nature with no hard separation between arts and sciences or other disciplines.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is a centrally sponsored scheme?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A centrally sponsored scheme is one where the cost of implementation is likely to split in the 60:40 ratio among the Union government and the states/Union Territories.</li>
<li>For instance, the mid-day meal scheme (PM Poshan) or the PM Awas Yojana are examples of centrally sponsored schemes.</li>
<li>In the case of the Northeastern states, Himachal Pradesh, Uttarakhand, Jammu and Kashmir and UTs without legislatures, the Centre’s contribution can go up to 90 per cent.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How will PM SHRI schools be different from Kendriya Vidyalayas or Jawahar Navodaya Vidyalayas?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Kendriya Vidyalayas or Jawahar Navodaya Vidyalayas come entirely under the Centre’s Ministry of Education. They are fully funded by the Union government under Central Sector Schemes.</li>
<li>While KVs largely cater to children of Union government employees posted in states and UTs, JNVs were set up to nurture talented students in rural parts of the country.</li>
<li>In contrast, PM SHRI schools will be an upgrade of existing schools run by the Centre, states, UTs and local bodies.</li>
<li>This essentially means that PM SHRI schools can either be KVs, JNVs, state government schools or even those run by municipal corporations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where will the PM SHRI schools come up?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Centre has not yet released the list of schools that have been chosen for this purpose.</li>
<li>It has however announced that the PM SHRI schools will also “offer mentorship” to other schools in their vicinity.</li>
<li>These schools will be equipped with modern infrastructure including labs, smart classrooms, libraries, sports equipment, art room etc.</li>
<li>It shall also be developed as green schools with water conservation, waste recycling, energy-efficient infrastructure and integration of organic lifestyle in curriculum.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-pm-shri-scheme/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Bangladesh favours early solution for Teesta Dispute</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/teesta-water-sharing-issue/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Teesta River</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India-Bangladesh Relations</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-575770" height="586" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 524px) 100vw, 524px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/tist.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/tist.jpg 524w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/tist-268x300.jpg 268w" width="524"/></p>
<p>India and Bangladesh should resolve all bilateral issues, including the differences over the waters of the Teesta, at an early date, said Bangladesh PM on her visit to India.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Bangladeshi PM is on a visit to India.</li>
<li>Both ministers discussed the long-standing disputes over Teesta river water sharing.</li>
<li>The two sides shared 54 rivers that required both nations to work together and share “environmental responsibility” in areas such as the Sundarbans.</li>
</ul>
<h4>About Teesta River</h4>
<ul>
<li>Teesta River is a 315 km long river that rises in the eastern Himalayas, flows through the Indian states of Sikkim and West Bengal through Bangladesh and enters the Bay of Bengal.</li>
<li>It is a tributary of the Brahmaputra (known as Jamuna in Bangladesh), flowing through India and Bangladesh.</li>
<li>It originates in the Himalayas near Chunthang, Sikkim and flows to the south through West Bengal before entering Bangladesh.</li>
<li>Originally, it continued southward to empty directly into the Padma River but around 1787 the river changed its course to flow eastward to join the Jamuna river.</li>
<li>The Teesta Barrage dam helps to provide irrigation for the plains between the upper Padma and the Jamuna.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the dispute about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The point of contention between India and Bangladesh is mainly the lean season flow in the Teesta draining into Bangladesh.</li>
<li>The river covers nearly the entire floodplains of Sikkim while draining 2,800 sq km of Bangladesh, governing the lives of hundreds of thousands of people.</li>
<li>For West Bengal, Teesta is equally important, considered the lifeline of half-a-dozen districts in North Bengal.</li>
<li>Bangladesh has sought an “equitable” distribution of Teesta waters from India, on the lines of the Ganga Water Treaty of 1996, but to no avail.</li>
<li>The failure to ink a deal had its fallout on the country’s politics, putting the ruling party of PM Sheikh Hasina in a spot.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>Q.The hydrological linkages between India and Bangladesh are a product of geography and a matter of shared history. Discuss this statement in line with the Teesta water sharing dispute.</p></blockquote>
<h4>The deal</h4>
<ul>
<li>Following a half-hearted deal in 1983, when a nearly equal division of water was proposed, the countries hit a roadblock. The transient agreement could not be implemented.</li>
<li>Talks resumed after the Awami League returned to power in 2008 and the former Indian PM Manmohan Singh visited Dhaka in 2011.</li>
<li>In 2015, PM Modi’s visit to Dhaka generated more ebullient lines: deliberations were underway involving all the stakeholders to conclude the agreement as soon as possible.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues from the Indian side</h4>
<ul>
<li>It remains an unfinished project and one of the key stakeholders — West Bengal CM is yet to endorse the deal.</li>
<li>Her objection is connected to “global warming. Many of the glaciers on the Teesta basin have retreated.</li>
<li>The importance of the flow and the seasonal variation of this river is felt during the lean season (from October to April/May) as the average flow is about 500 million cubic metres (MCM) per month.</li>
<li>The CM opposed an arrangement in 2011, by which India would get 42.5% and Bangladesh 37.5% of the water during the lean season, and the plan was shelved.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why does this deal matters?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India and Bangladesh have resolved border problems through the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/land-boundary-agreement-lba-with-bangladesh/">Land Boundary Agreement of 2015</a>.</li>
<li>However, both nations have locked horns over the sharing of multiple rivers that define the borders and impact lives and livelihoods on both sides.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/teesta-water-sharing-issue/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>In news: Sutlej-Yamuna Link (SYL) Canal</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sutlej-yamuna-link-syl-canal-ias/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>SYL Canal</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Interstate water disputes</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632166" height="438" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 409px) 100vw, 409px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/sutlej-280x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/sutlej-280x300.jpg 280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/sutlej.jpg 670w" width="409"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court drew an assurance from the State of Punjab that it will meet the Haryana counterpart within this month to discuss the construction of the Sutlej-Yamuna Link (SYL) Canal which has been languishing for two decades.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The observations came after the Centre complained that Punjab had “refrained” from coming to the negotiating table to engage in talks with Haryana over the issue.</li>
<li>The construction of Punjab’s portion of the canal had led to <strong><u>militant attacks in the 1980s</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The issue had also been a political thorn for successive governments in Punjab, so much so that it led to the State’s unilateral enactment of the <strong><u>controversial Punjab Termination of Water Agreements Act of 2004. </u></strong></li>
<li>This law was, however, <strong><u>struck down by a Constitution Bench in 2016</u></strong>, dashing the hopes of Punjab’s farmers to reclaim lands acquired for the SYL canal project.</li>
</ul>
<h4>About Sutlej-Yamuna Link (SYL) Canal</h4>
<ul>
<li>Satluj Yamuna Link Canal or SYL as it is popularly known, is an under-construction 214-kilometer long canal in India to connect the Sutlej and Yamuna rivers.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the SYL canal issue?</h4>
<ul>
<li>At the time of reorganization of Punjab in 1966, the issue of sharing of river waters between both the states emerged.</li>
<li>Punjab refused to share waters of Ravi and Beas with Haryana stating it was against the riparian principle.</li>
<li>Before the reorganization, in 1955, out of 15.85 MAF of Ravi and Beas, the Centre had allocated 8 MAF to Rajasthan, 7.20 MAF to undivided Punjab, 0.65MAF to Jammu and Kashmir.</li>
<li>Out of 7.20 MAF allocated, Punjab did not want to share any water with Haryana.</li>
<li>In March 1976, when the Punjab Reorganization Act was implemented, the Centre notified fresh allocations, providing 3.5 MAF To Haryana.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Inception of the canal project</h4>
<ul>
<li>Later, in 1981, the water flowing down Beas and Ravi was revised and pegged at 17.17 MAF, out of which 4.22 MAF was allocated to Punjab, 3.5 MAF to Haryana, and 8.6 MAF to Rajasthan.</li>
<li>Finally, to provide this allocated share of water to southern parts of Haryana, a canal linking the Sutlej with the Yamuna, cutting across the state, was planned.</li>
<li>Finally, the construction of 214-km SYL was started in April 1982, 122 km of which was to run through Punjab and the rest through Haryana.</li>
<li>Haryana has completed its side of the canal, but work in Punjab has been hanging fire for over three decades.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why has the SYL canal come up again now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The issue is back on centre stage after the Supreme Court directed the CMs of Punjab and Haryana to negotiate and settle the SYL canal issue.</li>
<li>The apex court asked for a meeting at the highest political level to be mediated by the Centre so that the states reach a consensus over the completion of the SYL canal.</li>
<li>The meeting remained inconclusive with the Centre expressing the view that the construction of the SYL canal should be completed. But Punjab CM refused categorically.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Punjab’s resentment with the project</h4>
<ul>
<li>The dispute is based on the <strong><u>bloody history around the SYL canal</u></strong>. The trouble-torn days of terrorism in Punjab started in the early 1980s when work on the SYL started.</li>
<li>Punjab feels it utilized its precious groundwater resources to grow the crop for the entire country and should not be forced to share its waters as it faces desertification.</li>
<li>It is feared that once the construction of the canal restarts, the youth may start feeling that the state has been discriminated against.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Punjab CM fears Pakistan and secessionist organisations could exploit</u></strong> this and foment trouble in the state.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Water crisis in Punjab</h4>
<ul>
<li>Punjab is facing severe water crisis due to over-exploitation of its underground aquifers for the wheat/paddy monocycle.</li>
<li>According to the Central Underground Water Authority’s report, its underground water is over-exploited to meet the agriculture requirements in about 79 per cent area of the state.</li>
<li>Out of 138 blocks, 109 are “over-exploited”, two are “critical” five are “semi-critical” and only 22 blocks are in “safe” category.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Punjab expects a new tribunal</h4>
<ul>
<li>The state wants a tribunal seeking a fresh time-bound assessment of the water availability.</li>
<li>The state has been saying that till date there has been no adjudication or scientific assessment of Punjab river waters.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this PYQ:</strong></h4>
<p> </p>
<p><strong> Which one of the following pairs is not correctly matched? (CSP 2017)</strong></p>
<p>Dam/Lake River</p>
<p>(a) Govind Sagar: Satluj</p>
<p>(b) Kolleru Lake: Krishna</p>
<p>(c) Ukai Reservoir: Tapi</p>
<p>(d) Wular Lake: Jhelum</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sutlej-yamuna-link-syl-canal-ias/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SC asks Centre, States to allay EWS Quota concerns</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-asks-centre-states-ews-quota-concerns/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>EWS Quota , 103rd Amendment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632163" height="385" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 426px) 100vw, 426px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ews-300x271.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ews-300x271.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ews.jpg 481w" width="426"/></p>
<p>A five-judge Constitution Bench led by CJI U.U. Lalit are hearing petitions challenging the 10% quota for the economically weaker sections (EWS) and an Andhra Pradesh law that grants reservation to Muslims.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The five-judge Bench, led by CJI, is considering the validity of the 103rd Constitutional Amendment.</li>
<li>The said amendment provides the 10% reservation to economically weaker sections (EWS) of society in government jobs and educational institutions.</li>
<li>Economic reservation was introduced by amending Articles 15 and 16 and adding clauses empowering the State governments to provide reservation on the basis of economic backwardness.</li>
</ul>
<h4>EWS Quota: A backgrounder</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 10% reservation was introduced through the 103rd Constitution Amendment and enforced in January 2019.</li>
<li>It added Clause (6) to Article 15 to empower the Government to introduce special provisions for the EWS among citizens except those in the classes that already enjoy reservation.</li>
<li>It allows reservation in educational institutions, both public and private, whether aided or unaided, excluding those run by minority institutions, up to a maximum of 10%.</li>
<li>It also added Clause (6) to Article 16 to facilitate reservation in employment.</li>
<li>The new clauses make it clear that the EWS reservation will be in addition to the existing reservation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of the quota</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Constitution initially allowed special provisions only for the socially and educationally backward classes.</li>
<li>The Government introduced the concept of EWS for a new class of affirmative action program for those not covered by or eligible for the community-based quotas.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the court’s questions about the criteria?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reduction within general category:</strong> The EWS quota remains a controversy as its critics say it reduces the size of the open category, besides breaching the 50% limit on the total reservation.</li>
<li><strong>Arbitrariness over income limit:</strong> The court has been intrigued by the income limit being fixed at ₹8 lakh per year. It is the same figure for excluding the ‘creamy layer’ from OBC reservation benefits.</li>
<li><strong>Socio-economic backwardness:</strong> A crucial difference is that those in the general category, to whom the EWS quota is applicable, do not suffer from social or educational backwardness, unlike those classified as the OBC.</li>
<li><strong>Metropolitan criteria:</strong> There are other questions as to whether any exercise was undertaken to derive the exceptions such as why the flat criterion does not differentiate between metropolitan and non-metropolitan areas.</li>
<li><strong>OBC like criteria:</strong> The question the court has raised is that when the OBC category is socially and educationally backward and, therefore, has additional impediments to overcome.</li>
<li><strong>Not based on relevant data:</strong> In line with the Supreme Court’s known position that any reservation or norms for exclusion should be based on relevant data.</li>
<li><strong>Breaches reservation cap:</strong> There is a cap of 50% on reservation as ruled in the Indira Sawhney Case. The principle of balancing equality ordains reservation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the current status of the EWS quota?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The reservation for the EWS is being implemented by the Union Government for the second year now.</li>
<li>Recruitment test results show that the category has a lower cut-off mark than the OBC, a point that has upset the traditional beneficiaries of reservation based on caste.</li>
<li>The explanation is that only a small number of people are currently applying under the EWS category — one has to get an income certificate from the revenue authorities — and therefore the cut-off is low.</li>
<li>However, when the number picks up over time, the cut-off marks are expected to rise.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Practical issues with EWS Quota</h4>
<p>The EWS quota will come in for judicial scrutiny soon. But it’s not only a matter for the judiciary, India’s Parliament should revisit the law too.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hasty legislation:</strong> This law was passed in haste. It was passed in both the houses within 48 hours, and got presidential approval the next day.</li>
<li><strong>Minority appeasement:</strong> It is widely argued that the law was passed to appease a certain section of upper-caste society and to suppress the demands for minority reservations.</li>
<li><strong>Morality put to question: </strong>Imagine! A constitutional amendment has been made with few hours of deliberation and without consultation of the targeted group. This is certainly against constitutional morality and propriety.</li>
<li><strong>Substantial backing is missing:</strong> This amendment is based on a wrong or unverified premise. This is at best a wild guess or a supposition because the government has not produced any data to back this point.</li>
<li><strong>Under-reservation of Backward Classes:</strong> The assertion is based on the fact that we have different data to prove the under-representation of SC, ST, OBCs. That implies that ‘upper’ castes are over-represented (with 100 minus reservation).</li>
<li><strong>Rationale of 10%:</strong> There is one more problem in this regard. The SC and ST quota is based on their total population. But the rationale for the 10 per cent quota was never discussed.</li>
<li><strong>Principle of Equality:</strong> Economic backwardness is quite a fluid identity. It has nothing to do with historic wrongdoings and liabilities caused to the Backward Classes.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Preserving the merit: </strong>We cannot rule out the sorry state of economic backwardness hampering merit in our country.</li>
<li><strong>Rational critera: </strong>There has to be collective wisdom to define and measure the economic weakness of certain sections of the society in order to shape the concept of economic justice.</li>
<li><strong>Judicial guidance: </strong>Judicial interpretation will pave the wave forward for deciding the criterion for EWS Quota.</li>
<li><strong>Targetted beneficiaries. </strong>The centre needs to resort to more rational criteria for deciding the targeted beneficiary of this reservation system. Caste Census data can be useful in this regard.</li>
<li><strong>Income study: </strong>The per capita income or GDP or the difference in purchasing power in the rural and urban areas, should be taken into account while a single income limit was formulated for the whole country.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Reservation is a constitutional scheme to ensure the participation of backward classes shoulder to shoulder with all citizens in the nation-building process.</li>
<li>The EWS quota with above discussed ambiguities is the subversion of the constitutional scheme for reservation.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-asks-centre-states-ews-quota-concerns/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the idea of Climate Reparation?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-idea-of-climate-reparation/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Climate reparation</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632165" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 100vw, 542px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-1024x684.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-768x513.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-1536x1025.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-1200x801.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-1980x1322.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation.jpg 2000w" width="542"/></p>
<p>Facing the worst <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-urban-deluge-floods/">flooding disaster</a> in its history, <strong><u>Pakistan has begun demanding reparations</u></strong>, or compensation, from the rich countries that are mainly responsible for causing climate change.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>On the face of it, Pakistan’s demand for reparations appears to be a long shot, but the principles being invoked are fairly <strong><u>well-established in environmental jurisprudence</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In fact, <strong><u>Pakistan is not alone</u></strong> in making this demand.</li>
<li>Almost the entire developing world has for years been insisting on setting up an <strong><u>international mechanism for financial reparation</u></strong> for loss and damage caused by climate disasters.</li>
<li>The issue has <strong><u>come up repeatedly at international negotiations</u></strong> for climate change, and on other platforms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Climate Reparation?</h4>
<ul>
<li>At its heart, the demand for compensation for loss and damage from climate disasters is an extension of the universally acknowledged <strong><u>“Polluter Pays” principle</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This makes the polluter liable for paying not just for the cost of remedial action, but also for <strong><u>compensating the victims of environmental damage caused by their actions.</u></strong></li>
<li>Climate justice is based on the <strong><u>notion of not being punished for someone else’s bad behaviour</u></strong>, but it does not sanction additional bad behaviour.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who are responsible for climate change?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the climate change framework, the burden of <strong><u>responsibility falls on those rich countries that have contributed most of the greenhouse gas emissions since 1850</u></strong>, generally considered to be the beginning of the industrial age.</li>
<li>The United States and the European Union, including the UK, account for over 50% of all emissions during this time.</li>
<li>If Russia, Canada, Japan, and Australia too are included, the combined contribution goes past 65%, or almost two-thirds of all emissions.</li>
<li>Historical responsibility is important because carbon dioxide remains in the atmosphere for hundreds of years, and it is the <strong><u>cumulative accumulation of carbon dioxide</u></strong> that causes global warming.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What about developing countries?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A country like India, currently the third largest emitter, <strong>accounts for only 3% of historical emissions</strong>.</li>
<li>China, which is the world’s biggest emitter for over 15 years now, has contributed about <strong><u>11% to total emissions since 1850.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>Why need climate reparations?</h4>
<ul>
<li>While the <strong><u>impact of climate change</u></strong> is global, it is much more <strong><u>severe on the poorer nations</u></strong> because of their geographical locations and weaker capacity to cope.</li>
<li>Countries that have had negligible contributions to historical emissions and <strong><u>have severe limitations of resources</u></strong> are the ones that face the most devastating impacts of climate change.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Institutional mechanism for Climate Reparations</h4>
<h4>(1) United Nations</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>UN Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC)</u></strong>, the 1994 international agreement that lays down the broad principles of the global effort to fight climate change.</li>
<li>It explicitly acknowledges this <strong><u>differentiated responsibility of nations</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It makes it very clear that <strong><u>rich countries must provide both the finance and the technology to the developing nations</u></strong> to help them tackle climate change.</li>
<li>It is this mandate that later evolved into the <strong><u>$100 billion amount that the rich countries agreed to provide</u></strong> every year to the developing world.</li>
<li>While this promise is <strong><u>yet to be met</u></strong>, this $100 billion per year amount is not meant for loss and damage.</li>
<li>Climate disasters were not a regular occurrence in 1994, and as such the <strong><u>UNFCCC does not make a mention of loss and damage. </u></strong></li>
<li>This particular demand emerged much later, and faced <strong><u>stiff resistance from the developed nations</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(2) Warsaw International Mechanism (WIM)</h4>
<ul>
<li>The WIM for Loss and Damages, set up in 2013, was the <strong><u>first formal acknowledgment</u></strong> of the need to <strong><u>compensate developing countries struck by climate disasters</u></strong>.</li>
<li>However, the <strong><u>progress</u></strong> on this front has been painfully <strong><u>slow</u></strong>.</li>
<li><strong><u>No funding mechanism</u></strong>, or even a promise to provide funds, has come about.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Pushback from Developed Countries</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is not hard to understand why the developed countries are dead against compensation claims.</li>
<li>They are struggling to put together even the $100 billion per year flow that they had <strong><u>reluctantly agreed to provide.</u></strong></li>
<li>Further, loss and damage claims can easily spiral into billions of dollars, or even more.</li>
<li>The report said that the United States alone is estimated to have “inflicted more than $1.9 trillion in damages to other countries” due to its emissions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with loss assessment</h4>
<ul>
<li>There are practical difficulties in estimating <strong><u>how much a country has actually suffered</u></strong> due to the actions of others.</li>
<li>To begin with, it has to be established that the <strong><u>disaster was caused by climate change</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Then there are <strong><u>non-economic losses</u></strong> as well, including <strong><u>loss of lives</u></strong>, <strong><u>displacement</u></strong> and <strong><u>migration</u></strong>, <strong><u>health impacts</u></strong>, and <strong><u>damage to cultural heritage</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Then there is this other step about assessing how much of the losses are due to the event itself, and <strong><u>what could be attributed to misgovernance</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>A lot of background work is going on to create the framework in which it would be possible to quantify the compensation due to an affected country.</li>
<li>What Pakistan has done, through its demands for reparations, is to call attention to this often neglected aspect.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-idea-of-climate-reparation/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Effecting the Ban on Single-Use Plastics</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/effecting-the-ban-on-single-use-plastics/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Single use plastics</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Need for plastic waste management</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-629408" height="234" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 355px) 100vw, 355px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-300x198.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-300x198.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1024x675.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-768x506.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1536x1013.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1200x791.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1980x1306.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban.jpg 2000w" width="355"/></p>
<p>Since July 1, 2022, India has banned the manufacture, import, stocking, distribution, sale, and use of single-use plastics (SUP) items with low utility and high littering potential.</p>
<h4>What are single-use plastics?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Single-use plastics, often also referred to as <strong><u>disposable plastics</u></strong>, are commonly used for plastic packaging and include items intended to be <strong><u>used only once</u></strong> before they are thrown away or recycled.</li>
<li>These include, among other items, grocery bags, food packaging, bottles, straws, containers, cups and cutlery.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why are single-use plastics harmful?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The purpose of single-use plastics is to use them once or for a short period of time before disposing of them. Plastic waste has drastic impacts on the environment and human health.</li>
<li>There is a greater likelihood of single-use plastic products <strong><u>ending up in the sea</u></strong> than reusable ones.</li>
</ul>
<h4>SUP ban in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has taken resolute steps to mitigate pollution caused by littered single-use plastics.</li>
<li>A number of items are banned, including earbuds with plastic sticks, balloon sticks, plastic flags, candy sticks, ice cream sticks, polystyrene (thermocol) for decorations, plates, cups, glasses, cutlery such as forks, spoons, knives, straws etc.</li>
<li>India has also banned plastic or PVC banners less than 100 micron, stirrers, etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the impact on the environment?</h4>
<p><strong>[A] Solid Waste generation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The disposal of plastics is one of the least recognized and most highly problematic areas of plastic’s ecological impact.</li>
<li>Ironically, one of plastic’s most desirable traits: its <strong>durability and resistance to decomposition</strong>, is also the source of one of its greatest liabilities when it comes to the disposal of plastics.</li>
<li>A very small amount of total plastic production (less than 10%) is effectively recycled; the remaining plastic is sent to landfills.</li>
<li>It is destined to remain entombed.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>[B] Ecological Impact</strong></p>
<p><strong>(i) Groundwater and soil pollution</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Plastic is a material made to last forever, and due to the same chemical composition, plastic cannot biodegrade; it breaks down into smaller and smaller pieces.</li>
<li>When buried in a landfill, plastic lies untreated for years.</li>
<li>In the process, toxic chemicals from plastics drain out and seep into groundwater, flowing downstream into lakes and rivers.</li>
<li>The seeping of plastic also causes soil pollution and have now started resulting in presence of micro plastics in soil.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(ii) Water Pollution</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The increased presence of plastic on the ocean surface has resulted in more serious problems.</li>
<li>Since most of the plastic debris that reaches the ocean remains floating for years as it does not decompose quickly, it leads to the dropping of oxygen level in the water.</li>
<li>It has severely affected the survival of marine species.</li>
<li>When oceanic creatures and even birds consume plastic inadvertently, they choke on it which causes a steady decline in their population.</li>
<li>In addition to suffocation, ingestion, and other macro-particulate causes of death in larger birds, fish, and mammals.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>[C] Health Hazards</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Burning of plastic results into formation of a class of flame retardants called as Halogens.</li>
<li>Collectively, these harmful chemicals are known to cause the following severe health problems: cancer, neurological damage, endocrine disruption, birth defects and child developmental disorders etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Ban elsewhere</h4>
<ul>
<li>India is not the first country to ban single-use plastics.</li>
<li>Bangladesh became the first country to ban thin plastic bags in 2002; New Zealand banned plastic bags in July 2019.</li>
<li>China had issued a ban on plastic bags in 2020 with a phased implementation.</li>
<li>As of July 2019, 68 countries have plastic bag bans with varying degrees of enforcement.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the plastic waste management rules in India?</h4>
<ul>
<li>With effect from September 30, 2021 India has the Plastic Waste Management Amendment Rules, 2021.</li>
<li>It prohibited the manufacture, import, stocking, distribution, sale, and use of plastic carry bags whose thickness is less than 75 microns.</li>
<li>From December 31, 2022, plastic carry bags whose thickness is less than 120 microns will be banned.</li>
<li>It means that the ban does not cover all plastic bags; however, it requires the manufacturers to produce plastic bags thicker than 75 microns which was earlier 50 microns.</li>
<li>As per the notification, the standard shall be increased to 120 microns in December this year.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the role of the manufacturer?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In addition, the Ministry of Environment, Forests, and Climate Change notified the Plastic Waste Management Amendment Rules, 2022 on February 16, 2022.</li>
<li>Extended Producer Responsibility (EPR) is the responsibility of a producer for the environmentally sound management of the product until the end of its life.</li>
<li>The guidelines provide a framework to strengthen the circular economy of plastic packaging waste, promote the development of new alternatives to plastic packaging and provide the next steps for moving towards sustainable plastic packaging by businesses.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Various steps taken</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian government has taken steps to promote innovation and create an ecosystem for accelerated adoption and availability of alternatives across the country.</li>
<li>To ensure the effective enforcement of the ban, national and State-level control rooms will be established, as well as special enforcement teams for the purpose of checking the illegal sale and use of single-use plastics.</li>
<li>To prevent the movement of banned single-use plastic items between States and Union Territories, border checkpoints have been established.</li>
<li>In an effort to empower citizens to help curb the plastic menace, the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB) has launched a grievance redressal application.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the challenges?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ban will succeed only if all stakeholders participate enthusiastically and engage in effective engagement and concerted actions.</li>
<li>However, if we look back at our past, almost 25 Indian States previously banned plastic at the state level.</li>
<li>However, these bans had a very limited impact in reality because of the widespread use of these items.</li>
<li>Now the challenge is to see how the local level authorities will enforce the ban in accordance with the guidelines.</li>
<li>Banned items such as earbuds with plastic sticks, plastic sticks for balloons, etc., are non-branded items and it is difficult to find out who the manufacturer is and who is accountable.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>The consumer needs to be informed about the ban through advertisements, newspaper or TV commercials, or on social media.</li>
<li>In order to find sustainable alternatives, companies need to invest in research and development.</li>
<li>The solution to the plastic pollution problem is not the responsibility of the government alone, but of industries, brands, manufacturers and most importantly consumers.</li>
<li>Finding alternatives to plastic seems a little difficult, however, greener alternatives to plastic may be considered a sustainable option.</li>
<li>For example, compostable and bio-degradable plastic, etc., may be considered as an option.</li>
<li>While the total ban on the use of plastic sounds a great idea, its feasibility seems difficult at this hour, especially in the absence of workable alternatives.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/effecting-the-ban-on-single-use-plastics/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Fruit Fly: Novel method to study Nuclear Matrix</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nuclear Matrix</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627770" height="489" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 566px) 100vw, 566px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly.jpg 665w" width="566"/></p>
<p>Now, using a novel method, Indian researchers have established a way of studying the nuclear matrix of the fruit fly (Drosophila melanogaster) without removing the nucleus from the embryo.</p>
<h4>Nuclear Matrix of fruit flies</h4>
<ul>
<li>Every cell that makes up an organism contains a copy of its genome.</li>
<li>This genome is packaged in special ways with the help of a structure known as the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>The nuclear matrix gives an organisation and architecture to the nucleus.</li>
<li>A familiar figure, the nuclear matrix of fruit flies, for instance, has been studied for many years, mainly by isolating it in nuclei that have been taken out from fruit fly embryos.</li>
<li>This allows comparative study of nuclear matrix in different cells within the embryo, giving a boost for fruit fly genetics.</li>
<li>Two of the most recent papers on this work have been published in the journals Nucleus and Molecular and Cell Proteomics.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What exactly is Nuclear Matrix?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The nuclear matrix is like a scaffolding.</li>
<li>Using biochemical means, if the nucleus is taken out and treated with an enzyme that digests all the DNA.</li>
<li>It is then washed with a solution of high salt concentration so that viable DNA proteins or protein-protein interactions are removed.</li>
<li>What is then left is a fibrous meshwork of proteins called the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>This is like a building from which all movables have been sucked out, leaving only the beams, ceiling, and walls, plug points, etc.</li>
<li>Analogous to the building, the nuclear matrix creates the architecture in which the genome is packaged.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why study them?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Studying the nuclear matrix is, therefore, very important to get a better picture of how precisely development progresses every time a new individual is born.</li>
<li>We have 220 different types of cells in the body, but all contain identical genomes.</li>
<li>The same genome sequence is present in neurons, where it works for thinking; in the liver, the same sequence enacts metabolism; and in the intestine, it works to digest.</li>
<li>So, this information is packaged differently in different cell types.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Revisiting the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-627767" height="188" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-768x481.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji.jpg 885w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has referred to a three-judge Bench a series of petitions seeking a judicial direction that political parties who make wild promises should also reveal in their poll manifestos where they will get the money to pay for them.</p>
<p>The reference is a shift from the court’s own stand in the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs Tamil Nadu judgment of 2013.</p>
<h4>Hefty promises: A no lesser corrupt practice</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the <strong><u>Balaji case judgment</u></strong>, a Division Bench of the Supreme Court had held that making promises in election manifestos <strong><u>do not amount to a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> under Section 123 of the Representation of People Act (RP).</li>
<li>However, the Supreme Court is now worried that <strong><u>freebies promised</u></strong> by political parties to win elections could <strong><u>bleed the public exchequer dry</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Court said that parties who form the government riding the wave created by their pre-poll promises of free gifts are bleeding the State finances dry.</li>
<li>Parties actually try to <strong><u>fulfil their outlandish promises using public money</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Supreme Court has therefore decided to revisit the Balaji verdict.</p>
<h4>What triggered the Balaji case?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The course of events started in 2006, during the run-up to the Tamil Nadu Assembly elections.</li>
<li>A party released its election manifesto announcing a scheme of free distribution of colour television sets (CTVs) to each and every household if voted to power.</li>
<li>The party swept to power in the polls and decided to implement its scheme and portioned off ₹750 crore from the budget for the project.</li>
<li>The government finally distributed 30,000 TV sets across the State.</li>
<li>In 2011, the rival party also announced its election manifesto with free gifts to “equalise” the gifts offered.</li>
<li>It promised grinders, mixies, electric fans, laptop computers, four gram gold thalis, a cheque of ₹50,000 for women’s marriage, green houses, 20 kg of rice to ration card holders and free cattle and sheep.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Balaji case</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji, a resident of Tamil Nadu, challenged the schemes introduced by the parties in the Madras High Court.</li>
<li>He said that the <strong><u>expenditure was incurred by the State from the exchequer</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This was “<strong><u>unauthorised, impermissible and ultra vires the constitutional mandates</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>High Court dismissed his case</u></strong>, following which he had moved the apex court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did the case play out?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji argued that <strong><u>the State cannot act</u></strong> in furtherance of “<strong><u>eccentric principles of socialistic philanthropy</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>He argued that the promises of <strong><u>free distribution of non-essential commodities</u></strong> in an election manifesto amounts to electoral bribe under Section 123 of the RP Act.</li>
<li>Money can be taken out of the Consolidated Fund of the State <strong><u>only for “public purposes”</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>distribution of goods to certain sections</u></strong> of people was <strong><u>violative of Article 14 of the Constitution</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Argument provided against the Balaji Case</h4>
<ul>
<li>In response, the State of Tamil Nadu countered that <strong><u>promises do not constitute corrupt practice. </u></strong></li>
<li>Political parties are not the State and ‘<strong><u>freebies’ is a nebulous term which has no legal status</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises implemented by the party after forming the government is an <strong><u>obligation under the Directives Principles of State Policy</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The State is only doing its duty to promote the <strong><u>welfare of its people</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises are <strong><u>implemented by framing various schemes/guidelines/eligibility</u></strong> criteria etc. as well as <strong><u>with the approval of the legislature. </u></strong></li>
<li>Thus, it <strong><u>cannot be construed as a waste of public money</u></strong> or be prohibited by any statute or scheme.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Outcome of the Judgement</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court’s judgment held that <strong><u>promises by a political party cannot constitute a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> on its part.</li>
<li>It would be <strong><u>“misleading” to generalize</u></strong> that all promises in the election manifesto would amount to corrupt practice.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>manifesto is a statement of the policy</u></strong> for a political party.</li>
<li>The question of implementing the manifesto arises only if the political party forms a government.</li>
<li>It is the promise of a future government and not of an individual candidate.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Scope for revisiting the judgment</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court agreed that <strong><u>freebies create an “uneven playing field”.</u></strong></li>
<li>It had asked the Election Commission of India to <strong><u>consult political parties</u></strong> and issue guidelines on the election manifesto and make it a <strong><u>part of the Model Code of Conduct</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the Court’s move to review the Balaji judgment significant?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In its order, the court foresees that “freebies may create a situation wherein the <strong><u>State governments cannot provide basic amenities due to lack of funds</u></strong> and the State is pushed towards imminent bankruptcy”.</li>
<li>The court said it wants a <strong><u>transparent debate</u></strong> before the three-judge Bench on whether an “enforceable” judicial order can stop political parties from promising and distributing ‘irrational freebies’.</li>
<li>The case is unique as the Supreme Court is exploring <strong><u>whether judicial parameters can be set on a purely political act of promising freebies.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>