<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2022 19:08:39 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Centre adds 4 new tribes to Scheduled Tribes (ST) List</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/new-tribes-to-scheduled-tribes-list/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Tribes in news</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Union Cabinet under the chairmanship of PM has approved the addition of four tribes to the list of Scheduled Tribes (ST), including those from Himachal Pradesh, Tamil Nadu and Chhattisgarh.</p>
<h4>Which tribes are we talking about?</h4>
<ol>
<li><strong><u>Hatti </u></strong>tribe in the Trans-Giri area of Sirmour district in Himachal Pradesh</li>
<li><strong><u>Narikoravan</u></strong> and <strong><u>Kurivikkaran</u></strong> hill tribes of Tamil Nadu and</li>
<li><strong><u>Binjhia</u></strong> tribe in Chhattisgarh, which was listed as ST in Jharkhand and Odisha but not in Chhattisgarh</li>
</ol>
<h4>Other tribes in news</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Cabinet also approved ‘<span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Betta-Kuruba</strong></span>’ as a synonym for the Kadu Kuruba tribe In Karnataka.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who are the Scheduled Tribes?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The term ‘<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/what-is-the-reason-for-special-provisions-for-the-scheduled-tribes-in-the-constitution-of-india-are-these-provisions-successful-in-ameliorating-their-conditions-250-words/">Scheduled Tribes’</a> first appeared in the Constitution of India.</li>
<li><strong><u>Article 366 (25)</u></strong> defined scheduled tribes as “such tribes or tribal communities or parts of or groups within such tribes or tribal communities as are deemed under Article 342 to be Scheduled Tribes for the purposes of this constitution”.</li>
<li><strong><u>Article 342</u></strong> prescribes procedure to be followed in the matter of specification of scheduled tribes.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Among the tribal groups, several have adapted to modern life but there are tribal groups who are more vulnerable.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Dhebar Commission (1973)</u></strong> created a separate category “Primitive Tribal Groups (PTGs)” which was renamed in 2006 as “<strong><u>Particularly Vulnerable Tribal Groups (PVTGs</u></strong>)”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How are STs notified?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The first specification of Scheduled Tribes in relation to a particular State/ Union Territory is by a notified order of the President, after consultation with the State governments concerned.</li>
<li>These orders can be modified subsequently only through an Act of Parliament.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Status of STs in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Census 2011 has revealed that there are said to be 705 ethnic groups notified as Scheduled Tribes (STs).</li>
<li>Over 10 crore Indians are notified as STs, of which 1.04 crore live in urban areas.</li>
<li>The STs constitute 8.6% of the population and 11.3% of the rural population.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="uvIVi0e0Qc"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/what-is-the-reason-for-special-provisions-for-the-scheduled-tribes-in-the-constitution-of-india-are-these-provisions-successful-in-ameliorating-their-conditions-250-words/">What is the reason for special provisions for the Scheduled Tribes in the constitution of India? Are these provisions successful in ameliorating their conditions? (250 Words)</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="uvIVi0e0Qc" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/what-is-the-reason-for-special-provisions-for-the-scheduled-tribes-in-the-constitution-of-india-are-these-provisions-successful-in-ameliorating-their-conditions-250-words/embed/#?secret=Y52cNVyCdp#?secret=uvIVi0e0Qc" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“What is the reason for special provisions for the Scheduled Tribes in the constitution of India? Are these provisions successful in ameliorating their conditions? (250 Words)” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/new-tribes-to-scheduled-tribes-list/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How the National Logistics Policy will speed up lumbering freight sector?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/how-the-national-logistics-policy-will-speed-up-lumbering-freight-sector/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NLP</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="logistics" class="alignnone wp-image-636221" height="263" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logistics-300x148.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logistics-300x148.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logistics.jpg 684w" width="533"/></strong></p>
<p>The government will announce the National Logistics Policy (NLP) this week, aiming to bring down logistics costs and address challenges plaguing importers and exporters.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Logistics? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Logistics refers to the overall process of managing <strong><u>how resources are acquired, stored, and transported</u></strong> to their final destination.</li>
<li>It involves identifying prospective distributors and suppliers and determining their effectiveness and accessibility.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need a logistics policy?</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="logistics" class="alignnone wp-image-636220" height="273" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 438px) 100vw, 438px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist-300x187.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist-300x187.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist-768x479.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist.jpg 827w" width="438"/></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Organizing and consolidating the sector:</strong> India’s logistics sector is largely unorganized and fragmented.</li>
<li><strong>Reducing logistics cost:</strong> This is why the country’s logistics costs are as high as 14-15% of the GDP, against 7-8% in developed nations such as the Singapore and the US, who leverage it to boost exports. The NLP aims to bring down India’s logistics cost to 8% in the next five years.</li>
<li><strong>Preventing waste of perishable items:</strong> As per some estimates in India, about 16% of agri-production is wasted at different stages of the supply chain.</li>
<li><strong>Warehousing development:</strong> Moreover, due to factors such as limited capacity and availability of warehouses, the cost of transaction increases.</li>
<li><strong>Multi-modal integration:</strong> The new policy is going about simplification, technology and will have a multimodal approach that will combine rail, water, and air — all modes of transport.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What role will technology play?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Advanced analytics:</strong> The NLP will aim to harness technologies such as AI and blockchain. It aims to create a data analytics centre for driving greater transparency and continuous monitoring of key logistics metrics.</li>
<li><strong>Single window portal:</strong> Under NLP, a portal will be created, where service providers such as warehousing providers, shipping experts, transporters, customs brokers, and various governmental agencies will be unified.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Will it boost cooperation between ministries?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Unifying multiple departments:</strong> Currently, the logistics value chain is managed by several ministries—road transport and highways, shipping, railways, and civil aviation.</li>
<li><strong>Single-point clearances:</strong> Agencies like the Central Drug Standard Control Organization and the Food Safety and Standard Authority of India provide clearances.</li>
<li><strong>Nationwide integration:</strong> The NLP could enhance their integration at the central level.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What about reducing the carbon footprint?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Energy-efficient transportation:</strong> The draft logistics policy lays emphasis on the shift to more energy-efficient means of transportation, as well as the use of greener fuels which could reduce the supply chain’s carbon footprint.</li>
<li><strong>Vehicular emission reduction:</strong> Moreover, the draft policy, released earlier, emphasized creating regulations for controlling vehicular noise, emissions, and wastage.</li>
<li><strong>Green warehousing principles:</strong> The new logistics policy also aims to incorporate green principles in the functioning of warehouses which contribute to nearly 10% of the logistics costs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Will it change India’s commodity transport?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Transport of crucial commodities:</strong> The proposed policy aims to focus on the transport of crucial commodities such as coal, steel, iron ore, food grains, steel, cement, fruits and vegetables.</li>
<li><strong>Creating nationwide clusters:</strong> The current logistical network for transporting them is mainly confined to regional clusters.</li>
<li><strong>Integrating national supply-chains:</strong> The NLP could help establish a link between the place of origin, and destination place and integrate the supply on a national level.</li>
<li><strong>Optimum logistics identification:</strong> The draft also proposes identification of the right mode of transport for each of these commodities to minimise losses during transport.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/how-the-national-logistics-policy-will-speed-up-lumbering-freight-sector/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Hindi not a competitor of regional languages: Home Minister</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hindi-not-a-competitor-regional-languages/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>National language debate</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-636219" height="223" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 426px) 100vw, 426px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hindi-300x157.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hindi-300x157.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hindi.jpg 500w" width="426"/></strong></p>
<p>Union Home Minister has appealed to guardians to speak to children in their mother tongue to enable them to learn Hindi without much effort, on the Hindi Divas.</p>
<h4>What did HM say on Hindi?</h4>
<ul>
<li>He said it was time that <strong><u>inferiority complex around Indian languages</u></strong>, instilled by the British, was overthrown from people’s conscience with the help of regional languages and Hindi.</li>
<li>He also said that <strong><u>Hindi was not a competitor but a “friend” of all the other regional languages</u></strong> in the country and they were mutually dependent on each other for their growth.</li>
<li>He said there was a concerted <strong><u>disinformation campaign to pit Hindi against other languages</u></strong> such as Marathi and Tamil, and underlined the need to strengthen local languages with Hindi.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Debate over Hindi</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Between September 12 and 14, 1949, that the Constituent Assembly debated the status of India’s languages.</li>
<li>Among the issues that were discussed were the use of the term ‘<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-national-language-debate/">national language’</a> instead of ‘official’ language.</li>
<li>Hindi author Seth Govind Das, who represented the Central Provinces and Berar, argued for ‘one language and one script’ and suggested that Hindi should replace English at the earliest.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the status of Hindi?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Finally, the Constituent Assembly adopted what was known as “<strong><u>Munshi-Ayyangar Formula</u></strong>.”</li>
<li>According to this, Hindi in the Devnagari script would be the official language of the Union.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Official, not national</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>English would continue to be used for all official purposes for the next 15 years, to enable a smooth transition for non-Hindi speaking states.</li>
<li>The deadline was 26 January 1965.</li>
<li>Under Article 343 of the Constitution, the official language of the Union shall be Hindi in Devanagari script.</li>
<li>The international form of Indian numerals will be used for official purposes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why has language become a sensitive issue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Self-identification:</strong> A strong identification with one’s regional language and an underlying fear of homogenisation is at the heart of the national language question in India. An individual conceptualises and communicates his thoughts in a language, enabling him to be an active part of society.</li>
<li><strong>Language defines primary group:</strong> People identify with one another based on language, thus giving them a primary group. A nation is the largest primary group that once can address.</li>
<li><strong>Learning abilities at stake:</strong> The dangers of imposing a language are manifold. It can affect the learning ability of non-native speakers thereby affecting their self-confidence.</li>
<li><strong>Threats to endangered languages:</strong> It can also endanger other languages and dialects and reduce diversity.</li>
<li><strong>Threats to diversity:</strong> National integration cannot come at the cost of people’s linguistic identities. Language is integral to culture and therefore privileging Hindi over all other languages spoken in India takes away from its diversity.</li>
<li><strong>Promises made by Constituent Assembly:</strong> Then PM Pt. Nehru had promised that Hindi would only serve as a linking language and it would not be imposed on non-Hindi speaking states as long as they were against it.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Benefits of having a national language</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Wide range of speakers:</strong> Hindi is still the most widely spoken language in the country with an estimated 258 million people declaring that Hindi is their native language and millions more comfortable with Hindi.</li>
<li><strong>Language as a unifying language:</strong> A complete usage of Hindi language whilst respecting the various native languages would also ensure better coordination and cooperation among all the states and act as a strong unifying factor and eliminate all regional differences.</li>
<li><strong>Reputation at international fora:</strong> When countries like Germany, Japan, France, Italy etc. use their respective language as a medium of communication even during International forums not only has the reputation of those countries have greatly enhanced but also those languages have gained a huge reputation worldwide.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues with Hindi</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inherent opposition to Hindi:</strong> The Constituent Assembly was bitterly divided on the question, with members from States that did not speak Hindi initially opposing the declaration of Hindi as a national language.</li>
<li><strong>Fear of imposition:</strong> Opponents were against English being done away with, fearing that it may lead to Hindi domination in regions that did not speak the language.</li>
<li><strong>Symbol of identity politics:</strong> The approach towards linguistic policy seems to be driven more by the politics of identity than values of aspiration or accommodation.</li>
<li><strong>Favour for majoritarianism:</strong> The primary argument in favour of Hindi has been reduced to assertions of slim majoritarianism.</li>
<li><strong>Few speakers, still dominant:</strong> Even then, there are concerns about the claim based on mere numerical strength, as only 25 per cent of Indians seem to recognise Hindi as their mother tongue (Census 2011).</li>
<li><strong>Demographic barriers:</strong> Today nearly 35% of people are migrating daily for work. In such a situation, we have to conceptualise a new form of language identity for our states.</li>
<li><strong>Economic barriers:</strong> Any idea of one link language, whether Hindi or English, will be economically disastrous for India. It will slow down migration and reduce the ease of capital flow.</li>
<li><strong>Multiple dialects:</strong> Only five states in India have Hindi as their’ native language’. However, in those states, too, the dialects of Hindi are associated with locals and their communities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why Hindi cannot be the national language?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multiple dialects:</strong> Hindi has largely been influenced by Persian — and then English, among other languages. Also, when the languages were enumerated, Hindi subsumed Bhojpuri, which is spoken by a little over five crore people.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inefficacy of Sanskrit:</strong> There were demands to make Sanskrit the official language, while some argued in favour of ‘Hindustani’.</li>
<li><strong>Issue over Script:</strong> There were differences of opinion over the script too. When opinion veered towards accepting Hindi, proponents of the language wanted the ‘Devanagari’ script to be adopted both for words and numerals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why this issue needs a rational consideration?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Linguistic chauvinism:</strong> Various policies on language have been framed both by the central and state governments that have been termed as forms of linguistic chauvinism.  Ex. Obsession for Marathi in Mumbai</li>
<li><strong>Secular fabric under threat:</strong> The states’ fear of the central government’s ideology of monopolising faith, education, and language will adversely affect the Indian political system, which is based on pluralism and accommodation.</li>
<li><strong>Monolingualism can prove disastrous: </strong>If there is a mechanical and monolithic idea of unity followed by any entity, such an entity generally generates great hostility beyond its immediate borders.  In neighbouring Bangladesh – then East Pakistan – the language movement against the imposition of Urdu on Bengali speakers was a key driver of Pakistan splitting into two nations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Language as a skill:</strong> Language should be looked at as an important skill to operate in a world which is more connected today than at any other point in time.</li>
<li><strong>Language not a cultural burden:</strong> A united nation has to have space for diversity. India is united in its diversity. Diversity is a great philosophical idea and should never be seen as a cultural burden.</li>
<li><strong>Linguistic heritage needs priority:</strong> This is not to contend that our linguistic heritage should be neglected or trivialised. Our metropolises must be recognized as multilingual entities.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hindi-not-a-competitor-regional-languages/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>FAME India is promising scheme because the future is electric</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fame/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>FAME India scheme</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>sustainable mobility</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="FAME" class="alignnone wp-image-636654" height="405" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 627px) 100vw, 627px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fame-scheme-300x194.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fame-scheme-300x194.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fame-scheme.jpg 620w" width="627"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Centralized procurement of 5,450 electric buses and subsequent increase in ambition to have 50,000 e-buses on the country’s roads by 2030 under FAME scheme.</li>
<li>With the shared aim to rapidly electrify a key pillar of India’s public transportation, recent governance efforts of Union and state governments have created a new business model for e-buses.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Status of State-owned buses</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Status</strong>: There are currently around 1,40,000 registered public buses on India’s roads.</li>
<li><strong>Condition</strong>: Large numbers of them having sputtering engines which emits planet-warming fumes into the atmosphere. At least 40,000 of these buses are at the end of their lifespan and must be taken off the roads</li>
<li><strong>Operators:</strong> Most buses are owned and operated by State transport undertakings, which are in poor financial health.</li>
<li><strong>Revenue loss:</strong> They incur large losses because of the subsidized fares to crores of Indians each day.</li>
<li><strong>Problem: </strong>problems of fragmented demand and high prices.</li>
<li><strong>Limitation:</strong> As State governments control issues such as transit, urban governance and pollution control so there’s a limitation for the nation-wide action on this issue.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="FAME" class="alignnone wp-image-636655" height="416" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 675px) 100vw, 675px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Godawari-E-mobility-EV-unit-300x185.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Godawari-E-mobility-EV-unit-300x185.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Godawari-E-mobility-EV-unit-768x474.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Godawari-E-mobility-EV-unit.jpg 1018w" width="675"/>What is FAME India scheme?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The National Electric Mobility Mission Plan (NEMMP) 2020</strong>: Is a National Mission document providing the vision and the roadmap for the faster adoption of electric vehicles and their manufacturing in the country.</li>
<li><strong>FAME</strong>: As part of the NEMMP 2020, Department of Heavy Industry formulated a Scheme viz. <strong>Faster Adoption and Manufacturing of (Hybrid &amp;) Electric Vehicles in India (FAME India)</strong> Scheme in the year 2015 to promote manufacturing of electric and hybrid vehicle technology and to ensure sustainable growth of the same.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-technical-analysis-of-fame-ii-scheme/"><strong>FAME Phase-II</strong>:</a> Government has approved Phase-II of FAME Scheme with an outlay of Rs. 10,000 Crore for a period of 3 years commencing from 1st April 2019.</li>
<li>Out of total budgetary support, about 86 percent of fund has been allocated for Demand Incentive so as to create demand for EVs in the country.</li>
<li>This phase aims to generate demand by way of supporting 7000 e-Buses, 5 lakh e-3 Wheelers, 55000 e-4 Wheeler Passenger Cars (including Strong Hybrid) and 10 lakh e-2 Wheelers. However, depending upon off-take of different category of EVs, these numbers may vary as the provision has been made for inter as well as intra segment wise f</li>
<li>Incentives: Only advanced battery and registered vehicles will be incentivized under the scheme.</li>
<li><strong>Coverage</strong>: With greater emphasis on providing affordable &amp; environment friendly public transportation options for the masses, scheme will be applicable mainly to vehicles used for public transport or those registered for commercial purposes in e-3W, e-4W and e-bus segments. However, privately owned registered e-2Ws are also covered under the scheme as a mass segment.<strong> </strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="FAME" class="alignnone wp-image-636656" height="452" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 603px) 100vw, 603px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/imgonline-com-ua-CompressToSize-CuDyNCv0Aqi9-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/imgonline-com-ua-CompressToSize-CuDyNCv0Aqi9-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/imgonline-com-ua-CompressToSize-CuDyNCv0Aqi9.jpg 640w" width="603"/>Obstacles in electric vehicle mobility </strong></p>
<p><strong>   EV Cost and Battery cost:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The cost is the most concerning point for an individual when it comes to buying an electric vehicle.</li>
<li>However, there are many incentives given off by central and state governments. But the common condition in all policies is that the incentives are only applicable for up to a certain number of vehicles only and after removing the discount and incentives the same EV which was looking lucrative to buy suddenly becomes unaffordable</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>   Beta version of vehicles:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Right now, both the technology and companies are new to the market and the products they are manufacturing are possibly facing real costumers for the first time.</li>
<li>It’s nearly impossible to make such a complex product like an automobile perfect for the customers in the first go, and as expected the buyers faced many issues. Vehicles like RV400, EPluto 7G, Nexon all them has to update their vehicle up to a very high extent after customer feedback and reviews.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>   Poor Infrastructure and range anxiety:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Poor infrastructure is among the most pressing issue among people thinking to opt for electric vehicles.</li>
<li>Poor infra doesn’t only include a lack of charging stations but also the lack of proper charging set up in their home.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> No Universal charger and Ecosystem (Lack of standardization):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Every second electric vehicle-making company has its own different charging port which is becoming a hurdle to setting up a proper charging ecosystem.</li>
<li>Also, many EV users complained about facing moral trouble for charging their vehicle in different EV-making Company’s charging stations which can impact the growth of the EV industry.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>   Temperature Issues:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Temperature can affect the performance of an EV battery at a large extent which makes EV’s inappropriate for too cold (Uttarakhand, Meghalaya) or too hot regions like (Rajasthan, Kerala). The battery can give its ideal performance when it’s in use under the temperature range of 15-40 degrees.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>   Environmental concerns:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The EV revolution is necessary for the most populated and polluted parts of India like Delhi, Mumbai, etc. but in such cities the major chunk of electricity is generated through burning fossil fuels which are equivalent to spreading the pollution through the ICE vehicle smoke, even most of the charging stations are reportedly operating upon diesel-driven electricity generator.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Way ahead </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>With anything new, there will always be challenges.</li>
<li>The EV industry is still in a nascent stage in India but developing at a rapid pace. Catching up to speed are the infrastructure requirements to support the EV demand.</li>
<li>Even with the current challenges, electric vehicles present huge potential to reduce our carbon footprints and provide a cost-effective system of transportation.</li>
<li>And one way to contribute towards this growth is to buy an electric vehicle.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you understand by FAME India scheme? How it will help tackling climate change? What are the obstacles in implementation of this scheme? </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fame/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Parliamentary Committees are not working properly</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/parliamentary-committees/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CCI</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>deliberation for effective democracy</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Parliamentary Committees" class="alignnone wp-image-636702" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 649px) 100vw, 649px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/parliament-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/parliament-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/parliament.jpg 759w" width="649"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the recent monsoon session of Parliament (July-August) the Competition (Amendment) Bill, 2022 and the Electricity (Amendment) Bill, 2022 sent to the Parliamentary Committees for detailed examination and a report thereon.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Parliament had only limited legislative time this session and could pass only five pieces of legislation</li>
<li><strong>Oppositions stand:</strong> opposition alleging that the Government has been trying to steamroll various pieces of legislation in the last few sessions.</li>
<li><strong>Governments stand:</strong> Government worries that so much time is lost in disruptions in Parliament that the legislative process, as it is, becomes unduly delayed and therefore, referring the bills to the Standing Committees.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Parliamentary Committees" class="alignnone wp-image-636703" height="415" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 623px) 100vw, 623px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/loks888-16599611063x2-1-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/loks888-16599611063x2-1-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/loks888-16599611063x2-1-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/loks888-16599611063x2-1-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/loks888-16599611063x2-1.jpeg 1200w" width="623"/>Parliamentary Committees</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Need of parliamentary committees</strong>: The functions of the Parliament are varied, complex and voluminous. Moreover, it has neither the adequate time nor necessary expertise to make a detailed scrutiny of all legislative measures.</li>
<li><strong>Function</strong>: To assist parliament to discharge of its duties.</li>
<li><strong>Mandate:</strong> To examine various legislations referred to it, the budget proposals of different Ministries, and also to do policy thinking on the vision, mission and future direction of the Ministries concerned.</li>
<li><strong>Composition</strong>: Members of the Parliament of both the LokSabha and the RajyaSabha in the ratio 2:1,</li>
<li><strong>Authority</strong>: constituted by the Speaker of the LokSabha and the Chairman of the RajyaSabha, jointly.</li>
<li><strong>Classification</strong>: Broadly, two kinds–Standing Committees and <em>Ad Hoc </em> Standing Committees are permanent (constituted every year or periodically) and work on a continuous basis, while<em> Ad Hoc </em>Committees are temporary and cease to exist on completion of the task assigned to them.</li>
<li><strong>Parliament has 24 Department Related Parliamentary Standing Committees (DRSC).</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Relevance of parliamentary committees </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Withdrawal of farm law bills shows that if bills are not discussed thoroughly, these laws are just bizarre pieces of legislation from point of view consumers and stakeholders.</li>
<li>Parliamentary committee’s discussions are held closed door. Members can express their opinion freely.</li>
<li>Members of DRSC always try reach to consensus despite political differences. Such practices are essential for healthy democracy.</li>
<li>To strengthen the relevance of parliamentarians the parliamentary committees are crucial tools.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Parliamentary Committees" class="alignnone wp-image-636704" height="402" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 619px) 100vw, 619px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tab1-300x195.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tab1-300x195.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/tab1.jpg 700w" width="619"/>How to improve Efficacy of committees?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Compulsory process: </strong>The Speaker of the Lok Sabha and the Chairman of the Rajya Sabha have powers to refer Bills to a DRSC of Parliament. Making the process of reference of Bills to these committees compulsory/an automatic process will be useful. An exemption could be made with the specific approval of the Speaker/ Chairman after detailed reasons for the same.</li>
<li><strong>No whip: </strong>All discussions in the Parliamentary Standing Committee should be frank and free. No whip of the party would apply to them during the discussion.</li>
<li><strong>Time bound:</strong> fixed timeline to come up with the recommendation and present its report which can be decided by the Speaker/Chairman. In case the committee if fails to give its recommendation within the approved/extended time, the Bill may be put up before the House concerned directly.</li>
<li><strong>Inviting filed Expertise:</strong> To ensure quality work in the committees, experts in the field may be invited who could bring with them the necessary domain knowledge and also help introduce the latest developments and trends in that field from Some subject matter experts/young researchers could be associated with the committee for a short period would be fruitful.</li>
<li><strong>Authority</strong>: The Speaker/Chairman should have the right to fix a time limit, sometimes even stringent, if the government of the day asks for it and the demand is found to be reasonable by the Speaker/Chairman.</li>
<li><strong>Organized work in the gap: </strong>Between two sessions, there is generally enough time to organise committee meetings for discussions on Bills in the parliamentary committees. It is important for the Ministry of Parliamentary Affairs in collaboration with the committee chairmen to get these parliamentary works organized during the intersessional period, in advance.</li>
<li><strong>Other than Budget Proposals</strong>: The committees should not limit themselves to discussing just the budget proposals and endorsing them with a few qualifications here or amendments there. They should also come up with suggestions for the Ministry to take up new initiatives and people friendly measures.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Discussion is not a stumbling block but an indispensable preliminary of any wise actions.</li>
<li>Discussion is soul of democracy.</li>
<li>Parliamentary committees are truly democratic institutions in India due to its consensus and bonhomie while functioning.</li>
<li>Government of the day should take step to strengthen DRSC and refer more bills to committees.<strong> </strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other related information</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Parliamentary sessions</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The president from time to time summons each House of Parliament to meet.</li>
<li>The maximum gap between two sessions of Parliament cannot be more than six months.</li>
<li>In other words, the Parliament should meet at least twice a year.</li>
<li>There are usually three sessions in a year: 1. The Budget Session (February to May); 2. The Monsoon Session (July to September); and 3. The Winter Session (November to December).</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-competition-commission-of-india/"><strong>Competition Commission of India</strong> <strong>(CCI)</strong></a></p>
<ul>
<li>CCI is the <strong>chief national competition regulator</strong>in India.</li>
<li>The commission was established on 14 October 2003. It became fully functional in May 2009</li>
<li>It is a <strong>statutory body</strong> within the <strong>Ministry of Corporate Affairs</strong></li>
<li><strong>Responsibility</strong>: To enforce the Competition Act, 2002 to promote competition and to prevent activities that effects negatively on competition in India.</li>
<li>The CCI looks into cases and investigates them if the same has a negative impact on competition.</li>
<li>CCI also approves combination under the act so that two merging entities do not overtake the market.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question Q.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Evaluate the significance of parliamentary standing committee in parliamentary democracy. Suggest the steps to strengthen the parliamentary committees. </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/parliamentary-committees/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>UNEP launches Green Fins Hub</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/green-fins-hub/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Green Fins Hub</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="fins" class="alignnone wp-image-636709" height="202" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 348px) 100vw, 348px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/green-fin-300x174.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/green-fin-300x174.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/green-fin-768x446.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/green-fin.jpg 1005w" width="348"/></p>
<p>The United Nations Environmental Programme (UNEP) has launched the Green Fins Hub, a global digital platform to give sustainable marine tourism a ‘major boost’.</p>
<h4>Green Fins Hub</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Green Fins Global Hub will be a first-of-its-kind online support system to motivate scuba operators to improve their daily environmental practices at scale.</li>
<li>It aims to help diving and snorkeling operators worldwide to make simple, cost-efficient changes to their daily practices by utilizing tried and tested solutions.</li>
<li>It would also help them keep track of their annual improvements and communicate with their communities and customers.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Membership of Green Fins Hub</h4>
<ul>
<li>It will host two types of membership. One would be digital membership available for diving, snorkelling and liveaboard operations globally.</li>
<li>Throughout every year of membership, operators will receive environmental scores based on a detailed online self-evaluation and progress made on their action plans.</li>
<li>The Certified Members will continue to be assessed annually and trained in person at their operation.</li>
<li>The platform will be for operators around the world to raise industry needs, discuss environmental issues and share lessons and ideas with like-minded industry leaders, non-profits and governments.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/green-fins-hub/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Delay in govt.’s flagship PMAY-G scheme to invite penalty</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/delay-in-govt-pmay-g-scheme-penalty/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PMAY- Urban and Rural</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Housing for All</p></div></div><p>Pulling up the States for the delay in completion of the government’s flagship rural household scheme — Pradhan Mantri Awas Yojana –Gramin (PMAY-G) — the Union Ministry of Rural Development has come up with a set of penalties that the State governments will have to bear for any further delay.</p>
<h4>About PMAY-G Scheme</h4>
<ul>
<li>In pursuance of the goal – Housing for all by 2022, the rural housing scheme <strong><u>Indira Awas Yojana was revamped</u></strong> to PMAY-G and approved during March 2016.</li>
<li>The main aim of the PMAY-G scheme is to provide pucca house with some of the basic amenities.</li>
<li>This scheme is meant for people who do not own a house and people who live in kutcha houses or houses which are severely damaged.</li>
<li>At present, the minimum size of the houses to be built under the PMAY-G scheme has been increased to 25 sq. mt. from 20 sq. mt.</li>
<li>Under PMAY, the cost of unit assistance is to be shared between Central and State Governments in the ratio 60:40 in plain areas and 90:10 for North Eastern and hilly states.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Subsidies under PMAY – G scheme</h4>
<p>There are various subsidies offered under PMAY G. These include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Loans up to Rs. 70,000 from financial institution</li>
<li>Interest subsidy of 3%</li>
<li>Subsidy for the maximum principal amount is Rs. 2 lakh</li>
</ul>
<p>Why in news?</p>
<ul>
<li>Opposition-ruled states such as West Bengal, Chhattisgarh and Odisha are the leading four States who are far behind their targets.</li>
<li>The initial deadline for the scheme was March 2022, which owing to the COVID-19 pandemic was extended by another two years till March 2024.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the penalty provisions?</h4>
<ul>
<li>If the sanction of the house is <strong><u>delayed for more than one month</u></strong> from the date of issue of the target, the State government will be penalised.</li>
<li>The penal fees are <strong><u>per week</u></strong> <strong><u>₹10 per house</u></strong> for the first month of delay and ₹20 per house for each subsequent month of delay.</li>
<li>Similarly, if the first instalment due to the beneficiary is delayed for more than seven days from the date of sanction, then the State governments will have to pay <strong><u>₹10 per house per week of delay</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="dn8amPj9J4"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/govt-extends-pmay-urban-scheme/">Govt. extends PMAY-Urban scheme</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="dn8amPj9J4" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/govt-extends-pmay-urban-scheme/embed/#?secret=jJEUVlcsxg#?secret=dn8amPj9J4" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“Govt. extends PMAY-Urban scheme” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/delay-in-govt-pmay-g-scheme-penalty/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What are the Big Seven Cats?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-the-big-seven-cat/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Big cats</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-636710" height="394" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 436px) 100vw, 436px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/panthera-300x271.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/panthera-300x271.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/panthera.jpg 633w" width="436"/></strong></p>
<p>We often get confused to differentiate between Cheetah/Bagh/Sher/Puli. The cheetah, which is being re-introduced to India from Africa, is not to be confused with the leopard, which too has spots that look somewhat similar.</p>
<h4><strong>How are all Big Cats differentiated?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>[A] Genus Panthera</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>This is the genus of large wild cats that can roar but can’t purr.</li>
<li>Among them, the lion, the leopard, and the jaguar are more closely related, while the other strand has the tiger and the snow leopard.</li>
<li>The snow leopard is an exception to the rest of the group in that it can’t roar.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(1)</strong> <strong>Tiger <em>(Panthera Tigris)</em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Size: 75-300 kg | IUCN status : Endangered</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Jim Corbett’s “large-hearted gentleman with boundless courage”, the solitary and strongly territorial tiger is the largest of all wild cats and also the earliest Panthera member to exist.</li>
<li>Primarily a forest animal, they range from the Siberian taiga to the Sunderban delta.</li>
<li>The national animal of India, Bangladesh, Malaysia, and South Korea, the tiger was voted the world’s favourite animal ahead of the dog in a 2004 Animal Planet global online poll.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Lion <em>(Panthera Leo</em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Size: 100-250 kg | IUCN status: Vulnerable</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Native to Africa and Asia, the lion is the most social cat, and lives in groups called prides.</li>
<li>They prefer open forests such as scrubland, and adult males have a prominent mane.</li>
<li>The lion is arguably the most widely recognised animal symbol in human culture — be it the Ashoka pillar in Sarnath, the main entrance to Buckingham Palace, or the 20th Century Fox and MGM logo.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3)</strong> <strong>Jaguar<em> (Panthera Onca)</em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Size: 50-110 kg | IUCN status: Near Threatened</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The largest cat in the Americas, the Jaguar has the strongest bite force of all wild cats, enabling it to bite directly through the skull of its prey.</li>
<li>Melanistic (black) Jaguars are common and are often called black panthers.</li>
<li>Jaguar was a powerful motif in the Mayan and Aztec civilisations.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Leopard<em> (Panthera Pardus)</em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Size: 30-90 kg | IUCN status: Vulnerable</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Similar in appearance to the Jaguar with a rosette patterned coat, the leopard was described by Jim Corbett as “the most beautiful of all animals” for its “grace of movement and beauty of colouring”.</li>
<li>The most adaptable of all big cats, they occupy diverse habitats at all altitudes across Africa and Asia.</li>
<li>Like black jaguars, melanistic leopards are called black panthers.</li>
<li>In some African cultures, leopards are considered to be better hunters than lions.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5)</strong> <strong>Snow leopard <em>(Panthera Uncia)</em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Size: 25-55 kg | IUCN status : Vulnerable</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The ghost of the mountains, this smokey-grey cat lives above the snow line in Central and South Asia.</li>
<li>The most elusive of all big cats, it cannot roar, and has the longest tail of them all — which comes in handy for balance while hunting along the cliffs, and also gives warmth when wrapped around the body.</li>
<li>The snow leopard is the state animal of Ladakh and Himachal Pradesh.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>[B] Genus Puma</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Closely related to the domestic cat, this genus has only one extant species, the cougar.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cougar <em>(Puma concolor)</em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Size: 40-100 kg | IUCN status: Least Concern</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The cougar is the second-largest cat in the Americas. (The Jaguar is the largest.)</li>
<li>Cougars are also called ‘mountain lion’ and ‘panther’ across their range from the Canadian Yukon to the Southern Andes.</li>
<li>Concolor is latin for “of uniform colour”. The Incas designed the city of Cusco in the shape of a cougar.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>[C] Genus Acinonyx</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>This is a unique genus within the cat family, with only one living member, the cheetah.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cheetah<em> (Acinonyx jubatus)</em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Size: 20-70 kg | IUCN status: Vulnerable</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The fastest land mammal, the cheetah is the only cat without retractable claws — the grip helps it accelerate faster than any sports car (0-100 km/hr in 3 seconds).</li>
<li>Cheetahs are not aggressive towards humans, and they have been tamed since the Sumerian era.</li>
<li>They don’t breed well in captivity — picky females play hard to get.</li>
<li>Cheetahs are not really big, and they hunt during the day to avoid competing with other big cats.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-the-big-seven-cat/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Tamil Nadu’s new Breakfast Scheme in Schools</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tamil-nadus-breakfast-scheme-in-schools/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Meal schemes for students</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="breakfast" class="alignnone wp-image-636711" height="230" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 408px) 100vw, 408px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/food-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/food-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/food.jpg 700w" width="408"/></strong></p>
<p>Tamil Nadu CM has launched the Chief Minister’s Breakfast Scheme for students of Class I to V in government schools.</p>
<h4><strong>CM’s Breakfast Scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme covers around 1.14 lakh students in 1,545 schools which include 417 municipal corporation schools, 163 municipality schools and 728 taluk and village panchayat-level schools.</li>
<li>The inauguration of the scheme marks an important milestone in the State’s history of providing <strong><u>free meals to school students.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>How has the idea evolved?</h4>
<p><strong>(a) Pre-independence</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In November 1920, the Madras Corporation Council approved a proposal for providing tiffin to the students of a Corporation School at Thousand Lights at a cost not exceeding one anna per student per day.</li>
<li>Theagaraya Chetty, the then President of the Corporation and one of the stalwarts of the Justice Party, said the boys studying at the school were poor, which affected the strength of the institution ‘greatly’.</li>
<li>The scheme, which was extended to four more schools and facilitated higher enrollment of students.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(b) Post-independence</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The concept saw a <strong><u>Statewide application in 1956</u></strong> when the then CM K. Kamaraj decided to provide free noon meal to poor children in all primary schools across the State.</li>
<li>The Budget for 1956-57 contained a provision for supplying mid-day meals to schoolchildren for 200 days a year, initially covering 65,000 students in 1,300 feeding centres.</li>
<li>In July 1982, it was left to the then CM MG Ramachandran to extend the programme to children in the 2-5 age group in Anganwadis and those in 5-9 age group in primary schools in rural areas.</li>
<li>Subsequently, the scheme now called <strong><u>Puratchi Thalaivar MGR Nutritious Meal Programme</u></strong> — was extended to urban areas as well.</li>
<li>Since September 1984, students of standards VI to X have been covered under the scheme.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Beneficiaries of the programme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As of now, there are nearly <strong><u>7 lakh beneficiaries</u></strong> spread over 43,190 nutritious meal centres.</li>
<li>This includes around 3,500 students of <strong><u>National Child Labour Project (NCLP)</u></strong> special schools.</li>
<li>Besides, as a consequence of the collaborative implementation of the <strong><u>Integrated Child Development Scheme (ICDS)</u></strong> and the nutritious meal programme, around 15.8 lakh children in the age group of 2+ to 5+ years receive nutritious meals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Impact on school education</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rise in enrolment:</strong> After the improved version of the mid-day meal scheme in 1982, the Gross Enrollment Ratio (GER) at primary level (standards I to V) went up by 10% during July-September, 1982 as compared to the corresponding period in 1981.</li>
<li><strong>Girls’ enrolment:</strong> The rise in boys’ enrollment was 12% and in the case of girls, 7%, according to a publication brought out by the Tamil Nadu government on the occasion of the launch of the Scheme.</li>
<li><strong>Increase in attendance:</strong> Likewise, attendance during July-September 1982 rose by 33% over the previous year’s figure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Focus areas programme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Anaemia</u></strong> is a major health problem in Tamil Nadu, especially among women and children, says the 2019-21 National Family Health Survey (NFHS)-5’s report.</li>
<li>From 50% during the period of the 2015-16 NFHS-4, the prevalence of anaemia in children now went up to 57%.</li>
<li>This and many other health issues can be addressed through the combined efforts of the departments of School Education, Public Health and Social Welfare and Women Empowerment.</li>
<li>Besides, a continuous and rigorous review of the progress of the scheme and nutritious meal programme should be carried out in a sustained manner.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tamil-nadus-breakfast-scheme-in-schools/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre cites law to deny medical seats to Ukraine-returnees</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-deny-medical-seat-ukraine-returns/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Medical education pursuance in foreign and issues</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="medical" class="alignnone wp-image-636747" height="241" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 402px) 100vw, 402px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ukr-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ukr-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ukr-768x461.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ukr.jpg 917w" width="402"/></strong></p>
<p>The Centre has told the Supreme Court that the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/national-medical-commission-replaces-the-mci/">law</a> does not allow undergraduate medical students, who fled the “war-like situation” in Ukraine, to be accommodated in Indian medical colleges.</p>
<h4><strong>Which laws is the govt talking about?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There are no provisions either under the <strong><u>Indian Medical Council Act, 1956</u></strong>, or the <strong><u>National Medical Commission Act, 2019</u></strong> to accommodate or transfer medical students.</li>
<li>Till now, no permission has been given by the National Medical Commission to transfer or accommodate any foreign medical students in any Indian medical institute/university.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why foreign undergraduates are not permitted?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Absence of law:</strong> The extant regulations in India do not permit migration of students from foreign universities to India.</li>
<li><strong>No backdoor entry:</strong> The public notice cannot be used as a back door entry into Indian colleges offering undergraduate courses.</li>
<li><strong>Merit issue:</strong> The students had left for foreign universities for two reasons, poor marks in the National Eligibility cum Entrance Test (NEET) and affordability of medical education in foreign countries.</li>
<li><strong>High cost:</strong> Besides, these students, if admitted in Indian colleges, would again face the problem of affordability.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why do Indians go abroad for medical studies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to estimates from Ukraine, reported in the media, around 18,000 Indian students are in Ukraine (before Operation Ganga).</li>
<li>Most of them are pursuing medicine.</li>
<li>This war has turned the spotlight on something that has been the trend for about three decades now.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Preferred countries for a medical degree</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>For about three decades now, Indian students have been heading out to Russia, China, Ukraine, Kyrgyzstan, Kazakhstan, and Philippines to pursue a medical degree.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Hype of becoming a Doctor</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Prestige:</strong> The desire to study medicine still holds a lot of value in the Indian community (the other is becoming an IAS officer).</li>
<li><strong>Shortages of Doctor:</strong> In many rural areas, people still look at doctors as god’s incarnate.</li>
<li><strong>Rarity of opportunity:</strong> The lack of equal opportunities exacerbated by the caste factor in the Indian context, has a great deal of impact on the prestige still associated with being a doctor.</li>
<li><strong>Social upliftment ladder:</strong> For years, certain communities were denied the opportunities, and finally they do have a chance at achieving significant educational status.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why do Indians prefer going abroad?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>No language barrier:</strong> The medium of education for these students is English, a language they are comfortable with.</li>
<li><strong>Affordability:</strong> The amount spent on living and the medical degree are far more affordable than paying for an MBBS seat in private medical colleges in India.</li>
<li><strong>Aesthetics and foreign culture:</strong> People are willing to leave their home to study far away in much colder places and with completely alien cultures and food habits.</li>
<li><strong>Practice and OPD exposure:</strong> It broadens students’ mind and thinking, expose them to a whole range of experiences, and their approach to issues and crises is likely to be far better.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Doesn’t India have enough colleges?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(a) More aspirants than seats</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There are certainly far more MBBS aspirants than there are MBBS seats in India.</li>
<li>In NEET 2021, as per a National Testing Agency press release, 16.1 lakh students registered for the exam, 15.4 lakh students appeared for the test, and 8.7 lakh students qualified.</li>
<li>As per data from the National Medical Commission (NMC), in 2021-22, there were 596 medical colleges in the country with a total of 88,120 MBBS seats.</li>
<li>While the skew is in favour of Government colleges, it is not greatly so, with the number of private medical institutions nearly neck-to-neck with the state-run ones.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(b) Fees structure</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>That means over 50% of the total seats are available at affordable fees in Government colleges.</li>
<li>Add the 50% seats in the private sector that the NMC has mandated must charge only the government college fees.</li>
<li>In fully private colleges, the full course fees range from several lakhs to crores.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(c) Uneven distribution of colleges</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>These colleges are also not distributed evenly across the country, with States such as Maharashtra, Karnataka, Tamil Nadu and Kerala having many more colleges.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What about costs?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The cost factor on both sides of an MBBS degree is significant.</li>
<li>The costs of an MBBS degree in a Government college tot up to a few lakhs of rupees for the full course, but in a private medical college, <strong><u>it can go up to ₹1 crore</u></strong> <strong><u>for the five-year course</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In case it is a management seat, capitation fees can inflate the cost by several lakhs again.</li>
<li>Whereas, an MBBS course at any foreign medical university in the east and Eastern Europe costs far less (upto ₹30lakh-₹40 lakh).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While PM Modi emphasised that more private medical colleges must be set up in the country to aid more people to take up MBBS, medical education experts have called for pause on the aspect.</li>
<li>If the aim is to make medicine more accessible to students of the country, the path ahead is not in the private sector, but in the public sector, with the Central and State governments’ involvement.</li>
<li>Starting private medical colleges by reducing the strict standards set for establishing institutes may not actually be the solution to this problem, if we think this is a concern.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Creating more medical colleges will be beneficial for the country, if access and availability can be ensured.</li>
<li>This will not be possible by resorting to private enterprise only.</li>
<li>The State and Central governments can start more medical colleges, as recommended by NITI Aayog, by utilising district headquarters hospitals, and expanding the infrastructure.</li>
<li>This way, students from the lower and middle socio-economic rung, who are otherwise not able to access medical seats, will also benefit.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-deny-medical-seat-ukraine-returns/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Eastern Economic Forum (EEF) and India’s Balancing Act</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/eastern-economic-forum-eef/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>EEF</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="eef" class="alignnone wp-image-636707" height="229" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 409px) 100vw, 409px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/eef--300x168.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/eef--300x168.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/eef-.jpg 610w" width="409"/></strong></p>
<p>Russia hosted the seventh Eastern Economic Forum- EEF Vladivostok from September 5 to 8. The four-day forum is a platform for entrepreneurs to expand their businesses into Russia’s Far East (RFE).</p>
<h4><strong>What is the Eastern Economic Forum-EEF?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The EEF was <strong><u>established in 2015</u></strong> aiming <strong><u>to encourage foreign investments</u></strong> in the RFE to display:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Economic potential</li>
<li>Suitable business conditions and</li>
<li>Investment opportunities in the region</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>Focus areas: </strong>The agreements focus on infrastructure, transportation projects, mineral excavations, construction, industry and agriculture.</li>
<li>With EEF, Russia is trying to attract the Asian economies in investing and developing the Far East.</li>
<li>This year, the Forum aimed at <strong><u>connecting the Far East with the Asia-Pacific</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does the EEF aim for?</strong></h4>
<p><strong><img alt="eef" class="alignnone wp-image-635634" height="237" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 439px) 100vw, 439px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/far-east-300x162.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/far-east-300x162.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/far-east.jpg 750w" width="439"/></strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>FDI inflows:</strong> The primary objective of the EEF is to increase the Foreign Direct Investments in the RFE.</li>
<li><strong>Natural resource exploitation:</strong> The region encompasses one-third of Russia’s territory and is rich with natural resources such as fish, oil, natural gas, wood, diamonds and other minerals.</li>
<li><strong>Demographic revamp:</strong> The sparse population living in the region is another factor for encouraging people to move and work in the Far East.</li>
<li><strong>Unleashing economic potential:</strong> The region’s riches and resources contribute to five percent of Russia’s GDP.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Success of EEF</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-636708" height="434" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 418px) 100vw, 418px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/eef-289x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/eef-289x300.jpg 289w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/eef.jpg 505w" width="418"/></p>
<ul>
<li>Agreements signed at the EEF increased from 217 in 2017 to 380 agreements in 2021, worth 3.6 trillion roubles.</li>
<li>As of 2022, almost 2,729 investment projects are being planned in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h5><strong>Who are the major actors in the EEF? </strong></h5>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>China is the biggest investor</u></strong> in the region as it sees potential in promoting the Chinese Belt and Road Initiative and the Polar Sea Route in the RFE.</li>
<li>China’s investments in the region account for <strong><u>90% of the total investments</u></strong>.</li>
<li><strong><u>South Korea</u></strong> has invested in shipbuilding projects, manufacturing of electrical equipment, gas-liquefying plants, agricultural production and fisheries.</li>
<li><strong><u>Japan</u></strong> is another key trading partner. In 2017, its investments through 21 projects amounted to $16 billion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does Russia see Chinese investment in EEF?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Russia has been welcoming</u></strong> Chinese investments since 2015; more now than ever due to the economic pressures caused by the war in Ukraine.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Trans-Siberian Railway</u></strong> has further helped Russia and China in advancing trade ties.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>countries share a 4000-km-long border</u></strong>, which enables them to tap into each other’s resources with some infrastructural assistance.</li>
<li>China is also looking to develop its <strong><u>Heilongjiang Province</u></strong> which connects with the RFE.</li>
<li>Both nations have invested in a fund to develop <strong><u>connectivity between the cities of</u></strong><u> <strong>Blagoveshchensk and Heihe</strong></u>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>India and Russia’s Far East</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India seeks to expand its influence in the RFE.</li>
<li>In 2019, India also offered a <strong><u>$1 billion line of credit</u></strong> to develop infrastructure in the region.</li>
<li>During the forum, PM Modi expressed the country’s readiness in expanding trade, connectivity and investments in Russia.</li>
<li>India is keen to deepen its cooperation in energy, pharmaceuticals, maritime connectivity, healthcare, tourism, the diamond industry and the Arctic.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Strategic significance of EEF for Russia</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Gateway to Asia:</strong> The RFE is geographically placed at a strategic location; acting as a gateway into Asia.</li>
<li><strong>Negating the Ukrainian war impact:</strong> The Ukraine war is a worrying issue as it affects the economic growth of the country.</li>
<li><strong>Surviving sanctions:</strong> Although, the EEF is an annual gathering, the forum comes at an opportune time for Russia who is dealing with the impact of the sanctions.</li>
<li><strong>Supply chain resilience:</strong> The IPEF will also play a key role in building resilient supply chains.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Will India be able to strike a balance between the EEF and IPEF?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Both are incomparable:</strong> The US-led <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indo-pacific-economic-framework-for-prosperity-ipef/">Indo-Pacific Economic Framework for Prosperity (IPEF)</a> and the EEF are incomparable based on its geographic coverage and the partnership with the host-countries.</li>
<li><strong>India values both:</strong> India has not shied away from investing in the Russia-initiated EEF despite the current international conditions.</li>
<li><strong>India is firm for its purpose:</strong> At the same time, India has given its confirmation and acceptance to three of the four pillars in the IPEF.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India understands the benefits of being involved in the development in the RFE but it also perceives the IPEF as a vital platform to strengthen its presence in the Indo-Pacific region.</li>
<li>India’s participation in the forum will help in disengaging from supply chains that are dependent on China and will also make it a part of the global supply chain network.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="0hZLajNAi5"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/russia-far-east/">[Sansad TV] Perspective: Russia’s Far East- Opportunities for India</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="0hZLajNAi5" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/russia-far-east/embed/#?secret=GSQYzFWcUp#?secret=0hZLajNAi5" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Sansad TV] Perspective: Russia’s Far East- Opportunities for India” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/eastern-economic-forum-eef/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Should India choose manufacturing over services? Here is because</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/manufacturing/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PLI scheme</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>sectors of economy</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Manufacturing" class="alignnone wp-image-636754" height="430" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 648px) 100vw, 648px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/43b07911-7d31-47db-b3dd-2c230924a198-300x199.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/43b07911-7d31-47db-b3dd-2c230924a198-300x199.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/43b07911-7d31-47db-b3dd-2c230924a198-768x510.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/43b07911-7d31-47db-b3dd-2c230924a198.jpg 1000w" width="648"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Manufacturing can create higher productivity jobs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is service sector?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The service sector, also known as the tertiary sector, is <strong>the third tier in the three-sector economy</strong>. Instead of product production, this sector produces services maintenance and repairs, training, or consulting. Examples of service sector jobs include housekeeping, tours, nursing, and teaching.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is called manufacturing sector?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Manufacturing is the making of goods by hand or by machine that upon completion the business sells to a customer. Items used in manufacture may be raw materials or component parts of a larger product. The manufacturing usually happens on a large-scale production line of machinery and skilled labor.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong style="letter-spacing: -0.0415625em;"><img alt="Manufacturing" class="alignnone wp-image-636756" height="404" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 673px) 100vw, 673px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector-1024x614.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector-768x461.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector-1536x922.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector-1200x720.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector.jpg 1600w" width="673"/>Should India focus on manufacturing over services?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Services sector failed to create more jobs</strong>: So far, in services, we have certainly developed some advantage and we are doing rather well. Services’ share of the economy has gone up to over 50% of the GDP. However, this sector has not been able to create enough jobs in a commensurate manner. The result is that agriculture still continues to sustain nearly half of India’s workforce, which means that 15% of GDP is supporting some 45% of the workforce.</li>
<li><strong>Manufacturing can provide productive jobs</strong>: We need more productive job opportunities for the workforce to shift away from agriculture. We need to focus attention on the manufacturing sector because of the direct and indirect jobs that it can create.</li>
<li><strong>Empirical fact</strong>: It is an empirical fact that manufacturing of all productive sectors has the highest backward and forward linkages.</li>
<li><strong>Significant potential:</strong> So, all together, there is significant potential for the manufacturing sector to create higher productivity jobs for people stuck in agricultural activities. That is the future for India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Manufacturing" class="alignnone wp-image-636757" height="400" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 710px) 100vw, 710px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sectors-of-Indian-Economy-backup-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sectors-of-Indian-Economy-backup-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sectors-of-Indian-Economy-backup-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sectors-of-Indian-Economy-backup-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sectors-of-Indian-Economy-backup-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sectors-of-Indian-Economy-backup.jpg 1280w" width="710"/>What is<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pli-scheme-will-help-india-nurture-manufacturing-giants/"> PLI</a> Scheme?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As the name suggests, the scheme provides incentives to companies for enhancing their domestic manufacturing apart from focusing on reducing import bills and improving the cost competitiveness of local goods.</li>
<li>PLI scheme offers incentives on incremental sales for products manufactured in India.</li>
<li>The scheme for respective sectors has to be implemented by the concerned ministries and departments.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Criteria laid for the scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Eligibility criteria for businesses under the PLI scheme vary based on the sector approved under the scheme.</li>
<li>For instance, the eligibility for telecom units is subject to the achievement of a minimum threshold of cumulative incremental investment and incremental sales of manufactured goods.</li>
<li>The minimum investment threshold for MSME is Rs 10 crore and Rs 100 crores for others.</li>
<li>Under food processing, SMEs and others must hold over 50 per cent of the stock of their subsidiaries, if any.</li>
<li>On the other hand, for businesses under pharmaceuticals, the project has to be a green-field project while the net worth of the company should not be less than 30 per cent of the total committed investment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the incentives offered?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An incentive of 4-6 per cent was offered last year on mobile and electronic components manufacturers such as resistors, transistors, diodes, etc.</li>
<li>Similarly, 10 percent incentives were offered for six years (FY22-27) of the scheme for the food processing industry.</li>
<li>For white goods too, the incentive of 4-6 per cent on incremental sales of goods manufactured in India for a period of five years was offered to companies engaged in the manufacturing of air conditioners and LED lights.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Benefits of PLI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme has a direct employment generation potential of over 2,00,000 jobs over 5 years.</li>
<li>It would lead to large scale electronics manufacturing in the country and open tremendous employment opportunities. Indirect employment will be about 3 times of direct employment as per industry estimates.</li>
<li>Thus, the total employment potential of the scheme is approximately 8,00,000.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In order to integrate India as a pivotal part of this modern economy, there is a strong need to step up our manufacturing capabilities.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Should India focus on manufacturing over services for job creation? Discuss the role Production Linked Incentive Scheme could play in boosting manufacturing in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/manufacturing/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Highlights of India Discrimination Report, 2022</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-discrimination-report/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>India Discrimination Report, 2022</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economic and social discrimination in India</p></div></div><p>Oxfam India’s latest ‘India Discrimination Report 2022’ finds women in India despite their same educational qualifications and work experience as men will be discriminated in the labour market due to societal and employers’ prejudices.</p>
<h4>About the report</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Oxfam India report refers to unit-level data from:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>61st round National Sample Survey (NSS) data on employment-unemployment (2004-05)</li>
<li>Periodic Labour Force Survey in 2018-19 and 2019-20 and</li>
<li>All India Debt and Investment Survey by the government</li>
</ol>
<h4>Key highlights</h4>
<p><strong>(1) Decline of women in workforce</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>As per the Union Ministry of Statistics &amp; Programme Implementation (MoSPI), LFPR for women in India was only 25.1 percent in 2020-21 for urban and rural women.</li>
<li>This is considerably lower than Brazil, Russia, China and South Africa as per the latest World Bank estimates.</li>
<li>The LFPR for women in India has rapidly declined from 42.7 percent in 2004-05 to mere 25.1 percent in 2021 showing the withdrawal of women from the workforce.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Earning Gap</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is also a significant gap in the earnings between men and women in the case of regular and self-employment in urban areas.</li>
<li>The average earning is INR 15,996 for men and merely INR 6,626 for women in urban areas in self-employment.</li>
<li>The men’s average earning is nearly 2.5 times that of the earnings of women</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Communal aspects of discrimination</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Oppressed communities such as Dalits and Adivasis along with religious minorities such as Muslims also continue to face discrimination in accessing jobs, livelihoods, and agricultural credit.</li>
<li>The mean income for SCs or STs persons in urban areas who are regular employed is INR 15,312 as against INR 20,346 for persons belonging to the General Category.</li>
<li>The rural SC and ST communities are facing increase in discrimination in casual employment, the report shows.</li>
<li>The data shows that the unequal income among urban SC and ST casual wage work is because of 79 percent discrimination in 2019-20.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Muslims and economic backwardness</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Muslims continue to face multidimensional challenges in accessing salaried jobs and income through self-employment as compared to non-Muslims.</li>
<li>In rural areas, the sharpest increase of 17 percent in unemployment was for Muslims as compared to non-Muslims during the first quarter of the COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
<li>6 percent of the urban Muslims population aged 15 and above were engaged in regular salaried jobs whereas 23.3 percent of non-Muslims are in regular salaried jobs in 2019-20.</li>
<li>The lower employment for urban Muslims attributes 68.3 percent to discrimination in 2019-20.</li>
<li>The report shows that the discrimination faced by Muslims in 2004-05 was 59.3 percent, indicating an increase in discrimination by 09 percent over the last 16 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Recommendations from the report</h4>
<ul>
<li>Actively<strong><u> enforce effective measures</u></strong> for the implementation of the right to equal wages and work for all women.</li>
<li>Work to actively<strong><u> incentivise the participation of women</u></strong> in workforce including enhancements in pay, upskilling, job reservations and easy return-to-work options after maternity.</li>
<li>Work to actively <strong><u>challenge and change societal and caste/religion-based norms</u></strong>, around women’s’ participation in labour markets.</li>
<li>Strengthen <strong><u>civil society’s engagement</u></strong> in ensuring a more equitable distribution of household work and childcare duties between women and men and facilitating higher participation of women in labour market</li>
<li>Implement “<strong><u>living wages” as opposed to minimum wages</u></strong>, particularly for all informal workers and formalise contractual, temporary and casual labour as much as possible.</li>
<li>Extend <strong><u>priority lending and credit access</u></strong> to all farmers, regardless of social groups and penalize biased lending.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Labour Force Participation Rate (LFPR)</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is the percentage of the population which is either working (employed) or seeking for work (unemployed).</li>
<li>According to the International Labour Organisation (ILO), the LFPR is a ‘measure of the proportion of a country’s working-age population that engages actively in the labour market, either by working or looking for work’.</li>
<li>The breakdown of the labour force (formerly known as economically active population) by sex and age group gives a profile of the distribution of the labour force within a country.</li>
<li>As per the ministry of statistics and programme implementation, LFPR for women in India was only 25.1% in 2020-21.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-discrimination-report/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Eklavya Schools get short shrift in teacher recruitments</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/eklavya-schools-get-short-in-teachers/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>EMRS</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Schooling for Tribal students</p></div></div><p>The Ministry of Tribal Affairs has so far been unable to fix the teacher shortage faced across 378 of Eklavya model residential schools (EMRS) that are currently functional.</p>
<h4>Eklavya Model Residential Schools (EMRS)</h4>
<ul>
<li>EMRS started in the year 1997-98 to impart quality education to <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/tribes-protecting-the-tribes-india-ias/">Scheduled Tribes (ST)</a> children in remote areas in order.</li>
<li>It aims to enable them to avail of opportunities in high and professional educational courses and get employment in various sectors.</li>
<li>The schools focus not only on academic education but on the all-round development of the students.</li>
<li>Each school has a capacity of 480 students, catering to students from Class VI to XII.</li>
<li>Hitherto, grants were given for construction of schools and recurring expenses to the State Governments under Grants under Article 275 (1) of the Constitution.</li>
<li>Eklavya schools are on par with Navodaya Vidyalaya and have special facilities for preserving local art and culture besides providing training in sports and skill development.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Features of Eklavya Schools</h4>
<ul>
<li>Admission to these schools will be through selection/competition with suitable provision for preference to children belonging to Primitive Tribal Groups, first-generation students, etc.</li>
<li>Sufficient land would be given by the State Government for the school, playgrounds, hostels, residential quarters, etc., free of cost.</li>
<li>The number of seats for boys and girls will be equal.</li>
<li>In these schools, education will be entirely free.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where are the Eklavya schools located?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It has been decided that by the year 2022, every block with more than 50% ST population and at least 20,000 tribal persons, will have an EMRS.</li>
<li>Wherever density of ST population is higher in identified Sub-Districts (90% or more), it is proposed to set up Eklavya Model Day Boarding School (EMDBS) on an experimental basis.</li>
<li>They aim for providing additional scope for ST Students seeking to avail school education without residential facility.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/eklavya-schools-get-short-in-teachers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>PM Modi pitches for ‘Full Transit Right’ among SCO members</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pm-modi-pitches-for-full-transit-right-among-sco-members/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>International North–South Transport Corridor (INSTC)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>With Pakistan PM listening, Prime Minister Modi urged <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/iran-belarus-to-be-newest-sco-members/">Shanghai Cooperation Organisation</a> member states to “give each other full right to transit”.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>PM Modi framed the <strong><u>right to transit in the context of connectivity</u></strong> and how it could help establish reliable and resilient supply chains in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did PM pitch this?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lack of <strong><u>transit across Pakistan’s territory has been a challenge for India</u></strong> to access Central Asian markets.</li>
<li>Iran’s President also said that despite the impressive potential, infrastructural connections in the <strong><u>field of transit between members of the SCO are not so extensive.</u></strong></li>
<li>Iran already provides special priority to the development of the North-South Corridor and has made huge investments.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is International North-South Transport Corridor (INSTC)?</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-637170" height="259" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 411px) 100vw, 411px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/instc--300x189.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/instc--300x189.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/instc-.jpg 580w" width="411"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The INSTC is a <strong><u>7,200 km-long multimodal transportation network</u></strong> encompassing <strong><u>sea, road, and rail routes</u></strong> to offer the shortest route of connectivity.</li>
<li>It was <strong><u>established on 12th September 2000 in St. Petersburg</u></strong>, <strong><u>by Iran, Russia and India</u></strong> for the purpose of promoting transportation cooperation among the Member States.</li>
<li>It links the <strong><u>Indian Ocean to the Caspian Sea via the Persian Gulf</u></strong> onwards into Russia and Northern Europe.</li>
<li>It will move freight between India, Iran, Afghanistan, Armenia, Azerbaijan, Russia, Central Asia and Europe.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of INSTC</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Trade facilitation:</strong> INSTC is aimed at reducing the carriage cost between India and Russia by about 30 percent and bringing down the transit time by more than half.</li>
<li><strong>New corridor in making:</strong> It has the potential to transform the economies of countries along the corridor into specialized manufacturing, logistics, and transit hubs by facilitating access to newer markets.</li>
<li><strong>Multimodal transit:</strong> The recent Suez Canal blockade, which cost the global economy hefty damage amounting to US$9 billion, has amplified the optimistic outlook towards the INSTC as a cheaper and faster alternative multimodal transit corridor.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Benefits offered to India</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Export promotion:</strong> The INSTC connects India with Central Asia, and Russia, and has the potential to expand up to the Baltic, Nordic, and Arctic regions, increasing the scope of trade multifold.</li>
<li><strong>Ease of trade:</strong> For India, it provides a shorter trade route with Iran, Russia, and beyond to Europe, creating scope for increased economic engagement.</li>
<li><strong>Alternative Route to Central Asia:</strong> It opens up a permanent alternative route for India to trade with Afghanistan and Central Asia, given the hurdles in the direct route through Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pm-modi-pitches-for-full-transit-right-among-sco-members/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Complex issue of Assisted Suicide</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/complex-issue-of-assisted-suicide/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Assisted Suicide</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Assisted Suicide and issues involved</p></div></div><p><img alt="suicide" class="alignnone wp-image-637178" height="273" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 371px) 100vw, 371px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/suicide-300x221.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/suicide-300x221.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/suicide.jpg 718w" width="371"/></p>
<p>A renowned French filmmaker died earlier this week by assisted suicide at the age of 91.</p>
<h4>What is Assisted Suicide?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Assisted suicide and euthanasia are practices under which a person intentionally ends their life with active assistance from others.</li>
<li>These have long been contentious topics of debate as they involve a complex set of moral, ethical and in some cases, religious questions.</li>
<li>Several European nations, some states in Australia and Colombia in South America allow assisted suicide and euthanasia under certain circumstances.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Difference between assisted suicide and euthanasia</h4>
<ul>
<li>Euthanasia is the act of <strong><u>intentionally ending a life to relieve suffering</u></strong> – for example a lethal injection administered by a doctor.</li>
<li><strong><u>Intentionally helping another person</u></strong> to kill themselves is known as assisted suicide.</li>
<li>This can include providing someone with strong sedatives with which to end their life or buying them a ticket to Switzerland (where assisted suicide is legal) to end their life</li>
<li>Euthanasia can further be divided into active and passive.</li>
<li>The practice of passive euthanasia involves simply stopping lifesaving treatment or medical intervention with the consent of the patient or a family member or a close friend representing the patient.</li>
<li>Active euthanasia, which is legal in only a few countries, entails the use of substances to end the life of the patient.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India and Assisted suicide/ Euthanasia</h4>
<ul>
<li>In a landmark judgment, the Supreme Court of <strong><u>India legalised passive euthanasia in 2018</u></strong>, stating that it was a matter of ‘living will’.</li>
<li>According to the judgment, an adult in his conscious mind is permitted to refuse medical treatment or voluntarily decide not to take medical treatment to embrace death in a natural way, under certain conditions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Consideration for ‘living will’</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the 538-page judgment, the court laid down a set of guidelines for ‘living will’ and defined passive euthanasia and euthanasia as well.</li>
<li>It also laid down guidelines for ‘living will’ made by <strong><u>terminally ill patients who beforehand know about their chances of slipping into a permanent vegetative state.</u></strong></li>
<li>The court specifically stated that the rights of a patient, in such cases, w<strong><u>ould not fall out of the purview of Article 21</u></strong> (right to life and liberty) of the Indian Constitution.</li>
<li>The SC’s judgment was in accordance with its <strong><u>verdict in March 2011</u></strong> on a separate plea.</li>
<li>While ruling on a petition on behalf of <strong><u>Aruna Shanbaug Case</u></strong>, the court had <strong><u>allowed passive euthanasia</u></strong> for the nurse who had spent decades in a vegetative state.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who was Aruna Shanbaug?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Shanbaug had become central to debates on the legality of right to die and euthanasia in India.</li>
<li>Shanbaug died of pneumonia in March 2015 at the age of 66, 42 years of which she had spent in a room at KEM Hospital in Mumbai, after a brutal rape left her in a permanent vegetative state.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Recent cases in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2018, an old couple from Mumbai wrote to then President Kovind, seeking permission for active euthanasia or assisted suicide.</li>
<li>Neither of them suffered from a life-threatening ailment.</li>
<li>The couple stated in their plea that they had lived a happy life and <strong><u>didn’t want to depend on hospitals for old age ailments.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>Justification for Euthanasia/Assisted Suicide</h4>
<ul>
<li>It provides a way to relieve extreme pain.</li>
<li>Euthanasia can save  life  of  many  other  people  by  donation  of  vital organs.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with such killings</h4>
<ul>
<li>Euthanasia can be misused. Many psychiatrists are of the opinion that a terminally ill person or someone who is old and suffering from an incurable disease is often not in the right frame of mind to take a call.</li>
<li>Family members deciding on behalf of the patient can also lead to abuse of the law legalizing euthanasia as it can be due to some personal interest.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/complex-issue-of-assisted-suicide/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SC seeks Centre’s reply on issue of Marital Rape</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-seeks-centres-reply-on-marital-rape/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Persistence of marital rape and need for its criminalization</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has sought a response from the government on appeals to criminalize marital rape.</p>
<h4><strong>Split opinions on Marital Rape</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="rape" class="alignnone wp-image-637177" height="465" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 346px) 100vw, 346px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rape-223x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rape-223x300.jpg 223w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rape.jpg 595w" width="346"/></p>
<ul>
<li>This follows a split decision from the Delhi High Court on whether or not to prosecute husbands for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/criminalizing-marital-rape-in-india/">non-consensual </a>intercourse with their wives.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Marital Rape?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Marital rape is the act of sexual intercourse with one’s spouse without her consent.</li>
<li>It is no different manifestation of domestic violence and sexual abuse.</li>
<li>It is often a chronic form of violence for the victim which takes place within abusive relations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Status in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Historically considered as right of the spouses, this is now widely classified as rape by many societies around the world.</li>
<li>In India, marital rape is not a criminal offense (as protected under IPC section 375).</li>
<li>India is one of fifty countries that have not yet outlawed marital rape.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reasons for disapproval of this concept</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The reluctance to define non-consensual sex between married couples as a crime and to prosecute has been attributed to:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Traditional views of marriage</li>
<li>Interpretations of religious doctrines</li>
<li>Ideas about male and female sexuality</li>
<li>Cultural expectations of subordination of a wife to her husband</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>It is widely held that a husband cannot be guilty of any sexual act committed by himself upon his lawful wife their on account of their mutual matrimonial consent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why it must be a crime?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Associated physical violence:</strong> Rape by a spouse, partner or ex-partner is more often associated with physical violence.</li>
<li><strong>Mental harassment:</strong> There is research showing that marital rape can be more emotionally and physically damaging than rape by a stranger.</li>
<li><strong>Compulsive relationship:</strong> Marital rape may occur as part of an abusive relationship.</li>
<li><strong>Revengeful nature:</strong> Furthermore, marital rape is rarely a one-time event, but a repeated if not frequent occurrence.</li>
<li><strong>Obligation on women:</strong> In the case of marital rape the victim often has no choice but to continue living with their spouse.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Violation of fundamental rights</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Marital rape is considered as the violation of FR guaranteed under <u>Article 14</u> of the Indian constitution which guarantees the equal protection of laws to all persons.</li>
<li>By depriving married women of an effective penal remedy against forced sexual intercourse, it violates their right to privacy and bodily integrity, aspects of the right to life and personal liberty under <u>Article 21</u>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Problems in prosecuting marital rape</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of awareness:</strong> A lack of public awareness, as well as reluctance or outright refusal of authorities to prosecute, is common globally.</li>
<li><strong>Gender norms:</strong> Additionally, gender norms that place wives in subservient positions to their husbands, make it more difficult for women to recognize such rape.</li>
<li><strong>Acceptability of the concept:</strong> Another problem results from prevailing social norms that exist.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Present regulations in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian Penal Code criminalizes rape in most cases, although marital rape is not illegal when the woman is over the age of 18.</li>
<li>However, until 2017, men married to those between 15 and 18 could not be convicted of rape.</li>
<li>Marital rape of an adult wife, who is unofficially or officially separated, is a criminal offence punishable by 2 to 7 year in prison; it is not dealt by normal rape laws which stipulate the possibility of a death sentence.</li>
<li>According to the Protection of Women From Domestic Violence Act (2005), other married women subject to such crime by their husband may demand for financial compensation.</li>
<li>They also have the right to continue to live in their marital household if they wish, or may approach shelter or aid homes.</li>
</ul>
<p>However, marital rape is still not a criminal offence in this case and is only a misdemeanor.</p>
<h4><strong>Arguments against criminalization</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Subjective:</strong> It is very subjective and intricate to determine whether consent was acquired or not.</li>
<li><strong>Prone to Misuse</strong>: If marital rape is criminalized without adequate safeguards it could be misused like the current dowry law by the dissatisfied wives to harass and torture their Husbands.</li>
<li><strong>Burden on Judiciary</strong>: It will increase the burden of judiciary which otherwise may serve other more important causes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sanctioning marital rape is an acknowledgment of the woman’s right to self-determination (i.e., control) of all matters relating to her body.</li>
<li>In the absence of any concrete law, the judiciary always finds it difficult to decide the matter of domestic rape in the absence of solid evidence.</li>
<li>The main purpose of marriage is procreation, and sometimes divorce is sought on the ground of non-consummation of marriage.</li>
<li>Before giving a final interpretation, the judiciary must balance the rights and duties of both partners.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-seeks-centres-reply-on-marital-rape/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How lower fertility rate hampers demographic dividend in number of ways</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fertility-rate/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>human population</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="fertility rate" class="alignnone wp-image-637033" height="467" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 623px) 100vw, 623px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives.jpg 1200w" width="623"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Though the Global population, in terms of numbers, has been steadily increasing the average global fertility rate has been consistently declining over the past 70 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What Reports say?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Reports suggest that the global population could grow to around 8.5 billion in 2030.</li>
<li>According to the World Population Prospects 2022, Average number of children per woman in the reproductive age group has declined by 50%, from an average of five children per woman in 1951 to4 children in 2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Fertility?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fertility is the quality or state of being fertile<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>Fertility is the ability to reproduce through normal sexual interaction. In other words it is the natural capacity to conceive a biological child.</li>
<li>Fertilitychanges with age. Both males and females become fertile in their teens following puberty.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fertility rate" class="alignnone wp-image-637034" height="343" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 571px) 100vw, 571px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/e_440_x_264_14_2034043615--300x180.png" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/e_440_x_264_14_2034043615--300x180.png 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/e_440_x_264_14_2034043615-.png 440w" width="571"/> What is fertility rate?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The number of live births in women over a specific length of time.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/replacement-level-fertility-achieved-in-india/">Total fertility rate</a> is the average number of children born to a woman during her lifetime.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Recent findings</strong></h4>
<p>The newly released World Population Prospectus notes that the global fertility rate fell from three in 1990 to 2.3 in 2021.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Overview of fertility dynamics </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reason: </strong>Speeding up the social phenomenon of demographic transition.</li>
<li><strong>Poorer countries:</strong> speeding up the Transition a lot faster than the richer ones.</li>
<li><strong>Britain</strong>: Took 130 years to transition from a fertility rate of five per woman in 1800 to two in 1930, whereas</li>
<li><strong>South Korea: </strong>Took 20 years from 1965 to 1985 to achieve the same. South Korea reporting the lowest fertility rate, 1.05 children per woman.</li>
<li><strong>Most advanced economies</strong>: Have their fertility rate below the replacement rate of 2.1.</li>
<li><strong>Sub-Saharan African countries</strong>: Expected to contribute more than half the population growth after 2050 and grow through 2100. For example, Niger a sub Saharan country with highest fertility rate in the world, estimated to be 91 children per woman.</li>
<li><strong>What is Demographic transition</strong>: is a long-term trend of declining birth and death rate. It is shift from high birth rates to low birth rates in societies with minimal technology, education (especially of women) and economic development and from high death rates to Low death rates in societies with advanced economies and development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fertility rate" class="alignnone wp-image-637036" height="391" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 587px) 100vw, 587px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/shutterstock_-india-population-93427363-1-16577155543x2-1-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/shutterstock_-india-population-93427363-1-16577155543x2-1-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/shutterstock_-india-population-93427363-1-16577155543x2-1.jpeg 510w" width="587"/><br/>
Where India Stands</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to National Family Health Survey (NFHS), fertility rate falling below the replacement level for the first time to 2.0 in 2021.dropped from 2.2 to 2.0.</li>
<li>only five States have a fertility rate above the replacement rate: Bihar (3), Meghalaya (2.9), Uttar Pradesh (2.4), Jharkhand (2.3), and Manipur (2.2)</li>
<li>At the time of Independence, India’s fertility rate was six per woman, and it had taken 25 years to reach five, with the government launching the first ever family planning program in the world in 1952.</li>
<li>India’s fertility further declined to four in the 1990s when Kerala became the first State in India to have a fertility rate below replacement l</li>
<li>Increased use of contraception, more years of average schooling, better health care, and an increase in the mean marriage age of women are of the reasons behind the steady dip in fertility rate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Lower fertility rate as cause and consequences on the economy</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Positive impact:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Lower fertility leads to rise in women’s education.</li>
<li>Window of time where the ration of working-age population is higher than that of the dependent age groups.</li>
<li>This high proportion of people in the workforce boosts income and investment, and higher level of saving.</li>
<li>Lower pressure on land, water and other resources and would also contribute to achieving environmental goals.</li>
<li>Advanced health care and better nutrition, results in increased life expectancy and productivity of citizens.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>Negative impact:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Lower fertility impacts women’s education positively, which in turn lowers the fertility of the next generations.</li>
<li>While the income rises with better health care and better infrastructure development, Fertility drops.</li>
<li>A fall in fertility rate beyond replacement level would have a negative effect on the proportion of the working population, which in turn will affect output in an economy.</li>
<li>After the window of demographic dividend, the huge working age population moves to old age, supported by fewer workers.</li>
<li>Japan was the first country to experience the implications of falling fertility rates. Country is now facing fiscal challenges to meet rising social security costs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Experiments to deal with fertility decline</strong></h4>
<p>Countries across the globe are experimenting with policies to boost fertility.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Germany: </strong>found success in boosting births through liberal labour laws, allowing more parental leave and benefits.</li>
<li><strong>Denmark</strong>: offering state-funded IVF for women below 40 years</li>
<li><strong>Hungary</strong>: Recently nationalized IVF clinics.</li>
<li><strong>Poland</strong>: Gives out monthly cash payments to parents having more than two children</li>
<li><strong>Russia</strong>: Makes one-time payment to parents when their second child is born. Reinstituted the Soviet-era ‘Mother Heroine’ title, who bore and raised more than 10 children amounting to almost a one-time payment of 13 lakh<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Way ahead </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Need of the hour is to ensure liberal labor reforms, encourage higher female labor force participation, higher focus on nutrition and health.</li>
<li>Although India’s working age population will continue to grow for many more decades, it would need to keep an eye on fertility dips.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>What are Implications of lower fertility rate on the economy? What steps could be taken to deal with fertility decline? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><u><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></u></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fertility-rate/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>RBI’s attempt to manage currency could prove to be a costly mistake</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/currency/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Impossible trinity</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>RBI functions</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="currency" class="alignnone wp-image-637056" height="294" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 522px) 100vw, 522px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560.jpg 1600w" width="522"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A currency defence will also impose costs on the economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Legally, the Reserve Bank of India is mandated to target an inflation rate. But with the global economic environment taking a turn for the worse, the central bank has also been targeting the exchange rate. This could prove to be a costly mistake.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a simple definition for inflation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Inflation is the rate of increase in prices over a given period of time. Inflation is typically a broad measure, such as the overall increase in prices or the increase in the cost of living in a country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is exchange rate?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An exchange rate is a rate at which one currency will be exchanged for another currency. Most exchange rates are defined as floating and will rise or fall based on the supply and demand in the market. Some exchange rates are pegged or fixed to the value of a specific country’s currency.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is monetary policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Monetary policy is the control of the quantity of money available in an economy and the channels by which new money is supplied. Economic statistics such as gross domestic product (GDP), the rate of inflation, and industry and sector-specific growth rates influence monetary policy strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is fixed exchange rate in simple words?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A fixed exchange rate is a regime applied by a government or central bank that ties the country’s official currency exchange rate to another country’s currency or the price of gold. The purpose of a fixed exchange rate system is to keep a currency’s value within a narrow band.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="currency" class="alignnone wp-image-637058" height="346" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 519px) 100vw, 519px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dollar-kS6F-621x414%40LiveMint-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dollar-kS6F-621x414%40LiveMint-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dollar-kS6F-621x414%40LiveMint.jpg 621w" width="519"/>What is a simple definition of capital?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Capital is a broad term that can describe anything that confers value or benefit to its owners, such as a factory and its machinery, intellectual property like patents, or the financial assets of a business or an individual.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is meant by the impossible trinity?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Many economists think of possible policy responses to capital flows in terms of the so-called “impossible trinity,” or “policy trilemma”, according to which, with an open capital account, a central bank cannot simultaneously exercise monetary control and target the exchange rate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>A currency defence will impose costs on the economy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Little economic gain</strong>: Some may believe that a stronger currency gives the impression of economic stability and generates confidence in the economy. But there is an inherent contradiction between artificially propping up the rupee and the country’s growth prospects. Very little economic gain will accrue from turning the currency’s value into a political issue.</li>
<li><strong>Inflation should be tackled through monetary policy</strong>: Understandably, a depreciating currency leads to concerns over higher imported inflation. But inflation should be tackled through monetary policy, while exchange rate management should be linked to growth. Not the other way around.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Significance of currency defence for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-global-trade-in-rupees/">foreign exchange reserves</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Decline by 10 per cent:</strong> A large part of the current relative strength of the rupee vis-à-vis other currencies is due to the sale of dollars by the RBI  it has lost more than 10 per cent of its foreign reserves in the space of about nine months.</li>
<li><strong>Why country needs foreign exchange:</strong> A developing economy needs foreign exchange to finance its international transactions for both the current account (goods and services) and capital account (assets) transactions.</li>
<li><strong>Cost involved:</strong> The benefits of this stock are obvious, but there are also costs associated with the holding of these.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong><img alt="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-global-trade-in-rupees/" class="alignnone wp-image-637059" height="340" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 603px) 100vw, 603px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131.jpg 1600w" width="603"/>We should follow Tenfold Path to manage Exchange Rate Volatility rather monetary policy path</strong></h4>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong><u>(1) Selling dollars</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The first course of action has been selling dollars in the spot forex market.</li>
<li>This is fairly straightforward, but has limits as all crises are associated with declining reserves.</li>
<li>While this money is meant for a rainy day, they may just be less than adequate.</li>
<li>The idea of RBI selling dollars works well in the currency market, which is kept guessing how much the central bank is willing to sell at any point of time.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(2) NRI deposits</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The second tool used is aimed at garnering non-resident Indian (NRI) deposits.</li>
<li>It was done in 1998 and 2000 through Resurgent India bonds and India Millennium Deposits, when banks reached out asking NRIs to put in money with attractive interest rates.</li>
<li>The forex risk was borne by Indian banks.</li>
<li>This is always a useful way for the country to mobilize a good sum of forex, though the challenge is when the debt has to be redeemed.</li>
<li>At the time of deposits, the rates tend to be attractive, but once the crisis ends, the same rate cannot be offered on deposit renewals.</li>
<li>Therefore, the idea has limitations.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(3) Let oil importers buy dollars themselves</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The third option exercised often involves getting oil importing companies to buy dollars directly through a facility extended by a public sector bank.</li>
<li>Its advantage is that these deals are not in the open and so the market does not witness a large demand for dollars on this account.</li>
<li>It is more of a sentiment cooling exercise.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(4) Let exporters trade in dollars</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Another tool involves a directive issued for all exporters to mandatorily bring in their dollars on receipt that are needed for future imports.</li>
<li>This acts against an artificial dollar supply reduction due to exporter hold-backs for profit.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(5) Liberalized Exchange Rate</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The other weapon, once used earlier, is to curb the amount of dollars one can take under the Liberalized Exchange Rate Management System.</li>
<li>This can be for current account purposes like travel, education, healthcare, etc.</li>
<li>The amounts are not large, but it sends out a strong signal.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(6) Forward-trade marketing</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Another route used by RBI is to deal in the forward-trade market.</li>
<li>Its advantage is that a strong signal is sent while controlling volatility, as RBI conducts transactions where only the net amount gets transacted finally.</li>
<li>It has the same power as spot transactions, but without any significant withdrawal of forex from the system.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(7) Currency swaps</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The other tool in India’s armoury is the concept of swaps.</li>
<li>This became popular post 2013, when banks collected foreign currency non-resident deposits with a simultaneous swap with RBI, which in effect took on the foreign exchange risk.</li>
<li>Hence, it was different from earlier bond and deposit schemes.</li>
<li><strong>Most preferred options by the RBI</strong></li>
<li>Above discussed instruments have been largely direct in nature, with the underlying factors behind demand-supply being managed by the central bank.</li>
<li>Of late, RBI has gone in for more policy-oriented approaches and the last three measures announced are in this realm.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(8) Allowing banks to work in the NDF market</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>First was allowing banks to work in the non-deliverable forwards (NDF) market.</li>
<li>This is a largely overseas speculative market that has a high potential to influence domestic sentiment on our currency.</li>
<li>Here, forward transactions take place without real inflows or outflows, with only price differences settled in dollars.</li>
<li>This was a major pain point in the past, as banks did not have access to this segment.</li>
<li>By permitting Indian banks to operate here, the rates in this market and in domestic markets have gotten equalized.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(9) Capital account for NRI deposits</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>More recently, RBI opened up the capital account on NRI deposits (interest rates than can be offered), external commercial borrowings (amounts that can be raised) and foreign portfolio investments (allowed in lower tenure securities), which has the potential to draw in forex over time.</li>
<li>Interest in these expanded contours may be limited, but the idea is compelling.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(10) Settlement in Rupees</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>RBI’s permission for foreign trade deals to be settled in rupees is quite novel; as India is a net importer, gains can be made if we pay in rupees for imports.</li>
<li>The conditions placed on the use of surpluses could be a dampener for potential transactions.</li>
<li>But the idea is innovative and could also be a step towards taking the rupee international in such a delicate situation.</li>
<li>Clearly, RBI has constantly been exploring ways to address our forex troubles and even newer measures shouldn’t surprise us.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The RBI (which is in charge of monetary policy) should focus on containing inflation, as it is legally mandated to do.</li>
<li>The government (which is in charge of the fiscal policy) should contain its borrowings.</li>
<li>Higher borrowings (fiscal deficit) by the government eat up domestic savings and force the rest of the economic agents to borrow from abroad.</li>
<li>Policymakers (both in the government and the RBI) have to choose what their priority is containing inflation or being hung up on exchange rate and forex levels.</li>
<li>If they choose to contain inflation (that is, by raising interest rates) then it will require sacrificing economic growth. So be prepared for that.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.What do you understand by the term impossible trinity? How should RBI respond to manage currency exchange rate? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/currency/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>100 years of periyar because of whom tamil nadu became modern and progressive</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/periyar/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Vaikom satyagraha</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Social reform movement in tamil nadu</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Periyar" class="alignnone wp-image-637096" height="439" sizes="(max-width: 439px) 100vw, 439px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/71pQGUTHWKL._AC_SS450_-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/71pQGUTHWKL._AC_SS450_-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/71pQGUTHWKL._AC_SS450_-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/71pQGUTHWKL._AC_SS450_.jpg 450w" width="439"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>We celebrate Periyar E.V. Ramasamy’s birth anniversary (September 17) as Social Justice Day.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who is periyar?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Erode Venkatappa Ramasamy, revered as Periyar or Thanthai Periyar, was an Indian social activist and politician who started the Self-Respect Movement and Dravidar Kazhagam. He is known as the ‘Father of the Dravidian movement’. He rebelled against Brahminical dominance and gender and caste inequality in Tamil Nadu.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who started self-respect movement?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The self-respect movement was founded by V.Ramaswamy Naicker, commonly known as Periyar. It was a dynamic social movement aimed at destroying the contemporary Hindu social order in its totality and creating a new, rational society without caste, religion and god.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Periyar" class="alignnone wp-image-637097" height="644" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unnamed-200x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unnamed-200x300.jpg 200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unnamed.jpg 341w" width="429"/>Why Periyar is called as vaikom hero?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>V. Ramasamy Periyar led the famous <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/op-ed-snap-periyar-the-hero-of-vaikom/">Vaikom Sathya Graha</a> in 1924, where the people of down trodden community were prohibited to enter into the temple. Finally the Travancore government relaxed such segregation and allowed the people to enter into the temple. Hence periyar was given the title of ‘Vaikom Hero’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Leadership at a critical juncture</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The satyagraha began with the active support of the Kerala Pradesh Congress Committee.</li>
<li>Within a week all its leaders were behind bars. George Joseph sought directions from Gandhi and C. Rajagopalachari. He also wrote to Periyar pleading with him to lead the satyagraha.</li>
<li>Periyar was in the midst of political work. As he was then the president of the Tamil Nadu Congress Committee, Periyar handed over temporary charge to Rajaji before reaching Vaikom in 1924.</li>
<li>From that date to the day of the victory celebrations in 1925, he was in the struggle giving it leadership at a critical juncture.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Periyar" class="alignnone wp-image-637099" height="809" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 539px) 100vw, 539px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-200x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-200x300.jpg 200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-600x900.jpg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-1200x1800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-scaled.jpg 1707w" width="539"/>Periyar’s role</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Against violence</strong> – Periyar presided over the satyagraha in the face of violence and indignity inflicted by the orthodox and the repression of the police.</li>
<li><strong>Mobilising </strong>– To mobilise support, he visited villages in and around Vaikom and delivered public speeches in several towns.</li>
<li><strong>Gandhi </strong>– When the Kerala leaders asked for Gandhi’s permission to make the satyagraha an all-India affair, Gandhi refused saying that volunteers from Tamil Nadu would keep it alive.</li>
<li><strong>In reports</strong> – the British Resident said in his report to the government of Madras: “In fact, the movement would have collapsed long ago but for the support it has received from outside Travancore…”</li>
<li><strong>Historian T.K. Ravindran</strong> — observes that Periyar’s arrival gave “a new life to the movement”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>His Vision for the future</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Ideas on rationality</strong>: When he presented his thoughts, there was nuance, honesty, and an explicitness, which prompted even people practising different faiths to discuss and debate his ideas on rationality and religion.</li>
<li><strong>Freedom of expression</strong>: Periyar himself said, “Everyone has the right to refute any opinion. But no one has the right to prevent its expression.”</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Eradication of social evils</strong>: Periyar is often referred to as an iconoclast, for the rebellious nature of his ideas and the vigour with which he acted. His vision for the future was a part of all his actions. He did not merely aim at the eradication of social evils; he also wanted to put an end to activities that do not collectively raise standards of society.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-637101" height="424" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 761px) 100vw, 761px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ramasamy-periyar-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ramasamy-periyar-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ramasamy-periyar.jpg 759w" width="761"/>Foundation of rationalism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>He understood the evolution of political thought</strong>: Periyar’s vision was about inclusive growth and freedom of individuals. He was an important ideologue of his day because of the clarity in his political stand. More importantly, he understood the evolution of political thought and was able to glide through time with this.</li>
<li><strong>He presented rationalism as a solid foundation:</strong> For thinking along these lines. He said, “Wisdom lies in thinking. The spearhead of thinking is rationalism.” Periyar was way ahead of his time.</li>
<li><strong>Concern towards poor</strong>: “Whomsoever I love and hate, my principle is the same. That is, the educated, the rich and the administrators should not suck the blood of the poor.”</li>
<li><strong>Periyar proclaimed that he would always stand with the oppressed: </strong>In the fight against oppressors and that his enemy was oppression. There have been several social reformers in Tamil Nadu who shared their revolutionary thoughts with the people in the past century. In that spectrum, Periyar occupies a unique place because he made interactions of multiple worlds possible.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em>Periyar said, “Any opposition not based on rationalism or science or experience, will one day or other, reveal the fraud, selfishness, lies, and conspiracies.”</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>His works against the Bhraminical dominance, oppression of women in Tamil Nadu, caste prevalence are exemplary. Periyar promoted the principles of rationalism, self-respect, women’s rights and eradication of caste. He opposed the exploitation and marginalisation of the people of South India and the imposition of what he considered Indo-Aryan India.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Discuss the future vision of periyar by discussing his role in vaikom satyagraha. Do you think he has placed foundation of rationalism in Tamil Nadu?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><u><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></u></strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/periyar/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>