<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 07:27:54 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>The heavy rainfall and the crazy Banglore flood: A case to study</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/flood/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>urban floods mitigation</p></div></div><h4><img alt="flood" class="alignnone wp-image-638490" height="321" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734.jpg 1600w" width="570"/>Context</h4>
<ul>
<li>The recent events of heavy downpours in short period of time and the recent example of Banglore flood, highlights how cities in India and elsewhere need to adapt to climate change as it brings more extreme rainfall in the future.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is heavy downpour?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A downpour or cloudburst is a sudden and unexpected heavy fall of rain.</li>
<li>It is usually local in nature and of brief duration. Most so-called cloudbursts occur in connection with thunderstorms.</li>
<li>Heavy downpour in short period causes flood, damage to buildings and infrastructure can disrupt transport, communications and connectivity, loss of crops and livestock.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The heavy rainfall and the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/floods/">Banglore flood</a> causes </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rise in built up area: </strong>Lakes and natural depressions may not always fill up during many monsoons so the people who are unaware of hydrology tempts to build and buy in the catchment areas of water-bodies, which will be disastrous when it rains heavily as there is rise in the quantity.</li>
<li><strong>Water-logging: </strong>rainwater and sewage water are forced to build up, which results in water-logging. The highway acts as a dam for the water ,Garbage frequently clogs drains, which limits the flow of sewage, and they are too small to support the weight of the expanding population.</li>
<li><strong>Physical shrinkage of water-bodies</strong>: Destruction of lakes is a major issue .lakes can store the excess water and regulate the flow of water however the pollution of natural water bodies and converting them for development purposes has increased the risks of floods<strong>. </strong>Unplanned growth, Rise in population<strong>, </strong>rise in the built up areas along streams, canals, around the lakes, leaving no storage capacity.</li>
<li><strong>Compromised runoff potential and health hazards</strong>: Choked and encroached drains and lakes, ill designed infrastructure and missing pipes compromising run off potential. Not only the physical quantity of the runoff that poses a hazard. When polluted drains and lakes overflow, the flood can pose a health hazard especially to vulnerable and exposed marginal communities living in informal settlements.</li>
<li><strong>Zero or limited ability to allow infiltration of water: </strong>Encroachments in and around wetlands and green lands harming the natural way of water infiltration and ground water recharge.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of vision in rain water harvesting: </strong>Ignorance towards the tradition rain water harvesting techniques and no or limited vision for creating new systems of rain water harvesting. Exceptionally heavy monsoon rains have been exacerbated by poor urban planning in the Indian tech hub, showing the need for improved water systems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="flood" class="alignnone wp-image-638492" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 641px) 100vw, 641px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/deccan-Herald-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/deccan-Herald-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/deccan-Herald.jpg 708w" width="641"/>What are the reasons behind the frequent floods in urban areas?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Meteorological factors</strong>: change in the weather patterns, increase in the temperature leading to heavy rainfall, sudden downpour, cloudburst, thunderstorms, hailstorms etc.</li>
<li><strong>Hydrological factors</strong>: Natural surface infiltration rate, soil moisture level, presence or absence of Overbank flows, Presence of impervious cover, the occurrence of high tides impeding the drainage in coastal cities.</li>
<li><strong>Man-Made factors: </strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Unplanned urbanization: </strong>Unplanned settlement is one of the main cause of urban flooding. Blocking of natural drainage pathways through construction activity and encroachment on catchment areas, streams, rivers, lakebeds. Reduced infiltration and ground water recharge of water, destruction of lakes, Land-use changes (e.g. surface sealing due to urbanization, deforestation) increase runoff and sedimentation. Inefficiency or non-maintenance of infrastructure etc.</li>
<li><strong>Outdated Drainage systems</strong>: The old and ill-maintained drainage system is one of the main factor making cities in India vulnerable to flooding</li>
<li><strong>Encroachments on and around water-bodies: </strong>Illegal Habitations started growing into towns and cities alongside rivers and watercourses. As a result of this, the capacity of the natural drains has decreased, resulting in flooding.</li>
<li><strong>Climate Change: </strong>Climate change due to various anthropogenic events has led to extreme weather events, increasing temperature which resulting in heavy rainfall in one part while drought and dry spells in other.</li>
<li><strong>Poor Solid Waste Management System:</strong> Indiscriminate disposal of solid waste, poor waste management system, clogging drains because of accumulation of non-biodegradable wastes are major concerns. Domestic, commercial and industrial waste and dumping of it into the drains also contribute significantly to reducing their capacities.</li>
<li><strong>Reduced Seepage:</strong> use of hard and non-porous construction material making the soil impervious, reducing the seepage capability in no of cities in India.</li>
<li><strong>Weak Implementation and lack of awareness:</strong>Even with provisions of rainwater harvesting, sustainable urban drainage systems, etc, in regulatory mechanisms like the Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA), adoption at user end as well as enforcement agencies remains weak.</li>
<li><strong>No Community Participation:</strong>Flood control measures planned without participation of the affected community are unsustainable as they do not meet the needs of relevant stakeholders.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to prevent the urban floods and prevent losses?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Developing climate Resilient Infrastructure:</strong> using permeable material for roads and pavement, green roofs and harvesting systems in buildings. To reduce the burden of road infrastructure in cities Outer Ring Road should be explored. Innovative approaches like Sponge Cities wetland restoration, flushing systems using collected rooftop water, public spaces as flexible water retention facilities can be applied to Indian urban areas.</li>
<li><strong>Use of technology in Early Warning Systems and Communication: </strong>Early-warning systems using sensors across waterbodies and drains, and a network of communication for hotspots of emerging flood risk in the wet-season should be put in place. Providing real-time data where traditional systems fail. Tools such as predictive precipitation modelingcan help do that and are also able to link it with the adaptive capacity of urban land use.</li>
<li><strong>Proper management and regular upgrade of Urban Drainage System:</strong> drains need to be cleaned on a regular basis to permit the free flow of water .Proper management of the drainage system is necessary to ensure that the water does not get stored in one place. Watershed management and emergency drainage plan should be clearly enunciated in policy.</li>
<li><strong>Rainwater Harvesting</strong>: It will serve the twin purposes of lowering the peak runoff and raising the groundwater table. Many municipal corporations in India have already made rainwater harvesting compulsory<strong>. </strong></li>
<li><strong>Conservation of Water Bodies: </strong>Urban water bodies like lakes, tanks, and ponds also play a very important role in the management of urban flooding by reducing the flood water run-off by capturing it.</li>
<li><strong>Holistic approach: </strong>Improved monitoring, forecasting, and decision-support systems. Find out the different method for improving the preparedness for urban flooding.</li>
<li><strong>Responsibility on every stakeholder: </strong>Locally, citizens, local ward officials and staff will need to work together to minimize dumping of solid waste and garbage in storm-water drains. As this is a socio –political problem, public participation awareness and responsibility of citizen is the need of the hour. To develop a long-lasting solution, all parties must acknowledge the issues and adopt a thorough strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What we as citizens can do on a personal level to prevent the urban environment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Raising voice at all available forums and platforms</li>
<li>Making politicians and bureaucrats accountable</li>
<li>Refuse to buy a house in the encroached lands.</li>
<li>Applying methods of rain water harvesting on individual level.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Exceptionally heavy monsoon rains have been exacerbated by poor urban planning in the Indian tech hub, showing the need for improved water systems.</li>
<li>Urbanization is a global and inevitable process, and with cities as engines of the economy, built-up areas will continue to grow. But we need to draw upon these experiences and the growing perils of climate change and extreme rain events and change course.</li>
<li>According to UN projections, by 2050 more than 68% of the world’s population could be concentrated in urban areas.</li>
<li>In this context, resilience-based strategies should be adopted to improve the capacity to handle the crisis arising out of climate change.</li>
<li>Wetlands are the kidneys of the earth, let’s keep it healthy.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What are the factors causing flood in the urban cities? What are the measures to prevent the urban flooding keeping in mind the sustainable development? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/flood/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Multilateralism will open pandora of opportunities for India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/multilateralism/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>SCO and QUAD</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>multilateralism</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="multilateralism" class="alignnone wp-image-638494" height="399" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 599px) 100vw, 599px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/brics-621x414-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/brics-621x414-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/brics-621x414-1.jpg 621w" width="599"/>Context</strong></h4>
<p>India may give up its strategic balancing of China and West if the Ukraine war weakens Russia. Because for major defence supplies India is dependent on Russia.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/growing-salience-of-multilateralism/"><strong>What is the concept of multilateralism?</strong></a></p>
<ul>
<li>Process of organizing relations between groups of three or more states. Beyond that basic quantitative aspect, multilateralism is generally considered to comprise certain qualitative elements or principles that shape the character of the arrangement or institution.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is SCO?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Shanghai Cooperation Organization (SCO) is a Eurasian political, economic and security organization.</li>
<li><strong>Global share:</strong> In terms of geographic scope and population, it is the world’s largest regional organization, covering approximately 60% of the area of Eurasia, 40% of the world population, and more than 30% of global GDP.</li>
<li><strong>Members</strong>: The SCO currently comprises eight Member States. They are- China, India, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Russia, Pakistan, Tajikistan and Uzbekistan.</li>
<li><strong>Headquarters</strong>: Beijing, China.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is QUAD?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (QSD), commonly known as the Quad.</li>
<li>It is a strategic security dialogue.</li>
<li><strong>Members</strong>: Australia, India, Japan, and the United States.</li>
<li><strong>Origin</strong>: The dialogue was initiated in 2007.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="multilateralism" class="alignnone wp-image-638498" height="562" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 538px) 100vw, 538px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-287x300.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-287x300.jpeg 287w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-978x1024.jpeg 978w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-768x804.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-860x900.jpeg 860w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2.jpeg 1200w" width="538"/>Which factors forced India to have more engagements with QUAD?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Chinese threat has been largely responsible in shaping New Delhi’s Indo Pacific Policy.</li>
<li>The China’s Belt and Road initiative and the growing China’s presence in India’s neighborhood- as evident from China’s investment not only in Pakistan and Myanmar, but also in Nepal and Sri Lanka. Because of such activities India felt encircled.</li>
<li>The very launch of the QUAD initiative was the reaction to China’s assertiveness in the Indo Pacific region.</li>
<li>India agreed to upgrade the quad meeting at the ministerial level only after the gunmen attack of 2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How India is maintaining balance between the West and China-Russia Alliance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Plurilateralism</strong>: India continued to believe in <strong>plurilateralism</strong>, a doctrine elucidated by external affairs Minister S Jaishankar in his book <strong>‘The Indian Way</strong>’.</li>
<li><strong>Member of both QUAD and SCO</strong>: Along with QUAD, India also took membership of SCO. It means India dealing with the USA and Japan on one side and Russia and China on the other.</li>
<li><strong>Simultaneously dealing with many powers: </strong>India is engaging with competing powers like the USA, China, the EU or Russia at the same time.</li>
<li><strong>Multipolar world: </strong>India stands in favor of a <strong>multipolar world</strong> where the plurality of power centers would allow her to play one pole against the other. In this context, New Delhi wants Russia to remain an important player.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="multilateralism" class="alignnone wp-image-638500" height="353" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 602px) 100vw, 602px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-300x176.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-300x176.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1.jpg 637w" width="602"/><br/>
What are India’s concerns regarding the West created world order?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The stand on Multilateralism goes together with India’s reservations (not being completely satisfied) against the West’s past hegemony and the international orders that were established after 1945.</li>
<li>MEA S Jaishankar emphasises that the West has imposed norms on the world that need to be dismantled. He says, “The key of western durability till now is the set of institutions and practices that it progressively but firmly established in the period of its dominance”.</li>
<li>The world order and the institutions are created and supported by the West by narratives that serve the West well, while diminishing its competitors.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the steps taken by India to deal with the West created world order and institutions ?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s engagement with the other regional organizations like BRICS, SCO, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Doctrine of Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam: </strong>India’s foreign policy has been based on the philosophy of Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam.</li>
<li><strong>UN Reforms:</strong> Efforts towards bringing reforms in the UNs.</li>
<li><strong>Shift from Non-Alignment to Multi-Alignment:</strong> Multi-alignment is the very essence of India’s foreign policy and the economic policy of India today. Promotion of multilateralism by engaging with many poles simultaneously.</li>
<li><strong>Various Multilateral initiatives: </strong>India has taken the lead in promoting various multilateral initiatives like International Solar Alliance, proposing CCIT for combating terrorism, Asia-Africa Growth corridor.</li>
<li><strong>Collaborating with Like-minded Countries: </strong>India could work closely with the <strong>Alliance for Multilateralism </strong>(an initiative launched by Germany and France) to shape both the alliance itself and the reform agenda at large.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is Russia important for India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Military supplies</strong>: India is heavily dependent on Russia for its military supplies with more than two-third of its weapons coming from Russia. For example: S-400 is the recent supply to India by Russia.</li>
<li><strong>Balancing China:</strong> Russia is important for India to balance China. More isolation of Russia may push Russia closer to China.</li>
<li><strong>To promote multilateralism</strong>: To maintain multilateral world order Russia is a major player or partner for India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A multilateral world order with power decentralized between all the regions and all the economic strata is critical for any sustainable model of peace and prosperity to be gained. The UN and similar bodies must recognize the need of the hour and must reform or else they will perish in yet another set of protectionism, distrust, and possible large-scale military conflicts like Russia- Ukraine.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What are the concerns of India regarding the present world order created by the West? </strong><strong>How can India promote multilateralism by playing a balancing role between the QUAD and the SCO?  What is the importance of Russia for India in the present global situation? Explain.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/multilateralism/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>On reservations for disempowered Dalit Christians and Muslims, a question of government’s intent</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dalit/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>social justice</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="dalit" class="alignnone wp-image-638560" height="367" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 551px) 100vw, 551px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1457603210-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1457603210-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1457603210.jpeg 555w" width="551"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Union government intends to appoint a national commission to study the status of Dalits (ex “untouchable” castes) belonging to the Muslim and Christian communities. Aim of study to check the socio-economic condition of Muslims and Christian Dalits on par with Hindu, Sikh, Buddhist Dalits.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Current reservation policy</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At present, scheduled caste reservation is applicable only to schedule caste (Dalit) belongs to Hindu, Sikh, Buddhist. Currently it is unavailable for schedule caste belongs to Muslims and Christians.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why Muslim and Christian Dalit needs reservation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2008 review-study commissioned by the National Commission of Minorities (NCM) and housed in the Sociology Department of <a href="https://indianexpress.com/section/cities/delhi/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Delhi</a> The remit of the study was to conduct a comprehensive review of already existing social-scientific evidence that might offer answers to three questions.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>What is the contemporary status of Dalit Muslims (DMs) and Dalit Christians (DCs) in terms of their material well-being and social status?</li>
<li>How does their situation compare with that of: a) non-Dalits of their own communities, and b) Dalits of other communities?</li>
<li>Do the caste disabilities suffered by these groups justify state intervention?</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong><img alt="dalit" class="alignnone wp-image-638564" height="308" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 547px) 100vw, 547px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537.jpg 777w" width="547"/>What were the findings of study?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The study reviewed two main kinds of available evidence, ethnographic-descriptive and macro-statistical, in addition to semi-academic NGO reports and publications.</li>
<li>The survey of ethnographic materials began with the finding that the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-caste-system/">existence of caste divisions</a> – including the presence of ex-untouchable castes recognised as such – among both Muslims and Christians – was beyond dispute.</li>
<li>DMs and DCs were identified and segregated much like their counterparts in the Hindu or Sikh communities.</li>
<li>Evidence was tabulated on five forms of caste-based social discrimination – the practice untouchability; enforced ban on inter-marriage; occupational segregation; social and cultural segregation and finally, economic discrimination.</li>
<li>The most common instances were separate mosques or churches (or hierarchically segregated seating); separate burial grounds; strict prohibition on inter-marriage with very severe punishments (sometimes extending to murder) for breaking this taboo; and general avoidance of social interaction and cooperation.</li>
<li>The main findings were that DMs are clearly the worst off among all Dalits, while DCs are somewhat better off than other Dalits except Sikh Dalits (who are by far the best off, especially in the rural sector).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why DMs and DCs doesn’t have reservation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The courts accept that “caste survives conversion” but complain about the lack of reliable data. No recognition, no data; no data, no recognition.</li>
<li>Informal guesstimates (based on the 2001 Census and the 2004-05 NSSO survey) place the proportion of DMs at 1 per cent or less of the Muslim population, and DCs as anything between 40-50 per cent of the Christian population of India.</li>
<li>As per the 2011 Census, Muslims are 14.2 per cent and Christians 2.3 per cent of our population. Taken together, DMs and DCs are likely to form less than 2 per cent of the total Dalit population of India, more than 90 per cent of which is Hindu.</li>
<li>According to experts Adding DMs and DCs will not rock the boat of reservation, since the increment will be roughly one-fifth of the 10 per cent reservation readily granted to the upper castes as the Economically Weaker Sections.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What efforts have been made to include Muslims and Christians of Dalit origin among SCs?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>After 1990, a number of Private Member’s Bills were brought in Parliament for this purpose.</li>
<li>In 1996, a government Bill called The Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Orders (Amendment) Bill was drafted, but in view of a divergence of opinions, the Bill was not introduced in Parliament.</li>
<li>Then government headed by PM Manmohan Singh set up two important panels:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Ranganath Misra Commission:</strong> The National Commission for Religious and Linguistic Minorities, popularly known as the Ranganath Misra Commission, in October 2004 and</li>
<li><strong>Sachar Committee:</strong> A seven-member high-level committee headed by former Chief Justice of Delhi High Court Rajinder Sachar to study the social, economic, and educational condition of Muslims in March 2005.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What did they recommend?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Sachar Committee Report</u></strong> observed that the social and economic situation of Dalit Muslims and Dalit Christians did not improve after conversion.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Ranganath Misra Commission</u></strong>, which submitted its report in May 2007, recommended that SC status should be completely de-linked from religion and Scheduled Castes should be made fully religion-neutral like Scheduled Tribes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="dalit" class="alignnone wp-image-638566" height="321" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 609px) 100vw, 609px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244.jpg 1200w" width="609"/>Reception to these recommendations</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The report was tabled in Parliament in 2009, but its recommendation was <strong><u>not accepted</u></strong> in view of inadequate field data and corroboration with the actual situation on the ground.</li>
<li>Few studies, commissioned by the National Commission for Minorities, was also <strong><u>not considered reliable due to insufficient data.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Schedule caste community from all religion India suffers from same fate of untouchability. Change of religion unfortunately, have change their social status. If 70+ year of reservation of Dalit in Hindu haven’t substantially change their social destiny, we have to think beyond reservation for social dignity and economic empowerment of schedule castes in India.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Reservation policy in India is religion based and not based on overall social discrimination. Comment in the context of demand for Dalit reservation extension to Christians and Muslims Dalits.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dalit/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the Dharavi Redevelopment Project?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dharavi-redevelopment-project/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Dharavi</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Slum rehabilitation</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-638844" height="424" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 563px) 100vw, 563px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dharavi-300x226.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dharavi-300x226.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dharavi.jpg 635w" width="563"/></p>
<p>The Maharashtra government gave the go-ahead for fresh tenders in the Dharavi redevelopment project, almost two decades after it was first proposed.</p>
<h4>About Dharavi</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dharavi, infamous as one of the world’s largest slums, is located in the heart of India’s financial capital – Mumbai.</li>
<li>A city within a city, it is one unending stretch of narrow dirty lanes, open sewers and cramped huts.</li>
<li>While the land (area of 535 acres) is owned by the government, the houses are maintained by individuals.</li>
<li>The Dharavi slum came into being in 1884. It was originally inhibited by fisherfolk when the area was still creeks, swamps.</li>
<li>It became attractive to migrant workers from South Mumbai and others when the swamp began to fill in due to natural and artificial causes.</li>
<li>The area grew as poor rural Indians migrated to urban Mumbai.</li>
<li>Today, an estimated 600,000 to 1 million people live crammed in Dharavi.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Economic significance of Dharavi</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dharavi stands near to India’s richest business district, the Bandra-Kurla Complex, where commercial office premiums are among the highest in the country.</li>
<li>The slum sprawl, spread over 2.8 sq.km. is home to an informal leather and pottery industry which employs over a lakh people.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the Dharavi Redevelopment Project all about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The state had envisaged this sprawl be transformed into a cluster of high-rises with improved urban infrastructure.</li>
<li>It entailed resettling 68,000 people, including slum dwellers and those with commercial establishments.</li>
<li>The state was to provide 300-sqft houses for free to residents with proof that their slum structure was in existence before January 1, 2000.</li>
<li>The project was initially mooted in 2004, but never got off the ground due to various reasons.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When redevelopment was first proposed?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 1999, the government first proposed to redevelop Dharavi.</li>
<li>Thereafter, the government of Maharashtra in the year 2003-04 decided to redevelop Dharavi as an integrated planned township.</li>
<li>An action plan for redevelopment was approved by issuing a government resolution.</li>
<li>It was decided to develop Dharavi by using land as a resource to cross-subsidie the cost of development through a sale component on the basis of the Slum Rehabilitation Scheme.</li>
<li>The government also decided to notify the whole of Dharavi as an undeveloped area and to appoint a Special Planning Authority for its development.</li>
<li>In 2011, the government cancelled all tenders and drew up a master plan.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dharavi-redevelopment-project/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Government approves 50% incentive of project cost for setting up Semiconductor Units</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/50-incentive-of-project-cost-for-setting-up-semiconductor-units/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Programme for Development of Semiconductors and Display Manufacturing Ecosystem</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The Union Cabinet has approved a uniform incentive of 50% of the project cost for setting up semiconductor, display and compound semiconductor fabrication units.</p>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="incentive" class="alignnone wp-image-638846" height="290" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 426px) 100vw, 426px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vedanta-300x204.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vedanta-300x204.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vedanta.jpg 640w" width="426"/></p>
<ul>
<li>Maharashtra is witnessing a political firestorm.</li>
<li>The Vedanta Limited shifted its decision to set up a $20 billion Vedanta-Foxconn semiconductor manufacturing facility in neighbouring Gujarat, despite finalising its location near Pune (Mh).</li>
<li>Foxconn is a major chip supplier to Apple. It has suspended its operations in the Chinese tech hub of Shenzhen and is now shifting to India.</li>
<li>Bigger companies, such as Intel, TSMC, Samsung, etc., have announced such plans.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em>Spats between states over the location of critical industries display the grim picture of competitive bidding in India. This portrays India’s negative image as against ease of doing business.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>About the Incentive Scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme has been named the “<strong><u>Programme for Development of Semiconductors and Display Manufacturing Ecosystem</u></strong>.”</li>
<li>Previously, the three schemes had an incentive range of 30-50%.</li>
<li>While incentives for setting up semiconductor fabrication were based on the size of the chip, for display fabrication and compound semiconductor fabs, the incentives were largely 30% of the total cost of the project.</li>
<li>This scheme aims to <strong><u>project India’s position as global hub for electronics manufacturing</u></strong> with semiconductors as the foundational building block.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need such an incentive?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Huge Investments involved: </strong>Semiconductor Fabrication facility requires many expensive devices to function. Complex tools and equipment are required to test quality and move silicon from location to location within the ultra-clean confines of the plant.</li>
<li><strong>Economy of scale:  </strong> In semiconductor fabrication, a high volume production is required to be maintain so as to meet the increasing demand of the marketplace, at the same time, a strong financial backing as Indian market is very much uncertain about financial fluctuations.</li>
<li><strong>Requirement highly skilled labour:</strong>   Semiconductor fabrication is a multiple-step sequence of photolithographic and chemical processing steps during which electronic circuits are gradually created on a wafer made of pure semiconducting material. This actually requires high skills.</li>
<li><strong>Scarcity of raw materials</strong>: From a value-chain perspective, it needs silicon, Germanium &amp; Gallium arsenide and Silicon carbide which are not available in India and needs to be imported.</li>
<li><strong>Uncertain Indian market</strong>: A semiconductor fabrication facility in India cannot independently rely on Indian customers for their entire sales structure. They have to maintain overseas customer base to balance inflections from Indian market due to market trends, government policies etc.</li>
<li><strong>Disposal of hazardous waste</strong>: Many toxic materials are used in the fabrication process such as arsenic, antimony, and phosphorus. Hazardous impact on the environment by the industry may act as an impediment to India’s commitment to mitigate climate change.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other supportive initiatives in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>India Semiconductor Mission (ISM):</strong> It was announced with the aim to attract large-scale investments for manufacturing facilities in the midst of a global chip crisis.</li>
<li><strong>Make in India:</strong> This aims to transform India into a global hub for Electronic System Design and Manufacturing (ESDM).</li>
<li><strong>PLI scheme:</strong> In December 2021 the Centre sanctioned ₹76,000 crore under the production-linked incentive (PLI) scheme to encourage the manufacturing of various semiconductor goods within India.</li>
<li><strong>DLI scheme:</strong> It offers financial incentives, design infrastructure support across various stages of development and deployment of semiconductor design for Integrated Circuits (ICs), Chipsets, System on Chips (SoCs), Systems &amp; IP Cores and semiconductor linked design.</li>
<li><strong>Digital RISC-V (DIR-V) program: </strong>It intends to enable the production of microprocessors in India in the upcoming days achieving industry-grade silicon and design wins by December 2023.</li>
<li><strong>India Semiconductor Mission (ISM):</strong> The vision is to build a vibrant semiconductor and display design and innovation ecosystem to enable India’s emergence as a global hub for electronics manufacturing and design</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Policy framework</strong>: As foundry setup is highly Capital intensive, it must be supported with a solid long term plan and financial backing. This backing is required from the entrepreneur &amp; the government both.</li>
<li><strong>Fiscal sustenance:</strong> In text of Indian Government as tax holiday, subsidy, zero duty, financial investment etc. will play an important role in promoting the Fab along with the semiconductor industry in India; this will put further pressure on already large Fiscal Deficit.</li>
<li><strong>Support Infrastructure:</strong> World class, sustainable infrastructure, as required by a modern Fab be provided, with swift transportation, large quantity of pure water, uninterrupted electricity, communication, pollutant free environment etc.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/50-incentive-of-project-cost-for-setting-up-semiconductor-units/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Recession unlikely to hit India: S&amp;P</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/recession-unlikely-to-hit-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Recessions, Depression</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="recession" class="aligncenter wp-image-638845" height="312" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 532px) 100vw, 532px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-1-300x176.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-1-300x176.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-1.jpg 670w" width="532"/></strong></p>
<p>Global rating agency S&amp;P has said that even though the US and the Euro zone are headed towards recession, India is unlikely to face the impact given the not-so-coupled nature of its economy with the global economy.</p>
<h4><strong>How is India immune to global recession?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian economy is a lot decoupled from the global economy than we normally think of, given its large domestic demand.</li>
<li>India has enough forex reserves on one hand and domestic companies have managed to maintain healthy balance sheets.</li>
<li>In fact, India was never coupled fully with the global economy and so is relatively independent of global markets.</li>
<li>Elsewhere, a lot depends on how global fund flows behave if there is a recession in the U.S. and Europe.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Recession?</strong></h4>
<p><strong><img alt="recession" class="alignnone wp-image-631660" height="240" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 442px) 100vw, 442px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-300x163.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-300x163.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-1024x555.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-768x416.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession.jpg 1026w" width="442"/></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>A recession is a significant decline in economic activity that lasts for months or even years.</li>
<li>Experts declare a recession when a nation’s economy experiences negative GDP, rising levels of unemployment, falling retail sales, and contracting measures of income and manufacturing for an extended period of time.</li>
<li>Recessions are considered an unavoidable part of the business cycle—or the regular cadence of expansion and contraction that occurs in a nation’s economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What causes Recessions?</strong></h4>
<p>These phenomena are some of the main drivers of a recession:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>A sudden economic shock:</strong> An economic shock is a surprise problem that creates serious financial damage. The coronavirus outbreak, which shut down economies worldwide, is a more recent example of a sudden economic shock.</li>
<li><strong>Excessive debt:</strong> When individuals or businesses take on too much debt, the cost of servicing the debt can grow to the point where they can’t pay their bills. Growing debt defaults and bankruptcies then capsize the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Asset bubbles:</strong> When investing decisions are driven by emotion, bad economic outcomes aren’t far behind. Investors can become too optimistic during a strong economy.</li>
<li><strong>Too much inflation:</strong> Inflation is the steady, upward trend in prices over time. Inflation isn’t a bad thing per se, but excessive inflation is a dangerous phenomenon. Central banks control inflation by raising interest rates, and higher interest rates depress economic activity.</li>
<li><strong>Too much deflation:</strong> While runaway inflation can create a recession, deflation can be even worse. Deflation is when prices decline over time, which causes wages to contract, which further depresses prices. When a deflationary feedback loop gets out of hand, people and business stop spending, which undermines the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Technological change:</strong> New inventions increase productivity and help the economy over the long term, but there can be short-term periods of adjustment to technological breakthroughs. In the 19th century, there were waves of labour-saving technological improvements.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What’s the difference between Recession and Depression?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Recessions and depressions have similar causes, but the overall impact of a depression is much, much worse.</li>
<li>There are greater job losses, higher unemployment and steeper declines in GDP.</li>
<li>Most of all, a depression lasts longer—years, not months—and it takes more time for the economy to recover.</li>
<li>Economists do not have a set definition or fixed measurements to show what counts as a depression. Suffice to say, all the impacts of a depression are deeper and last longer.</li>
<li>In the past century, the US has faced just one depression: The Great Depression.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The Great Depression</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Great Depression started in 1929 and lasted through 1933, although the economy didn’t really recover until World War II, nearly a decade later.</li>
<li>During the Great Depression, unemployment rose to 25% and the GDP fell by 30%.</li>
<li>It was the most unprecedented economic collapse in modern US history.</li>
<li>By way of comparison, the Great Recession was the worst recession since the Great Depression.</li>
<li>During the Great Recession, unemployment peaked around 10% and the recession officially lasted from December 2007 to June 2009, about a year and a half.</li>
<li>Some economists fear that the coronavirus recession could morph into a depression, depending how long it lasts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How long do recessions last?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Gulf War Recession (July 1990 to March 1991):</strong> At the start of the 1990s, the U.S. went through a short, eight-month recession, partly caused by spiking oil prices during the First Gulf War.</li>
<li><strong>The Great Recession (2008-2009):</strong> As mentioned, the Great Recession was caused in part by a bubble in the real estate market.</li>
<li><strong>Covid-19 Recession:</strong> The most recent recession began in February 2020 and lasted only two months, making it the shortest US recession in history.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Can we predict a recession?</strong></h4>
<p>Given that economic forecasting is uncertain, predicting future recessions is far from easy. However, the following warning signs can give you more time to figure out how to prepare for a recession before it happens:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>An inverted yield curve:</strong> The yield curve is a graph that plots the market value—or the yield—of a range. When long-term yields are lower than short-term yields, it shows that investors are worried about a recession. This phenomenon is known as a yield curve inversion, and it has predicted past recessions.</li>
<li><strong>Declines in consumer confidence:</strong> Consumer spending is the main driver of the US economy. If surveys show a sustained drop in consumer confidence, it could be a sign of impending trouble for the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Drop in the Leading Economic Index (LEI):</strong> Published monthly by the Conference Board, the LEI strives to predict future economic trends. It looks at factors like applications for unemployment insurance, new orders for manufacturing and stock market performance.</li>
<li><strong>Sudden stock market declines:</strong> A large, sudden decline in stock markets could be a sign of a recession coming on, since investors sell off parts and sometimes all of their holdings in anticipation of an economic slowdown.</li>
<li><strong>Rising unemployment:</strong> It goes without saying that if people are losing their jobs, it’s a bad sign for the economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does a recession affect individuals?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>We may lose your job during a recession, as unemployment levels rise. It becomes much harder to find a job replacement since more people are out of work.</li>
<li>People who keep their jobs may see cuts to pay and benefits, and struggle to negotiate future pay raises.</li>
<li>Investments in stocks, bonds, real estate and other assets can lose money in a recession, reducing your savings and upsetting your plans for retirement.</li>
<li>Business owners make fewer sales during a recession, and may even be forced into bankruptcy.</li>
<li>With more people unable to pay their bills during a recession, lenders tighten standards for mortgages, car loans, and other types of financing.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/recession-unlikely-to-hit-india/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Ratan Tata, KT Thomas appointed trustees of PM CARES</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ratan-tata-appointed-trustee-pm-cares/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PM CARES</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with PM CARES</p></div></div><p>The Union government has appointed veteran industrialist Ratan Tata, former Supreme Court judge K.T. Thomas, and former Lok Sabha Deputy Speaker Kariya Munda as trustees of the PM CARES Fund.</p>
<h4><strong>PM CARES Fund</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PM CARES Fund was created on 28 March 2020 following the COVID-19 pandemic in India.</li>
<li>The fund will be used for combat, containment and relief efforts against the coronavirus outbreak and similar pandemic like situations in the future.</li>
<li>The PM is the chairman of the trust. Members will include the defence, home and finance ministers.</li>
<li>The fund will also enable micro-donations. The minimum donation accepted is ₹10 (14¢ US).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Some intriguing facts about PM-CARES fund</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>PM CARES has been created not by law, not by notification, but by the mere creation of a webpage, and set up last year in March to raise funds for those affected by the COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
<li>The page lists its structure, functions and duties in an arbitrary manner.</li>
<li>The official appeals for funds are made under the national emblem.</li>
<li>The most significant lie of this sworn statement is that the Government has no control over the Fund.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The other funds</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) National Disaster Response Fund (NDRF)</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The statutorily constituted NDRF was established under the Disaster Management (DM) Act of 2005.</li>
<li>The NDRF is mandated to be accountable, and answerable under the RTI Act, being a public authority, and auditable by the Comptroller and Auditor General of India.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Disaster Response Fund</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The DM Act also provided for a Disaster Response Fund — state and district level funds (besides the national level).</li>
<li>It also collects and uses the donations at the local level, with mandatory transparency and audit provisions.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Prime Minister’s National Relief Fund</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is the PMNRF operative since the days of Jawaharlal Nehru. It was established with public contributions to assist displaced persons from Pakistan.</li>
<li>The resources are now utilised primarily to render immediate relief to families of those killed in natural calamities and to the victims of the major accidents and riots.</li>
<li>However, it has the President of India and the Leader of Opposition also as trustees.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues over PM-CARES Fund</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>No defined purpose:</strong> It is deliberately ignored while a new, controversial, unanswerable, and ‘non-accountable vehicle is created; its character is not spelt out till today.</li>
<li><strong>Non-accountable:</strong> The government seems to consider statutory provisions for enquiry and information seeking to be embarrassing obstacles.</li>
<li><strong>Centralization of donations:</strong> It centralises the collection of donations and its utility, which is not only against the federal character but also practically inconvenient. The issue is seeming, the trusteeship of the fund.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Questions and gaps</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Law/statute:</strong> The PM CARES Fund was neither created by the Constitution of India nor by any statute.</li>
<li><strong>Authority:</strong> If that is the case, under what authority does it use the designation of the Prime Minister, designated symbols of the nation, the tricolour and the official (gov.in) website of the PMO, and grant tax concessions through an ordinance.</li>
<li><strong>Collection and dispensation:</strong> The amount received by the Fund does not go to the Consolidated Fund of India. If it goes to the CFI, it could have been audited by the CAG.</li>
<li><strong>Uncontrolled:</strong> The This Trust is neither intended to be or is in fact owned, controlled or substantially financed by any instrumentality of the any govt even being chaired by the PM.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issue over tax benefits</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Income tax:</strong> An ordinance was promulgated to amend Income Tax Act, 1961 and declare that the donations to the PM CARES Fund “would qualify for 80G benefits for 100% exemption”.</li>
<li><strong>CSR Funds:</strong> It will also qualify to be counted as Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) expenditure under the Companies Act, 2013.</li>
<li><strong>Foreign donations:</strong> It has also got exemption under the FCRA [Foreign Contribution Regulation Act] and a separate account for receiving foreign donations has been opened.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be inferred from all these?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Centre now considers it as another obstacle and has created a new trust with the Prime Minister and his Ministers only.</li>
<li>The manner in which the PM CARES Fund was set up — with its acronym created to publicise the point that the PM cares for people — shows a bypassing of the statutory obligations of a public authority.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Query and response: Again ironical</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>After initial denials, the Government has conceded it to be a public charitable trust, but still maintains that it is not a ‘public authority’.</li>
<li>The point is that the PMO operates the Fund, but says it cannot supply any information about the PM CARES Fund because it is not a public authority.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Severe interpretations: Is it an Office of Profit?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>If the PM CARES Fund is unconnected with the Government, then the Fund could become an office of profit.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In order to uphold transparency, the PM CARES Fund should be declared as a Public Authority under the RTI Act, and all RTI queries answered truthfully.</li>
<li>The fund should be designated as a “public authority” under Section 2(h) of the RTI Act.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ratan-tata-appointed-trustee-pm-cares/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Rules for Identifying Criminals now notified</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rules-for-identifying-criminal-now-notified/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-638847" height="525" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 525px) 100vw, 525px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/criminal-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/criminal-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/criminal-150x150.jpg 150w" width="525"/></strong></p>
<p>On September 19, the Ministry of Home Affairs (MHA) notified the rules governing The Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022. The Act was passed in March by the Parliament.</p>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Until rules are notified, an Act cannot be implemented or come into force.</li>
<li>The legislation would enable police and central investigating agencies to collect, store and analyse physical and biological samples including retina and iris scan of arrested persons.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Ans.</strong> It is about critical measurements of Criminals.</p>
<ul>
<li>This act provides legal sanction to law enforcement agencies for taking measurements of convicts and other persons for the purposes of identification and investigation of criminal matters.</li>
<li>The Minister of Home Affairs has observed that with advancements in forensics, there was a need to recognise more kinds of “measurements” that can be used by law enforcement agencies for investigation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the use of identification details in criminal trials?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Measurements and photographs for identification have three main purposes:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>To establish the identity of the culprit against the person being arrested</li>
<li>To identify suspected repetition of similar offences by the same person and third</li>
<li>To establish a previous conviction</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What was the previous Identification of Prisoners Act, 1920 about?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Even though the police has powers of arrest, mere <strong><u>arrest does not give Police the right to search a person</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The police requires <strong><u>legal sanction to search the person</u></strong> and collect evidence.</li>
<li>These legal sanctions are designed so as <strong><u>to maintain a balance between the rights of an individual and the interests of society</u></strong> in prosecution and prevention of offences.</li>
<li>The Identification of Prisoners Act, 1920 became a necessity when the <strong><u>recording of newer forms of evidence such as fingerprints, footprints and measurements started</u></strong> becoming more accurate and reliable.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the need to replace this Act?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Ans. </strong>Changing nature of Crime</p>
<ul>
<li>Over the years, the need to amend/update the Identification of Prisoners Act, 1920 has been voiced several times.</li>
<li>In 1980, the <strong><u>87th Report of the Law Commission of India</u></strong> undertook a review of this legislation and recommended several amendments.</li>
<li>This was done in the backdrop of the <strong><u>State of UP vs. Ram Babu Misra case</u></strong>, where the Supreme Court had highlighted the need for amending this law.</li>
<li>The first set of recommendations laid out the need to amend the Act to expand the scope of measurements <strong><u>to include “palm impressions”, “specimen of signature or writing” and “specimen of voice”. </u></strong></li>
<li>The second set of recommendations raised the <strong><u>need of allowing measurements to be taken for proceedings</u></strong> other than those under the Code of Criminal Procedure (CrPC).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the main highlights and differences in both the legislations?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Both provide legal sanction:</strong> Like the 1920 Law, the new Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022 provides for legal sanction to law enforcement agencies for the collection of measurements.</li>
<li><strong>Creating usable database of evidences:</strong> The purpose is to create a useable database of these measurements.</li>
<li><strong>Notifying designated state agencies:</strong> At the State level, each State is required to notify an appropriate agency to collect and preserve this database of measurements.</li>
<li><strong>NCRB at centre stage:</strong> At the national level, the National Crime Records Bureau (NCRB) is the designated agency to manage, process, share and disseminate the records collected at the State level.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are some of the concerns with the present legislation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Striking a balance:</strong> The new legislation has raised some concerns related to the protection of fundamental rights.</li>
<li><strong>Unresolved right to Privacy debate:</strong> The legislation comes in the backdrop of the right to privacy being recognised as a fundamental right.</li>
<li><strong>Notion of physical privacy:</strong> A fundamental facet of the right to privacy is protection from the invasion of one’s physical privacy.</li>
<li><strong>Justifying necessity:</strong> As per the Puttaswamy judgment, there is a need for the measure to be taken in pursuance of a legitimate aim of the state, be backed by the law and be “necessary and proportionate” to the aim being sought to be achieved.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(1) Various tests behind</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In this case, while the first two tests are satisfied, as:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>“<strong><u>prevention and investigation of crime</u></strong>” is a legitimate aim of the state</li>
<li>“<strong><u>measurements</u></strong>” are being taken under a valid legislation,</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Satisfaction of the third test of “<strong><u>necessity and proportionality</u></strong>” has been challenged on multiple counts.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) A probable police state in making</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Analysis and measurement of behavioural attributes have raised concerns that data processing may go beyond recording of core “measurements”.</li>
<li>That is some of these measurements could be processed for <strong><u>predictive policing</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Includes petty offences</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The current law allows for “measurements” to be taken if a person has been convicted/arrested for any offence, including petty offences.</li>
<li>The necessity of taking measurements of such persons for investigation of offences is unclear, and such discretion is likely to result in abuse of the law at lower levels.</li>
<li>This would definitely overburden the systems used for collection and storage of these measurements.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Period of storage of data</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Given that these records will be stored for 75 years from the time of collection, the law has been criticised as being disproportionate.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Surveillance state</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Such collection can also result in mass surveillance, with the database under this law being combined with other databases such as those of the Crime and Criminal Tracking Network and Systems (CCTNS).</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Promotes self-incrimination</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Concerns are being raised that the <strong><u>present law violates the right against self-incrimination</u></strong> enshrined in Article 20(3) of the Constitution of India.</li>
<li>However, this argument is nebulous since the Supreme Court has already settled this point.</li>
<li>In the State of Bombay vs Kathi Kalu Oghad, the Supreme Court had conclusively held that “non-communicative” evidence i.e. evidence which does not convey information within the personal knowledge of the accused cannot be understood to be leading to self-incrimination.</li>
<li>Therefore, no challenge lies to the law on this ground.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Extensive pre-legislative consultation is must for any sensitive law as such.</li>
<li>Privacy and data protection-related concerns must be addressed in the Rules formulated under the legislation and through model Prison Manuals that States can refer to.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rules-for-identifying-criminal-now-notified/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Live Streaming of SC proceedings: the rationale and the concerns</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/live-streaming-of-sc-proceedings/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Live streaming of courts proceedings</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-638849" height="141" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/live-streaming-300x141.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/live-streaming-300x141.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/live-streaming-768x361.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/live-streaming.jpg 905w" width="300"/></p>
<p>From September 27 onward, all proceedings of Supreme Court Constitution Benches will be live-streamed, a full court meeting of the top court has decided.</p>
<h4><strong>Background of the move</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>History was made on August 26 (2022) when the proceedings from the Chief Justice’s Court in the Supreme Court (SC) were live streamed.</li>
<li>In the <strong><u>‘Swapnil Tripathi’ judgment</u></strong>, in September 2018, the SC had cleared the deck for live streaming of cases of national and constitutional importance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Immediate triggers for live streaming</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>They had agreed to hear a public interest litigation seeking live streaming of judicial proceedings <strong><u>on matters of constitutional and national importance.</u></strong></li>
<li>Prime considerations cited are:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>De-congestion of courts and</li>
<li>Improving physical access to courts for litigants who have to otherwise travel long distances</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Recommended by A-G</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court approved a set of guidelines suggested by the A-G, which included allowing transcripts and archiving the proceedings.</li>
<li>However, the A-G suggested that the court must retain the <strong><u>power to withhold broadcasting</u></strong>, and to also NOT permit it in cases involving:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Matrimonial matters,</li>
<li>Matters involving interests of juveniles or the protection and safety of the private life of the young offenders,</li>
<li>Matters of National security,</li>
<li>To ensure that victims, witnesses or defendants can depose truthfully and without any fear.</li>
<li>To protect confidential or sensitive information, including all matters relating to sexual assault and rape,</li>
<li>Matters where publicity would be antithetical to the administration of justice, and</li>
<li>Cases which may provoke sentiments and arouse passion and provoke enmity among communities.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Live streaming in HCs</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Following the SC’s decision, Gujarat High Court began live streaming its proceedings in July 2021.</li>
<li>Currently, the Jharkhand, Karnataka, Madhya Pradesh, Orissa, and Patna High Courts live stream their proceedings.</li>
<li>Allahabad High Court is learnt to be considering doing the same.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Global examples of live streaming</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>United States of America:</strong> While the US Supreme Court has rejected pleas for broadcast of its proceedings, it has <u>since 1955</u> allowed audio recording and transcripts of oral arguments.</li>
<li><strong>United Kingdom:</strong> In 2005, the law was amended to remove contempt of court charges for recording proceedings of the Supreme Court.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need live streaming of court?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Improved accountability:</strong> Live-streaming of court proceedings would serve as an instrument for greater accountability and formed part of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.</li>
<li><strong>Living up the expectation of Constitution:</strong> Live Streaming of Court proceedings is manifested in public interest. Public interest has always been preserved through the Constitution article 19 and 21</li>
<li><strong>Empowering the masses: </strong>It will enable the legal system to deliver on its promise of empowering the masses.</li>
<li><strong>More transparency: </strong>It will encourage the principle of open court and reduce dependence on second-hand views. It will effectuate the public’s right to know.</li>
<li>This would inspire confidence in the functioning of the judiciary as an institution and help maintain the respect that it deserved as a co-equal organ of the state.</li>
<li><strong>Academic help:</strong> Live streaming may also be a help for academic purposes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Concerns around live streaming</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Contempt of court:</strong> Video clips of proceedings from Indian courts are already on YouTube and other social media platforms with sensational titles and little context, such as “HIGH COURT super angry on army officer”.</li>
<li><strong>Disinformation and sensationalism:</strong> There are fears that irresponsible or motivated use of content could spread disinformation among the public.</li>
<li><strong>Unnecessary activism:</strong> With the advent of social media, every citizen became a potential journalist. Study shows that justices behave like politicians when given free television time, they act to maximize their individual exposure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues to judicial functioning</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Decency of questions:</strong> During hearings judges may not ask questions or make comments that could be perceived as unpopular.</li>
<li><strong>Triggers for oral observations:</strong> There is an increasing trend of oral observations of the court, which are not binding on parties replacing reasoned judgment and orders that are consequential.</li>
<li><strong>Dignity of court may be compromised:</strong> Similarly, lawyers, aware of their new audience, may choose to grandstand and play to the gallery, especially in a case they expect to lose.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Selective broadcast:</strong> The solution may lie in carefully determining how the live streaming proceeds.</li>
<li><strong>Careful selection of cases:</strong> Not uploading archived stream on the SC website until it is legally/technologically possible to ensure that such videos cannot be spliced.</li>
<li><strong>Understanding public perception and sentiments:</strong> Other similar measures that reflect an understanding of how the public consumes (dis)information will ensure that live streaming enriches constitutionalism across the country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A hasty and wholesale introduction on the other hand is likely to land the SC right in the middle of the majoritarian and toxic information swamp that prevails in the country.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/live-streaming-of-sc-proceedings/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why the India China Border situation is still risky?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-china-border/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>border security</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="india china border" class="alignnone wp-image-638843" height="304" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 540px) 100vw, 540px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/117159998_gettyimages-1231271682-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/117159998_gettyimages-1231271682-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/117159998_gettyimages-1231271682-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/117159998_gettyimages-1231271682.jpg 976w" width="540"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to the consensus reached in the 16th round of India China Corps Commander Level Meeting, the Indian and Chinese troops in the area of Gogra-Hotsprings (PP-15) have begun to disengage in a coordinated and planned way. With disengagement at PP 15 India China border, forces of the two countries have disengaged at all friction points in the region which included the North and South banks of the <a href="https://indianexpress.com/article/explained/india-china-conflict-in-ladakh-the-importance-of-the-pangong-tso-lake-6419377/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Pangong Tso</a>, PP 14, PP 15 and PP 17A.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="India china border" class="alignnone wp-image-638858" height="305" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 467px) 100vw, 467px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dispute-300x196.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dispute-300x196.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dispute-768x502.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dispute.jpg 966w" width="467"/>Why the India-China Border situation is still risky?</strong></h4>
<p>The tentative conciliatory steps between two nuclear-armed rivals are important; but they also carry risks, especially for India. The risks are as follows:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Uneasy peace: </strong>Despite the latest round of disengagement, the LAC remains deeply unsettled. Observers have pointed out that the buﬀer zones produced by the crisis inhibit India’s ability to patrol its own territory.</li>
<li><strong>Un-resolve areas: </strong>India and China have tacitly agreed to postpone settlement at two other confrontation sites, particularly tactically valuable area known as Depsangand Charding Nala regions.</li>
<li><strong>Persisting threat: </strong>The reinforcements that each side deployed since 2020 have not returned to garrison. Even if future rounds of talks continue “disengagement and de-escalation,” and reduce those forces, returning to the status quo ante is now impossible.</li>
<li><strong>Border infrastructure: </strong>Both sides on India China border are racing towards building permanent military infrastructure near the border, to help them surge forces to the border. Unsurprisingly, China seems to have outpaced India in building these roads, helipads, and communications nodes.</li>
<li><strong>Possibility of conflict: </strong>The increasing capabilities and mobility on both sides of the border means that a crisis can more quickly escalate to a large military stand-oﬀ anywhere on the LAC, and possibly even trigger a conflict</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-china-border-dispute-a-conflict-years-in-the-making/"><strong><img alt="india china border" class="alignnone wp-image-638848" height="528" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 793px) 100vw, 793px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/file7ejeq84moxlfs3ppjoa-952973-1613730158-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/file7ejeq84moxlfs3ppjoa-952973-1613730158-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/file7ejeq84moxlfs3ppjoa-952973-1613730158-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/file7ejeq84moxlfs3ppjoa-952973-1613730158-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/file7ejeq84moxlfs3ppjoa-952973-1613730158.jpg 1200w" width="793"/>What are the Strategic implications?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Changing priorities: </strong>India has reassigned one of three originally Pakistan-facing Strike Corps to the China front. It has deployed its newest artillery, jets, and drones to the China border.</li>
<li><strong>Unattended Indian Ocean: </strong>India has not yet improved its capabilities or posture in the Indian Ocean region significantly.</li>
<li><strong>Diversion from real threat: </strong>With the border crisis, China seems to have successfully ﬁxed India’s gaze to the land border, at the expense of that more consequential competition over the Indian Ocean.</li>
<li><strong>Loss of grazing</strong>: Ladakh’s elected representatives said the disengagement has caused loss of huge grazing land as it would now be converted into no man’s land.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="india china border" class="alignnone wp-image-638851" height="326" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 579px) 100vw, 579px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8f93238c-72cc-11ec-8f22-243e37ddc844_1641898533811.jpg 1600w" width="579"/>Steps taken by India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increasing capability: </strong>from cruise missile-equipped ﬁghter jets and U.S.-origin naval helicopters to a brand-new indigenously-built aircraft carrier.</li>
<li><strong>Atmanirbhar Bharat: </strong>India undertook several structural economic reforms for strengthening domestic capability and reducing the economic parity between two nations. Defence ministry has decided to increase CAB (capital acquisition budget), around 64% of modernization fund around 70000 cr. has been allocated for purchasing from domestic market. Atma Nirbhar Bharat and Make in India mission will also include Defence sector, we can see the local or private companies can also participate in procurement of defence equipment</li>
<li><strong>Defence India Start-up Challenge (DISC): </strong>Started by the defence ministry and over 1200 MSMEs participated in the fourth edition of the DISC in 2020. The government has prepared a negative list, it include light combat helicopters, artillery guns; these items will not be imported by anyone thus encouraging self-reliant India.</li>
<li><strong>The SRIJAN</strong> <strong>portal: </strong>Launched to facilitate the two initiatives, Atmanirbhar Bharat and make in India</li>
<li><strong>Sagarmala project</strong>: The sagarmala project has been started to revamp port Infrastructure which is a welcome step in modernization.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>For china Deception is diplomacy. Time and again China tries a deception strategy from its Confucius doctrine to defeat its enemy. From 1962 to 2022 India has made a lot of progress in military and economic sphere but China is way ahead than us. Strategic competition between two Asian giants will continue foreseeable future. So as long as India doesn’t gain domestic capabilities it would be prudent step to undertake strategic balancing.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. India has decided to maintain a strategic balance with china rather than being subsidiary to china. Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-china-border/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Domestic violence needs to stop for true women empowerment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/domestic-violence/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>women empowerment</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="domestic violence" class="alignnone wp-image-638948" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 501px) 100vw, 501px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101-1024x681.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101-768x511.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101.jpg 1200w" width="501"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Due to prevalence of patriarchy women have been discriminated not only in India but in most parts of the world. According to The United Nations, one out of every three women experience domestic violence. The same UN report suggests that the most dangerous place for women is their home. Gender equality and women’s empowerment are essential for the development and well-being of families, communities and nations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How UN women defines Violence against women and girls</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Any act of gender-based violence that results in, or is likely to result in, physical, sexual or mental harm or suffering to women and girls, including threats of such acts, coercion or arbitrary deprivation of liberty, whether occurring in public or in private life.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why Women are the victim</strong>?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Domestic violence is one of the most common forms of violence experienced by women globally.</li>
<li>Women are usually the victim of domestic violence that derives from unequal power relationships between men and women.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="domestic violence" class="alignnone wp-image-638960" height="443" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 575px) 100vw, 575px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/76064761-300x231.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/76064761-300x231.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/76064761.jpg 635w" width="575"/>Why there is recent spike in violence against women?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to UN, Violence against women and girls is one of the world’s most prevalent human rights violations, taking place every day, many times over, in every corner of the world.</li>
<li><strong>Conditions created by the pandemic</strong> – including lockdowns, reduced mobility, heightened isolation, stress and economic uncertainty have led to an alarming spike in domestic violence and have further exposed women and girls to other forms of violence, from child marriage to sexual harassment online.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Domestic violence?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Domestic violence is any pattern of behavior that is used to gain or maintain power and control over an intimate partner. It encompasses all physical, sexual, emotional, economic and psychological actions or threats of actions that influence another person.</li>
<li><strong>Domestic violence</strong> <strong>can include the following.</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Psychological violence: </strong>Psychological violence involves causing fear, threatening physical harm or forcing isolation from friends, family, school or work<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Economic violence: </strong>Making or attempting to make a person financially dependent by maintaining total control over financial resources.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Emotional violence: </strong>Undermining a person’s sense of self-worth through constant criticism; belittling one’s abilities; verbal abuse.</li>
<li><strong>Physical violence: </strong>Use of Physical force or hurting or trying to hurt a partner .it also includes denying medical care.</li>
<li><strong>Sexual violence: </strong>Forcing a partner to take part in a sex act when the partner does not consent</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the current Status in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Nearly one-third of women in India have experienced physical or sexual violence</li>
<li>The most common type of spousal violence is physical violence (28%), followed by emotional violence and sexual violence</li>
<li>While domestic violence against women has declined from 31.2% to 29.3% in the country, 30% women between the age of 18 and 49 have experienced physical violence since the age of 15 years, while 6% have experienced sexual violence in their lifetime,.</li>
<li>Only 14% of women who have experienced physical or sexual violence by anyone have brought the issue up.</li>
<li>32% of married women (18-49 years) have experienced physical, sexual, or emotional spousal violence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Recent findings from National Family health Survey Report-5</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Status</strong>: Domestic violence against women is highest in Karnataka at 48%, followed by Bihar, Telangana, Manipur and Tamil Nadu. Lakshawdeep has the least domestic violence at 2.1%.</li>
<li><strong>Rural</strong>–<strong>urban difference</strong>: Physical violence is more common among women in rural areas (32%) as compared to their urban areas (24%).</li>
<li><strong>Impact of schooling and education: </strong>40% women with no schooling are subject to physical violence compared to 18% who completed their schooling.</li>
<li><strong>Impact of employment and wealth:</strong> The experience of physical violence ranges between 39% among women in the lowest wealth quintile and 17% in the highest wealth quintile.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> </strong><strong>Why women left behind as compared to men in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Patriarchal structure: </strong>Patriarchal structures and ideologies and the mindset lead to women subordination and gender inequalities</li>
<li><strong>Low sex ratio: </strong>Sex ratios for women in India Is not good comparatively. It was even bad at the time of independence.</li>
<li><strong>Life expectancy</strong>: Women’s life expectancy, health, nutritional levels are significantly lower than that of men.</li>
<li><strong>Education: </strong>low investment on girl education, Girl children are kept out of schools, or made drop out of school at early age, girl is considered as burden on family in many societies.</li>
<li><strong>Employment</strong>: even if they are educated they are not allowed to work by their families Discrimination at the workplaces, lower wages for the work of equal value<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Decision making: </strong>The have little say in the families, socio economic, legal and political rules and policy formulations. Very limited or no decision making power.</li>
<li><strong>Political participation: </strong>The participation of women in political and social decision making power is abysmally low. Their number in parliament has never exceeded more than 10%.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-empowerment/"><strong>What can be done for empowering women?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Recognition: </strong>Recognition of women as productive, vital agents of family and environment should be a precondition for addressing their social needs. We need to change the way they are perceived.</li>
<li><strong>Treatment: </strong>They must not be only treated only as objects of welfare but needed to be treated as those who are contributing to the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Health: </strong>To provide quality and affordable healthcare and must be easily accessible.</li>
<li><strong>Education: </strong>Education of women is the most important component for women’s empowerment.</li>
<li><strong>Safe and secure environment: </strong>providing safety and security is the precondition for empowerment and social justice.</li>
<li><strong>Economic Independence: </strong>Helping women to stand on their legs, become independent and also to earn for their family is necessary to empowering women and to raise their hand in decision making process of family, society and nation</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="domestic violence" class="alignnone wp-image-638986" height="349" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 537px) 100vw, 537px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Downloads2-300x195.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Downloads2-300x195.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Downloads2.jpg 620w" width="537"/>Woman as the foundation stone of every family, society and nation</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has an ancient woman worship tradition.</li>
<li>In India we see woman as a mother goddess. There are no of evidences to support this idea</li>
<li>For instance the Sanskrit text “Yatra naryastu pujyante ramante tatra Devata”which means where women are honored, there gods resides.</li>
<li>Which means there is a overall development if the women of the family is happy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="domestic violence" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-639056" height="158" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India.jpg 1200w" width="300"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Domestic violence against women is major obstacle on progress on achieving development targets. Without addressing it, anybody have little chance of meeting millennium development. Recognition of women as productive, vital agents of family and environment should be a precondition for addressing their social needs. Gender equality and women’s empowerment are essential for the development and well-being of families, communities and nations.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Empowering women on every front is the pre-condition for the overall development of the nation. Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/domestic-violence/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The problem of fly ash generation and its proper disposal and usage</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fly-ash/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>composition of fly ash</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>environmental pollution</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="fly ash" class="alignnone wp-image-639139" height="352" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 100vw, 542px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.28841000_1663768775_0-300x195.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.28841000_1663768775_0-300x195.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.28841000_1663768775_0-768x498.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.28841000_1663768775_0.jpg 1024w" width="542"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India depends heavily on coal for power generation. This creates the problem of fly-ash generation and its proper disposal, usage.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/national-green-tribunal-ngt/">National Green Tribunal (NGT)</a> noted September 19, 2022 that there was an urgent need to augment the utilisation and disposal of fly ash in Chhattisgarh.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is fly ash?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fly ash is a by-product of coal combustion. It contains Aluminium Silicate, SiO2, CaO, oxides of iron, magnesium and toxic metals like lead, arsenic, cobalt, and copper.</li>
<li>It can travel to far places. India is growing to double its power generation in the next decade and with coal being the biggest source of fuel for power generation, the problem of fly ash is going to increase too.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fly ash " class="alignnone wp-image-639140" height="623" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 467px) 100vw, 467px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-225x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-225x300.jpg 225w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-1535x2048.jpg 1535w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-675x900.jpg 675w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-1200x1601.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-1980x2641.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-scaled.jpg 1919w" width="467"/>Environmental Problems with fly ash </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A large quantity of fly ash dumped into poorly designed and maintained ash ponds. About a billion tonnes of this toxic ash lie dumped in these ponds, polluting land, air, and water.</li>
<li>All the heavy metals found in fly ash—nickel, cadmium, arsenic, chromium, lead, etc—are toxic in nature. They leech into the surrounding soil and can enter food-chains.</li>
<li>Fly ash gets easily ingested through respiration, which causes many diseases such as asthma, neurological disorders.</li>
<li>Suspended fly ash in the air acts as a global warming agent and heats the earth’s surface.</li>
<li>Fly ash settles on leaves and crops and reduces crop productivity.</li>
<li>It pollutes the groundwater.</li>
<li>There is a reduction in recharging of groundwater due to fly ash filled mine voids.</li>
<li>Reduces visibility by creating dense fog in the winter season.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fly ash" class="alignnone wp-image-639144" height="339" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/flyash-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/flyash-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/flyash-768x449.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/flyash.jpg 900w" width="581"/>Issues with fly ash management</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The government mandates that all coal power plants (CPPs) reach 100% utilization of fly ash.</li>
<li>Along with it, CPPs should give a certain amount of fly ash free of cost for MSMEs to manufacture bricks, tiles and rest of the fly ash should be sold to other industries.</li>
<li>CPPs will have to maintain fly ash ponds to reduce its suspension in air.</li>
<li>But all these steps for utilization areas are problematic as they do little to mitigate these risks.</li>
<li>The pricing of fly ash is increasingly becoming a contentious issue that is hampering its gainful utilization.</li>
<li>The current approaches to evaluating risks with fly ash disposal are very limited, and they may underestimate the true risks</li>
<li>In spite of initiatives taken by the government, several nongovernmental and research and development organizations for fly ash utilization, the level of fly ash utilization in the country is quite low at only 38% which is less than the global standards.</li>
<li>Hence, rather than being utilized, fly ash is being stored despite warnings from regulators.</li>
<li>Deposition in storage places has negative influences on water and soil because of their mineral composition as well as morphology and filtration properties.</li>
<li>Ash-handling units are the biggest consumers of water in CPPs. The government advocates the designed ash-to-water ratios as approximately 1:5 for fly ash, but the observed ratios have been around 1:20.</li>
<li>Certain states have discouraged the use of blended cement and fly ash bricks in public works.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fly ash" class="alignnone wp-image-639142" height="353" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-4.jpeg" width="630"/>The above issues can be addressed by</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Greater regulatory oversight and price control,</li>
<li>Revision of cement blending standards,</li>
<li>Research in improving fly ash quality,</li>
<li>Reducing the cost of transportation,</li>
<li>Provisions for overcoming information asymmetries,</li>
<li>Incentivising use in brick kilns for producing fly ash bricks,</li>
<li>Overall sensitization of key decision-makers on the matter.</li>
<li>Instead of dumping it on ash ponds, can be used for construction due to its reuse as pozzolan, and replacement of portland cement by hydraulic cement</li>
<li>Due to its grain size distribution, enhanced strength permeability, it can be used to construct embankments at road construction, concrete dams like GHATGHAR DAM</li>
<li>Strong penalties for those production units who do not use proper filtration devices</li>
<li>Moving to renewable energy production away from coal-based thermal production.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Utilization of Fly Ash is not only possible but also essential. In this context “Fly Ash Mission of Government of India” is a slow but steady start, the pace of which needs to be ramped up. An honest effort is required by the concerned stakeholders to improve the perceptions of fly ash-based cement or concrete; increase its use, particularly for government works; and impart scientific knowledge about fly ash, its uses, and possible impacts.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What is fly ash? Discuss the environmental challenges it poses. Suggest how to address the situation. </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fly-ash/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Dvorak Technique of Weather Forecasting</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dvorak-technique-of-weather-forecasting/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Dvorak Technique</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Weather forecasting</p></div></div><p>Recently, the American meteorologist Vernon Dvorak passed away at the age of 100 who pioneered the widely used Dvorak Technique.</p>
<h4>Who was Vernon Dvorak?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dvorak was an American meteorologist best credited for developing the Dvorak (read as Do-rak) technique in the early 1970s.</li>
<li>The technique helps forecast the tropical storm.</li>
<li>His technique has saved the lives of millions of people across the world and will continue to do so.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the Dvorak technique?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Dvorak technique was first developed in 1969 and tested for observing storms in the northwest Pacific Ocean.</li>
<li>Forecasters used the available satellite images obtained from polar orbiting satellites to examine the features of the developing tropical storms (hurricanes, cyclones and typhoons).</li>
<li>During day time, images in the visible spectrum were used while at night, the ocean would be observed using infrared images.</li>
<li>It was a cloud pattern recognition technique based on a concept model of the development and decay of the tropical cyclone.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is technique still widely in use?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Unlike land, ocean observations in the 1970s were sparse.</li>
<li>Today, there continues to be an improved network of land-based meteorological observations, either in the form of taking manual observations, installing automatic weather stations or automatic rain gauges.</li>
<li>On the other hand, ocean observations still remain limited.</li>
<li>There are many vast regions across the four oceans that have not been fully examined with meteorological instruments.</li>
<li>Ocean observations are mostly taken by deploying buoys or dedicated ships, but the number of observations from the seas is still not sufficient across the world.</li>
<li>That is why meteorologists have had to depend more on satellite-based imageries, and combine it with the available ocean-data at the time of forecasting the intensity and wind speed of the tropical cyclones.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dvorak-technique-of-weather-forecasting/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>NASA’s DART mission prepares for an asteroid Dimorphos collision</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dart-mission-prepares-for-an-asteroid-dimorphos-collision/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>DART Mission, Didymos, Dimorphos</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="dart" class="alignnone wp-image-639369 size-full" height="1497" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-scaled.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-scaled.jpg 2560w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-1024x599.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-768x449.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-1536x898.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-2048x1197.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-1200x702.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-1980x1158.jpg 1980w" width="2560"/></p>
<p>In the first-of-its kind NASA’s DART Mission is about to hit a small, harmless asteroid millions of miles away.</p>
<h4><strong>What is DART Mission?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The main aim of the mission is to test the newly developed technology that would allow a spacecraft to crash into an asteroid and change its course.</li>
<li>It is a suicide mission and the spacecraft will be completely destroyed.</li>
<li>The target of the spacecraft is a small moonlet called Dimorphos (Greek for “two forms”).</li>
<li>It is about 160-metre in diameter and the spacecraft is expected to collide when it is 11 million kilometres away from Earth.</li>
<li>Dimorphos orbits a larger asteroid named Didymos (Greek for “twin”) which has a diameter of 780 metres.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why Dimorphos?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Didymos is a perfect system for the test mission because it is an eclipsing binary which means it has a moonlet that regularly orbits the asteroid.</li>
<li>It is observable when it passes in front of the main asteroid.</li>
<li>Earth-based telescopes can study this variation in brightness to understand how long it takes Dimorphos to orbit Didymos.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Collision course</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At the time of impact, Didymos and Dimorphos will be relatively close to Earth – within 6.8 million miles (11 million kilometers).</li>
<li>The spacecraft will accelerate at about 24,140 kilometers per hour when it collides with Dimorphos.</li>
<li>It aims to crash into Dimorphos to change the asteroid’s motion in space.</li>
<li>This collision will be recorded by LICIACube, or Light Italian CubeSat for Imaging of Asteroids, a companion cube satellite provided by the Italian Space Agency.</li>
<li>Three minutes after impact, the CubeSat will fly by Dimorphos to capture images and video.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why such mission?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dimorphos was chosen for this mission because its size is relative to asteroids that could pose a threat to Earth.</li>
<li>The spacecraft is about 100 times smaller than Dimorphos, so it won’t obliterate the asteroid.</li>
<li>The fast impact will only change Dimorphos’ speed as it orbits Didymos by 1%, which doesn’t sound like a lot — but it will change the moon’s orbital period.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dart-mission-prepares-for-an-asteroid-dimorphos-collision/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>New Account Settlement System for Stock Trading</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/new-account-settlement-system-for-stock-trading/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Account settlement, T+1</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p>Beginning October 1, the new account settlement system for the stock broking industry will kick in under the new guidelines issued by the Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI).</p>
<h4><strong>What is Settlement of Accounts?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The SEBI mandates stockbrokers to settle i.e., transfer the available credit balance from trading account to bank account, at least once in a quarter (90 days) or 30 days.</li>
<li>The process of transferring the unutilised funds back into the bank account is called ‘Running Account Settlement’ or ‘Quarterly Settlement of Funds’.</li>
<li>The funds are transferred back to the primary bank account of the customer that is linked to the trading account.</li>
<li>As per the latest guidelines, the settlement will now be done on the first Friday of the quarter or the month depending upon the option selected by the customer.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are SEBI’s new settlement guidelines?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>On July 27, SEBI issued new guidelines on running accounts of client funds and securities lying with the broker.</li>
<li>As per the new guidelines, with effect from October 1, 2022, the settlement of running account of clients’ funds will be done by the trading members after considering the end of the day (EOD) obligation of funds.</li>
<li>In cases where the client has opted for a monthly settlement process, then the running account shall be settled on the first Friday of every month.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How will it impact investors and traders?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Changes in settlement brought in by SEBI over the last few years have had the aim of protecting the investor and preventing the misuse as money lying in trading accounts of investors for long periods.</li>
<li>SEBI’s move will give certainty to investors and trading members.</li>
<li>It will help brokers develop a system just like banks, which credit interest in the accounts of their customers at the end of the quarter.</li>
<li>Another advantage would be that if a customer has more than one demat account with different brokers, having one settlement date for the entire industry will make it easier for her to keep track of her funds.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4><strong>Back2Basics: Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The SEBI is the regulatory body for securities and commodity market in India under the jurisdiction of Ministry of Finance Government of India.</li>
<li>It was established on 12 April 1988 and given Statutory Powers on 30 January 1992 through the SEBI Act, 1992.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Jurisdiction of SEBI</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>SEBI has to be responsive to the needs of three groups, which constitute the market:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Issuers of securities</li>
<li>Investors</li>
<li>Market intermediaries</li>
</ol>
<p>SEBI has three powers rolled into one body: quasi-legislative, quasi-judicial and quasi-executive.</p>
<ul>
<li>It drafts regulations in its legislative capacity, it conducts investigation and enforcement action in its executive function and it passes rulings and orders in its judicial capacity.</li>
<li>Though this makes it very powerful, there is an appeal process to create accountability.</li>
<li>There is a Securities Appellate Tribunal which is a three-member tribunal and is currently headed by Justice Tarun Agarwala, former Chief Justice of the Meghalaya High Court.</li>
<li>A second appeal lies directly to the Supreme Court.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="0GTrfivoMm"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sebi-introduces-t1-settlement-system/">SEBI introduces T+1 Settlement System</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="0GTrfivoMm" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sebi-introduces-t1-settlement-system/embed/#?secret=ZkM1JNKkw9#?secret=0GTrfivoMm" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“SEBI introduces T+1 Settlement System” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/new-account-settlement-system-for-stock-trading/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Carbon Dating?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-carbon-dating/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Carbon Dating</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="carbon dating" class="alignnone wp-image-639365 size-full" height="694" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 618px) 100vw, 618px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/carbon-dating.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/carbon-dating.jpg 618w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/carbon-dating-267x300.jpg 267w" width="618"/></p>
<p>A Varanasi district court has issued notice regarding carbon-dating of the disputed structure known to have been found inside the premises of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gyanvapi-kashi-vishwanath-temple-complex-dispute/">Gyanvapi mosque</a>.</p>
<h4>What is Carbon Dating?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Carbon dating, also called radiocarbon dating is method of age determination that depends upon the decay to nitrogen of radiocarbon (Carbon-14).</li>
<li>This method was developed by the American physicist Willard F. Libby about 1946.</li>
<li>Carbon-14 is continually formed in nature by the interaction of neutrons with nitrogen-14 in the Earth’s atmosphere.</li>
<li>The neutrons required for this reaction are produced by cosmic rays interacting with the atmosphere.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How it works?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Radiocarbon present in molecules of atmospheric carbon dioxide enters the biological carbon cycle: it is absorbed from the air by green plants and then passed on to animals through the food chain.</li>
<li>Radiocarbon decays slowly in a living organism, and the amount lost is continually replenished as long as the organism takes in air or food.</li>
<li>Once the organism dies, however, it ceases to absorb carbon-14, so that the amount of the radiocarbon in its tissues steadily decreases.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The half-life concept</h4>
<ul>
<li>Carbon-14 has a half-life of <strong><u>5,730 ± 40 years</u></strong>—i.e., half the amount of the radioisotope present at any given time will undergo spontaneous disintegration during the succeeding 5,730 years.</li>
<li>Because carbon-14 decays at this constant rate, an estimate of the date at which an organism died can be made by measuring the amount of its <strong><u>residual radiocarbon</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Its uses</h4>
<ul>
<li>It has proved to be a versatile technique of dating fossils and archaeological specimens from 500 to 50,000 years old.</li>
<li>The method is widely used by geologists, anthropologists, archaeologists, and investigators in related fields.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-carbon-dating/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the draft Telecom Bill, and what changes it aims to bring?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/draft-telecom-bill/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Indian Telecommunication Bill, 2022</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="telecom" class="alignnone wp-image-639368 size-full" height="396" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1149px) 100vw, 1149px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/telecom.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/telecom.jpg 1149w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/telecom-300x103.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/telecom-1024x353.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/telecom-768x265.jpg 768w" width="1149"/></p>
<p>In a bid to do away with British-era laws governing the telecom sector, the Department of Telecommunications (DoT) issued the draft Indian Telecommunication Bill, 2022.</p>
<h4><strong>Indian Telecommunication Bill, 2022</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The proposed Bill aims to bring in sweeping changes to how the telecom sector is governed, primarily by giving the Centre more powers in several areas to do so.</li>
<li>The draft Bill consolidates three separate acts that govern the telecommunications sector:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Indian Telegraph Act 1885</li>
<li>Indian Wireless Telegraphy Act 1933, and</li>
<li>The Telegraph Wires, (Unlawful Protection) Act 1950</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Why has the government issued a draft Telecommunication Bill?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Through the bill, the Centre aims to consolidate and amend the existing laws governing the provision, development, expansion and operation of telecom services, networks and infrastructure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Key amendments introduced </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inclusion of messengers:</strong> One of the key changes is inclusion of new-age over-the-top communication services like WhatsApp, Signal and Telegram in the definition of telecommunication services.</li>
<li><strong>Licensing of telecom services:</strong> As per the draft law, providers of telecom services will be covered under the licensing regime, and will be subjected to similar rules as other telecom operators.</li>
<li><strong>Covering OTT services:</strong> This issue has been under contention for several years now with telecom service providers seeking a level-playing field with OTT apps over communication services such as voice calls, messages, etc. Operators had to incur high costs of licences and spectrum, while OTT players rode on their infrastructure to offer free services.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other focus areas</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Centre is also looking to amend the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act (TRAI Act) to dilute the sectoral watchdog’s function of being a recommendatory body.</li>
<li>The current TRAI Act mandates the telecom department to seek the regulator’s views before issuing a new licence to a service provider.</li>
<li>The proposed Bill does away with this provision.</li>
<li>It has also removed the provision that empowered TRAI to request the government to furnish information or documents necessary to make this recommendation.</li>
<li>Additionally, the new Bill also proposes to remove the provision where if the DoT cannot accept TRAI’s recommendations or needs modification, it had to refer back the recommendation for reconsideration by TRAI.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Addressing the concerns of telecom industry</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Insolvency of Telecoms</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The DoT has also proposed that if a telecom entity in possession of spectrum goes through bankruptcy or insolvency, the assigned spectrum will revert to the control of the Centre.</li>
<li>So far, in insolvency proceedings, there has been a lack of clarity on whether the spectrum owned by a defaulting operator belongs to the Centre, or whether banks can take control of it.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Granting relief</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The draft Bill also accords the Centre powers to defer, convert into equity, write off or grant relief to any licensee under extraordinary circumstances, including financial stress, consumer interest, and maintaining competition, among other things.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Replacing USOF</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>It also proposes to replace the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/universal-service-obligation-fund-usof/">Universal Service Obligation Fund (USOF)</a> with the Telecommunication Development Fund (TDF).</li>
<li>USOF is the pool of funds generated by the 5 per cent Universal Service Levy that is charged upon all telecom fund operators on their Adjusted Gross Revenue.</li>
<li>The USOF has largely been used to aid rural connectivity.</li>
<li>However, with the TDF, the objective is also to boost connectivity in underserved urban areas, R&amp;D, skill development, etc.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4><strong>Back2Basics: Universal Service Obligation Fund (USOF)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Universal Service Obligation Fund (USOF) was formed by an Act of Parliament, was established in April 2002 under the Indian Telegraph (Amendment) Act 2003.</li>
<li>It aims to provide financial support for the provision of telecom services in commercially unviable rural and remote areas of the country.</li>
<li>It is an attached office of the Department of Telecom, and is headed by the administrator, who is appointed by the central government.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/draft-telecom-bill/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysing the Kyrgyzstan-Tajikistan Conflict</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/the-kyrgyzstan-tajikistan-conflict/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Batken Region</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="conflict" class="alignnone wp-image-639366 size-full" height="883" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/conflict.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/conflict.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/conflict-300x221.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/conflict-1024x753.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/conflict-768x565.jpg 768w" width="1200"/></p>
<p>Nearly 100 people have been killed and scores injured in violent border clashes between Kyrgyzstan and Tajikistan over the last week.</p>
<h4>What is the Kyrgyzstan-Tajikistan Conflict?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The clashes are replaying old pre- and post-Soviet era legacies.</li>
<li>The borders of the two republics were demarcated under Joseph Stalin’s leadership.</li>
<li>Historically, the Kyrgyz and Tajik populations enjoyed common rights over natural resources.</li>
<li>The issue of the delimitation of the border is a relic of the Soviet era.</li>
<li>While regular talks have tried to resolve the issue, one of the crucial points of disagreement remains over the map which should be used for demarcation purposes.</li>
<li>Almost half of its close to a 1000 km border is disputed.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Genesis of the dispute</h4>
<ul>
<li>The creation of the Soviet Union saw the large-scale redistribution of livestock to collective and state farms, which upset the existing status quo.</li>
<li>Unfortunately, there was only so much land to go around.</li>
<li>The Tajik territory of Batken saw their livestock increase, and with scarce grazing land, agreements were signed between the two populations over the utilisation of Kyrgyz territory by the Tajiks’ livestock.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is happening now at the border?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The last few weeks have seen constant shelling, violent confrontations by local communities, and active engagement by security forces on either side.</li>
<li>The Batken region of Kyrgyzstan is seeing families being moved out and getting relocated.</li>
<li>According to Kyrgyzstan, close to 1,50,000 people out of the 5,50,000 odd population of the Batken region have either fled the area or have been relocated by the state.</li>
<li>The situation in Osh, Kyrgyzstan, is no different. The highly militarised borders also add to tensions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of Batken</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Batken region, bordering Tajikistan and Uzbekistan in the south of the country, is one of the seven regions of Kyrgyzstan with its natural underground and water resources, natural beauty, smooth transit routes and a population of around 500,000.</li>
<li>Located 750 kilometers (466.02 miles) from Bishkek, the capital of Kyrgyzstan, and in the southwest of the country, the Batken region is located on the edge of the famous Fergana Valley in Central Asia.</li>
<li>Fergana Valley includes Fergana, Namangan, Andijan in Uzbekistan, Hocand in Tajikistan, Osh, Jalalabad and Batken in Kyrgyzstan.</li>
<li>The Batken region borders the Republic of Uzbekistan in the northeast and the Republic of Tajikistan in the southwest and north.</li>
<li>Covering 8.5% of Kyrgyzstan’s land, the region has agricultural, underground, water and energy resources, as well as oil and natural gas resources, albeit small.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What led to the current flare-up?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ideological basis of the current set of clashes is reinforced by developmental issues, thus providing a fertile ground for the entire geopolitical space to become a hotbed of multiple minor conflicts and clashes.</li>
<li>The groups from either side planted trees in disputed areas and engaged in a physical confrontation using agricultural equipment as weapons.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why are the clashes occurring now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The collapse of the Soviet Union and the subsequent dissolution of the then-existing water and land agreements saw the creation of multiple smaller independent farms.</li>
<li>This has led to a marked increase in water consumption patterns among the farmers.</li>
<li>Both countries share multiple water channels with undulating trajectories and flow, which upset equitable access to water on both sides.</li>
<li>As a result, small-scale conflicts occur practically every year during the crucial irrigation period.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the road ahead?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The path to resolution of the conflict will require groups to agree upon a common map.</li>
<li>Russia often brokers between the two.</li>
<li>The international community will have to make efforts to solve the dispute by involving elders in the communities, as historically, elders have been used to resolve conflicts.</li>
<li>The informal small-scale governance mechanisms would also have to be further strengthened through a concerted effort by the respective countries to stabilize the geopolitical dynamics.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/the-kyrgyzstan-tajikistan-conflict/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Maoist movement declines along the Andhra-Odisha boundary</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/maoist-movement-declines-the-andhra-odisha-boundary/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Maoism, Leninism and Marxism</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>LWE in India</p></div></div><p><img alt="mao" class="alignnone wp-image-526403 size-full" height="994" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/lwe.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/lwe.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/lwe-300x249.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/lwe-1024x848.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/lwe-768x636.jpg 768w" width="1200"/></p>
<p>The Maoist movement is on the ebb on the Andhra Pradesh-Odisha boundary, with its cadre and militia strength heavily depleted.</p>
<h4><strong>Who are the Maoists?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Maoism is a form of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-left-wing-extremism/">communism</a> developed by Mao Zedong.</li>
<li>It is a doctrine to capture State power through a combination of armed insurgency, mass mobilization and strategic alliances.</li>
<li>The Maoists also use propaganda and disinformation against State institutions as other components of their insurgency doctrine.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Maoists and Maoism in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Communist Party of India (Maoist) is a Marxist–Leninist–Maoist banned communist political party and militant organization in India.</li>
<li>It aims to overthrow the “semi-colonial and semi-feudal Indian state” through people’s war.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Confused between Maoists and Naxalities?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Usually, people confuse themselves over Maoists and Naxalities and cannot exactly trace the difference between the two terminologies.</li>
<li>Media seems to be confused with the terms and uses Maoists and Naxalities quite inter-changeably.</li>
<li>This creates confusion in the readers’ minds over the actual meaning of individual terms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The actual difference between the terms is as follows:</h4>
<ul>
<li>The difference between Maoists struggle and the Naxalite movement is that both trace their origin to the Naxalbari uprising of 1967.</li>
<li>But while the Naxalite movement thrives on the original spirit of Naxalbari; the Maoist struggle is an outcome of the 1967 uprising.</li>
<li>Maoists work with an agenda and use weapons to achieve their aims.</li>
<li>Naxalism focuses on mass organisations while the Maoism relies mainly on arms.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>History and evolution</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Russian Revolution:</strong> Naxalism in India, like any other leftist movement around the globe draws its ideological basis from the Russian revolution.</li>
<li><strong>Overthrowing Tsarist Regime:</strong> Lenin successfully fought against the Czarist Rule through a combination of peasant movement and an armed struggle.</li>
<li><strong>Marxian ideology of class struggle:</strong> The prime intent was to bestow power in the hands of the exploited and marginalized and enforce societal control over governance and nation building.</li>
<li><strong>Neo-Marxism:</strong> After the success of the Lenin-led revolution in Russia, the intellectual class in many countries got inspired. Prominent amongst them were Fidel Castro and Mao Zedong.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Root cause of origin in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Corporate exploitation:</strong> Since Eastern India is rich in natural resources including forests, minerals and mines, tribal face exploitation and harassment from government and corporate bodies targeting to extract those resources.</li>
<li><strong>Tribal alienation:</strong> Tribal communities have been systematically alienated from their traditional rights over natural resources after independence.</li>
<li><strong>Livelihood losses:</strong> Tribal livelihood is at stake due to depletion of natural resource base.</li>
<li><strong>Forceful displacement:</strong> Forceful displacement from their homeland destroys their traditional governance system.</li>
<li><strong>Absence of governance: </strong>In such exploited areas, the absence of governance becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy since the delivery systems are extinguished through killings and intimidation.</li>
<li><strong>Foreign provocations:</strong> Many of LWE outfits are supported by external forces inimical to India and the Maoists consider such alliances as strategic assets.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other factors:</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li>Oppression and HR violations by Security Forces e.g. AFSPA</li>
<li>Violation of Constitutional Protections under PESA and FRA</li>
<li>Prevalence of Acute Poverty</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Impact of LWE</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Romanticism without a cause:</strong> Some sections of the society, especially the younger generation, have romantic illusions about the Maoists, arising out of an incomplete understanding of their ideology of Class –Struggle.</li>
<li><strong>Extreme violence:</strong> Their doctrine glorifies violence as the primary means to overwhelm the existing socio-economic and political structures.</li>
<li><strong>Destruction of governance mechanism:</strong> LWEs aims at creating a vacuum at the grassroots level of the existing governance structures by killing lower-level government officials, police personnel of the local police stations and the people’s representatives of the PRIs.</li>
<li><strong>Radicalization of youths:</strong> After creating a political and governance vacuum, they coerce the local population to join the movement.</li>
<li><strong>Urban-Maoism:</strong> Many extremists have facilitated mass-mobilization in semi-urban and urban areas through ostensibly democratic means often led by well-educated intellectuals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Outcomes of perpetrating LWE</strong></h4>
<p>The Leftist organizations skilfully use state structures and legal processes to further the Maoist agenda and weaken the enforcement regime through:</p>
<ol>
<li>Recruitment of ‘professional revolutionaries’</li>
<li>Raising funds for the insurgency</li>
<li>Creating urban shelters for underground cadres</li>
<li>Providing legal assistance to arrested cadres and</li>
<li>Mass- mobilization by agitating over issues of relevance/ convenience</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Govt initiatives for LWE-affected areas</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Aspirational Districts:</strong> The MHA has been tasked with the monitoring of the Aspirational districts programme in 35 LWE affected districts.</li>
<li><strong>HRD measures:</strong> Building of schools under the Eklavya model.</li>
<li><strong>Road Connectivity Project for LWE affected areas (RRP-II):</strong> This aims for improving road connectivity in LWE affected States. Under this, 9279 km of roads and 392 bridges are sanctioned.</li>
<li><strong>Naxal Surrender Policy:</strong> It aims to wean away misguided youth and hardcore naxalites who have strayed into the fold of the naxal movement and cannot find a way back.</li>
<li><strong>National Policy Action Plan</strong>: To address Left Wing Extremism approved in 2015, has development as one of the most important component.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>SAMADHAN doctrine: </strong>It encompasses the entire strategy of government from short-term policy to long-term policy formulated at different levels. SAMADHAN stands for-</p>
<ul>
<li>S- Smart Leadership</li>
<li>A- Aggressive Strategy</li>
<li>M- Motivation and Training</li>
<li>A- Actionable Intelligence</li>
<li>D- Dashboard Based KPIs (Key Performance Indicators) and KRAs (Key Result Areas)</li>
<li>H- Harnessing Technology</li>
<li>A- Action plan for each Theatre</li>
<li>N- No access to Financing</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian counterinsurgency has to work with a dual objective of defeating the insurgents militarily and fully quell the insurgent impulses.</li>
<li>This will need institutional overhauls.</li>
<li>States must do more to synergize their efforts by launching coordinated operations, thereby denying Maoists any space for manoeuvrability.</li>
<li>On parallel grounds, it is also important to segregate the population from the insurgents both operationally and ideologically.</li>
<li>The conflict over the distribution of resources can be mended with economic development.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/maoist-movement-declines-the-andhra-odisha-boundary/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>A census is not just about aimless counting sheep</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/census/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of census data</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Population issues</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="census" class="alignnone wp-image-639439" height="379" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-300x222.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-300x222.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-1024x759.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-768x570.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-1536x1139.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-2048x1519.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-1200x890.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-1980x1468.jpg 1980w" width="512"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As there is no official reassurance that India will not skip its decadal Census, we can declare that we have a case of the missing census.</li>
<li>The census is a very important source of statistics on various indicators.</li>
<li>The ability to hold a census peacefully, and not coercively, has been the hallmark of a civilized state and state of affairs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a census?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Census is nothing but a process of collecting, compiling, analyzing, evaluating, publishing and disseminating statistical data regarding the population.</li>
<li>It covers demographic, social and economic data and is provided as of a particular date.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the purpose of the census?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To collect the information for planning and formulation policies for Central and the State Governments.</li>
<li>The census tells us who we are and where we are going as a nation.</li>
<li>It helps the government decide how to distribute funds and assistance to states and localities.</li>
<li>The census data is widely used by National and International Agencies, scholars, business people, industrialists, and many more.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="census" class="alignnone wp-image-639440" height="263" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 499px) 100vw, 499px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/136455-zzzrhagmjy-1581566412-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/136455-zzzrhagmjy-1581566412-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/136455-zzzrhagmjy-1581566412.jpg 600w" width="499"/>Why is the census important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Provides most credible source of information</strong><strong>:</strong> information on Demography (Population characteristics), Economic Activity, Literacy and Education, Housing &amp; Household Amenities, Urbanisation, Fertility and Mortality, Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes, Language, Religion, Migration, Disability and many other socio-cultural and demographic data<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>The delimitation/reservation of Constituencies</strong><strong>: </strong>Parliamentary/Assembly/Panchayats and other Local Bodies are also done on the basis of the demographic data thrown up by the Census.</li>
<li><strong>Administration: </strong>Census is the basis for reviewing the country’s progress in the past decade, monitoring the ongoing Schemes of the Government.</li>
<li><strong>Planning the future:</strong> It provides pathways for planning and resolving problems, and fixing deficiencies. Government goes through analysis over the census data and formulates policies for the future accordingly.</li>
<li><strong>Detailed accounts: </strong>The best of sample surveys find it impossible to beat a census as It carries the promise of counting each and every Indian. A census is when the state connects to every individual and it will find it hard to hide or duck from the data.</li>
<li><strong>Welfare schemes</strong>: Identifying the actual beneficiaries<strong>, </strong>Census is the key to creating identity and affirming it over time .Census data enable neat, inter-temporal comparability.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Censuses in India so far</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Census operations started in India long back during the period of the Maurya dynasty.</li>
<li>It was systematized during the years 1865 to 1872, though it has been conducted uninterruptedly from the year 1881 being a trustworthy resource of information.</li>
<li>India has held its decadal censuses regularly from 1881 to 2011, despite diseases, world wars, Partition and other instances of turmoil only COVID-19 as an exception.</li>
<li>Census 2011 is the 15th National Census of the Country.</li>
<li>The Census established that the Total Fertility Rate (TFR) is coming down at a very rapid pace and is well on its way to stabilization.</li>
<li>The 2011 Census also dispelled the notion of divorce rate differentials between city and rural India. The urban divorce rate (0.89%) is almost equal to the rural rate (0.82%).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="census" class="alignnone wp-image-639441" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Census-exercise_featured-image-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Census-exercise_featured-image-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Census-exercise_featured-image-1024x572.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Census-exercise_featured-image-768x429.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Census-exercise_featured-image-1200x670.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Census-exercise_featured-image.jpg 1390w" width="600"/>Why census 2021 has been postponed indefinitely?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Ministry of Home Affairs told the Lok Sabha in August, 2021 that the massive, decennial exercise came to a grinding halt due to the advent of Coid-19 pandemic.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the original timeline of the Census and how is it being delayed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Gazette notification: </strong>The Centre’s intent to conduct Census 2021 was notified in the Gazette of India on March 28, 2019. The exercise was to have been conducted in two phases, with the housing Census from April to September 2020 and population enumeration from February 9, 2021.but it did not take place due to the spread of COVID-19.</li>
<li><strong>Alternative timeline post-covid-19: </strong>In March 2021, the Home Ministry gave a Parliamentary panel a tentative alternative timeline. The fieldwork for the first phase, which would provide data on housing conditions, household amenities and assets possessed by households, is expected during 2021-22, while the fieldwork to count the population and provide data on demography, religion, Scheduled Castes and Tribes (SC/ST), language, literacy and education, economic activity, migration and fertility would be done in 2023-24, it said.</li>
<li><strong>Said Provisional data: </strong>The Ministry added that provisional data would be released in 2023-24 before the next general elections. Usually, more detailed tables providing village-level data on specific indicators will continue to be released for several years after the key information.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="census" class="alignnone wp-image-639443" height="266" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 505px) 100vw, 505px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/population-census-2021-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/population-census-2021-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/population-census-2021-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/population-census-2021-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/population-census-2021.jpg 1200w" width="505"/>Impact of delay in census 2021</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Public distribution system</strong>:</li>
<li>The National Food Security Act, 2013, says that 75% of the rural population and 50% of the rural population are entitled to receive subsidised food grains from the government under the targeted public distribution system (PDS).</li>
<li>Under the 2011 Census, India’s population was about 121 crore, hence PDS covered approximately 80 crore people.</li>
<li>If we apply projected population of 137crore ,current delay in Census data would continue to deprive more than 10 crore people of subsidised food entitlements, with the biggest gaps in Uttar Pradesh and Bihar, with 2.8 crore and 1.8 crore projected exclusions respectively.</li>
<li><strong>welfare schemes:</strong></li>
<li>Although the Government’s intent to use SECC data but failed at budgetary allocation for the projected expansion<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>Census data may not be used to calculate the beneficiaries of most schemes, but it is critical to policy planning, budgeting and administration<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>A number of schemes need to use the disaggregated age and fertility indicators to assess effectiveness as demographics change over time.</li>
<li><strong>Huge lag in Migration data: </strong></li>
<li>From the COVID19 lockdowns it is realized that the Numbers, causes and patterns of migration, which could not be answered using outdated 2011 Census data.</li>
<li>The D-tables on migration from the 2011 Census were only released in 2019, so it’s outdated by the time it came out.</li>
<li>Apart from the One Nation, One Ration card scheme which now allows for portability of food subsidy entitlements, the migration data is actually not used too much in broader economic policy and planning.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/the-caste-census-debate/"><strong>Why there is a demand for caste census in India?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s population has since increased three-fold to 1.21 billion in 2011.</li>
<li>Experts believe the economic status of the dominant OBC castes have improved in the past 80 years and certain castes have not benefited as much.</li>
<li>So, the new caste census is required to measure the economic and social well-being of all castes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other related information Key findings of 2011 census</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Population</strong><strong>:</strong></li>
<li>India’s population grew by 17.7 per cent during 2001-11, against 21.5 per cent in the previous decade.</li>
<li>India’s total population stands at 1.21 billion, which is 17.7 per cent more than the last decade, and growth of females was higher than that of males.</li>
<li>The growth rate of females was 18.3 per cent which is higher than males — 17.1 per cent.</li>
<li>Among the major states, highest decadal growth in population has been recorded in Bihar (25.4 per cent) while 14 states and Union Territories have recorded population growth above 20 per cent.</li>
<li><strong>Rural and urban population:</strong></li>
<li>Urban proportion has gone up from 17.3 per cent in 1951 to 31.2 per cent in 2011.</li>
<li>Highest proportion of urban population is in NCT Delhi (97.5 per cent).</li>
<li>Top five states in share of urban population are Goa (62.2 per cent), Mizoram (52.1 per cent), Tamil Nadu (48.4 per cent), Kerala (47.7 per cent) and Maharashtra (45.2 per cent).</li>
<li><strong>Literacy</strong>:</li>
<li>Literacy rate in India in 2011 has increased by 8 per cent to 73 per cent in comparison to 64.8 per cent in 2001.</li>
<li>Male literacy rate stands at 80.9 per cent, which is 5.6 per cent more than the previous census whereas the female literacy rate stands at 64.6 per cent, increase of 10.9 per cent than 2001.</li>
<li>The highest increase took place in Dadra and Nagar Haveli by 18.6 points (from 57.6 per cent to 76.2 per cent), while in Bihar by 14.8 points (from 47.0 per cent to 61.8 per cent), Tripura by 14.0 points (from 73.2 per cent to 87.2 per cent)</li>
<li><strong>Density</strong>:</li>
<li>The density of population in the country has also increased from 325 in 2001 to 382 in 2011 in per sq km.</li>
<li>Among the major states, Bihar occupies the first position with a density of 1106, surpassing West Bengal which occupied the first position during 2001.</li>
<li>Delhi (11,320) turns out to be the most densely inhabited followed by Chandigarh (9,258), among all states and UT’s, both in 2001 and 2011 Census.</li>
<li>The minimum population density works out in Arunachal Pradesh (17) for both 2001 and 2011 Census.</li>
<li><strong>Sex ratio</strong>:</li>
<li>The sex ratio of population in the country in 2011 stands at 940 female against 1000 males, which is 10 per cent more than the last census when the number female per thousand male stood at 933.</li>
<li>The number of females per 1000 males in Haryana in 2011 stands at 879 followed by Jammu and Kashmir (889 female) and Punjab (895 females).</li>
<li>The other two worst-performing states in terms of skewed sex ration are Uttar Pradesh (912 females) and Bihar (918 females).</li>
<li>Five top performing states in terms of sex ratio were Kerala (1,084 females), Tamil Nadu (996), Andhra Pradesh (993), Chhattisgarh (991),Odisha (979).</li>
<li><strong>Child population</strong>:</li>
<li>Child population in the age of 0 to 6 years has seen an increase of 0.4 per cent.</li>
<li>There has been a decline of 8 per cent in the sex ratio of 0-6 age group. In 2011, the child sex ratio (0-6) stands at 919 female against 1000 male in comparison to 927 females in 2001.</li>
<li>Male child (0-6) population has increased whereas female child population has decreased during 2001-11.</li>
<li>The worst performing states in regard to sex ration in the age group of 0 to 6 years are Haryana (834 females), Punjab (846), Jammu and Kashmir (862), Rajasthan (888) and Gujarat (890).</li>
<li>The best performing states are Chhattisgarh (969), Kerala (964), Assam (962), West Bengal (956) Jharkhand (948) and Karnataka (948).</li>
<li><strong>SC/ST data</strong>:</li>
<li>According to the Census, Scheduled Castes are notified in 31 states and UTs and Scheduled Tribes in 30 states. There are altogether 1,241 individual ethnic groups notified as SC’s .The number of individual ethnic groups, notified as ST’s is 705.</li>
<li>There have been some changes in the list of SC’s/ST’s in states and UT’s during the last decade.</li>
<li>The SC population in India now stands at 201.4 million, which is 20 per cent more than the last census. The ST population stands at 104.3 million in 2011 – 23.7 per cent more than 2001.</li>
<li><strong>Religious demographics</strong>:</li>
<li>The religious data on India Census 2011 was released by the Government of India on 25 August 2015.</li>
<li>Hindus are 79.8% (966.3 million), while Muslims are 14.23% (172.2 million) in India.</li>
<li>For the first time, a “No religion” category was added in the 2011 census. 2.87 million Were classified as people belonging to “No Religion” in India in the 2011 census. – 0.24% of India’s population of 1.21 billion.</li>
<li><strong>Median marriage age</strong>:</li>
<li>The median age increased for men – from 22.6 (2001) to 23.5 (2011) and for women – from 18.2 (2001) to 19.2 (2011).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The census is vital and precious as it is a repository of complete data about the country which is gathered openly, voluntarily, and with the use of public money, making it a social good.</li>
<li>The new Census is likely to capture the extent of the observed movement in migration trends towards smaller two-tier towns apart from the large metropolitan centre.</li>
<li>It could help answer questions of what kind of healthcare and social services are most needed and where.</li>
<li>The Census is about many things. But, fundamentally, it is a way in which the state, by knocking at all doors, displays its desire to connect with the people who ultimately comprise the nation.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Apart from being used to demarcate constituencies, updated decadal census data is vital to administration. How will the indefinite postponement of census impact the policy formation for the future? Critically Analyse.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> Do follow this link </strong></p>
<p class="entry-title"><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/census-2011-the-basics-and-summary-of-important-findings/">Census 2011 | The basics and summary of important findings</a></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/census/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>