<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 11:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Supreme Court’s basic structure doctrine in a new context</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/basic-structure/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Various judgements on basic structure</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Features of constitution</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="basic structure" class="alignnone wp-image-637988" height="285" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 506px) 100vw, 506px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BASIC-STRUCURE-DOCTRINE-IN-INDIAN-CONSTITUTION-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BASIC-STRUCURE-DOCTRINE-IN-INDIAN-CONSTITUTION-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BASIC-STRUCURE-DOCTRINE-IN-INDIAN-CONSTITUTION.jpg 560w" width="506"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The basic structure doctrine constitutes a high watermark in the assertion of the Supreme Court’s judicial power in the teeth of a determined majoritarian regime.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is basic structure of Constitution?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The basic structure doctrine is one of the fundamental judicial principles connected with the Indian Constitution. The doctrine of the basic structure holds that there is a basic structure to the Indian Constitution, and the Parliament of India cannot amend the basic features.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the significance of the basic structure in the Constitution of India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The doctrine of basic structure is nothing but a judicial innovation to ensure that the power of amendment is not misused by Parliament. The idea is that the basic features of the Constitution of India should not be altered to an extent that the identity of the Constitution is lost in the process.08-Dec-2021</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Courts are empowered under our Constitution to invalidate not only executive orders, but also legislative enactments that violate any part of the Fundamental Rights guaranteed in Part III of the Constitution (Bill of Rights).</li>
<li>But as to whether they are also empowered to adjudicate on the validity of constitutional amendments passed with the requisite special majority and following the procedure prescribed in Article 368 the Constitution is silent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="basic structure" class="alignnone wp-image-637989" height="412" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 731px) 100vw, 731px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r.jpeg 770w" width="731"/>Historical developments on evolution of basic structure doctrine </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Constitution provided a mechanism for parliament to amend the constitution in the form of article 368 but the nature and scope of this amending power was questioned in Supreme Court on multiple occasions. Supreme Court gave a series of judgement which ultimately culminated in probably the most landmark judgement Basic structure doctrine judgement.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Shankari Prasad Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Sajjan Singh Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Golakh Nath Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Kesvananda Bharati Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Minerva Mills case</strong></li>
<li><strong>I.R. Koelhi</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Constitutional Provisions</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>1st amendment and 9th schedule</strong></li>
<li><strong>24th amendment</strong></li>
<li><strong>42nd amendment</strong></li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<p>His holiness, Kesavananda bharati, challenged before the supreme court, the validity of 29th CAA which inserted some laws in 9th schedule and affected property of his Hindu Mutt.</p>
<h4><strong>What else was at stake?</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li>Supreme Court (R. C. Cooper case) had struck down bank nationalization act of 1969 which had nationalized 14 major banks for illusory compensation though it conceded parliament’s right to nationalise banks in national interest.</li>
<li>Supreme Court had struck down abolition of privy purses which was a betrayal of solemn promise to erstwhile kings by Sardar Patel.</li>
</ol>
<p>Supreme Court could do all this as it had held in 1967 in Golaknath case that fundamental rights could not be abridged.</p>
<p>Before returning back to Kesavananda, Let’s take a look at the relevant provisions of the constitution and Supreme Court interpretation of the same.</p>
<ul>
<li>Art 13(2) – Any LAW abridging fundamental rights mentioned in part 3 shall be null and void to the extent of contravention</li>
<li>Art 368 -Procedure to amend the constitution.</li>
<li>Art 19(f) – freedom to acquire hold on and dispose off property.</li>
<li>Art 31 – right to property</li>
</ul>
<p>Both the rights were subject to reasonable restriction in public interest and restriction were subject to judicial review.</p>
<p>Soon after the coming into force of the constitution, states enacted land reform acts #Zamindars challenged them. #Patna high court declared Bihar act as unconstitutional for violating right to property #interim parliament passed 1st CAA.</p>
<ol>
<li>ART 31B created 9th schedule. Laws inserted under it by constitutional amendment were immune to judicial review.</li>
</ol>
<p>Other provisions not imp for this article but imp for exams –</p>
<ol>
<li>Reasonable restrictions against freedom of expression under art 19.</li>
<li>To nullify judgment in State of Madras v. Champakam Dorairajan and giving effect to art 46 (promoting educational and economic interests of weaker sections) amplified article 15 (3)</li>
</ol>
<p>Zamindars didn’t like it, not one bit. And here comes the 1st salvo</p>
<h4><strong>Shankari Prasad v Union of India</strong></h4>
<p>Challenged 1st CAA. What was the court’s judgment?</p>
<ol>
<li>Difference b/w constituent power and ordinary legislative power i.e. amendment not law for the purpose of article 13</li>
<li>art 13 and 368 in conflict # apply DOCTRINE OF HARMONIOUS CONSTRUCTION # ART 13 not applicable to art 368</li>
</ol>
<p>Govt 1-0 Zamindars</p>
<p>Govt passed 17th amendment and inserted more laws under 9th schedule ‘</p>
<p>Zamindars fired another salvo-</p>
<h4><strong>Sajjan Singh vs state of rajasthan</strong></h4>
<p>Supreme Court sang Shankari prasad song again</p>
<p>Govt 2-0 jamindars</p>
<p>But Justice Mudholkar was of the view that the every Constitution has certain features which are basic in nature and those features cannot be changed.</p>
<p>2 minority judgements…. utter confusion. And you can see seeds of basic structure were sown here.</p>
<p>Zamindars fired 3rd salvo</p>
<h4><strong>Golaknath v. State of Punjab</strong></h4>
<p>11 judge bench overturned earlier 2 verdicts by a slender majority of 6-5</p>
<p>Really? What was the logic given here?</p>
<ol>
<li>Nothing to suggest constituent power to be separate from legislative power and even if distinct, amending power not same as constituent power which is given only to constituent assembly i.e. amendment is law and subject to article 13</li>
<li>Fundamental rights so sacrosanct and transcendental that they cannot be abridged even if whole parliament unanimously decided to abridge them.</li>
</ol>
<p>But it validated all previous land reform acts as nullifying them would create utter confusion</p>
<p>Govt angry – Zamindars angry</p>
<p>New landlords happy.</p>
<p>Loss – loss to defendants as well as petitioner.</p>
<p>Madam Indira was in power and she did not like this. Not one bit.</p>
<p>Along came 24th amendment to neutralize GOLAKNATH JUDGEMENT</p>
<ol>
<li>Art 13 inapplicable to art 368</li>
<li>Art 368 provided powers as well as procedure to amend the constitution</li>
<li>Parliament by way of addition, variation or repeal can amend any provision of constitution</li>
<li>President shall give assent to CA bills ( VERY VERY IMP FOR PRELIMS )</li>
</ol>
<p>But madam Indira wouldn’t just stop here as Cooper judgment (Bank nationalization ) also had to be neutralized.</p>
<p>Smarting from this setback, Madam Indira (the parliament, herself) passed 24th CAA to neutralise GOLAKNATH judgement. But there was also a small matter of reversing Copper judgment in bank nationalisation case so parliament passed 25th CAA.</p>
<ol>
<li>Art 19f delinked from 31, in effect parliament deciding compensation amount payable instead of courts.</li>
<li>Art 31c  -inserted under which – art 39b and c, most socialist of DPSPs (equitable distribution and prevention of concentration of wealth respectively) precede over 7 freedoms (art 19 ), equality (14), property (31)</li>
<li>Parliament’s power to determine if policy is to give effect to 39b and c not subject to judicial review.</li>
</ol>
<p>29th CAA had put Kerala land reform act under 9th schedule and his holiness challenged the provisions and all hell broke loose.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Now the 4th salvo</p>
<h4><strong><img alt="basic structure" class="alignnone wp-image-637990" height="345" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 616px) 100vw, 616px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1-300x168.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1-300x168.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1-768x431.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1.jpg 896w" width="616"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/kesavananda-bharati-case-1973-the-judgment-that-upheld-basic-structure-of-indias-constitution/">Kesvanada Bharati Case</a></strong></h4>
<p>A 13 judge bench is constituted and what does it do!</p>
<ol>
<li>Overturned Golaknath i.e. amendment not law, fundamental rights amendable, no implied limit under art 368 i.e. CAA 24 constitutional</li>
<li>Art 25 invalid to the extent it takes away judicial review i.e. 39 b and c above 14, 19 and 31 but subject to judicial review</li>
</ol>
<p>Most imp decision of all by slimmest of all 7-6 majority stated Parliament can amend any provision of the Constitution but the basic structure should not be destroyed, damaged or abrogated.</p>
<p>What’s the logic?</p>
<ol>
<li>Expression amendment did not encompass defacing the constitution such that it lost its identity.</li>
<li>In the garb of amendment parliament can not rewrite the constitution.</li>
</ol>
<p>Court gave relief to govt but reserved for itself power to review all amendment not just those that violate fundamental rights.</p>
<p>Aftermath</p>
<p>Indira Gandhi didn’t like the judgement one  bit. She (via the president) superseded 3 judges to appoint justice A.N. Ray as CJI.</p>
<p>Knives had been drawn and the battle was gonna be very bloody –</p>
<ul>
<li>Navnirman movement of JP (Jayprakash<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jayaprakash_Narayan" rel="noopener" target="_blank">)</a> had gathered steam, Indira was on the back foot and along came the judgement of Allahabad High Court convicting Indira of corrupt electoral practices. Election was declared null and void and  6 years ban to contest election was imposed on her.</li>
<li>Supreme Court stayed it and allowed her to remain PM but not to draw salary or speak or vote in parliament.</li>
<li>Darkest chapter in democracy’ 21 month emergency was declared on 25th June 1975 without even consulting cabinet (44th amendment made it mandatory for the president to have written advice of cabinet to declare emergency)</li>
</ul>
<p>Indira Gandhi wasn’t to sit quiet.</p>
<p>CAA 39th – election of president, VP, PM and speaker beyond judicial review</p>
<p>Clownish Rajnarayan challenged the CAA 39.</p>
<h4><strong>Indira Gandhi v/s Raj Narain Case</strong></h4>
<p>For the 1st time Supreme Court applied basic structure doctrine and considered free and fair election and rule of law to be part of basic structure. #amending act invalidated.</p>
<p>Note here that 4 of the 5 judges on the bench had given dissenting judgment in Bharati case but still applied the same doctrine for Supreme Court judgment becomes law until overruled by bigger bench (art 141).</p>
<p>Then how did Indira continue to be prime minister and contest election again and not get banned for 6 years?</p>
<p>Supreme court accepted retrospective amendment to electoral law i.e. electoral malpractice of Indira was no longer a corrupt practice.</p>
<p>Find out for fun the charges against Mrs. Gandhi for which she was convicted and what a popular British magazine had to say about the judgement.</p>
<p>Along came the mini constitution i.e 42nd amendment act TO ELIMINATE IMPEDIMENTS TO THE GROWTH OF THE CONSTITUTION –</p>
<ol>
<li>PART 4a fundamental duties</li>
<li>Socialist,secular and integrity word to preamble</li>
<li>New <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/indepth-understanding-of-the-directive-principles-of-state-policy/">DPSP</a>s were added</li>
</ol>
<p>And for the purpose of this article amendment to article 368 nullifying basic structure doctrine by adding amendments can’t be challenged in courts and parliament possessing unlimited power of amendment</p>
<ol start="4">
<li>All DPSPs to take precedence over all fundamental rights not just 39b and 39c.</li>
</ol>
<p>And Minerva Textile mills of Karnataka fired the 5th and the last salvo</p>
<h4><strong>Minerva Mills v Union of India</strong></h4>
<p>SC unanimously struck down amendment to article 368 holding limited amending power and judicial review to be part of basic structure.</p>
<p>Court held that constitution is founded on the bedrock of balance b/w FRs and DPSPs. Goals set out by DPSPs have to be achieved without abrogation of means provided by FRs.</p>
<p>What’s the logic?</p>
<p>If a donee was vested with limited power, it could not be exercised to control that very power power and convert into unlimited one.</p>
<p>Or</p>
<p>If a genie grants u 3 wishes, it is understood u can not, as one of the wish, ask for unlimited number of wishes!</p>
<p>Janta govt comes to power and 44th CAA deletes art 31 (b) right to property and 19 (f) freedom to acquire, hold and dispose of property as they were not considered part of basic structure</p>
<p>Right to property now a constitutional right under art 300A.</p>
<p>9th schedule and judicial review</p>
<h4><strong>I.R.Coelho vs state of TN</strong></h4>
<p>Supreme Court held that acts placed under 9th schedule after basic structure subject would be subject to judicial review to the extent of those acts violating basic structure of constitution.</p>
<p>Impact of basic structure doctrine.</p>
<p>It certainly saved Indian democracy from degenerating into authoritarian regime during those testing times but it has also given immense untold unbridled power to Supreme Court and made it the most powerful court in the world.</p>
<p>As we would later see in the NJAC Verdict (let’s call it 4th judges case), Supreme Court applied this doctrine, many would say for wrong reasons to strike down the act and kept for itself the power to appoint brother judges. In the original constitution only fetters on the power of parliament was art 13.</p>
<p>Relevance –  It was delivered at the time of single party rule both at the centre and most of the states. In the era of coalition politics no govt is going to wield so much power to destroy the constitution and then there is ever present danger of tyranny of unelected.</p>
<p>But only legitimate way to overturn the verdict would be a 15 judge bench so don’t hold your breath for that.</p>
<p>Now is the time for some thought questions</p>
<p>#1. Consider these 2 statements –</p>
<ol>
<li>Any LAW that is ordinary law violating provisions of constitution would be declared null and void to the extent of contravention.</li>
<li>Any LAW violating art 13 would be declared null and void</li>
</ol>
<p>Both statements are true…..If amendments were not law, what was the purpose of art 13 (2) other laws would anyway be declared unconstitutional!</p>
<p>#2. Is basic structure doctrine relevant in the present political scenario where no single party is unlikely to enjoy majority in both the houses?</p>
<p>#3. What should be the limits to amending power of parliament? Do u think for very substantial amendments instead of courts, people by way of referendum should determine whether amendment should go through or not?</p>
<p>#4. Whatever happens to original intent theory that constitutional courts have to interpret constitution in accordance with the implied intentions of founding fathers and there is enough evidence to suggest founding fathers thoughtfully kept FRs sacrosanct to prevent their abrogation or as we would see in a later article how supreme court by creative interpretation virtually changed procedure established by law in art 21 to due process of law while founding fathers deliberately kept expression as procedure established by law.</p>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>By restraining the amending powers of legislative organ of State, it provided basic Rights to Citizens which no organ of State can overrule. Being dynamic in nature, it is more progressive and open to changes in time unlike the rigid nature of earlier judgements.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. What do you understand by basic structure of constitution? Trace evolution of basic structure in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/basic-structure/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SC takes up pleas against Places of Worship Act</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-takes-up-pleas-against-places-of-worship-act/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Places of Worship Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with the Act</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has set the ball rolling on a series of petitions challenging the validity of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-places-of-worship-act/">Places of Worship Act of 1991</a>, a parliamentary law that protects the identity and character of religious places as on August 15, 1947.</p>
<h4>What are the petitions about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A slew of petitions has been filed against the Act.</li>
<li>The Act has fixed a retrospective cut-off date illegally barring Hindus, Jains, Buddhists and Sikhs from approaching courts to re-claim their places of worship which were invaded and encroached.</li>
<li>The main objective of these petitions is to set right a historical wrong committed by barbaric invaders.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Places of Worship Act, 1991</h4>
<ul>
<li>It was passed in 1991 by the P V Narasimha Rao-led government.</li>
<li>The law seeks to maintain the “religious character” of places of worship as it was in 1947 — except in the case of the Ram Janmabhoomi-Babri Masjid dispute, which was already in court.</li>
<li>The law was brought in at the peak of the Ram Mandir movement, exactly a year before the demolition of the Babri Masjid.</li>
<li>Introducing the law, then Home Minister S B Chavan said in Parliament that it was adopted to curb communal tension.</li>
</ul>
<p>What are its provisions?</p>
<h4>What are its provisions?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Anti-conversion:</strong> Section 3 of the Act bars the conversion, in full or part, of a place of worship of any religious denomination into a place of worship of a different religious denomination — or even a different segment of the same religious denomination.</li>
<li><strong>Holiness of a place:</strong> Section 4(1) declares that the religious character of a place of worship “shall continue to be the same as it existed” on August 15, 1947.</li>
<li><strong>Litigation:</strong> Section 4(2) says any suit or legal proceeding with respect to the conversion of the religious character of any place existing on August 15, 1947, pending before any court, shall abate — and no fresh suit or legal proceedings shall be instituted.</li>
<li><strong>Exception for Ayodhya:</strong> Section 5 stipulates that the Act shall not apply to the Ramjanmabhoomi-Babri Masjid case, and to any suit, appeal or proceeding relating to it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the law under challenge?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>cut-off date of August 15, 1947, is “arbitrary, irrational and retrospective</u></strong>” and prohibits Hindus, Jains, Buddhists, and Sikhs from approaching courts to “reclaim” their places of worship.</li>
<li>Such places, he argued, were “<strong><u>invaded” and “encroached” upon by “fundamentalist barbaric invaders</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The right-wing politicians have opposed the law even when it was introduced, arguing that the Centre has no power to legislate on “pilgrimages” or “burial grounds” which is under the state list.</li>
<li>Another criticism against the law is that the cut-off is the date of Independence, which means that the status quo determined by a colonial power is considered final.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-takes-up-pleas-against-places-of-worship-act/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Species in news: Tasmanian Tiger</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/species-in-news-tasmanian-tiger/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Tasmanian Tiger</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-623646" height="220" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tas-300x220.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tas-300x220.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tas.jpg 607w" width="300"/></p>
<p>Scientists in the US and Australia have embarked on a $15-million project to resurrect the thylacine or Tasmanian Tiger, a marsupial that went extinct in the 1930s, using gene-editing technology.</p>
<h4>Tasmanian Tiger</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Tasmanian tiger or thylacine (a dog-headed pouched dog) was an exclusively carnivorous marsupial that is considered to be extinct.</li>
<li>It has a resemblance to a dog, with its distinguishing features being the dark stripes beginning at the rear of its body and extending into its tail, its stiff tail and abdominal pouch.</li>
<li>The last known thylacine died in captivity over 80 years ago, in Tasmania’s Hobart Zoo in 1936.</li>
<li>It may also be the only mammal to have become extinct in Tasmania since the European settlement.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did they become extinct?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It was confined to Tasmania in recent times and disappeared from mainland Australia over 2000 years ago, mainly because of over-hunting by humans, diseases and competition from the Dingo (Canis lupus), a wild dog native to Australia.</li>
<li>The Thylacine was also persecuted because it was believed to be a threat to sheep and in its latter years it was hunted for the purposes of collection by museums and zoos.</li>
<li>As per some accounts, the introduction of sheep in 1824 led to a conflict between the settlers and thylacine.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ambitious project aims to reintroduce the animal to its native place Tasmania to revive the region’s lost ecological balance.</li>
<li>Interestingly, this is not the first attempt to revive thylacines.</li>
<li>In 1999, an Australian scientist, Dr Michael Archer, embarked on an unsuccessful journey to resurrect the animal using cloning technology from a perfectly preserved specimen in a museum.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The resurrection process</h4>
<ul>
<li>Even though the last living thylacine died over 86 years ago, many embryos and young specimens of the species have been preserved.</li>
<li>Scientists will be using a genome sequenced from a DNA extracted from a 108-year-old specimen held at Australia’s Victoria Museum.</li>
<li>This genome will be compared with the closest living animal of the species– the fat tailed dunnart — to identify all the differences.</li>
<li>Once all the differences are identified, scientists will engineer the living cell’s DNA where it is different, essentially engineering the extinct species back.</li>
<li>The fat-tailed dunnart is a mouse-like species in the Dasyuridae family in Australia. With an average body length of 2.4–3.5 inches, they are one of the smallest carnivorous marsupials.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Criticisms of the move</h4>
<ul>
<li>Researchers have raised concerns about the practicality of the technology.</li>
<li>De-extinction is a fairytale science a/c to them and is more about media attention for the scientists and less about doing serious science.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: De-extinction technology</h4>
<ul>
<li>De-extinction, or resurrection biology, is the method of creating a species that went extinct or is endangered, in order to revitalise ecological diversity and balance shattered due to reasons ranging from biodiversity loss to climate change.</li>
<li>While cloning is the most widely used method of de-extinction, genome editing and selective breeding are also considered effective ways.</li>
<li>The Pyrenean ibex, a subspecies of Spanish ibex, was one of the first extinct animals that have been resurrected using somatic cell nuclear transfer (SCNT).</li>
<li>However, the baby Ibex died minutes after its birth from lung defect.</li>
<li>One of the challenges of de-extinction is that reintroducing the species to its former habitat may make it an invasive species, which will also impact the balance of the current ecological system.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/species-in-news-tasmanian-tiger/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Process of sustainable tourism should be holistic and inclusive</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tourism-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Incredible India</p></div></div><p>“<em>To other Country, I may go as a tourist. But to India I come as a pilgrim</em>”, the words of Martin Luther King says a lot about India’s wisdom and tourism potential.</p>
<h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The three-day National Conference of State Tourism Minister was held at Dharamshala , a first of its kind meeting aimed  to discuss, debate and deliberate on modes and mechanisms to develop tourism in India .</li>
<li>The three-day National Conference concluded with the adoption of “Dharamshala Declaration” which affirms commitment toward developing “sustainable and responsible tourism” and positions India as a “global leader in the tourism sector by 2047”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism is travel for pleasure or business; also the theory and practice of touring, the business of attracting, accommodating, and entertaining tourists, and the business of operating tours.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Types of tourism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Domestic tourism</strong>: Refers to activities of a visitor within their country of residence and outside of their home (e.g. a Indian visiting other parts of India)</li>
<li><strong>Inbound tourism</strong>: Refers to the activities of a visitor from outside of country of residence (e.g. a Spaniard visiting Britain).</li>
<li><strong>Outbound tourism</strong>: Refers to the activities of a resident visitor outside of their country of residence (e.g. an Indian visiting an overseas country).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640662" height="327" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341.jpg 550w" width="580"/>What does sustainable tourism mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sustainable tourism is defined by the UN Environment Program and UN World Tourism Organization as “tourism that takes full account of its current and future economic, social and environmental impacts, addressing the needs of visitors, the industry, the environment and host communities.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the main importance of tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism boosts the revenue of the economy, creates thousands of jobs, develops the infrastructures of a country, and plants a sense of cultural exchange between foreigners and citizens.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640663" height="379" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 605px) 100vw, 605px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan.jpg 1024w" width="605"/>Why tourism is needed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism is not a fad. It is a compulsion driven by the urge to discover new places. Because we have this compulsion to venture into the unknown, we need each other. When humans travel, meet and exchange ideas, civilization flourishes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is “The Dharamshala Declaration” is all about?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Aim of the declaration: </strong>The Dharamshala Declaration aims to recognise India’s role in contributing towards global tourism as well as focusing on recovery by also promoting domestic tourism.</li>
<li><strong>Action plan:</strong> In the declaration, the Tourism Ministry has come up with a with a action plan to encourage more Indians to travel domestically and explore India’s natural, cultural, and spiritual beauty while simultaneously reaching the goal of an ‘Ek Bharat Shrestha Bharat’ (interaction and mutual understanding).</li>
<li><strong>Strategy: </strong>The Tourism Ministry has also been working with the Ministry of External Affairs to identify 20 Indian missions abroad with the highest tourist footfalls to India and build country-specific strategies to attract foreign tourists.</li>
<li><strong>Plan according to G-20: </strong>The Dharamshala Declaration affirms the plan to position India as a major tourism destination during its presidency of G-20 next year. India’s age-old dictum of ‘Atithi Devo Bhava’ will come to the fore as it welcomes delegates from the 20 countries/European Union.</li>
<li><strong>Necessary steps:</strong> The Ministry of Tourism also plans to work with other Ministries to bring in necessary interventions such as visa reforms, ease of travel, travel-friendly and improved immigration facilities at airports.</li>
<li><strong>National Tourism policy</strong><strong>:</strong> Drafted with a holistic vision and strategy to revive India’s tourism and targets to contribute USD 1 trillion to the GDP by 2047.<strong><br/>
</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640666" height="519" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 692px) 100vw, 692px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1200x900.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1980x1485.jpg 1980w" width="692"/>A draft on National <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gujarats-mice-tourism-policy/">Tourism Policy 2022</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Framework:</strong></li>
<li>Draft on National Tourism Policy 2022 aims at improving the framework conditions for tourism development in the country.</li>
<li>Supporting tourism industries, strengthening tourism support functions and developing tourism sub-sectors.</li>
<li>Impetus to digitalisation, innovation and technology through the National Digital Tourism Mission and skilling through the Tourism and Hospitality Sector Skill Mission.</li>
<li>The policy also gives a special impetus to private sector participation through public-private-partnerships (PPP)</li>
<li><strong>Guiding Principles</strong> :</li>
<li>Promoting sustainable, responsible and inclusive tourism in line with our civilisational ethos From Gautama to Gandhi, India has always spoken about the inherent need to live harmoniously with nature and within our means.</li>
<li>The National Green Tourism Mission aims at institutionalising green approach.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.incredibleindia.org/content/incredible-india-v2/en.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640665" height="375" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 666px) 100vw, 666px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-768x433.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism.jpg 1170w" width="666"/>Tourism Potential in India</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Employement generation:</strong> India has huge tourism potential. If capitalised properly it can emerge as one of the leading sectors to contribute to GDP and also has the potential to augment employment.</li>
<li><strong>The Pandemic cost and recovery: </strong>The pandemic has caused conspicuous losses for this sector but over the past few months, all the major tourism indices such as domestic air passenger traffic, hotel occupancy and tourist footfalls have shown signs of recovery and are going back to pre-pandemic levels.</li>
<li><strong>Short term estimate:</strong> By 2024, in short term the country is estimated to contribute USD 150 billion to the GDP from tourism, USD 30 billion in Foreign Exchange earnings and can get 15 million foreign tourist arrivals..</li>
<li><strong>Medium term by 2030:</strong> It is estimated to grow at seven to nine per cent Compound Annual Growth Rate in the coming decade. In the medium term, that is 2030, the tourism-related goals are USD 250 billion GDP contribution; 137 million jobs, 56 million foreign tourist arrivals and USD 56 billion in foreign exchange earnings.</li>
<li><strong>Visionary schemes</strong>: The visionary schemes like Swadesh Darshan or Dekho Apna Desh have the potential to increase tourism value while maintaining cultural integrity and ecological sustainability of the places.</li>
<li><strong>Dekho Apna Desh</strong>: Dekho apna desh rolled out in 2020 envisages encouraging domestic tourism, urging people to visit places in India. India is a land of rich cultural heritage.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>If the goal of positioning of India as one of the world’s best tourism destinations by 2047, there is need to integrate various schemes of different ministries. Need to involve various stakeholders, and local communities; necessary interventions at urban and rural level should be a priority.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Since the positive and negative outcomes of tourism depend on human factors, including the attitude and behavior of both tourists and hosts, in this context discuss India’s potential to become a global leader in tourism sector.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tourism-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SC Collegium approves names for appointments in three High Courts</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-collegium-approves-names-for-appointments-in-three-high-courts/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Collegium system, NJAC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court Collegium led by Chief Justice of India (CJI) U.U. Lalit has recommended eight names for appointment to the Bombay High Court.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Collegium System?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-collegium-system/">Collegium</a> of judges is the Indian Supreme Court’s invention.</li>
<li>It does not figure in the Constitution, which says judges of the Supreme Court and High Courts are appointed by the President and speaks of a process of consultation.</li>
<li>In effect, it is a system under which judges are appointed by an institution comprising judges.</li>
<li>After some judges were superseded in the appointment of the CJI in the 1970s, and attempts made subsequently to effect a mass transfer of High Court judges across the country.</li>
<li>Hence there was a perception that the independence of the judiciary was under threat. This resulted in a series of cases over the years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Evolution: The Judges Cases</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>First Judges Case (1981)</strong> ruled that the “consultation” with the CJI in the matter of appointments must be full and effective.</li>
<li>However, it rejected the idea that the CJI’s opinion, albeit carrying great weight, should have primacy.</li>
<li><strong>Second Judges Case (1993)</strong> introduced the Collegium system, holding that “consultation” really meant “concurrence”.</li>
<li>It added that it was not the CJI’s individual opinion, but an institutional opinion formed in consultation with the two senior-most judges in the Supreme Court.</li>
<li><strong>Third Judges Case (1998):</strong> On a Presidential Reference for its opinion, the Supreme Court, in the Third Judges Case (1998) expanded the Collegium to a five-member body, comprising the CJI and four of his senior-most colleagues.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The procedure followed by the Collegium</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Appointment of CJI</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The President of India appoints the CJI and the other SC judges.</li>
<li>As far as the CJI is concerned, the outgoing CJI recommends his successor.</li>
<li>In practice, it has been strictly by seniority ever since the supersession controversy of the 1970s.</li>
<li>The Union Law Minister forwards the recommendation to the PM who, in turn, advises the President.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Other SC Judges</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>For other judges of the top court, the proposal is initiated by the CJI.</li>
<li>The CJI consults the rest of the Collegium members, as well as the senior-most judge of the court hailing from the High Court to which the recommended person belongs.</li>
<li>The consultees must record their opinions in writing and it should form part of the file.</li>
<li>The Collegium sends the recommendation to the Law Minister, who forwards it to the Prime Minister to advise the President.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>For High Courts</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The CJs of High Courts are appointed as per the policy of having Chief Justices from outside the respective States. The Collegium takes the call on the elevation.</li>
<li>High Court judges are recommended by a Collegium comprising the CJI and two senior-most judges.</li>
<li>The proposal, however, is initiated by the Chief Justice of the High Court concerned in consultation with two senior-most colleagues.</li>
<li>The recommendation is sent to the Chief Minister, who advises the Governor to send the proposal to the Union Law Minister.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Does the Collegium recommend transfers too?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Yes, the Collegium also recommends the transfer of Chief Justices and other judges.</li>
<li>Article 222 of the Constitution provides for the transfer of a judge from one High Court to another.</li>
<li>When a CJ is transferred, a replacement must also be simultaneously found for the High Court concerned. There can be an acting CJ in a High Court for not more than a month.</li>
<li>In matters of transfers, the opinion of the CJI “is determinative”, and the consent of the judge concerned is not required.</li>
<li>However, the CJI should take into account the views of the CJ of the High Court concerned and the views of one or more SC judges who are in a position to do so.</li>
<li>All transfers must be made in the public interest, that is, “for the betterment of the administration of justice”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Loopholes in the Collegium system</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of Transparency:</strong> Opaqueness and a lack of transparency, and the scope for nepotism are cited often.</li>
<li><strong>Judges appointing Judge:</strong> The attempt made to replace it with a ‘National Judicial Appointments Commission’ was struck down by the court in 2015 on the ground that it posed a threat to the independence of the judiciary.</li>
<li><strong>Criteria:</strong> Some do not believe in full disclosure of reasons for transfers, as it may make lawyers in the destination court chary of the transferred judge.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In respect of appointments, there has been an acknowledgment that the “zone of consideration” must be expanded to avoid criticism that many appointees hail from families of retired judges.</li>
<li>The status of a proposed new memorandum of procedure, to infuse greater accountability, is also unclear.</li>
<li>Even the majority opinions admitted the need for transparency, now Collegiums’ resolutions are now posted online, but reasons are not given.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-collegium-approves-names-for-appointments-in-three-high-courts/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Supreme Court’s Three-Question Test for Validity of 10% EWS quota</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/supreme-courts-three-question-test-for-validity-of-ews-quota/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>EWS Quota , 103rd Amendment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court will today examine whether The Constitution (103rd Amendment) Act, which introduced a 10 per cent quota for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/economically-weaker-sections-ews-as-defined-by-govt-panel/">Economically Weaker Sections (EWS)</a> in government jobs and admissions, violates the basic structure of the Constitution.</p>
<p><strong>What is the news?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Constitution Bench has decided to examine three key issues to ascertain the validity of the amendment.</li>
<li>The challenge to the EWS quota was referred to a five-judge Bench in August 2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>EWS Quota: A backgrounder</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The 10% reservation was introduced through the 103rd Constitution Amendment and enforced in January 2019.</li>
<li>It added Clause (6) to Article 15 to empower the Government to introduce special provisions for the EWS among citizens except those in the classes that already enjoy reservation.</li>
<li>It allows reservation in educational institutions, both public and private, whether aided or unaided, excluding those run by minority institutions, up to a maximum of 10%.</li>
<li>It also added Clause (6) to Article 16 to facilitate reservation in employment.</li>
<li>The new clauses make it clear that the EWS reservation will be in addition to the existing reservation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>EWS quota: What are the issues fixed by the Supreme Court?</h4>
<p>Attorney General K K Venugopal had drafted <strong><u>four issues related to </u></strong><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/the-basic-structure-and-essential-feature-govern-now-the-political-and-juristic-destiny-of-indian-constitutional-development-comment-10-marks/"><strong>Basic Structure</strong></a> for the consideration of the Bench.  On September 8, the court decided to take up three of them:</p>
<ol>
<li>Whether the 103rd Constitution Amendment can be said to breach the basic structure of the Constitution <strong><u>by permitting the state to make special provisions, including reservation, based on economic criteria</u></strong>”;</li>
<li>Whether the amendment can be said to breach the basic structure <strong><u>by permitting the state to make special provisions in relation to admission to private unaided institutions</u></strong></li>
<li>Whether the basic structure is violated by excluding the SEBCs (Socially and Educationally Backward Classes)/ OBCs (Other Backward Classes)/ SCs (Scheduled Castes)/ STs (Scheduled Tribes) from the scope of EWS reservation.</li>
</ol>
<h4>What is the 103rd Amendment?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 103rd Amendment inserted Articles 15(6) and 16(6) in the Constitution to provide up to 10 per cent reservation to EWS other than backward classes, SCs, and STs in higher educational institutions and initial recruitment in government jobs.</li>
<li>The amendment empowered state governments to provide reservation on the basis of economic backwardness.</li>
<li>Article 15 prohibits discrimination on grounds of religion, race, caste, sex, or place of birth.</li>
<li>Article 16 guarantees equal opportunity in matters of public employment.</li>
<li>The additional clauses gave Parliament the power to make special laws for EWS like it does for SCs, STs, and OBCs.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Basis of EWS reservation: Sinho Commission</h4>
<ul>
<li>The EWS reservation was granted based on the recommendations of a commission headed by <strong><u>Major General (retd) S R Sinho. </u></strong></li>
<li>The commission, which was <strong><u>constituted in March 2005</u></strong> by the UPA government, <strong><u>submitted its report in July 2010.</u></strong></li>
<li>It recommended that <strong><u>all below-poverty-line (BPL) families</u></strong> <strong><u>within the general category</u></strong> and also all families <strong><u>whose annual family income from all sources is below the taxable limit</u></strong>, should be identified as EBCs (economically backward classes).</li>
</ul>
<h4>How is EWS status determined under the law?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The EWS criteria for employment and admission was notified on January 31, 2019 by the Department of Personnel and Training (DoPT) based on the 103rd Amendment.</li>
<li>Under the 2019 notification:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>A person who was not covered under the scheme of reservation for SCs, STs, and OBCs, and</li>
<li>Whose family had a gross annual income below Rs 8 lakh, was to be identified as EWS for the benefit of reservation.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The notification specified what constituted “income”, and excluded some persons from the EWS category if their families possessed certain specified assets.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Debate over the criteria</h4>
<ul>
<li>In October 2021, <strong><u>the Supreme Court</u></strong> <strong><u>asked the government how the threshold of Rs 8 lakh had been reached</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Centre told the court that it would <strong><u>revisit the income criterion</u></strong>, and set up a three-member panel for this purpose.</li>
<li>In January this year, the government accepted the committee’s report, which said that the threshold of <strong><u>Rs 8 lakh of annual family income seems reasonable</u></strong> for determining EWS and may be retained.</li>
<li>However, the committee said, EWS may exclude, irrespective of income, a person whose family has <strong><u>5 acres of agricultural land and above. </u></strong></li>
<li>Also, the committee recommended, the <strong><u>residential asset criteria may altogether be removed</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the basis of the challenge to the amendment?</h4>
<h4>(1) Vagueness of Basic Structure</h4>
<ul>
<li>The primary argument in this case is that the amendment violates the basic structure of the Constitution.</li>
<li>Although there is <strong><u>no clear definition of basic structure</u></strong>, any law that violates it is understood to be unconstitutional.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(2) Burden of Proof</h4>
<ul>
<li>When a law is challenged, the <strong><u>burden of proving it is unconstitutional lies on the petitioners</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(3) Sole economic criteria</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 103rd Amendment departs from this by promising special <strong><u>protections on the sole basis of economic status</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(4) Violating 50% cap</h4>
<ul>
<li>The petitioners have also challenged the amendment on the ground that it violates the Supreme Court’s 1992 ruling in <strong><u>Indra Sawhney &amp; Ors v Union of India</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This has <strong><u>upheld the Mandal report</u></strong> and capped reservations at 50 per cent.</li>
<li>The court had held that <strong><u>economic backwardness cannot be the sole criterion</u></strong> for identifying a backward class.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(5) Rights of educational institutions</h4>
<ul>
<li>Another challenge is on behalf of private, unaided educational institutions.</li>
<li>They have argued that their fundamental right to practise a trade/ profession is violated when the <strong><u>state compels them to implement its reservation policy</u></strong> and admit students on any criteria other than merit.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What has been the government’s stand in this matter so far?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In counter-affidavits, the govt has said that <strong><u>the state has a duty</u></strong> to protect the interests of economically weaker sections.</li>
<li>Against the argument of violation of the basic structure, the government said that the <strong><u>very identity of the Constitution has NOT been altered</u></strong>.</li>
<li>On the Indra Sawhney principle, the government has relied on the <strong><u>SC’s 2008 ruling in Ashoka Kumar Thakur v Union of India</u></strong>, in which the court upheld the 27 per cent quota for OBCs.</li>
<li>The argument is that the co<strong><u>urt accepted that the definition of OBCs was not made on the sole criterion of caste but a mix of caste and economic factors</u></strong>; thus, there need not be a sole criterion for according reservation.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/supreme-courts-three-question-test-for-validity-of-ews-quota/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>“Government of the people, by the people and for the people” for vibrant democracy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/democracy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Democratic credentials</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="democracy" class="alignnone wp-image-640675" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-300x199.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-300x199.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-1024x678.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-768x508.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-1536x1017.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-1200x794.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-1980x1311.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy.jpg 2000w" width="585"/>Context</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.g7germany.de/g7-en" rel="noopener" target="_blank">G7 nations and partner countries</a> including India recently signed “2022 Resilient democracies statement”-We, the Leaders of Germany, Argentina, Canada, France, India, Indonesia, Italy, Japan, Senegal, South Africa, the United Kingdom, the United States of America, and the European Union, affirm our commitment to strengthening the resilience of our democracies and to working towards equitable, inclusive and sustainable solutions to global challenges, including climate change and the COVID-19 pandemic, and reaffirm our commitment to the rules-based international order.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>How we define Democracy?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>“Government of the people, by the people and for the people” the words used by Abraham Lincoln in the year 1863 while talking about democracy<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Purpose of democracy</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Cornerstones of democracy include freedom of assembly, association, property rights, freedom of religion and speech, inclusiveness and equality, citizenship, consent of the governed, voting rights, freedom from unwarranted governmental deprivation of the right to life and liberty, and minority rights.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/highlights-of-the-democracy-report-2022/"><strong>Democracy Report 2022</strong></a></p>
<ul>
<li>The study, titled ‘Democracy Report 2022: Autocratisation Changing Nature?’ states that more than twice as many countries are undergoing Autocratisation as are witnessing democratization.</li>
<li>The conceptual scheme takes into account not only the electoral dimension (free and fair elections) but also the liberal principle that democracy must protect “individual and minority rights”</li>
<li>The V-Dem report classifies countries into four regime types based on their score in the Liberal Democratic Index (LDI): a)Liberal Democracy b)Electoral Democracy c)Electoral Autocracy and d)Closed Autocracy</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="democracy" class="alignnone wp-image-640676" height="383" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 676px) 100vw, 676px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/democracy-voting-1-300x170.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/democracy-voting-1-300x170.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/democracy-voting-1-768x435.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/democracy-voting-1.jpg 1000w" width="676"/>Where do the Reports and Indices put India?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Sweden based Sweden-based V-Dem Institute was harsher in its latest report on democracy. It said India had become an “electoral autocracy”</li>
<li>US-based non-profit Freedom House downgraded India from a free democracy to a “partially free democracy”.</li>
<li>India, described as a “flawed democracy”, slipped two places to 53rd position in the latest Democracy Index published by The Economist Intelligence Unit<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Status of Supporters of Democracy</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Decolonised African Countries: </strong></li>
<li>The number of African countries that have adopted democratic systems of government has grown since decolonisation, the collapse of communism and the ending of a number of civil wars.</li>
<li>Some countries, such as Ghana, are seen as resilient democracies, while for others the democratic transition is more fragile, after months of pro-democracy protests in 2019 in Sudan, a civilian-led transitional government is now paving the way for democracy after decades of military rule.</li>
<li><strong>India as example: </strong></li>
<li>India is the world’s largest democracy. India is staying as one unit despite having vast no of cultures, languages and religions. This is possible because of the democracy in India.</li>
<li>Minorities and disadvantaged sections are represented in parliament which enabled inclusive growth.</li>
<li>When India got independence, its economy was in shambles. Extreme poverty, unemployment, food insecurity were the major problems before Indian government. But India’s democratic constitution successfully balanced development and welfare of the country.</li>
<li>Now, India is one of the fastest growing economies in the world.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What critics arguing?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Democracy in crisis</strong>: Democracy is more in crisis than ever before, with the onset of centralisation of power, with a foreign policy defying public opinion, with the media centralised, and with corporate control of the economy tighter than ever.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing polarity: </strong>Threatening world order is emerging, which seeks to abrogate all individual rights and divide us along the extremist polarities that we thought had been neutralised.</li>
<li><strong>Global Crisis: </strong>We move into this new stage of conﬂict carrying the risk of a nuclear tragedy, further exacerbated by the collective buttressing of a global crisis of the novel coronavirus pandemic, uncontrollable ecological disasters, and food and water deﬁciency.</li>
<li><strong>Populism: </strong>Blatant fascist leanings of the so-called “democracies”, and escalating hunger and disease in Africa and other parts of the under-developed world give enough evidence that democracy faces serious issues of populism.</li>
<li><strong>Other global problems: </strong>Growing economic discrimination, overpopulation and environmental degradation, Misgivings about moral progress, about mutual understanding, exacerbate the dismal situation that faces humanity.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="democracy" class="alignnone wp-image-640677" height="301" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 602px) 100vw, 602px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-1024x512.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-1536x768.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-2048x1024.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-1200x600.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-1980x990.jpg 1980w" width="602"/>What can be done to strengthen the democracies further?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Strengthening public support:</strong> To protect freedom domestically and build support for a foreign policy that protects democratic rights and values abroad, it is essential to foster a stronger public understanding of democratic principles, especially among young people<strong>. </strong>civic education is necessary.</li>
<li><strong>Rule of law: </strong>In order to maintain trust in public institutions, the principles of legality, legal certainty and prohibition of arbitrariness of the executive powers, judicial independence, impartiality, and equality before the law need to be respected.</li>
<li><strong>Individual rights</strong><strong>: </strong>Democracy entails the right of individuals to participate in and influence the development of society, with free and fair elections at its core. Without an active turnout in elections and proper mechanisms for participation, the essence of democracy can be lost.</li>
<li><strong>Free speech: </strong>Free speech guard the freedom of expression and opinion, and affirmation of commitment to the very idea of democracy and a move towards opposing oppression and violence</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Democracy is always a work in progress. The key ingredients of democracy are effective and accountable institutions, and leadership. Institutions build resilience by embedding norms and standards and bridging periods of weak leadership.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Do you think Democracy is the best solution to tackle the growing fault lines between the communities? What makes India as the best example of Democracy to the world? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/democracy/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Backsliding on climate action</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/backsliding-on-climate-action/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Paris agreement</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Climate change</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>Europe is staring at a recession and its appetite for climate action is waning.</p>
<h4>Developed countries moving away from commitment</h4>
<ul>
<li>Countries in Europe led by Germany, Austria and the Netherlands are cranking up their coal plants again.</li>
<li>Fossil fuels are making a comeback and countries are rejecting the European Union (EU)’s plan to reduce natural gas consumption by 15%. Dutch, Polish and other European farmers are protesting against emission cuts from agriculture.</li>
<li>In the U.S. too, the Senate and the Supreme Court have struck blows to climate action.</li>
<li>And in the U.S. too, prices of fuel started increasing last year, not just this year.</li>
<li>Fossil fuels are making a quiet comeback, since the strength of the U.S. is its oil and gas industry.</li>
<li>That is why we have just witnessed a ‘re-calibration’ of U.S. policy towards the Gulf.</li>
<li>Coal, oil and gas are not going anywhere in the developed world; they are, in fact, making a comeback.</li>
<li>The West had rushed to draw down on fossil fuels even before technology for renewables were in place.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Global peaking issue</h4>
<ul>
<li>Article 4 of the Paris Agreement defines ‘Global Peaking’ thus: “In order to achieve the long-term temperature goal set out in Article 2, Parties aim <strong>to reach global peaking</strong> of greenhouse gas emissions as soon as possible, recognizing that peaking will take longer for developing country Parties.”</li>
<li>The developed countries, given their historical emissions, will have to peak first.</li>
<li>That’s why the reference is to<strong> ‘global peaking’</strong> and not ‘individual peaking’.</li>
<li>From this, it logically follows that when developing country parties peak later than developed countries, they will also achieve net zero later than developed countries.</li>
<li>Consequently, it is the logical conclusion of the Article 4 of the Paris Agreement that when we consider net zero, we should only consider ‘global net zero’ and not ‘individual net zero’ for 2050.</li>
<li>The statement calls on developed countries to do a net negative on mitigation by 2050 rather than just “net zero”, if they are serious about fighting climate change.</li>
<li>In effect, the West needs to do a net minus and not just net zero.</li>
<li>Thanks to the efforts of India, the phrase used in the 2021 summit-level declarations at both G-20 and Quad is ‘global net zero’. We need to build on this understanding.</li>
<li>India stands as beacon of hope in renewables.</li>
<li>It is time for all developing countries, especially the small island developing states, to make sure that the developed world doesn’t backslide on its commitments on mitigation yet again.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward for developing countries</h4>
<ul>
<li>With countries of the developed world almost sure to renege on their 2030 Paris Agreement commitments, countries of the developing world must do everything to hold the countries of the developed world to their commitments.</li>
<li>The Western nations have already started reinterpreting the Paris Agreement and look to downgrade their commitments.</li>
<li>The concept of net zero is being cleverly misinterpreted.</li>
<li> To bring this to the attention of the Global South, India, China and eight other countries from Africa, Asia and Latin America made a cross-regional statement on ‘global net zero’ on June 7 at the UN on World Environment Day.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>COP 27 in Egypt gives us that opportunity to hold their feet to the fire. It is time for the developed world to make net minus pledges. If we don’t collectively push for it, we will be collectively pushed back.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/backsliding-on-climate-action/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Fruit Fly: Novel method to study Nuclear Matrix</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nuclear Matrix</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627770" height="489" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 566px) 100vw, 566px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly.jpg 665w" width="566"/></p>
<p>Now, using a novel method, Indian researchers have established a way of studying the nuclear matrix of the fruit fly (Drosophila melanogaster) without removing the nucleus from the embryo.</p>
<h4>Nuclear Matrix of fruit flies</h4>
<ul>
<li>Every cell that makes up an organism contains a copy of its genome.</li>
<li>This genome is packaged in special ways with the help of a structure known as the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>The nuclear matrix gives an organisation and architecture to the nucleus.</li>
<li>A familiar figure, the nuclear matrix of fruit flies, for instance, has been studied for many years, mainly by isolating it in nuclei that have been taken out from fruit fly embryos.</li>
<li>This allows comparative study of nuclear matrix in different cells within the embryo, giving a boost for fruit fly genetics.</li>
<li>Two of the most recent papers on this work have been published in the journals Nucleus and Molecular and Cell Proteomics.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What exactly is Nuclear Matrix?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The nuclear matrix is like a scaffolding.</li>
<li>Using biochemical means, if the nucleus is taken out and treated with an enzyme that digests all the DNA.</li>
<li>It is then washed with a solution of high salt concentration so that viable DNA proteins or protein-protein interactions are removed.</li>
<li>What is then left is a fibrous meshwork of proteins called the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>This is like a building from which all movables have been sucked out, leaving only the beams, ceiling, and walls, plug points, etc.</li>
<li>Analogous to the building, the nuclear matrix creates the architecture in which the genome is packaged.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why study them?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Studying the nuclear matrix is, therefore, very important to get a better picture of how precisely development progresses every time a new individual is born.</li>
<li>We have 220 different types of cells in the body, but all contain identical genomes.</li>
<li>The same genome sequence is present in neurons, where it works for thinking; in the liver, the same sequence enacts metabolism; and in the intestine, it works to digest.</li>
<li>So, this information is packaged differently in different cell types.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Revisiting the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-627767" height="188" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-768x481.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji.jpg 885w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has referred to a three-judge Bench a series of petitions seeking a judicial direction that political parties who make wild promises should also reveal in their poll manifestos where they will get the money to pay for them.</p>
<p>The reference is a shift from the court’s own stand in the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs Tamil Nadu judgment of 2013.</p>
<h4>Hefty promises: A no lesser corrupt practice</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the <strong><u>Balaji case judgment</u></strong>, a Division Bench of the Supreme Court had held that making promises in election manifestos <strong><u>do not amount to a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> under Section 123 of the Representation of People Act (RP).</li>
<li>However, the Supreme Court is now worried that <strong><u>freebies promised</u></strong> by political parties to win elections could <strong><u>bleed the public exchequer dry</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Court said that parties who form the government riding the wave created by their pre-poll promises of free gifts are bleeding the State finances dry.</li>
<li>Parties actually try to <strong><u>fulfil their outlandish promises using public money</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Supreme Court has therefore decided to revisit the Balaji verdict.</p>
<h4>What triggered the Balaji case?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The course of events started in 2006, during the run-up to the Tamil Nadu Assembly elections.</li>
<li>A party released its election manifesto announcing a scheme of free distribution of colour television sets (CTVs) to each and every household if voted to power.</li>
<li>The party swept to power in the polls and decided to implement its scheme and portioned off ₹750 crore from the budget for the project.</li>
<li>The government finally distributed 30,000 TV sets across the State.</li>
<li>In 2011, the rival party also announced its election manifesto with free gifts to “equalise” the gifts offered.</li>
<li>It promised grinders, mixies, electric fans, laptop computers, four gram gold thalis, a cheque of ₹50,000 for women’s marriage, green houses, 20 kg of rice to ration card holders and free cattle and sheep.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Balaji case</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji, a resident of Tamil Nadu, challenged the schemes introduced by the parties in the Madras High Court.</li>
<li>He said that the <strong><u>expenditure was incurred by the State from the exchequer</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This was “<strong><u>unauthorised, impermissible and ultra vires the constitutional mandates</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>High Court dismissed his case</u></strong>, following which he had moved the apex court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did the case play out?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji argued that <strong><u>the State cannot act</u></strong> in furtherance of “<strong><u>eccentric principles of socialistic philanthropy</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>He argued that the promises of <strong><u>free distribution of non-essential commodities</u></strong> in an election manifesto amounts to electoral bribe under Section 123 of the RP Act.</li>
<li>Money can be taken out of the Consolidated Fund of the State <strong><u>only for “public purposes”</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>distribution of goods to certain sections</u></strong> of people was <strong><u>violative of Article 14 of the Constitution</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Argument provided against the Balaji Case</h4>
<ul>
<li>In response, the State of Tamil Nadu countered that <strong><u>promises do not constitute corrupt practice. </u></strong></li>
<li>Political parties are not the State and ‘<strong><u>freebies’ is a nebulous term which has no legal status</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises implemented by the party after forming the government is an <strong><u>obligation under the Directives Principles of State Policy</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The State is only doing its duty to promote the <strong><u>welfare of its people</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises are <strong><u>implemented by framing various schemes/guidelines/eligibility</u></strong> criteria etc. as well as <strong><u>with the approval of the legislature. </u></strong></li>
<li>Thus, it <strong><u>cannot be construed as a waste of public money</u></strong> or be prohibited by any statute or scheme.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Outcome of the Judgement</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court’s judgment held that <strong><u>promises by a political party cannot constitute a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> on its part.</li>
<li>It would be <strong><u>“misleading” to generalize</u></strong> that all promises in the election manifesto would amount to corrupt practice.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>manifesto is a statement of the policy</u></strong> for a political party.</li>
<li>The question of implementing the manifesto arises only if the political party forms a government.</li>
<li>It is the promise of a future government and not of an individual candidate.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Scope for revisiting the judgment</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court agreed that <strong><u>freebies create an “uneven playing field”.</u></strong></li>
<li>It had asked the Election Commission of India to <strong><u>consult political parties</u></strong> and issue guidelines on the election manifesto and make it a <strong><u>part of the Model Code of Conduct</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the Court’s move to review the Balaji judgment significant?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In its order, the court foresees that “freebies may create a situation wherein the <strong><u>State governments cannot provide basic amenities due to lack of funds</u></strong> and the State is pushed towards imminent bankruptcy”.</li>
<li>The court said it wants a <strong><u>transparent debate</u></strong> before the three-judge Bench on whether an “enforceable” judicial order can stop political parties from promising and distributing ‘irrational freebies’.</li>
<li>The case is unique as the Supreme Court is exploring <strong><u>whether judicial parameters can be set on a purely political act of promising freebies.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Explained: Bail for Women</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-bail-for-women/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Bails</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Different bail provisions</p></div></div><p>An activist recently walked out of a prison, a day after the Supreme Court granted her <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mudda-aapka-supreme-court-suggests-bail-act/">interim bail</a> in a case of allegedly fabricating evidence related to the 2002 Gujarat riots.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>Here we get to know that bail laws in India are not gender neutral. They somewhat favor women due to certain disprivileged social backgrounds.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>What is Bail?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bail is the conditional release of a defendant with the promise to appear in court when required.</li>
<li>The term also means the security that is deposited in order to secure the release of the accused.</li>
<li>In India’s legal world, the term offense has been categorized as bailable offenses and non-bailable under the Code of Criminal Procedure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need Bail?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bail is a <strong><u>fundamental aspect</u></strong> of any criminal justice system.</li>
<li>The practice of bail grew out of the need <strong><u>to safeguard the fundamental right to liberty</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Liberty is the right of one whose <strong><u>guilt has not yet been proven</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Types of Bail in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Depending upon the sage of the criminal matter, there are commonly three types of bail in India:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Regular bail:</strong> Regular bail is generally granted to a person who has been arrested or is in police custody. A bail application can be filed for regular bail under sections 437 and 439 of CrPC.</li>
<li><strong>Interim bail:</strong> This type of bail is granted for a short period of time and it is granted before the hearing for the grant of regular bail or anticipatory bail.</li>
<li><strong>Anticipatory bail:</strong> Anticipatory bail is granted under section 438 of CrPC either by session court or High Court. An application for the grant of anticipatory bail can be filed by the person who discerns that he may be arrested by the police for a non-bailable offense.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<p>Ans. <strong><u>Favorable treatment for Women</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>During the hearing, the Supreme Court of India has made an oral observation that under Section 437 of the Code of Criminal Procedure (CrPC), a woman is entitled to favourable treatment.</li>
<li>The provision says that, being a woman is a possible ground for granting bail, even when otherwise it cannot be considered.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does the bail provision say in favor of Women? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Section 437</u></strong> of the CrPC deals with bail in case of non-bailable offences.</li>
<li>It says a person shall not be released on bail if there is reasonable ground to believe that he has committed an offence punishable with <strong><u>death or life imprisonment</u></strong>.</li>
<li>However, it also contains exceptions in a provision that says the court may grant bail even in these cases, “<strong><u>if such person is under the age of 16 or is a woman or is sick or infirm</u></strong>”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Are there other provisions favourable to women accused? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There are several provisions in criminal law that give special consideration to women, of any age, when they are victims of offences, including sexual offences, in the way they are treated as witnesses and victims of crimes.</li>
<li>There are also some provisions relating to women when they are made an accused, and arrested.</li>
<li>For instance, when a police officer requires the attendance of any person who he believes is acquainted with a case under investigation, the person has to appear before the officer (Section 160).</li>
<li>However, no woman shall be required to do so at any place other than the place in which she resides.</li>
<li>This is understood to mean that the officer has to visit the place of residence to make enquiries.</li>
<li>This benefit is also available to boys under 15, men above 65 and any mentally or physically disabled person.</li>
<li>In its 84th and 135th Report in 1980 and 1989, the Law Commission suggested that the word ‘place’ is ambiguous, and it would be better to amend it to ‘dwelling place’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does the CrPC say on the arrest of a woman? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A police officer <strong><u>may arrest a person who has committed a cognisable offence without a judicial order</u></strong> or a warrant (Section 41).</li>
<li>If the person does not submit to custody based on the word or action of the police, Section 46 enables the police officer to confine the person physically to effect the arrest.</li>
<li>A proviso was introduced in the CrPC in 2009 to the effect that where a woman is to be arrested, <strong><u>only a female police officer may touch the woman’s person</u></strong>, unless circumstances otherwise require.</li>
<li>Earlier, through a 2005 amendment, a subsection was added to Section 46 to <strong><u>prohibit the arrest of a woman after sunset or before sunrise. </u></strong></li>
<li>However, in exceptional circumstances, a woman police officer can obtain the prior permission of a judicial magistrate to make the arrest.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does it say on women who don’t appear in public? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The police <strong><u>may seek entry into any premises</u></strong> where they suspect that a person who is required to be arrested is present.</li>
<li>In a situation where any such place is an apartment in the occupancy of a female (who is not the person to be arrested) and if the woman is one who, by custom, does not appear in public, <strong><u>the police have to give notice to her</u></strong> so that she may withdraw before they enter it (Proviso to Section 47).</li>
<li>It adds that they shall afford her every reasonable facility for withdrawing before they break open and enter the place.</li>
<li>In yet another exception, a woman who intends to file a defamation case, but is one who does not appear in public according to custom, can ask someone else to file the complaint on her behalf.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="dMXZ5OMscU"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mudda-aapka-supreme-court-suggests-bail-act/">[Sansad TV] Mudda AapKa: Supreme Court Suggests “Bail Act”</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="dMXZ5OMscU" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mudda-aapka-supreme-court-suggests-bail-act/embed/#?secret=bbmaYrMwEk#?secret=dMXZ5OMscU" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Sansad TV] Mudda AapKa: Supreme Court Suggests “Bail Act”” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-bail-for-women/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was Ramon Magsaysay of Philippines?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-ramon-magsaysay-of-philippines/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ramon Magsaysay</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-631406" height="237" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 350px) 100vw, 350px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay-300x203.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay-300x203.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay.jpg 637w" width="350"/></p>
<p>A leftist leader and former Kerala health minister has declined to receive the Ramon Magsaysay Award as the late President of the Philippines was known for his alleged brutality against the Communists.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lunched in 1958, the Ramon Magsaysay Award, widely considered to be Asia’s equivalent to the Nobel Prize, recognises outstanding leadership and communitarian contributions in Asia.</li>
<li>This year’s annual list of awardees was announced last week.</li>
<li>Shailaja was considered for the award for her performance as state health minister from 2016 to 2021, a period which saw Kerala fight against the Nipah virus and Covid-19.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who was Ramon Magsaysay?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Born on August 31, 1907 to a father who worked as a blacksmith and a mother who was a teacher, Ramon Del Fierro Magsaysay Senior was the seventh president of the Philippines, from 1953 until his death in an air crash in 1957.</li>
<li>Magsaysay started out as an automobile mechanic before being drafted into the Pacific War (1941-1945), during World War II.</li>
<li>The Pacific War would see the Japanese occupation of the Philippines — then a colony of the US — for nearly four years.</li>
<li>The US formally recognised the Philippines as an independent nation in 1946.</li>
</ul>
<h4>His legacy</h4>
<ul>
<li>As a guerrilla leader resisting the Japanese occupation, Magsaysay’s bravery and leadership saw his appointment as a military governor.</li>
<li>In 1946, he would be elected under the Liberal Party to the Philippine House of Representatives, where he would serve two terms as a Congressman before being appointed secretary of National Defence in 1950.</li>
<li>On December 30, 1953, he would be elected president from the Nationalist Party, the oldest political party in the Philippines.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Communism and Magsaysay</h4>
<ul>
<li>Founded in 1902, the Unión Obrera Democrática is considered the first modern trade federation in the Philippines.</li>
<li>The Communist Party of the Philippines or the Partido Komunista ng Pilipinas (PKP) was formed in 1930.</li>
<li>The Hukbong Bayan Laban sa Hapon or the People’s Army Against the Japanese, popularly known as the Hukbalahap (Huk), was a prominent guerrilla outfit that fought the Japanese.</li>
<li>As the country plunged into post-war chaos after 1946, the fortunes of the Hukbalahaps, too, changed dramatically.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How he rose to his fame?</h4>
<ul>
<li>With the expansion of capitalism, the gap between the rich and poor widened and the farmers continued to languish.</li>
<li>Huk leaders were viewed with suspicion over their declaration of commitment to communism and the demand for peasant rights.</li>
<li>With the US as its close ally, the Philippine government cracked down on the Huks, who formed an alliance with the PKP to take their struggle to a parliamentary platform.</li>
<li>The severe crackdown against the Huks continued until Magsaysay became the National Defence Secretary under President Elpidio Quirino.</li>
<li>Magsaysay drew upon his own experience of guerrilla warfare to initiate a two-pronged system of reforms and military campaigns.</li>
<li>It was under his administrative and military policies that the Huk threat was considered to be neutralised.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Ramon Magsaysay Award</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 1957, the Ramon Magsaysay award was set up by trustees of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund and the Philippine government to carry forward Magsaysay’s legacy of service to the people, good governance, and pragmatic idealism.</li>
<li>In the six decades since 1958 — the first year the Award was given out — over 300 organisations and individuals have been recognised for their developmental endeavours crucial to Asia, and, consequently, to the world.</li>
<li>The award is given out every year on August 31, on Magsaysay’s birth anniversary.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Indian winners on the list</h4>
<ul>
<li>Prominent Indians who have won the award include Vinoba Bhave in 1958, Mother Teresa in 1962, Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay in 1966, Satyajit Ray in 1967, Mahasweta Devi in 1997.</li>
<li>In recent years, Arvind Kejriwal (2006), Anshu Gupta of Goonj (2015), human rights activist Bezwada Wilson (2016), and journalist Ravish Kumar (2019) have won the award.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-ramon-magsaysay-of-philippines/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Carl-Gustaf M4 to be produced in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gustaf-m4-to-be-produced-in-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Carl-Gustaf M4</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="gustaf" class="alignnone wp-image-641101 size-full" height="853" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav.jpg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav-300x237.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav-1024x809.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav-768x607.jpg 768w" width="1080"/></p>
<p>Swedish defense major SAAB announced plans to manufacture its Carl-Gustaf M4 weapon system in India.</p>
<h4>What is the Carl-Gustaf M4?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Carl-Gustaf recoilless rifle is a man-portable, multi-role weapon system that allows dismounted soldiers to effectively deal with multiple challenges on the modern battlefield.</li>
<li>A proven performer in battle, the Carl-Gustaf M4 is said to be adaptable and flexible.</li>
<li>The Indian Army has been using the iconic Carl-Gustaf since 1976 and currently operates the Mk2 and Mk3 versions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Key features of Carl-Gustaf M4</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lightweight, robust, reliable, effective and easy to use</li>
<li>Tactical flexibility through a wide range of ammunition</li>
<li>Combat proven system</li>
<li>Ammunition: Anti-armour, anti-structure, anti-personnel, support</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In recent years, the Indian government has taken several steps to boost the defense manufacturing sector under the ‘Make in India’ and <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-self-reliance-in-defence/">‘Atmanirbhar Bharat’</a></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gustaf-m4-to-be-produced-in-india/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Jaldoot App to capture data on Groundwater Levels</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/jaldoot-app-to-capture-data-on-groundwater-levels/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Jaldoot App</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-641102" height="451" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 372px) 100vw, 372px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-248x300.jpg 248w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-845x1024.jpg 845w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-768x931.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-743x900.jpg 743w" width="372"/></p>
<p>With the rapidly declining water table threatening to push many regions into drought, the Union government on has launched a mobile application — Jaldoot.</p>
<h4>Jaldoot App</h4>
<ul>
<li>Jaldoot is jointly developed by the Rural Development and Panchayati Raj Ministries to monitor the groundwater levels across the country.</li>
<li>The App will enable Gram Rojgar Sahyak to measure the water level of well twice a year pre-monsoon and post-monsoon.</li>
<li>Jaldoots, that is, officers assigned to measure the water levels, should also upload the geo-tagged photographs through the app on every occasion of measurement.</li>
<li>This Mobile app will work in both online and offline mode.</li>
<li>So water level can be captured even without internet connectivity and captured date will be stored in mobile and when mobile comes in the connectivity area, data will synchronize with the central server.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Utility of the app</h4>
<ul>
<li>The despite promoting watershed development, afforestation, waterbody development and renovation, rainwater harvesting like initiatives, the ground water level in various parts of the country has depleted.</li>
<li>The regular data to be input by the Jaldoots would be integrated with the database of National Water Informatics Centre (NWIC), which can be utilised for analysis and display.</li>
<li>The app will facilitate in observing water tables across the country and the resulting data can be utilised for Gram Panchayat Development Plan and Mahatma Gandhi NREGA Plans.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/jaldoot-app-to-capture-data-on-groundwater-levels/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Places in news: Ram Setu</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-ram-setu/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ram Setu</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="ram setu" class="alignnone wp-image-641104 size-full" height="313" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 556px) 100vw, 556px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/setu.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/setu.jpg 556w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/setu-300x169.jpg 300w" width="556"/></p>
<p>A movie has once again generated buzz around the chain of shoals off the southeast coast of India that many believe is the Ram Setu or the bridge to Lanka mentioned in the Ramayana.</p>
<h4>The Ram Setu</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Ram Setu, also known as Adam’s Bridge, is a 48-km chain of limestone shoals between Rameswaram on India’s southeast coast and Mannar Island near Sri Lanka’s northwest coast.</li>
<li>The structure has significance in both Hindu and Muslim mythology – while Hindus believe this is the bridge (Setu) built by Lord Ram and his army to cross to Lanka and fight Ravan.</li>
<li>As per Islamic legend, Adam used this bridge to reach Adam’s Peak in Sri Lanka, where he stood on one foot for 1,000 years in repentance.</li>
</ul>
<p>Factual details of the bridge</p>
<ul>
<li>Scientists believe Ram Setu is a natural structure formed due to tectonic movements and sand getting trapped in corals.</li>
<li>However, over the years, evidence has been offered to claim that the bridge is man-made.</li>
<li>The bridge is not entirely natural, Hindu right wing outfits argue, which proves that it was indeed built by Lord Ram.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When was the structure came into highlights?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Ram Setu issue snowballed into a major controversy when the Sethusamudram Project, flagged off during the UPA I government.</li>
<li>The project aimed to reduce travel time between the eastern and western coasts of India, as ships would no longer have to circle Sri Lanka to travel between the Bay of Bengal and Arabian Sea.</li>
<li>The project was perceived as an attack on Hindu sentiments.</li>
<li>Various studies have been proposed on the Ram Setu, with the most recent being in 2021, when the government approved an underwater research project to ascertain its origins.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Ecological arguments against the project</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Sethusamudram project has been opposed on environmental grounds.</li>
<li>Some claims that it will harm marine life, and that dredging of the line of shoals will make India’s coast more vulnerable to tsunamis.</li>
<li>In March 2018, the Centre told the Supreme Court that the Ram Setu will not be affected in the execution of the Sethusamudram Shipping Canal project.</li>
</ul>
<h4>NASA images, and other proofs</h4>
<ul>
<li>Images of the Ram Setu clicked by NASA have been used over and over again to claim that this proves the existence of a man-made bridge.</li>
<li>NASA has repeatedly clarified that it does not agree with these claims.</li>
<li>Remote sensing images or photographs from orbit cannot provide direct information about the origin or age of a chain of islands.</li>
<li>It certainly cannot be determined whether humans were involved in producing any of the patterns seen.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-ram-setu/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Maharashtra Election Symbols Issue</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/maharashtra-election-symbols-issue/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Allocation of election symbols</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>In a blow to one faction, a Constitution Bench of the Supreme Court allowed the Election Commission (EC) to take a decision on the Maharashtra CM claim that his faction represents the “real” party.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Bench led by Justice D.Y. Chandrachud rejected the plea to stay the EC proceedings under the Election Symbols (Reservation and Allotment) Order of 1968.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A party has lost a large number of members in the rebellion that eventually caused the fall of the government in Maharashtra.</li>
<li>The rebel has claimed to be the only original leader of the party on the basis of the support of more than two-thirds of the party’s legislators in the Maharashtra Assembly.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Options for ECI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ECI in all likelihood can freeze the symbol so that neither of the two sides is able to use it until a final decision is made.</li>
<li>EC hearings are long and detailed, and may take at least six months.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>EC’s powers in Election Symbol Dispute</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The question of a split in a political party outside the legislature is dealt by Para 15 of the Symbols Order, 1968.</li>
<li>It states that the ECI may take into account all the available facts and circumstances and undertake a test of majority.</li>
<li>The decision of the ECI shall be binding on all such rival sections or groups emerged after the split.</li>
<li>This applies to disputes in recognised national and state parties.</li>
<li>For splits in registered but unrecognized parties, the EC usually advises the warring factions to resolve their differences internally or to approach the court.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How did the EC deal with such matters before the Symbols Order came into effect?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Before 1968, the EC issued notifications and executive orders under the Conduct of Election Rules, 1961.</li>
<li>The most high-profile split of a party before 1968 was that of the CPI in 1964.</li>
<li>A breakaway group approached the ECI in December 1964 urging it to recognise them as CPI(Marxist). They provided a list of MPs and MLAs of Andhra Pradesh, Kerala and West Bengal who supported them.</li>
<li>The ECI recognised the faction as CPI(M) after it found that the votes secured by the MPs and MLAs supporting the breakaway group added up to more than 4% in the 3 states.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the first case decided under Para 15 of the 1968 Order?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It was the first split in the Indian National Congress in 1969.</li>
<li>Indira Gandhi’s tensions with a rival group within the party came to a head with the death of President Dr Zakir Hussain on May 3, 1969.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Is there a way other than the test of majority to resolve a dispute over election symbols?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In almost all disputes decided by the EC so far, a clear majority of party delegates/office bearers, MPs and MLAs have supported one of the factions.</li>
<li>Whenever the EC could not test the strength of rival groups based on support within the party organisation (because of disputes regarding the list of office bearers), it fell back on testing the majority only among elected MPs and MLAs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What happens to the group that doesn’t get the parent party’s symbol?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The EC in 1997 did not recognise the new parties as either state or national parties.</li>
<li>It felt that merely having MPs and MLAs is not enough, as the elected representatives had fought and won polls on tickets of their parent (undivided) parties.</li>
<li>The EC introduced a new rule under which the splinter group of the party — other than the group that got the party symbol — had to register itself as a separate party.</li>
<li>It could lay claim to national or state party status only on the basis of its performance in the state or central elections after registration.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/maharashtra-election-symbols-issue/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why India has lashed out at the US over its F-16 package to Pakistan?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-india-has-lashed-out-at-the-us-over-its-f-16-package/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>F-16</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>US's double standards over Pakistan</p></div></div><p><img alt="f-16" class="alignnone wp-image-641100 size-full" height="447" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f-16.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f-16.jpg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f-16-300x224.jpg 300w" width="600"/></p>
<p>EAM S Jaishankar has lashed out at the US for its decision to provide Pakistan with a $450 million package for F-16 case fighter aircraft upgrade.</p>
<h4>F-16 and Pakistan</h4>
<ul>
<li>The F-16 is a single-engine multirole fighter aircraft originally developed by General Dynamics for the United States Air Force (USAF).</li>
<li>Designed as an air superiority day fighter, it evolved into a successful all-weather multirole aircraft.</li>
<li>The F-16 were inducted into Pakistan Air Force in 1983 during the Soviet-Afghan War.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Suspicion over US move</h4>
<ul>
<li>This is the first American military assistance package to Pakistan after the Trump Administration.</li>
<li>Mr Trump ended defence and security co-operation with Pakistan in 2018 after accusing it of giving only “lies and deceit” for the billions of dollars that the US had “foolishly” given it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What specific reasons has the Biden Administration given for its decision?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As per US version, the proposed sale does not include any new capabilities, weapons, or munitions.</li>
<li>The upgrade package aimed to retain interoperability with US and partner forces in ongoing counter-terrorism efforts and in preparation for future contingency operations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did US provide F-16 to the US?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has been concerned about the F-16s from the time the US first gave Pakistan F-16s as a reward for its assistance in the first Afghan war.</li>
<li>The US then had supplied weapons and money to Pakistan to unleash armies of jihadists against the Soviet Army.</li>
<li>When the US objective was achieved with the Soviet Union’s departure from Afghanistan, the US too resized its relations with Pakistan.</li>
<li>The Pressler Amendment, aimed against Pakistan’s nuclear ambitions, froze it out of military assistance.</li>
<li>A decade later, the Bush Administration not only approved the release of previously blocked F-16s, but also provided a refurbishment package, and sale of new F-16s.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s concerns</h4>
<ul>
<li>As pointed out by EAM, how the F-16s help in counter-terrorism remains unclear.</li>
<li>Jaishankar questioned the merits of the US-Pakistan partnership.</li>
<li>He said that the relations had “not served” either country (but created more troubles for India).</li>
<li>This move by the US will alter the basic military balance in the region.</li>
<li>The decision to provide military aid to Pakistan incensed India as the F-16 was used against Indian warplanes following the 2019 Balakot air strikes.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>Washington’s $450 million package has only resurrected old prejudices centred on the US not being a dependable ally for ever.</li>
<li>India needs to respond firmly and in no uncertain terms to the PAF’s F-16 upgrade programme to convey the message that India cannot be taken for granted.</li>
<li>India will have to effectively enhance the conventional combat capability of the IAF to continue to meet the challenge of a resurgent PAF.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-india-has-lashed-out-at-the-us-over-its-f-16-package/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India and UNSC</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-quest-for-permanent-membership-of-unsc/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UN Security council</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>International Relations</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641313" height="506" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 843px) 100vw, 843px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5edc92b402a52-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5edc92b402a52-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5edc92b402a52.jpg 500w" width="843"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is greater support for India to be a permanent member of the UN Security Council and also a broad global consensus over the need to reform the Council, said External Affairs Minister S Jaishankar. India has once again renewed its bid for permanent membership of UNSC.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">What is UNSC?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The United Nations Security Council (UNSC) is one of the six principal organs of the United Nations (UN) and is charged with ensuring international peace and security, recommending the admission of new UN members to the General Assembly, and approving any changes to the UN Charter.</li>
<li>Its powers include establishing peacekeeping operations, enacting international sanctions, and authorizing military action. The UNSC is the only UN body with the authority to issue binding resolutions on member states.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641314" height="509" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 697px) 100vw, 697px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_11largeimg_1702223617-300x219.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_11largeimg_1702223617-300x219.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_11largeimg_1702223617.jpg 660w" width="697"/>What is the composition of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/g4-countries-call-for-unsc-reforms/">UNSC</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Presently there five permanent members (P-5) with veto and 10 non-permanent members without veto elected for tenure of 2 years.</li>
<li>India has been the non-permanent member multiple times. Presently India is serving its tenure that will end in December 2022.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641315" height="469" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 833px) 100vw, 833px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1658498206-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1658498206-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1658498206.jpg 715w" width="833"/>Who are P-5 members?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The victors of World War 2 – USA, RUSSIA, CHINA, UK, FRANCE.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the hurdles that India facing?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Elite club:</strong> Most exclusive club in international relations. All other clubs have been breached. Until a quarter century ago, the nuclear weapon club had five members, the same five as the P-5.India, Pakistan, North Korea and Israel have since joined the club. But UNSC is unbreachable till date.</li>
<li><strong>All are reluctant: </strong>The inescapable fact is that none of the P-5 wants the UNSC’s ranks to be increased. One or the other of them might make some noise about supporting one or more of the aspirants. Each is confident that someone among them will torpedo the enlargement of the club. Declarations of support for India’s candidature need to be taken with a fistful of salt.</li>
<li><strong>Veto issue: </strong>Former UN Secretary-General Kofi Annan bluntly told India not to expect to get the veto power. Though India has said it will not accept a seat without veto power.</li>
<li><strong>China-Pakistan axis: </strong>China, which has historically blocked India’s aspirations to become a permanent member of the UNSC. Beijing has an “all-weather ally” in Islamabad, another neighbour who also strongly opposes India’s candidature to the UNSC.</li>
<li><strong>Odd man out: </strong>Four out of the five permanent members of the United Nations Security Council have bilaterally expressed official affirmations of support for India’s candidature to a permanent seat in an expanded UN Security Council.</li>
<li><strong>Coffee club opposition: </strong>Members like Italy, South Korea, Canada, Spain, Mexico, Turkey, Argentina, Pakistan, and others, who have together formed the Uniting for Consensus (UfC) movement. Also known as the Coffee Club, the movement argues that bids for permanent seats by India, Japan, Germany, and Brazil (G4 countries) must not be considered without first reaching an international consensus regarding the form and size of the new Security council.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641318" height="310" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768.jpeg 770w" width="550"/>What are the Efforts taken by India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Text based negotiation: </strong>External affairs minister is canvassing for the country’s candidature, meeting his counterparts from several countries. He has repeated the call, made often in the past, for a text-based negotiation on what has been euphemistically referred to as the reform of the United Nations Security Council (UNSC), i.e., negotiation on a written document outlining the proposed reform instead of just holding forth verbally.</li>
<li><strong>Woking together with G-4: </strong>INDIA, JAPAN, GEMANY, BRAZIL works together to get permanent UNSC seat however these efforts are opposed by coffee club.</li>
<li><strong>Multilateral engagements: </strong>By expanding its footprint in multilateral organisations, India is gearing up to become a global rule-maker.</li>
<li>Distinguished group of experts suggested a few years ago that a new category of semi-permanent members should be created. Countries would be elected for a period of eight to 10 years and would be eligible for re-election. India ought to give serious consideration to this idea.</li>
<li><strong>With or without veto: </strong>According to former foreign secretary Chinmaya gharekhan, if by some miracle we are offered or manage to obtain permanent membership without veto, we must grab it. Even a permanent membership without veto will be tremendously helpful in protecting our interests.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Looking at the present geopolitical divide India’s dream of seat at the highest table is unlikely to get fulfilled in near future. India must analyse the utility of UNSC membership for securing its national interest. India should not give up anything in bargain against UNSC seat which harms its international interest.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. India’s quest for UNSC is like “Sisyphus carrying the boulder  just to see how it falls”. In this context Analyse the utility of Permanent seat at UNSC.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-quest-for-permanent-membership-of-unsc/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Advantage of Market Based Economic Dispatch</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/market-based-economic-dispatch-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economics,Energy,Infrastructure</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641126" height="316" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-3-1.jpg" width="565"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The game changing scheme is being proposed by the central government in power sector governance. The scheme under consideration is the market-based economic dispatch (MBED). When it comes to any drastic change in the power sector, a clash between the Centre and the states is inevitable.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Market Based Economic Dispatch (MBED)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Market Based Economic Dispatch (MBED) is new approach towards power distribution to help distribution companies save costs and transition to a new form of power market.</li>
<li>It is a shift to a centralised framework, marks a radical departure from the current decentralised, voluntary pool-based electricity market.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641122" height="291" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-1-2.jpg" width="508"/>What is the framework under MBED?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The cheapest power from across the country will be dispatched to meet the system wide demand. The architecture would also lead to a “Market clearing price”.</li>
<li>Sellers and buyers will place their bids for the day market, and an outcome of this will be the discovery of the market clearing price.</li>
<li>This process is expected to generate significant savings for consumers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Present system of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/assessment-of-discoms/">power Distribution?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Under the present regime, each distribution company (Discom) is bound by the power purchase agreements (PPAs) that it holds.</li>
<li>It can schedule power only from its own PPAs, starting from the cheapest PPA and then moving up; it cannot schedule power from the PPA of some other distribution company.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> <img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641124" height="365" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-2.jpg" width="488"/></strong><strong>What are the drawbacks of present system?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Financial Burdon:</strong></li>
<li>The Indian government responded to COVID-19’s economic shock with a stimulus package of Rs.20-lakh crore, out of which Rs.90,000 crore was earmarked for discoms (later upgraded to Rs.1,25,000 crore). While it was called a stimulus, it is really a loan, meant to be used by discoms to pay off generators.</li>
<li>Discoms owe one lakh crore rupees to generators, and without such an infusion the chain will collapse.</li>
<li><strong>States are defaulters:</strong></li>
<li>State governments are the biggest defaulters, responsible for an estimated a third of trade receivables, besides not paying subsidies in full or on time.</li>
<li>On an annual cash flow basis, the shortfall in subsidy payments appears very low, only about 1% but cumulative unpaid subsidies, with modest carrying costs, make discoms poorer by over Rs.70,000 crore just over the last 10 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641125" height="323" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-12-1.jpg" width="570"/>What will be the Advantages of MBED?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Centralized approach: </strong>The centralised dispatch will be done with the assistance of electricity exchanges. Each discom and each generator will place a bid in the day-ahead market of the electricity exchanges, which will indicate how much power is being demanded/ supplied at what price.</li>
<li><strong>Pan India market: </strong>These bids will enable the load dispatcher to construct a pan India demand and supply curve, the intersection of which will determine the market clearing price (MCP). All generators whose variable cost of generation is below the MCP will be asked to dispatch and all of them will receive the same MCP irrespective of what they had bid. Generators whose variable cost is higher than the MCP will sit idle.</li>
<li><strong>No loss to discom: </strong>The MBED is so devised that its operation will not affect the current finances of either the discoms or the generators for the following reasons.</li>
<li>First, the fixed cost of the generators will still be paid by the discoms outside the market as determined by the regulator.</li>
<li>Second, if the MCP comes out to be Rs 3 per unit, and if in the case of any PPA, the variable cost is Rs 2.75 per unit, then the generator will compensate the discom to the extent of Rs 0.25 per unit. Similarly, if the MCP so determined is Rs 2.50 per unit, then the discom will compensate the generator to the extent of Rs 0.25 per unit.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing efficiency: </strong>The logic is that by adopting MBED, only the relatively efficient plants will generate, without affecting the revenues of either the discoms or generators. Hence, the total cost of generation under the MBED system would be less.</li>
<li><strong>Less pollution: </strong>There would be less coal consumption and less carbon dioxide injected into the atmosphere.</li>
<li><strong>Easy integration with renewable: </strong>It would also mean less movement of coal leading to decongestion of railway tracks. Further, there would be enhanced renewable integration since the balancing area would shift from state to national level.</li>
<li><strong>Single market clearing price (MCP): </strong>Incidentally, since there are three electricity exchanges in operation today, there would be three different MCPs determined. What we need is a single MCP for which there will be an institution called the “market coupler”. It will be the job of the coupler to determine a national MCP based on what has arrived at the three different exchanges.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why states are opposing?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>High generation cost: </strong>The reason is the state-owned generators are relatively inefficient and may have to sit idle as their variable cost of generation is likely to be more than the MCP.</li>
<li><strong>Political backlash: </strong>Today, the states are operating their own generators to the hilt, even though they are inefficient, and drawing only the balance from the more efficient interstate generating stations. Keeping state generators idle has its own political implications and no state would be enamoured of this idea.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Power distribution companies (discom) are sinkhole of government finances. Every year budgetary support is needed to this loss-making companies , With due consultation, all states and union territories need to adopt and implement the MBED and save the resources for other development activities.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. </strong><strong>India has became the power surplus nation, however power distribution and financial unsustainability is still a nightmare for union and states. Elaborate.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/market-based-economic-dispatch-2/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian Railways powerful experiment on AC III tier economy class coaches</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ac-iii-tier-economy-class-coaches/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economics, Infrastructure,Transport</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="AC III tier economy class coaches" class="alignnone wp-image-641307" height="361" sizes="(max-width: 633px) 100vw, 633px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-300x171.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-300x171.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1024x583.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-768x437.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1536x874.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-2048x1166.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1200x683.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1980x1127.jpg 1980w" width="633"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian Railways’ experiment to introduce AC III tier economy class coaches has started to pay off. Since its introduction, in the last one year, these coaches have earned the Railways more than Rs.230 crore in revenue.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="AC III tier economy class" class="alignnone wp-image-641094" height="289" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-6.jpg" width="514"/>What is </strong><strong>AC III tier economy class coach?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AC 3 tier economy class in Indian Railways is a milestone concerning pocket-friendly traveling experience for common man.</li>
<li>With fare slightly more than sleeper class and lower than conventional AC class.</li>
<li>The objective of the railway is to move sleeper class passengers to a comfortable AC class with luxurious facilities. AC-3 tier comprises air-conditioned coaches with 64 sleeping berths.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>When it is introduced?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian Railway has introduced the first AC III tier Economy Class for North Central Railway Zone in 2021 to provide a convenient traveling experience to the passengers<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>As of now 7 trains are equipped with AC III tier economy class coaches are running on the tracks</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="AC III tier economy class coaches" class="alignnone wp-image-641308" height="377" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 669px) 100vw, 669px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038.jpg 1600w" width="669"/>Features of the AC </strong>III<strong> tier economy coach</strong><strong>:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pocket friendly</strong>: According to the Indian Railways, the fair in these coaches are cheaper than the normal AC three-tier coach. Fares in AC III tier economy are 6%-7% cheaper than the AC III tier class. The economy class has a capacity of 83 berths compared to 72 in the regular coach.</li>
<li><strong>Divyang friendly and modern designs: </strong>The coaches were specially designed for the convenience of the divyangs. Providing Improved and modular design of berths and ergonomically designed ladder for accessing the middle and upper berths etc.</li>
<li><strong>Modern features: </strong>In these, modern arrangements have been made for mobile phones and magazine holders, fire safety, personalised reading lights, AC vents, USB points, mobile charging points.</li>
<li><strong>Optimum Speed</strong>: These air-conditioned three-tier economy class coaches are capable of running at an optimum speed of 160 kilometers per hour.</li>
<li><strong>More Capacity:</strong> The economy class has a capacity of 83 berths compared to 72 in the regular coach.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the current status of AC </strong><strong>III tier class?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>AC- III tier, the favorite mode of train travel of people falling in the bottom rung of the middle class, is the only class that earns the Railways profit among all its passenger services.</li>
<li>The AC III tier is the only class of service which has generated consistent profits for the Railways. Between FY16 and FY20,</li>
<li>AC III tier coaches carried only 1% of the total passengers, but were responsible for 21% of the earnings from travelers. Such a low-passenger, high-revenue dichotomy was not seen in any other class.</li>
<li>It is not as expensive as the other AC classes and at the same time, its share in revenue has not been impacted by the relatively low pricing</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong style="letter-spacing: -0.0415625em;"><img alt="AC III tier economy class coaches" class="alignnone wp-image-641309" height="464" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 619px) 100vw, 619px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84998782-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84998782-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84998782.jpg 400w" width="619"/>Revenue of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vande-bharat-production-to-begin/">Indian railways</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The overall revenue of Indian Railways at the end of August 2022 was Rs 95,486.58 crore, showing an increase 38 per cent over the corresponding period of last year.</li>
<li>Goods revenue climbed by Rs 10,780.03 crore (or 20 per cent) to Rs 65,505.02 crore till August-end this year</li>
<li>The revenue from passenger traffic was Rs 25,276.54 crore, an increase of Rs 13,574.44 crore (116 per cent) year-on-year.</li>
<li>Passenger traffic also increased compared to last year in both the segments — reserved and unreserved</li>
<li>Railways’ total revenue during the entire last fiscal (2021-22) stood at Rs.1,91,278.29 crore.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the issues faced by Indian railways to increase its revenue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cross Subsidized: </strong>The cross-subsidiszation in respect of second class, ordinary class and suburban services has increased continuously in the past five years with subsidy on ordinary class being the maximum,</li>
<li><strong>Concessional fare</strong>: The revenue forgone in passenger earnings due to concessions to various categories of passengers (physically challenged persons, patients, senior citizens, Izzat monthly season tickets, press correspondents, sport persons and war widows among others) increased from Rs 1,994.83 crore in 2018-19 to Rs 2,058.61 crore in 2019-20.</li>
<li><strong>Low -Revenue dichotomy in Expensive class:</strong> A high-passenger, low-revenue dichotomy was seen in the inexpensive classes. For instance, over 90% passengers travelled by second class which accounted for only 37% of the earnings.</li>
<li><strong>Operational Los</strong><strong>s</strong>: Operational losses (in crore) incurred while operating various classes of service. For instance, in operating AC first class service, the Railways incurred a loss of 403 crore in FY20</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Adding more AC III tier economy class coaches is a step in the right direction as it has shown positive result in revenue generation for railways and it provides a travel with dignity to a common man. But If Indian railway has to benefit it have to work extensively on operational loss incurred out of low Revenue dichotomy in Expensive classes.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. Indian Railways is often referred to as the lifeline of the country but runs at a loss when it comes to running class-divided coaches. In this context discuss the utility of class divided coaches.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ac-iii-tier-economy-class-coaches/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>