<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 16:14:11 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Green finance for green future</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/green-finance/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Network for Greening the Financial System</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>green future ,green finance</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="green finance " class="alignnone wp-image-626762" height="454" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 682px) 100vw, 682px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/d9e58a08ed54835e9a92fc788385f6cc247f2359-1657283519-41cf5979-1920x1280-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/d9e58a08ed54835e9a92fc788385f6cc247f2359-1657283519-41cf5979-1920x1280-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/d9e58a08ed54835e9a92fc788385f6cc247f2359-1657283519-41cf5979-1920x1280-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/d9e58a08ed54835e9a92fc788385f6cc247f2359-1657283519-41cf5979-1920x1280-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/d9e58a08ed54835e9a92fc788385f6cc247f2359-1657283519-41cf5979-1920x1280-1.jpg 1200w" width="682"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Inclusion of climate change and green finance in policy is crucial for a strong economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/the-term-green-finance-has-gained-a-lot-of-attention-in-the-past-few-years-with-the-increased-focus-on-greed-development-why-the-green-finance-is-an-ambiguous-tern-and-what-are-the/"><strong>What is green finance?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Green finance is a phenomenon that combines the world of finance and business with environment friendly behaviour. It may be led by financial incentives, a desire to preserve the planet, or a combination of both.</li>
<li>In addition to demonstrating proactive, environment friendly behaviour, such as promoting of any business or activity that could be damaging to the environment now or for future generations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Green finance instruments        </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dedicated fund: </strong>A “green super fund” could be established to jumpstart green investments by pooling together international and domestic capital.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/green-bonds-digital-currency-hold-promise/"><strong>Sovereign green bond (SGB): </strong></a>The sovereign green bond is a novel idea. It will be a part of the government’s borrowing programme. The gross borrowing programme of the government is pegged at Rs 14.95 lakh crore. The SGB (sovereign green bond) raised will be part of the aggregate borrowing programme and has to be used for projects which are ESG (environment, social and governance) compliant.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="green finance" class="alignnone wp-image-626764" height="355" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 612px) 100vw, 612px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Green-financing-01-300x174.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Green-financing-01-300x174.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Green-financing-01-768x446.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Green-financing-01.jpg 840w" width="612"/>Network for Greening the Financial System</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Network for Greening the Financial System is a network of 114 central banks and financial supervisors that aims to accelerate the scaling up of green finance and develop recommendations for central banks’ role for climate change.</li>
<li>The NGFS was created in 2017 and its secretariat is hosted by the Banque de France.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Purpose</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Network’s purpose is to help strengthening the global response required to meet the goals of the Paris agreement and to enhance the role of the financial system to manage risks and to mobilize capital for green and low carbon investments in the broader context of environmentally sustainable development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="green finance" class="alignnone wp-image-626765" height="279" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1395268786138-300x142.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1395268786138-300x142.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/1395268786138.jpg 750w" width="590"/>Significance </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Green goals</strong>: Reaching net-zero emissions and other climate-related and environmental goals will require significant investments to enable decarbonisation and innovation across all sectors of the economy. Greening the financial system is key to making these investments happen.</li>
<li><strong>SDG goals: </strong>Green finance initiatives also aim to achieve the 2030 Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs), shifting the focus from creating value for shareholders (economic) to creating value for stakeholders (economic, environmental, and social).</li>
<li><strong>Green future: </strong>And as we begin to recover from the pandemic, green finance presents a huge opportunity to build back with a greener future, creating new businesses and jobs.</li>
<li><strong>Robust growth: </strong>Supports strong and green growth in all sectors of economy .</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The issues in mobilization and effective use of green finance are</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low incentives</strong>: The return on green finance is long term, low in monetary value &amp; many times intangible, so that the ability of the financial system to mobilize private green finance, especially in developed countries is difficult.</li>
<li><strong>Distribution challenge</strong>: Developing countries like India have challenges of development &amp; poverty alleviation, so allocation of resources towards meeting fundamental needs &amp; promoting the green projects which require heavy investment is a challenge.</li>
<li><strong>Skewed investment</strong>: In many countries, green finance &amp; much of the green projects are limited to the investment in renewable energy: India whose 60% of installed capacity is coal based, greening of coal technology is required which is mostly limited to private players in developed countries. It is subjected to IPR &amp; makes them cost prohibitory.</li>
<li><strong>High risk</strong>: Green bonds are perceived as new and attach higher risk and their tenure is also shorter. There is a need to reduce risks to makes them investment grade.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Our future depends on how we resolve our environmental challenges. Further, we are the world’s third-largest carbon emitter and will play a crucial role in getting the planet to a low-carbon trajectory. Simply put, we must urgently transform our economy to get to the green frontier.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. As the world copes with the repercussions of carbon emissions, there is growing pressure to achieve climate-compatible growth. In this context What do you understand by the term green finance? Discuss how it will help to achieve climate-compatible growth along with limitations of green finance.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/green-finance/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Government e-Marketplace (GeM) eyes procurement of ₹2 lakh crore</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/government-e-marketplace-gem-eyes-procurement-of-%e2%82%b92-lakh-crore/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Government e-Marketplace</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-626761" height="150" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gem-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gem-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gem-1024x512.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gem-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gem.jpg 1200w" width="300"/></p>
<p>Government e-Marketplace (GeM), a national procurement portal, is eyeing annual procurement worth ₹2 lakh crore during FY23. Such a huge amount it is!</p>
<h4>Government e-Marketplace</h4>
<ul>
<li>GeM is an online platform for public procurement in India by various Government Departments / Organizations / PSUs.</li>
<li>The initiative was launched on August 9, 2016 by the Ministry of Commerce and Industry with the objective to create an open and transparent procurement platform for government buyers.</li>
<li>It is owned by GeM SPV (Special Purpose Vehicle) which is a 100 per cent Government-owned, non-profit company under the Ministry of Commerce and Industries</li>
<li>GeM aims to enhance transparency, efficiency and speed in public procurement.</li>
<li>It provides the tools of e-bidding, reverse e-auction and demand aggregation to facilitate the government users achieve the best value for their money.</li>
<li>The purchases through GeM by Government users have been authorized and made mandatory by Ministry of Finance.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong><em>Note:</em></strong><em> The government has made it mandatory for sellers on the Government e-Marketplace (GeM) portal to clarify the country of origin of their goods when registering new products.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4>Advantages for Buyers</h4>
<ul>
<li>Offers rich listing of products for individual categories of Goods/Services</li>
<li>Makes available search, compare, select and buy facility</li>
<li>Enables buying Goods and Services online, as and when required.</li>
<li>Provides transparency and ease of buying</li>
<li>Ensures continuous vendor rating system</li>
<li>Up-to-date user-friendly dashboard for buying, monitoring supplies and payments</li>
<li>Provision of easy return policy</li>
</ul>
<h4>Advantages for Sellers</h4>
<ul>
<li>Direct access to all Government departments.</li>
<li>One-stop shop for marketing with minimal efforts</li>
<li>One-stop shop for bids / reverse auction on products / services</li>
<li>New Product Suggestion facility available to Sellers</li>
<li>Dynamic pricing: Price can be changed based on market conditions</li>
<li>Seller friendly dashboard for selling, and monitoring of supplies and payments</li>
<li>Consistent and uniform purchase procedures</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/government-e-marketplace-gem-eyes-procurement-of-%e2%82%b92-lakh-crore/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Nepal postponed Gorkhas’ recruitment under the Agnipath scheme?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-nepal-postponed-gorkha-recruitment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Gorkha regiment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Indian Army</p></div></div><p>Nepal has postponed the recruitment rallies which were to be held in that country to recruit Gorkha soldiers for the Indian Army under the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-mudda-aapka-agnipath-scheme/">Agnipath scheme</a>.</p>
<h4>Why has Nepal postponed Agnipath recruitment rallies?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Nepal is of the opinion that this new form of entry into the Indian military is not covered under the Tripartite Agreement signed between Nepal, Indian and UK governments in 1947, soon after Indian independence.</li>
<li>The government feels that the Agnipath scheme must be approved by it and for that political consultations with all parties in Nepal must take place.</li>
<li>This is move is visibly ‘inspired’ with inputs from China.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What was the Tripartite Agreement between India, Nepal and UK?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Soon after Indian Independence on August 15, 1947, an agreement was reached by the governments of India, Nepal and the UK <strong><u>regarding the future of the Gorkha soldiers</u></strong> who were serving in the Indian Army.</li>
<li>As per the terms of this agreement four regiments of Gorkha soldiers – 2nd, 6th, 7th and 10th – were transferred to the British Army while the rest – 1st, 3rd, 4th, 5th, 8th and 9th – remained with the Indian Army.</li>
<li>A new Gorkha Regiment, the 11th Gorkha Rifles, was raised by India soon after Independence.</li>
<li>The agreement also provides for the terms and conditions of the <strong><u>Nepal-domiciled Gorkha soldiers in the Indian Army</u></strong> and for their post-retirement benefits and pensions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of Gorkha Soldiers</h4>
<ul>
<li>Legend has it that Hitler’s very words were, “If I had Gurkhas, no army in the world could defeat me.”</li>
<li>An interesting historical aspect of Gorkha troops is that Pakistan, at the time of Independence, and China, soon after the 1962 war, had also requested Nepal for Gorkha soldiers.</li>
<li>However, this request was turned down by the Nepal government.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>largest body of Gorkha troops serves in the Indian Army</u></strong> while in the UK their presence has been reduced from four regiments to just two.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Can Nepalese Gorkhas in foreign Armies be called mercenaries?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Mercenaries are understood as fighters who take part in a conflict for financial gain and usually are not parties to that conflict.</li>
<li>As per the definition of the 1949 Geneva Convention, gives the officially agreed definition of a mercenary.</li>
<li>It says that <strong><u>soldiers serving in sovereign armies are not considered mercenaries</u></strong>, and Gorkha soldiers cannot be called mercenaries.</li>
<li>In addition, Gorkha soldiers from Nepal serve side-by-side with Gorkha soldiers who are born and brought up in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Have any changes been made in Gorkha unit recruitments over the years?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There have been attempts to reduce the dependence on Nepal for the Gorkha soldiers in the Indian Army,</li>
<li>To this effect, the composition has increasingly been attempted to be balanced between Indian and Nepal-domiciled troops.</li>
<li>Also, a pure Indian Gorkha battalion was raised in 2016.</li>
<li>This unit, 6th Battalion of the 1st Gorkha Rifles (6/1 GR), was raised in Subathu, in Himachal Pradesh.</li>
<li>Otherwise, the ratio of Nepalese-domiciled soldiers and Indian-domiciled soldiers in a Gorkha battalion ranges from 60:40 to 70:30, though this will change further in future.</li>
<li>A change was made in the recruitment rules for Gorkha Rifles recently when the Army decided that soldiers hailing from the Kumaon and Garhwal regions of Uttarakhand will also be eligible for serving in Gorkha Rifles.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the socio-economic impact on Nepal of Gorkha soldiers serving in the Indian Army?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A major economic and social impact is felt in Nepal due to the Nepal-domiciled Gorkha soldiers serving in the Indian Army and much of it has to do with the remittances that they send home.</li>
<li>Kathmandu receives a <strong><u>sustainable source of remittances from Gorkhas</u></strong> working in foreign armies.</li>
<li>This has significantly contributed to social modernization in the isolated villages, while the financial remittances spurred entrepreneurship development thereby contributing to regional development.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why induct Gorkha soldiers?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Gorkha soldiers are tough. Living in the hills of Nepal makes them <strong><u>strong and resilient</u></strong> and they can stand war, climate and terrain better than most.</li>
<li>No one can match their <strong><u>swift movement in the mountainous terrain</u></strong>.</li>
<li>They are <strong><u>cheerful in disposition</u></strong> and nothing disturbs their equanimity.</li>
<li>They are <strong><u>loyal to the core</u></strong> and fearless in battle.</li>
<li>All this makes them amongst the <strong><u>best soldiers in the world</u></strong> and they are much sought after.</li>
<li>Historically, they have <strong><u>deep rooted connection and affinity for India</u></strong> definitely due to cultural assimilations.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-nepal-postponed-gorkha-recruitment/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>INS Vikrant: All about India’s first indigenous aircraft carrier</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ins-vikrant-indias-first-indigenous-aircraft-carrier/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>INS Vikrant</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Indian navy modernization</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-626759" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 633px) 100vw, 633px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ins-vikrant-300x184.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ins-vikrant-300x184.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ins-vikrant-768x471.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ins-vikrant.jpg 887w" width="633"/></p>
<p>The nation’s first Indigenous Aircraft Carrier (IAC-1) , INS Vikrant is set to be commissioned on September 2, the Indian Navy has announced.</p>
<h4>About INS Vikrant</h4>
<ul>
<li>The name ‘INS Vikrant’ originally belonged to India’s much-loved first aircraft carrier, a source of immense national pride over several decades of service before it was decommissioned in 1997.</li>
<li>The original ‘Vikrant’, a Majestic-class 19,500-tonne warship, which was acquired from the UK in 1961, played a <strong><u>stellar role in the 1971 War with Pakistan</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The IAC-1 is 262 m long and 62 m wide ‘Vikrant’ displaces approximately 43,000 tonnes when fully loaded, and has a maximum designed speed of 28 knots (about 52 km/h) with an endurance of 7500 NM.</li>
<li>It has around 2,200 compartments designed for a crew of around 1,600, including specialised cabins to accommodate women officers and sailors.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is it important for India to have an aircraft carrier?</h4>
<ul>
<li>An aircraft carrier is one of the <strong><u>most potent marine assets</u></strong> for any nation.</li>
<li>It enhances a Navy’s capability to travel far from its home shores to carry out air <strong><u>domination operations</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Having an aircraft carrier as essential to be considered a “blue water” navy — that is, a navy that has the capacity to <strong><u>project a nation’s strength and power across the high seas</u></strong>.</li>
<li>An aircraft carrier generally <strong><u>leads as the capital ship of a carrier strike/ battle group</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is it a big deal that this warship has been Made in India?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Only five or six nations currently have the capability</u></strong> of manufacturing an aircraft carrier, and India has joined this prestigious club now.</li>
<li>India has <strong><u>demonstrated the capacity and self-reliance</u></strong> to build what is considered to be one of the most advanced and complex battleships in the world.</li>
<li>India has had aircraft carriers earlier too — but those were built either by the British or the Russians.</li>
<li>The ‘INS Vikramaditya’, which was commissioned in 2013 and which is currently the Navy’s only aircraft carrier, started out as the Soviet-Russian warship ‘Admiral Gorshkov’.</li>
<li>India’s two earlier carriers, the ‘INS Vikrant’ and the ‘INS Viraat’, were originally the British-built ‘HMS Hercules’ and ‘HMS Hermes’.</li>
<li>These two warships were commissioned into the Navy in 1961 and 1987 respectively.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What indigenous components does the new ‘Vikrant’ have?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The indigenous <strong><u>content of the project is approximately 76%</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The warship-grade <strong><u>steel was indigenised</u></strong> through Steel Authority of India Limited (SAIL) in collaboration with Defence Research &amp; Development Laboratory (DRDL).</li>
<li>It includes 23,000 tonnes of steel, 2,500 km of electric cables, 150 km of pipes, and 2,000 valves.</li>
<li>It also includes a wide range of finished products including rigid hull boats, galley equipment, air-conditioning and refrigeration plants, and steering gear.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What weapons and equipment will the new ‘Vikrant’ have?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The new warship can carry up to 34 aircraft, including both fighter jets and helicopters.</li>
<li>It will be capable of operating 30 aircraft including MiG-29K fighter jets, Kamov-31 Air Early Warning Helicopters, MH-60R Seahawk multi-role helicopters, as well as the Advanced Light Helicopters (ALH).</li>
<li>Using a novel aircraft-operation mode known as Short Take Off But Arrested Recovery (STOBAR), the IAC is equipped with a ski-jump for launching aircraft.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What else will be there on the new INS Vikrant?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The carrier is designed with a very high degree of automation for machinery operations, ship navigation and survivability.</li>
<li>The carrier is equipped with the latest state of the art equipment and systems.</li>
<li>It boasts a fully-fledged state of the art medical complex with the latest medical equipment facilities..</li>
</ul>
<h4>Now that India has shown the capability, will it build more carriers?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Since 2015, the Navy has been seeking approval to build a third aircraft carrier for the country, which, if approved, will become India’s second Indigenous Aircraft Carrier (IAC-2).</li>
<li>This proposed carrier, to be named ‘INS Vishal’, is intended to be a giant 65,000-tonne vessel, much bigger than both IAC-1 and the ‘INS Vikramaditya’.</li>
<li>The Navy has been trying to convince the government of the “operational necessity” of having a third carrier.</li>
<li>Also, it is argued that now that India has developed the capability to build such vessels, it should not be whittled away.</li>
<li>The expertise gained by the Navy and the country over the past 60 years in the art of maritime aviation should not be wasted either.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of the induction</h4>
<ul>
<li>Vikrant is the largest warship to have ever been built in India, and the <strong><u>first indigenously designed and built</u></strong> aircraft carrier for the Indian Navy.</li>
<li>It puts India in an <strong><u>elite club of nations</u></strong> that have the capability to design and build these giant, powerful warships.</li>
<li>The indigenisation efforts led to the <strong><u>development of ancillary industries</u></strong>, and generated employment opportunities for 2,000 CSL personnel and about 13,000 employees in ancillary industries.</li>
<li>This bolstered <strong><u>plough-back effect on the nation’s economy</u></strong>. That is, it pushed all money back that it consumed.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ins-vikrant-indias-first-indigenous-aircraft-carrier/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Three-judge bench to review SC Verdict on Poll Promises</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/three-judge-bench-to-review-sc-verdict-on-poll-promises/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Lofty poll promises and election freebies</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-626758" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 207px) 100vw, 207px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/freebie-207x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/freebie-207x300.jpg 207w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/freebie.jpg 239w" width="207"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has decided to reconsider a 2013 judgment on Poll Promises, which held that promises in the election manifesto do not constitute a “corrupt practice” under the law.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A Bench led by the CJI, Ramana, ordered a three-judge Bench to be set up to review the court’s earlier position.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Subramaniam Balaji Judgment: Invalidating certain Poll Promises</h4>
<ul>
<li>It was held that <strong><u>pre-poll promises made by political parties to entice voters do not fall within the ambit of Section 123 (corrupt practices) under the Representation of the People (RP) Act</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The judgment, delivered by a two-judge Bench, had observed that although the law is obvious that the promises in the election manifesto cannot be construed as ‘corrupt practice’ under Section 123 of RP Act.</li>
<li>The reality cannot be ruled out that distribution of freebies of any kind, undoubtedly, influences all people.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why revisit this judgment?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rationale of the freebie:</strong> Now the CJI has said the three-judge Bench should consider whether an enforceable order can be passed to stop political parties in power from promising and distributing “irrational freebies”.</li>
<li><strong>Freebie vs. Welfare schemes:</strong> He opined that such freebies are completely divorced from actual welfare schemes, using public money in order to merely “capture vote banks”.</li>
<li><strong>Prevent bankruptcy:</strong> Freebies may create a situation wherein the State government cannot provide basic amenities due to lack of funds and the State is pushed towards imminent bankruptcy.</li>
<li><strong>Expert review:</strong> The new Bench would also deliberate if an expert body can be formed to independently study and make recommendations against the distribution of largesse at the cost of the national economy and public welfare.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What amounts to Freebie?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The term Freebies is not new; rather it is a prevalent culture in Indian politics (in the name of socialism).</li>
<li>The political parties are always trying to outdo each other in luring the Indian voters with assorted freebies.</li>
<li>From free water to free smartphones the Indian politicians promise everything to attract prospective voters in favour.</li>
<li>This trend has gained more momentum in the recent times with the political parties being innovative in their offerings as the ‘traditional free water and electricity’ is no longer sufficient as election goodies.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Examples of freebies</h4>
<ol>
<li>Promise of Rs 15 lakh in our bank accounts</li>
<li>Free TV, Laptops</li>
<li>Free electricity</li>
<li>Loan waivers</li>
<li>Offering free public transport ride to all women in Delhi</li>
</ol>
<h4>Why are such policies popular among the public?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Failure of economic policies:</strong> The answer lies in the utter failure of our economic policies to create decent livelihood for a vast majority of Indians.</li>
<li><strong>Quest for decent livelihood:</strong> The already low income had to be reoriented towards spending a disproportionately higher amount on education and health, from which, the state increasingly withdrew.</li>
<li><strong>Prevailing unemployment:</strong>  Employment surveys have shown that employment growth initially slowed down from the 1990s, and then has turned negative over the past few years.</li>
<li><strong>Increased cost of living:</strong> Real income growth of the marginal sections has actually slowed down since 1991 reforms.</li>
<li><strong>Increased consumerism:</strong> The poor today also spend on things which appear to be luxuries; cellphones and data-packs are two such examples which are shown as signs of India’s increased affluence.</li>
<li><strong>Necessity:</strong> For migrant workers, the mobile phone helps them keep in touch with their families back home, or do a quick video-call to see how their infant is learning to sit up or crawl.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Can Freebies be compared with Welfare Politics?</h4>
<ul>
<li>These freebies are not bad. It is a part of social welfare.</li>
<li>Using freebies to lure voters is not good.</li>
<li>Voter’s greediness may lead to a problem in choosing a good leader.</li>
<li>When we don’t have a good leader then democracy will be a mockery.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Impact of such policies</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Never ending trail:</strong> The continuity of freebies is another major disadvantage as parties keep on coming up with lucrative offers to lure more number of votes to minimize the risk of losing in the elections.</li>
<li><strong>Burden on exchequer:</strong> People forget that such benefits are been given at the cost of exchequer and from the tax paid.</li>
<li><strong>Ultimate loss of poors:</strong> The politicians and middlemen wipe away the benefits and the poor have to suffer as they are deprived from their share of benefits which was to be achieved out of the money.</li>
<li><strong>Inflationary practice:</strong> Such distribution freebie commodity largely disrupts demand-supply dynamics.</li>
<li><strong>Lethargy in population:</strong> Freebies actually have the tendency to turn the nation’s population into: Lethargy and devoid of entrepreneurship.</li>
<li><strong>Money becomes only remedy:</strong> Everyone at the slightest sign of distress starts demanding some kind of freebies from the Govt.</li>
<li><strong>Popular politics:</strong> This is psychology driving sections of the population expecting and the government promptly responds with immediate monetary relief or compensation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What cannot be accounted to a freebie?</h4>
<ul>
<li>MGNREGA scheme (rural employment guarantee scheme)</li>
<li>Right to Education (RTE)</li>
<li>Food Security through fair price shops ( under National Food Security Act)</li>
<li>Prime Minister Kisan Samman Yojana (PM-KISAN)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Arguments in favour</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Social investment:</strong> Aid to the poor is seen as a wasteful expenditure. But low interest rates for corporates to get cheap loans or the ‘sop’ of cutting corporate taxes are never criticized.</li>
<li><strong>Socialistic policy:</strong> This attitude comes from decades of operating within the dominant discourse of market capitalism.</li>
<li><strong>Election manifesto:</strong> Proponents of such policies would argue that poll promises are essential for voters to know what the party would do if it comes to power and have the chance to weigh options.</li>
<li><strong>Welfare:</strong> Economists opine that as long as any State has the capacity and ability to finance freebies then its fine; if not then freebies are the burden on economy.</li>
<li><strong>Other wasteful expenditure:</strong> When the Centre gives incentives like free land to big companies and announce multi-year tax holidays, questions are not asked as to where the money will come from.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>There is nothing wrong in having a policy-led elaborate social security programme that seeks to help the poor get out of poverty.</li>
<li>But such a programme needs well thought out preparation and cannot be conjured up just before an election.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="kbw9dvC4Ms"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-election-freebies-politics-and-economy/">[Sansad TV] Mudda Aapla: Culture of Freebies</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="kbw9dvC4Ms" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-election-freebies-politics-and-economy/embed/#?secret=HC6BWj5Fkm#?secret=kbw9dvC4Ms" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Sansad TV] Mudda Aapla: Culture of Freebies” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/three-judge-bench-to-review-sc-verdict-on-poll-promises/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>This is right time to repeal AFSPA</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/afspa/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<h4><strong><img alt="AFSPA" class="alignnone wp-image-626789" height="451" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 541px) 100vw, 541px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA_Protests_Nagaland_16122021_PTI-300x250.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA_Protests_Nagaland_16122021_PTI-300x250.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA_Protests_Nagaland_16122021_PTI-1024x853.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA_Protests_Nagaland_16122021_PTI-768x640.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA_Protests_Nagaland_16122021_PTI-1080x900.jpg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA_Protests_Nagaland_16122021_PTI.jpg 1200w" width="541"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While AFSPA is repealed in 28 districts in Assam, 7 districts in Nagaland and 6 in Manipur, NSF president Kegwayhun Tep said that it should be repealed in all Northeastern states .</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/armed-forces-special-powers-act/"><strong>What is Armed Forces (Special Powers) Act, 1958? </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Armed Forces Special Powers Act, to put it simply, gives armed forces the power to maintain public order in “disturbed areas.”</li>
<li>AFSPA gives armed forces the authority use force or even open fire after giving due warning if they feel a person is in contravention of the law.</li>
<li>The Act further provides that if “reasonable suspicion exists”, the armed forces can also arrest a person without warrant; enter or search premises without a warrant; and ban the possession of firearms.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>AFSPA: A Backgrounder</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AFSPA, 1958 came into force in the context of insurgency in the North-eastern States decades ago.</li>
<li>It provides “special power” to the Armed Forces applies to the Army, the Air Force and the Central Paramilitary forces etc.</li>
<li>It has been long contested debate whether the “special powers” granted under AFSPA gives total immunity to the armed forces for any action taken by them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="AFSPA" class="alignnone wp-image-626785" height="316" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 637px) 100vw, 637px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA-300x149.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA-300x149.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/AFSPA.jpg 524w" width="637"/>What are the Special Powers?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Power to use force</strong>: including opening fire, even to the extent of causing death if prohibitory orders banning assembly of five or more persons or carrying arms and weapons, etc are in force in the disturbed area;</li>
<li><strong>Power to destroy structures</strong>: used as hide-outs, training camps, or as a place from which attacks are or likely to be launched, etc;</li>
<li><strong>Power to arrest</strong>: without warrant and to use force for the purpose;</li>
<li><strong>Power to enter and search premises</strong>: without a warrant to make arrest or recovery of hostages, arms and ammunition and stolen property etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who can declare/notify such areas?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Central Government or the Governor of the State or administrator of the Union Territory can declare the whole or part of the State or Union Territory as a disturbed area.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="AFSPA" class="alignnone wp-image-626786" height="445" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 543px) 100vw, 543px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/afsrem-300x246.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/afsrem-300x246.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/afsrem.jpg 600w" width="543"/>Issues with AFSPA</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Power to kill: </strong>Section 4 of the Act granted officers the authority to “take any action” even to the extent to cause the death.</li>
<li><strong>Sexual Misconduct by Armed Forces</strong>: The issue of violation of human rights by actions of armed forces came under the consideration of the Committee on Amendments to Criminal Law (popularly known as Justice Verma Committee) set up in 2012. It observed that- in conflict zones, legal protection for women was neglected.</li>
<li><strong>Autocracy</strong>: The reality is that there is no evidence of any action being taken against any officer of the armed forces or paramilitary forces for their excesses.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Recommendations to repeal AFSPA</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Justice B.P. Jeevan Reddy Commission: </strong>The 2004 Committee headed by Justice B.P. Jeevan Reddy, the content of which has never officially been revealed by the Government, recommended that AFSPA be repealed.</li>
<li><strong>ARC II: </strong>The Administrative Reforms Commission in its 5th Report on ‘Public Order’ had also recommended that AFSPA be repealed.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/its-time-to-repeal-afspa/"><strong>Why AFSPA should be repealed?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Human right violations</strong>: The repeal of AFSPA is necessary not just for restoring constitutional sanity, but also as a way of acknowledging dark history of our conduct in Nagaland.</li>
<li><strong>Need for ensuring individual dignity</strong>: The political incorporation of Nagaland (and all other areas where this law applies) will be set back if the guarantees of individual dignity of the Indian Constitution are not extended.</li>
<li><strong>Not state of exception</strong>: We often describe AFSPA in terms of a “state of exception”. But this theoretical term is misleading. How can a law that has been in virtually continuous existence since 1958 be described as an “exception”.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of human empathy</strong>: At the heart of AFSPA is a profound mutilation of human empathy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To bring in lasting peace in the North East, the government needs to avoid the trap of watered-down peace accords. While the move to withdraw AFSPA is welcome, it needs to be gradually erased. For that, changes in the ground situation would be crucial. Mere smoke signals or drum-beating can never do the job.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Do you think AFSPA is license to kill? Critically examine the utility of AFSPA today.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/afspa/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Right to privacy after 5 years</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-privacy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>article 21</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>right to privacy</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="right to privacy" class="alignnone wp-image-626979" height="418" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 558px) 100vw, 558px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/data-privacy-example-1024x768-1-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/data-privacy-example-1024x768-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/data-privacy-example-1024x768-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/data-privacy-example-1024x768-1.jpg 1024w" width="558"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Data privacy breaches which result in the loss and theft of personal, sensitive data have not reduced in terms of measurable frequency or their impact.</li>
<li>It has been 5 years since the nine-judge Supreme Court bench delivered the judgment in the Puttaswamy case. It asserted that Indians have a constitutionally protected fundamental right to privacy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/right-to-privacy/#:~:text=Without%20a%20data%20protection%20law,to%20writ%20proceedings%20in%20India."><strong>Right to Privacy can be defined as</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>A right to be let alone;</li>
<li>The right of a person to be free from any unwarranted publicity;</li>
<li>The right to live without any unwarranted interference by the public in matters with which the public is not necessarily concerned.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="right to privacy" class="alignnone wp-image-626980" height="282" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/privacy-10x10-featured-300x197.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/privacy-10x10-featured-300x197.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/privacy-10x10-featured-1024x672.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/privacy-10x10-featured-768x504.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/privacy-10x10-featured-1200x788.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/privacy-10x10-featured.jpg 1280w" width="429"/>Definition of data </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Data is a collection of discrete values that convey information, describing quantity, quality, fact, statistics, other basic units of meaning, or simply sequences of symbols that may be further interpreted.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Data Protection?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Data protection refers to policies and procedures seeking to minimise intrusion into the privacy of an individual caused by collection and usage of their personal data.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is data privacy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Data privacy refers to controlling access to the data. Organizations must determine who has access to data. Understandably, a privacy breach can lead to <a href="https://www.techtarget.com/searchdatamanagement/feature/Top-3-data-privacy-challenges-and-how-to-address-them" rel="noopener" target="_blank">data security issues</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is data security?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Data security refers specifically to measures taken to protect the integrity of the data itself against manipulation and malware. It provides defense from internal and external threats.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why we need data protection?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increasing internet</strong> <strong>use:</strong> India currently has over 750 million Internet users, with the number only expected to increase in the future.</li>
<li><strong>Data breaches: </strong>At the same time, India has among the highest data breaches in the world. Without a data protection law in place, the data of millions of Indians continues to be at risk of being exploited, sold, and misused without their consent.</li>
<li><strong>Individual privacy</strong>: Data monetization may happen at cost of individual privacy. The most sought-after datasets are those that contain sensitive personal data of individuals, ex. medical history, financial data.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="right to privacy" class="alignnone wp-image-626983" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 407px) 100vw, 407px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pega-300x246.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pega-300x246.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/pega.jpg 492w" width="407"/><br/>
Issues with the data breaches in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Violation of the right to privacy</strong>: The right to privacy was recognized as a fundamental right, included under the right to life and liberty by the Supreme Court of India in 2017.</li>
<li><strong>Absence of legal framework</strong>: Without a law in place to regulate data collection and to act as an oversight mechanism, valid concerns about privacy and other rights violations continue to arise.</li>
<li><strong>High Infrastructural Costs:</strong> Technologies like Artificial Intelligence and Big Data are costly to implement. The size of stored information is extremely large and requires huge network &amp; data storage facilities, which are currently not available in India.</li>
<li><strong>The concern of Data Leakage</strong>: In today’s world of cybercrime, it is important to put appropriate safeguards in place in order to ensure the integrity of the repository/database, so that it doesn’t leak out the information and is not privatized or monetized.</li>
<li><strong>Reliability &amp; Authenticity</strong>: As the data collected may be used in the court of law during the course of a criminal trial, the reliability and the admissibility of the data along with standards and procedures followed would be taken into consideration. Hence, the authenticity of the data is crucial.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Today, there is a relentless pace of digitisation that relies on gathering personal data in all spheres of our lives. All of this is done in a legal vacuum without any oversight or remedy. This underscores the urgent need for robust data protection law.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.  What do you understand by the term data privacy? Explain how data leakages threatens the sacred right to privacy?</strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-privacy/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Strong gender norms of japan reducing gender equality</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gender-norms/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>gender norms , women empowerment</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Gender norms " class="alignnone wp-image-627336" height="559" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 725px) 100vw, 725px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/8-300x231.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/8-300x231.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/8.jpg 620w" width="725"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Japan ranked lowest among the developed countries in the World Economic Forum’s Global Gender Gap Index 2022 due to its prevalent gender norms.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What Is a Gender-equal Society?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A society in which both women and men shall be given equal opportunities to participate voluntarily in activities in all fields as equal partners, and be able to enjoy political, economic, social and cultural benefits equally as well as to share responsibilities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is sexism in simple words?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Prejudice or discrimination based on sex especially discrimination against women. Behaviour, conditions, or attitudes that foster stereotypes of social roles based on sex.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the meaning of gender norms?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Gender norms are social principles that govern the behaviour of girls, boys, women, and men in society and restrict their gender identity into what is considered to be appropriate. Gender norms are neither static nor universal and change over time.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Gender norms " class="alignnone wp-image-627337" height="413" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 339px) 100vw, 339px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-246x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-246x300.jpg 246w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-838x1024.jpg 838w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-768x938.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-1257x1536.jpg 1257w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-737x900.jpg 737w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-1200x1466.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms.jpg 1676w" width="339"/>Persistent gender norms in japan </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Men should work outside the home.</li>
<li>Genders should be brought up differently.</li>
<li>Women are more suited to household work and child rearing than men.</li>
<li>Full time housewives are valuable to society because of their family raising role.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is womenomic’s? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>“Womenomics”, a theory linking the advancement of women to increased development rates. The concept, originally defined by the Japanese Prime Minister Abe.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/women-empowerment-issues-jobsreservation-education/"><strong>What is women’s empowerment all about?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Women’s empowerment can be defined to promoting women’s sense of self-worth, their ability to determine their own choices, and their right to influence social change for themselves and others.</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="gender norms " class="wp-image-627339" height="415" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-2-300x214.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-2-300x214.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-2-1024x730.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-2-768x548.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-2-1536x1095.jpeg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-2-1200x856.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-2-1980x1412.jpeg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/japaneese-gender-norms-2.jpeg 2000w" width="581"/></p>
<h4><strong>Measures toward the Realization of a Gender-equal Society</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Promoting the Participation of Women in National Advisory Councils and Committees.</li>
<li>Recruiting and Promoting of Female National Public Officers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is needed to improve women’s welfare?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Community sensitization</strong>: Persistent effort must be directed toward community sensitization to root out patriarchal social norms.</li>
<li><strong>Directional efforts</strong>: In addition to enforcing existing regulations like minimum wages, there must be supportive ancillary policies including childcare; secure transport; lighting; safety at work; and quotas in hiring, corporate boards, and politics to foster more  women  in  leadership.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Key fact </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Japan is the world’s fourth largest economy.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Due to the labour shortage in Japan, women are undoubtedly an essential resource for the nation. Hence, they should also be further involved in policy-making and social decisions such as gender inequality solving and feasible Womenomic’s adjustments for the next future.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>Japan’s struggle with gender parity teaches us that investing in women’s education and health may have limited impact if that society is trapped in gender norms that restrict women from capitalising these investments for themselves, the society and the country. Critically analyse.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gender-norms/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>James Webb telescope : The most powerful space telescope</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/james-webb-telescope/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>JSWT</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>JSWT, Big bang</p></div></div><h4><strong style="letter-spacing: -0.0415625em;"><img alt="James Webb telescope" class="alignnone wp-image-627363" height="289" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst.jpg 1500w" width="512"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Much of the universe remains unknown. The James Webb telescope will hopefully provide a powerful window to help resolve some of the cosmos’s many mysteries.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/in-news-james-webb-space-telescope/"><strong>What is James Webb Space Telescope (JWST)? </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is a space telescope being jointly developed by NASA, the European Space Agency (ESA), and the Canadian Space Agency (CSA).</li>
<li>It has taken 30 years and $10bn to develop, and is being described as one of the grand scientific endeavors of the 21st Century.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Where it is placed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The James Webb Space Telescope will not be in orbit around the Earth, like the Hubble Space Telescope is – it will actually orbit the Sun, 1.5 million kilometres (1 million miles) away from the Earth at what is called the second Lagrange point or L2.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Mission</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It will be “a giant leap forward in quest to understand the Universe and our origins”, as it will examine every phase of cosmic history: from the Big Bang to the formation of galaxies, stars, and planets to the evolution of our own Solar System.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="james webb telescope " class="alignnone wp-image-627356" height="446" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 446px) 100vw, 446px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-768x770.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-897x900.jpg 897w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1.jpg 1021w" width="446"/>Special features of JWST</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Time machine in space: </strong>Powerful space telescopes, like JWST or the Hubble Telescope, are often called time machines because of their ability to view very faraway objects. The light coming from those objects, stars or galaxies, which is captured by these telescopes, began its journey millions of years earlier. Essentially, what these telescopes see are images of these stars or galaxies as they were millions of years ago. The more distant the planet or star, the farther back in time are the telescopes able to see.</li>
<li><strong>Farthest from Earth: </strong>James Webb telescope will also be positioned much deeper into space, about a million miles from Earth, at a spot known as L2. It is one of the five points, known as Lagrange’s points, in any revolving two-body system like Earth and Sun, where the gravitational forces of the two large bodies cancel each other out.</li>
<li><strong>Engineering marvel: </strong>JWST has one large mirror, with a diameter of 21 feet (the height of a typical two-storey building), that will capture the infra-red light coming in from the deep universe while facing away from the Sun.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the goal of this telescope?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The telescope will be able to see just about anything in the sky.</li>
<li>However, it has one overriding objective – to see the light coming from the very first stars to shine in the Universe.</li>
<li>These pioneer stars are thought to have switched on about 100-200 million years after the Big Bang, or a little over 13.5 billion years ago.</li>
<li>James Webb telescope will be picking out groupings of these stars.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="james webb telescope " class="alignnone wp-image-627357" height="291" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 516px) 100vw, 516px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC.jpg 1280w" width="516"/>Its significance</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is widely expected to unveil many secrets of the universe, particularly those related to the Formation of stars and galaxies in the early period the first few hundred million years after the Big Bang.</li>
<li>Some have called James Webb telescope  the “telescope that ate astronomy”.</li>
<li>It is said to look back in time to the Dark Ages of the universe.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The universe is vast and most of it is unknown. We hope that the James Webb telescope, over its lifetime would provide us with a powerful window to help resolve some of the many mysteries of the cosmos and make it a little bit more comprehensible.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What is James Webb telescope experiment? Do you think it shades light on dark matter? Explain.  </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/james-webb-telescope/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Construction and demolition waste should be managed properly</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/construction-and-demolition-waste/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>solid waste management</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Construction and demolition" class="alignnone wp-image-627621" height="352" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 986px) 100vw, 986px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.20510300_1598362635_0-300x107.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.20510300_1598362635_0-300x107.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.20510300_1598362635_0-768x275.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.20510300_1598362635_0.jpg 1024w" width="986"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Huge amounts of construction and demolition waste in a residential area is hazardous for human health and warrants immediate disposal.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Twin towers in Noida, Uttar Pradesh were demolished by controlled implosion. Their being located in a residential neighbourhood of Noida makes it even more essential to introduce interventions to mitigate pollution and waste, post-demolition.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is construction and demolition waste?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Construction and demolition wastes (CDW) are the status of building materials after the end life of buildings. CDW could be concrete, steel, wood products, asphalt shingles, and bricks from building.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/managing-indias-growing-waste/"><strong>What is waste management?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Waste management refers to the activities and actions required to manage waste from its start till its disposal. This includes collection, transport, treatment and disposal of waste together with monitoring and regulation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Construction and demolition" class="alignnone wp-image-627622" height="315" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 559px) 100vw, 559px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-1536x864.jpeg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-2048x1152.jpeg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-1200x675.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/image-1980x1113.jpeg 1980w" width="559"/>Why they should be managed properly?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Waste management and diligent planning becomes critical for regulation of humongous solid waste being generated every day. With growing urbanization and rise of smart cities on the offing the issue of solid waste management becomes even more imperative<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Data to remember </strong></h4>
<p><strong>62 million tons of waste is generated annually in the country at present.</strong></p>
<p><strong>India manages to recover and recycle only about 1 per cent of its construction and demolition (C&amp;D) waste, says new CSE analysis.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="Construction and demolition" class="alignnone wp-image-627623" height="322" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 578px) 100vw, 578px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Debris-1-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Debris-1-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Debris-1-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Debris-1.jpg 980w" width="578"/>What are the impacts of construction waste on the environment and human health?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Air: </strong>Disassembling and shredding of construction waste generate dust or large particulates into the surroundings and affects the respiratory health of waste management workers and others.</li>
<li><strong>Water: </strong>(Landfills are not properly designed to hold construction waste + Illegal dump sites + Improper recycling &amp; disposal of e-waste) = compounds leach into the ground = Groundwater gets toxified due to heavy metals from demolition waste.</li>
<li><strong>Soil: </strong>Soil is contaminated by direct contact with contaminants from construction waste or its by-products from recycling &amp; disposal + indirectly through irrigation. Soils become toxic when substances such as lead, mercury, cadmium, arsenic, and polychlorinated biphenyl’s (PCBs) are deposited in landfills. Contaminated soils have bad impacts on microbes and plants =&gt; the pollutants reach higher animals or humans through the food chain.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Some positive suggestions </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Need robust estimation and characterisation of C&amp;D waste to design systems for material recovery: </strong>Cities need comprehensive assessment and quantification of C&amp;D waste generation, to plan adequate infrastructure and systems for treatment and management.</li>
<li><strong>Need of documentation:</strong> Cities must create easily accessible databases of buildings and their physical and legal attributes. Construction/demolition permits need to be inventorised with associated waste management plans attached<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Preparing for waste management from new generation material: </strong>Expanded polystyrene insulation (EPS), Styrofoam, plastic spacers, bituminous material and asbestos embedded within new wall assemblies are a recycling challenge. This needs special attention.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure projects need to set up their own recycling facilities</strong>: DMRC has done so. Concrete can be easily recycled. Butt excavated waste is a challenge. Other infrastructure projects like highway and roadwork find recycling of bituminous material waste challenging. Globally, proactive prevention of waste is undertaken through modification of existing on site construction practices etc.</li>
<li><strong>Responsibility of the construction Industry</strong>: The current system provides no incentive to the construction agencies for managing their own waste via waste reduction and on-site reuse and recycling. The Rules have created a push by creating a legal requirement for waste management but the financial drivers are missing. This requires fiscal strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Environmental and material challenges associated with the Construction and Demolition waste problem need urgent and immediate attention nation-wide to recover material, protect environment, and for clean air.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. India manages to recover and recycle only about 1 per cent of its construction and demolition waste analyse the constraints in it. Also suggest some positive measures to address this challenge.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/construction-and-demolition-waste/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Places in news: Taiwan Strait</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-taiwan-strait-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Taiwan Strait</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>One China Policy</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627769" height="424" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 346px) 100vw, 346px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/taiwan-strait-245x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/taiwan-strait-245x300.jpg 245w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/taiwan-strait.jpg 607w" width="346"/></strong></p>
<p>India has for the first time referred to what it called “the militarization of the Taiwan Strait”, marking a rare instance of New Delhi appearing to comment on China’s actions towards Taiwan.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Two American warships have recently sailed very close to China through Taiwan Strait.</li>
<li>This has intimidated the China which is already fuming due to the visit of Nancy Pelosi.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Taiwan Strait</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Taiwan Strait is a 180-kilometer wide strait separating the island of Taiwan and continental China (and Asia of course).</li>
<li>The strait is part of the South China Sea and connects to the East China Sea to the north.</li>
<li>The narrowest part is 130 km wide.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues over Taiwan Strait</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Taiwan Strait is itself a subject of an international dispute over its political status.</li>
<li>China claims to enjoy sovereignty, sovereign rights and jurisdiction over the Taiwan Strait” and regards the waterway as “internal territorial waters” instead of being international waters.</li>
<li>This means that the Chinese government denies any foreign vessel having the freedom of navigation in the strait.</li>
<li>This position has drawn strong objections from the western World.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s change of stance</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has followed a “<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-china-taiwan-tension-a-flash-point-in-indo-pacific/">One China policy</a>” since its recognition of the PRC in 1949, and only maintains trade and cultural relations with Taiwan.</li>
<li>India routinely reiterated this policy until 2008 after which it stopped mentioning it in official statements.</li>
<li>This is a demand that China usually asks of most countries in official declarations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is India shifting its stance?</h4>
<ul>
<li>China often make provocative statements claiming Arunachal Pradesh.</li>
<li>It often moves to issue “stapled visas” to Indian citizens in Jammu and Kashmir and Arunachal.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-taiwan-strait-2/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Positive Indigenisation List (PIL)?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-positive-indigenisation-list-pil/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Positive Indigenisation List (PIL)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Defence indigenization</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627775" height="560" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL-768x768.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL-900x900.jpg 900w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Positive-Indigenisation-List-PIL.jpg 1200w" width="560"/></p>
<p>In line with the effort to promote self-reliance in defence manufacturing, the Defence Minister has approved the third Positive Indigenisation List (PIL) of 780 strategically important line replacement units (LRU).</p>
<h4>What is a Positive Indigenisation List (PIL)?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The positive indigenisation list essentially means that the Armed Forces—Army, Navy, and Air Force—will only procure the listed items from domestic manufacturers.</li>
<li>The manufacturers could be private sector players or Defense Public Sector Undertakings (DPSUs).</li>
<li>This concept was rolled out in the Defence Acquisition Procedure (DAP) 2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>This third list is different from the three PILs announced for the armed forces.</li>
<li>This list is in continuation to the two PILs of LRUs, sub-systems, assemblies, sub-assemblies and components that were published in December 2021 and March 2022.</li>
<li>These lists contain 2,500 items which are already indigenised and 458 (351+107) items which will be indigenised within the given timelines.</li>
<li>Out of the 458 items, 167 items (163 from the first PIL, and four from the second PIL) have been indigenised, so far, it stated.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Other steps taken by the Centre to boost defence production</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Licensing relaxation:</strong> Measures announced to boost exports since 2014 include simplified defence industrial licensing, relaxation of export controls and grant of no-objection certificates.</li>
<li><strong>Lines of Credit:</strong> Specific incentives were introduced under the foreign trade policy and the Ministry of External Affairs has facilitated Lines of Credit for countries to import defence product.</li>
<li><strong>Policy boost:</strong> The Defence Ministry has also issued a draft Defence Production &amp; Export Promotion Policy 2020.</li>
<li><strong>Budgetary allocation:</strong> In addition, a percentage of the capital outlay of the defence budget has been reserved for procurement from domestic industry.</li>
<li><strong>Defence Industrial Corridors:</strong> The government has also announced 2 dedicated Corridors in the States of TN and UP to act as clusters of defence manufacturing that leverage existing infrastructure, and human capital.</li>
<li><strong>Long-term vision:</strong> The vision of the government is to achieve a turnover of $25 bn including export of $5 bn in Aerospace and Defence goods and services by 2025.</li>
<li><strong>Push for self-reliance:</strong> The govt has identified the Defence and Aerospace sector as a focus area for the ‘Aatmanirbhar Bharat’ or Self-Reliant India initiative.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues retarding defence indigenization</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Excess reliance on Public Sector:</strong> India has four companies (Indian ordnance factories, Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL), Bharat Electronics Limited (BEL) and Bharat Dynamics Limited (BDL)) among the top 100 biggest arms producers of the world.</li>
<li><strong>Policy delays:</strong> In the past few years, the government has approved over 200 defence acquisition worth Rs 4 trillion, but most are still in relatively early stages of processing.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of Critical Technologies:</strong> Poor design capability in critical technologies, inadequate investment in R&amp;D and the inability to manufacture major subsystems and components hamper the indigenous manufacturing.</li>
<li><strong>Long gestation:</strong> The creation of a manufacturing base is capital and technology-intensive and has a long gestation period. By that time newer technologies make products outdated.</li>
<li><strong>‘Unease’ in doing business:</strong> An issue related to stringent labour laws, compliance burden and lack of skills, affects the development of indigenous manufacturing in defence.</li>
<li><strong>Multiple jurisdictions:</strong> Overlapping jurisdiction of the Ministry of Defence and Ministry of Industrial Promotion impair India’s capability of defence manufacturing.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of quality:</strong> The higher indigenization in few cases is largely attributed to the low-end technology.</li>
<li><strong>FDI Policy:</strong> The earlier FDI limit of 49% was not enough to enthuse global manufacturing houses to set up bases in India.</li>
<li><strong>R&amp;D Lacunae:</strong> A lip service to technology funding by making token allocations is an adequate commentary on our lack of seriousness in the area of Research and Development.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of skills:</strong> There is a lack of engineering and research capability in our institutions. It again leads us back to the need for a stronger industry-academia interface.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reducing import dependence:</strong> India was the world’s second-largest arms importer from 2014-18, ceding the long-held tag as the largest importer to Saudi Arabia, says 2019 SIPRI report.</li>
<li><strong>Security Imperative:</strong> Indigenization in defence is critical to national security also. It keeps intact the technological expertise and encourages spin-off technologies and innovation that often stem from it.</li>
<li><strong>Economic boost:</strong> <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indigenisation-in-defence-technologies-manufacturing-will-ensure-indias-strategic-autonomy/">Indigenization in defence</a> can help create a large industry which also includes small manufacturers.</li>
<li><strong>Employment generation:</strong> Defence manufacturing will lead to the generation of satellite industries that in turn will pave the way for a generation of employment opportunities.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-positive-indigenisation-list-pil/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is a Full Court Meeting?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-full-court-meeting/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Full Court Meeting</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>Within hours of taking over, the new Chief Justice of India Uday Umesh Lalit called a meeting of the ‘full court’ where the judges discussed how to deal with issues relating to listing and backlog of cases.</p>
<h4>What is a Full Court Meeting?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A full court meeting literally means one which is attended by all the judges of the court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When is it held?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There are no written rules dealing with this.</li>
<li>As per convention, full-court meetings are called by the Chief Justice of India to discuss issues of importance to the judiciary.</li>
<li>The senior designations of practising advocates in the Supreme Court and high courts are also decided during the full court meetings.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the significance of a full court meeting?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The basic idea is to take everyone along.</li>
<li>Full court meetings are an ideal occasion to arrive at common solutions to deal with problems that beset the country’s legal system and to make any amends, if necessary, in the administrative practices of the court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How frequently is it held?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As a full court meeting is convened at the discretion of the Chief Justice of India, it does not follow any particular calendar.</li>
<li>Full court meetings have been held many times in the past.</li>
<li>In March 2020, it was convened to discuss demands by associations of lawyers to close the court till further notice following the Covid-10 outbreak.</li>
<li>Also, a full court meeting held on May 7, 1997 decided that “every Judge should make a declaration of all his/her assets in the form of real estate or investment” held in own name or in the name of spouse or any person dependent.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong><em>Do you know?</em></strong></h4>
<p><em>Justice Uday Umesh Lalit, sworn in as the 49th Chief Justice of India on Saturday, will be the sixth head of the Indian judiciary to have a tenure of less than 100 days. </em></p>
<p><em>Lalit will demit office on November 8 with a tenure of 74 days.</em></p>
<p><em>Justice Kamal Narain Singh, who was the CJI between November 25, 1991 and December 12, 1991, had a tenure of 18 days.</em></p>
<p><em>Justice S Rajendra Babu had a tenure of 30 days as the chief justice of India between May 2, 2004 and May 31, 2004.</em></p>
<p><em>Justice J C Shah had a tenure of 36 days when he was the CJI between December 17, 1970 and January 21, 1971.</em></p>
<p><em>Justice G B Patnaik had a 41-day tenure as the head of the Indian judiciary when he held the office of the CJI from November 8, 2002 to December 18, 2002.</em></p>
<p><em>Justice L M Sharma had a tenure of 86 days as the CJI when he was in office between November 18, 1992 and February 11, 1993.</em></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/justice-lalit-appointed-49th-cji/">Tap to read more about appointment of CJIs.</a></p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-full-court-meeting/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Fruit Fly: Novel method to study Nuclear Matrix</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nuclear Matrix</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627770" height="489" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 566px) 100vw, 566px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly.jpg 665w" width="566"/></p>
<p>Now, using a novel method, Indian researchers have established a way of studying the nuclear matrix of the fruit fly (Drosophila melanogaster) without removing the nucleus from the embryo.</p>
<h4>Nuclear Matrix of fruit flies</h4>
<ul>
<li>Every cell that makes up an organism contains a copy of its genome.</li>
<li>This genome is packaged in special ways with the help of a structure known as the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>The nuclear matrix gives an organisation and architecture to the nucleus.</li>
<li>A familiar figure, the nuclear matrix of fruit flies, for instance, has been studied for many years, mainly by isolating it in nuclei that have been taken out from fruit fly embryos.</li>
<li>This allows comparative study of nuclear matrix in different cells within the embryo, giving a boost for fruit fly genetics.</li>
<li>Two of the most recent papers on this work have been published in the journals Nucleus and Molecular and Cell Proteomics.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What exactly is Nuclear Matrix?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The nuclear matrix is like a scaffolding.</li>
<li>Using biochemical means, if the nucleus is taken out and treated with an enzyme that digests all the DNA.</li>
<li>It is then washed with a solution of high salt concentration so that viable DNA proteins or protein-protein interactions are removed.</li>
<li>What is then left is a fibrous meshwork of proteins called the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>This is like a building from which all movables have been sucked out, leaving only the beams, ceiling, and walls, plug points, etc.</li>
<li>Analogous to the building, the nuclear matrix creates the architecture in which the genome is packaged.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why study them?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Studying the nuclear matrix is, therefore, very important to get a better picture of how precisely development progresses every time a new individual is born.</li>
<li>We have 220 different types of cells in the body, but all contain identical genomes.</li>
<li>The same genome sequence is present in neurons, where it works for thinking; in the liver, the same sequence enacts metabolism; and in the intestine, it works to digest.</li>
<li>So, this information is packaged differently in different cell types.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Lifetime perks for former CJIs, SC Judges</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/lifetime-perks-for-former-cjis-sc-judges/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Perks and privileges to Judges</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627766" height="320" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 416px) 100vw, 416px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/judge-300x231.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/judge-300x231.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/judge.jpg 455w" width="416"/></p>
<p>The Centre amended the Supreme Court Judges Rules the second time in a week to provide chauffeurs (car driver) and domestic help for retired Chief Justices of India and Supreme Court judges for their entire lifetime.</p>
<h4>Perks for Retired CJs</h4>
<ul>
<li>Retired CJIs would also get secretarial assistants.</li>
<li>The staff would be paid the salary and allowances of regular employees of the Supreme Court.</li>
<li>The first series of amendments in the Rules on August 23 had allowed retired Chief Justices of India and Supreme Court judges chauffeurs, secretarial assistants and security cover only for a year.</li>
<li>There was no mention of “domestic help”, who would be an employee in the level of junior court assistant.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What else?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The judiciary had recently raised concerns about attacks on judges.</li>
<li>Hence the benefit of 24-hour security cover has been extended to five years for retired Chief Justices and three years for retired judges of the Supreme Court.</li>
<li>Besides, former CJIs and retired judges of the top court can get their monthly mobile phone and Internet bills reimbursed to the extent of ₹4,200.</li>
<li>A retired CJI is also entitled to a rent-free Type VII accommodation, other than the designated official residence, in New Delhi for six months immediately after retirement.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why such move?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The government is one of the biggest litigants in the Supreme Court.</li>
<li>There has been public debate on whether post-retirement benefits dangled by the government could influence the judicial work of serving judges.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/lifetime-perks-for-former-cjis-sc-judges/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia blocks agreement on Nuclear Non-proliferation Treaty (NPT)</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/russia-blocks-agreement-on-nuclear-non-proliferation-treaty/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nuclear Non-proliferation Treaty</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>Russia has blocked the agreement on the final document of a four-week review of the Nuclear Non-proliferation Treaty (NPT).</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The NPT review conference is supposed to be held every five years but was delayed because of the COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
<li>This marked the second failure of its 191 state parties to produce an outcome document.</li>
<li>The last review conference in 2015 ended without an agreement because of serious differences over establishing a Middle East zone free of weapons of mass destruction.</li>
</ul>
<h4>About Nuclear Non-proliferation Treaty (NPT)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Between 1965 and 1968, the treaty was negotiated by the Eighteen Nation Committee on Disarmament, a United Nations-sponsored organization based in Geneva, Switzerland.</li>
<li>Opened for signature in 1968, the treaty entered into force in 1970.</li>
<li>The NPT is an international treaty whose objective is</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>To prevent the spread of nuclear weapons and weapons technology</li>
<li>To promote cooperation in the peaceful uses of nuclear energy and</li>
<li>To further the goal of achieving nuclear disarmament and general and complete disarmament</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The treaty <strong><u>defines nuclear-weapon states</u></strong> as those that have built and tested a nuclear explosive device before 1 January 1967; these are the United States (1945), Russia (1949), the United Kingdom (1952), France (1960), and China (1964).</li>
</ul>
<h4>Non-members of the treaty</h4>
<ul>
<li>Four UN member states have never accepted the NPT, three of which possess or are thought to possess nuclear weapons: India, Israel, and Pakistan.</li>
<li>In addition, South Sudan, founded in 2011, has not joined.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues in Nuclear Disarmament</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Notion of Nuclear ‘Haves’ and ‘Have-Nots’:</strong> The proponents of disarmaments are themselves nuclear armed countries thus creating a nuclear monopoly.</li>
<li><strong>Concept of Peaceful Nuclear Explosion (PNE):</strong> conducted for non-military purposes such as mining.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why didn’t India join NPT?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India is one of the only five countries that either did not sign the NPT or signed but withdrew, thus becoming part of a list that includes Pakistan, Israel, North Korea, and South Sudan.</li>
<li>India always considered the NPT as discriminatory and had refused to sign it.</li>
<li>India maintains that they are selectively applicable to the non-nuclear powers and legitimised the monopoly of the five nuclear weapons powers.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s commitment for de-nuclearization</h4>
<p>India has always batted for a universal commitment and an agreed global and non-discriminatory multilateral framework.</p>
<ul>
<li>It has outlined a <strong>working paper on Nuclear Disarmament</strong> submitted to the UN General Assembly in 2006.</li>
<li>India participated in the <strong>Nuclear Security Summit</strong> process and has regularly participated in the International Conferences on Nuclear Security organised by the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA).</li>
<li>India is also a member of the <strong>Nuclear Security Contact Group</strong> (but has signed off the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (NPT)).</li>
<li>India has expressed its readiness to support the commencement of negotiations on a <strong>Fissile Material Cut-off Treaty</strong> (FMCT).</li>
<li>India couldn’t join the <strong>Comprehensive Nuclear-Test-Ban Treaty (CTBT)</strong> due to several concerns raised by India.</li>
<li>India has piloted an annual UNGA Resolution on “<strong>Measures to Prevent Terrorists from Acquiring Weapons of Mass Destruction</strong>” since 2002, which is adopted by consensus.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has actively supported and contributed to the strengthening of the global nuclear security architecture.</li>
<li>There is a need for the international community to pay closer attention to the illicit proliferation of networks of nuclear weapons, their delivery systems, components and relevant technologies.</li>
<li>India hopes that the international community will continue to work towards realising our collective aspiration for a nuclear weapon-free world.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/russia-blocks-agreement-on-nuclear-non-proliferation-treaty/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Revisiting the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-627767" height="188" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-768x481.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji.jpg 885w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has referred to a three-judge Bench a series of petitions seeking a judicial direction that political parties who make wild promises should also reveal in their poll manifestos where they will get the money to pay for them.</p>
<p>The reference is a shift from the court’s own stand in the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs Tamil Nadu judgment of 2013.</p>
<h4>Hefty promises: A no lesser corrupt practice</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the <strong><u>Balaji case judgment</u></strong>, a Division Bench of the Supreme Court had held that making promises in election manifestos <strong><u>do not amount to a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> under Section 123 of the Representation of People Act (RP).</li>
<li>However, the Supreme Court is now worried that <strong><u>freebies promised</u></strong> by political parties to win elections could <strong><u>bleed the public exchequer dry</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Court said that parties who form the government riding the wave created by their pre-poll promises of free gifts are bleeding the State finances dry.</li>
<li>Parties actually try to <strong><u>fulfil their outlandish promises using public money</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Supreme Court has therefore decided to revisit the Balaji verdict.</p>
<h4>What triggered the Balaji case?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The course of events started in 2006, during the run-up to the Tamil Nadu Assembly elections.</li>
<li>A party released its election manifesto announcing a scheme of free distribution of colour television sets (CTVs) to each and every household if voted to power.</li>
<li>The party swept to power in the polls and decided to implement its scheme and portioned off ₹750 crore from the budget for the project.</li>
<li>The government finally distributed 30,000 TV sets across the State.</li>
<li>In 2011, the rival party also announced its election manifesto with free gifts to “equalise” the gifts offered.</li>
<li>It promised grinders, mixies, electric fans, laptop computers, four gram gold thalis, a cheque of ₹50,000 for women’s marriage, green houses, 20 kg of rice to ration card holders and free cattle and sheep.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Balaji case</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji, a resident of Tamil Nadu, challenged the schemes introduced by the parties in the Madras High Court.</li>
<li>He said that the <strong><u>expenditure was incurred by the State from the exchequer</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This was “<strong><u>unauthorised, impermissible and ultra vires the constitutional mandates</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>High Court dismissed his case</u></strong>, following which he had moved the apex court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did the case play out?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji argued that <strong><u>the State cannot act</u></strong> in furtherance of “<strong><u>eccentric principles of socialistic philanthropy</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>He argued that the promises of <strong><u>free distribution of non-essential commodities</u></strong> in an election manifesto amounts to electoral bribe under Section 123 of the RP Act.</li>
<li>Money can be taken out of the Consolidated Fund of the State <strong><u>only for “public purposes”</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>distribution of goods to certain sections</u></strong> of people was <strong><u>violative of Article 14 of the Constitution</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Argument provided against the Balaji Case</h4>
<ul>
<li>In response, the State of Tamil Nadu countered that <strong><u>promises do not constitute corrupt practice. </u></strong></li>
<li>Political parties are not the State and ‘<strong><u>freebies’ is a nebulous term which has no legal status</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises implemented by the party after forming the government is an <strong><u>obligation under the Directives Principles of State Policy</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The State is only doing its duty to promote the <strong><u>welfare of its people</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises are <strong><u>implemented by framing various schemes/guidelines/eligibility</u></strong> criteria etc. as well as <strong><u>with the approval of the legislature. </u></strong></li>
<li>Thus, it <strong><u>cannot be construed as a waste of public money</u></strong> or be prohibited by any statute or scheme.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Outcome of the Judgement</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court’s judgment held that <strong><u>promises by a political party cannot constitute a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> on its part.</li>
<li>It would be <strong><u>“misleading” to generalize</u></strong> that all promises in the election manifesto would amount to corrupt practice.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>manifesto is a statement of the policy</u></strong> for a political party.</li>
<li>The question of implementing the manifesto arises only if the political party forms a government.</li>
<li>It is the promise of a future government and not of an individual candidate.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Scope for revisiting the judgment</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court agreed that <strong><u>freebies create an “uneven playing field”.</u></strong></li>
<li>It had asked the Election Commission of India to <strong><u>consult political parties</u></strong> and issue guidelines on the election manifesto and make it a <strong><u>part of the Model Code of Conduct</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the Court’s move to review the Balaji judgment significant?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In its order, the court foresees that “freebies may create a situation wherein the <strong><u>State governments cannot provide basic amenities due to lack of funds</u></strong> and the State is pushed towards imminent bankruptcy”.</li>
<li>The court said it wants a <strong><u>transparent debate</u></strong> before the three-judge Bench on whether an “enforceable” judicial order can stop political parties from promising and distributing ‘irrational freebies’.</li>
<li>The case is unique as the Supreme Court is exploring <strong><u>whether judicial parameters can be set on a purely political act of promising freebies.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Concerns around Aadhaar-Voter ID linkage</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/concerns-around-aadhaar-voter-id-linkage/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Aadhaar</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Data Privacy and Aadhaar</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627768" height="238" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 422px) 100vw, 422px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vid-adhaar-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vid-adhaar-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vid-adhaar-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/vid-adhaar.jpg 849w" width="422"/></strong></p>
<p>Reports have surfaced online of instances where block level officers have asked individuals to link their Aadhaar with their Voter IDs, failing which their Voter IDs could be cancelled.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>This furore comes in the aftermath of the Election Commission’s (EC) campaign to promote the linkage of Voter ID and Aadhaar that began on August 1.</li>
<li>In the first ten days since its launch, the campaign saw almost 2.5 crore Aadhaar holders voluntarily submitting their details to the EC.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Aadhaar-Voter ID linkage: Why does the government want this?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The EC conducts regular exercises to maintain an <strong><u>updated and accurate record</u></strong> of the voter base.</li>
<li>A part of this exercise is to <strong><u>weed out duplication of voters</u></strong>.</li>
<li>There have been <strong><u>migrant workers</u></strong> who may have been registered more than once on the electoral rolls in different constituencies or for persons registered multiple times within the same constituency.</li>
<li>As per the government, linkage of Aadhaar with voter IDs will assist in ensuring that only one Voter ID is issued per citizen of India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Is the linking of Aadhaar with one’s Voter ID mandatory?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In December 2021, Parliament passed the <strong><u>Election Laws (Amendment) Act, 2021</u></strong> .</li>
<li>This was to <strong><u>amend the Representation of the People Act, 1950</u></strong> and Section 23(4) was inserted in the RP Act.</li>
<li>It states that the <strong><u>electoral registration officer</u></strong> <strong><em>may</em></strong> require voters to furnish their Aadhaar numbers to verify Authencity of voters list.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is it making headlines now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There has been the <strong><u>use of discretionary language</u></strong> throughout the amendments.</li>
<li>This has been <strong><u>accompanied by assurances that linkage is optional</u></strong> by both the government and the EC.</li>
<li>Alternative is provided to only who does not have an Aadhaar number.</li>
<li>To that extent, the <strong><u>limited element of choice</u></strong> that has been incorporated in the amendments seem to be negated or at the very least thrown into confusion.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why there is such proposal for linking?</h4>
<p>The preference to use Aadhaar for verification and authentication, both by the state and private sector, stems from few reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increase in UID-holders:</strong> First, at the end of 2021, 99.7% of the adult Indian population had an Aadhaar card.</li>
<li><strong>Most versatile document:</strong> This coverage exceeds that of any other officially valid document such as driver’s licence, ration cards, PAN cards etc. that are mostly applied for specific purposes.</li>
<li><strong>Reliable source of authentication:</strong> Since Aadhaar allows for biometric authentication, Aadhaar based authentication and verification is considered more reliable, quicker and cost efficient when compared to other IDs.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with mandatory linking: Puttaswamy judgment highlights</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Puttaswamy judgment:</strong> The above reasons do not suffice the mandating of Aadhaar except in limited circumstances as per the Puttaswamy judgment.</li>
<li><strong>Indispensability of the purpose:</strong> It needs to be considered whether such mandatory linkage of Aadhaar with Voter ID would pass the test of being “necessary and proportionate” to the purpose of de-duplication which is sought to be achieved.</li>
<li><strong>Constitutional ambiguity:</strong> In Puttaswamy, one of the questions that the Supreme Court explored was whether the mandatory linking of Aadhaar with bank accounts was constitutional or not.</li>
<li><strong>Against informational autonomy: </strong>It is the right to privacy which would allow a person to decide which official document they want to use for verification and authentication.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Other judicial observations: <u>Lal Babu Hussein (1995) Case</u></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court had held that the Right to vote cannot be disallowed by insisting only on four proofs of identity.</li>
<li>The voters are entitled to rely on any other proof of identity and obtain the right to vote.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the operational difficulties?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Aadhaar is not a citizenship proof:</strong> The preference to Aadhaar for the purposes of determining voters is puzzling as Aadhaar is only a proof of residence and not a proof of citizenship.</li>
<li><strong>Excluding non-citizens is not easy:</strong> Verifying voter identity against this will only help in tackling duplication but will not remove voters who are not citizens of India from the electoral rolls.</li>
<li><strong>Estimate of error rates in biometric based authentication:</strong> This certainly differs. As per the UIDAI in 2018, Aadhaar based biometric authentication had a 12% error rate.</li>
<li><strong>Disenfranchisement of existing voters:</strong> Errors have led to the disenfranchisement of around 30 lakh voters in AP and Telangana before the Supreme Court stalled the process of linkage.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Key concern: Right to Privacy</h4>
<ul>
<li>Some civil societies has highlighted that linking of the two databases of electoral rolls and Aadhaar could lead to the <strong><u>linkage of Aadhaar’s “demographic” information with voter ID information</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This could lead to violation of the right to privacy and <strong><u>surveillance measures by the state</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This would leave the EC with the option of verifying its information only through <strong><u>door-to-door checks</u></strong>.</li>
<li>There is a <strong><u>lack of enforceable data protection principles</u></strong> that regulate how authentication data will be used.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What lies ahead?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Even as the amendments have been made and the EC has launched a campaign for linkage, a writ petition has filed with the Supreme Court challenging the same.</li>
<li>It challenges the amendments as being violative of the right to privacy.</li>
<li>The Supreme Court has transferred the writ to the Delhi High Court.</li>
<li>In the meantime, it is important that the government clarifies through a correction in Form 6B that the linking is not mandatory.</li>
<li>The govt should expedite the enactment of a data protection legislation that allays concerns of unauthorized processing of personal data held by the government.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/concerns-around-aadhaar-voter-id-linkage/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Forest rights act failed to deliver justice to tribals</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/forest-rights-act/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Community forest rights</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Tribal welfare</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="forest right act" class="alignnone wp-image-627940" height="418" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 628px) 100vw, 628px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.18262600_1661773268_p38dlpix-local-woman-processing-mahua-seeds-in-kamtana-village-of-odisha-arabinda-mahapatra-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.18262600_1661773268_p38dlpix-local-woman-processing-mahua-seeds-in-kamtana-village-of-odisha-arabinda-mahapatra-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.18262600_1661773268_p38dlpix-local-woman-processing-mahua-seeds-in-kamtana-village-of-odisha-arabinda-mahapatra-768x513.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.18262600_1661773268_p38dlpix-local-woman-processing-mahua-seeds-in-kamtana-village-of-odisha-arabinda-mahapatra.jpg 1024w" width="628"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is a surge in demand by forest communities to not only access the resources of their habitat, but also to establish their ownership over forests as forest rights act in not meeting its objective.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Residents of 18 villages in <strong>Chhattisgarh’s Udanti Sitanadi Tiger Reserve</strong> blocked the busy National Highway 130C.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What tribal people say?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>“We need forest resources for survival. Being a tiger reserve, we already lead a life with many restrictions. There is no power supply, access to grazing lands is non-existent and we cannot undertake construction works,” says Arjun Nayak of Nagesh, one of the 18 villages in Gariaband district.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="forest right act" class="alignnone wp-image-627941" height="403" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 575px) 100vw, 575px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Odisha-forest-graphic-300x210.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Odisha-forest-graphic-300x210.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Odisha-forest-graphic-1024x716.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Odisha-forest-graphic-768x537.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Odisha-forest-graphic.jpg 1200w" width="575"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/evolution-of-forest-rights-in-india-from-1856-to-2006-in-depth-analysis-of-fra-its-issues/">What is forest rights act 2006?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Forest Rights Act (FRA), 2006 recognizes the rights of the forest dwelling tribal communities and other traditional forest dwellers to forest resources, on which these communities were dependent for a variety of needs, including livelihood, habitation and other socio-cultural needs.</li>
<li>It aimed to protect the marginalised socio-economic class of citizens and balance the right to environment with their right to life and livelihood.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="forest right act" class="alignnone wp-image-627942" height="410" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 557px) 100vw, 557px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tendu-768x566-1-300x221.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tendu-768x566-1-300x221.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tendu-768x566-1.jpg 768w" width="557"/>What are individual rights under FRA act?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Act encompasses Rights of Self-cultivation and Habitationwhich are usually regarded as Individual rights<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-community-forest-rights/"><strong>What are community forest rights under FRA act?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Community Rights as Grazing, Fishing and access to Water bodies in forests, Habitat Rights for PVTGs, Traditional Seasonal Resource access of Nomadic and Pastoral community, access to biodiversity, community right to intellectual property and traditional knowledge, recognition of traditional customary rights and right to protect, regenerate or conserve or manage any community forest resource for sustainable use.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Case study / Value addition </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Chargaon village, Dhamtari district, Chhattisgarh</strong></p>
<p>Migration has drastically reduced due to economic benefits after getting CFRR. Success in improving quality of tendu leaves with better management practices, increasing income.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="forest right act" class="alignnone wp-image-627943" height="798" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 354px) 100vw, 354px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.50357400_1661773367_31-133x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.50357400_1661773367_31-133x300.jpg 133w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.50357400_1661773367_31-454x1024.jpg 454w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.50357400_1661773367_31-399x900.jpg 399w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/0.50357400_1661773367_31.jpg 500w" width="354"/>Issues with Forest rights act</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Non responsive states</strong>: The forest rights claims of these tribes and forest-dwellers are mostly rejected by the States.</li>
<li><strong>Improper claims</strong>: Being poor and illiterate, living in remote areas, they do not know the appropriate procedure for filing claims.</li>
<li><strong>Low awareness</strong>: The gram sabhas, which initiate the verification of their claims, are low on awareness of how to deal with them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="forest right act" class="alignnone wp-image-627944" height="350" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/691848-updated-women-from-the-forest-village-of-dhamditola1500-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/691848-updated-women-from-the-forest-village-of-dhamditola1500-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/691848-updated-women-from-the-forest-village-of-dhamditola1500-1024x614.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/691848-updated-women-from-the-forest-village-of-dhamditola1500-768x461.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/691848-updated-women-from-the-forest-village-of-dhamditola1500-1200x720.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/691848-updated-women-from-the-forest-village-of-dhamditola1500.jpg 1500w" width="584"/>Why are forest rights important for tribals?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Justice</strong>: Aimed at undoing the “historic injustice” meted out to forest-dependent communities due to curtailment of their customary rights over forests, the FRA came into force in 2008.</li>
<li><strong>Livelihood</strong>: It is important as it recognises the community’s right to use, manage and conserve forest resources, and to legally hold forest land that these communities have used for cultivation and residence.</li>
<li><strong>Conservation</strong>: It also underlines the integral role that forest dwellers play in the sustainability of forests and in the conservation of biodiversity.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>Despite the contentious and debatable nature of this law, the importance and necessity of the FRA, 2006 can not be negated completely. The law assumes even more significant importance when the country is a developing economy and is full-fledged following the path of capitalism, thus making it even more substantial to provide a redressal mechanism for vulnerable and marginalised communities and groups, such as the <i>Adivasis </i>and the other similar tribes, from the necessary evil of development and infrastructural growth while also safeguarding their traditions, heritage and identity that forms an important part of the nation’s cultural diversity as well.</p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. There is a surge in demand by forest communities to not only access the resources of their habitat, but also to establish their ownership over forests. In this context analyse the issues with working of FRA 2006.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/forest-rights-act/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Strong nuclear diplomacy brings opportunities for India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nuclear-diplomacy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>credible minimum deterrence’</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Nuclear diplomacy and foreign policy</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="nuclear diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-627980" height="387" sizes="(max-width: 686px) 100vw, 686px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nuc.jpg 1920w" width="686"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The return of nuclear weapons on the global platform. After 1998, India premised its strategy on building ‘credible minimum deterrence’. The time has come to reflect on what is ‘credible’ and redefine what ‘minimum’ might be to strengthen nuclear diplomacy.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Definition of nuclear diplomacy</h4>
<ul>
<li>Nuclear diplomacy deals with prevention of nuclear war and peacetime proliferation. It also deals with the use of threat of nuclear warfare to achieve diplomatic goals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="nuclear diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-627983" height="370" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 656px) 100vw, 656px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/51236_nukeeeeee_1551964351734-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/51236_nukeeeeee_1551964351734-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/51236_nukeeeeee_1551964351734-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/51236_nukeeeeee_1551964351734.jpg 960w" width="656"/>Theme of article </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India, one of the world’s nuclear weapon powers, ought to be paying a lot more attention to the international nuclear discourse that is acquiring new dimensions and taking a fresh look at its own civilian and military nuclear programmes<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>Nuclear cooperation has brought a new dimension to India’s nuclear diplomacy in the 21<sup>st</sup> India’s status as a responsible nuclear power is predicated upon the civil relationships in the nuclear domain that it has established with major powers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-indias-doctrine-of-nuclear-no-first-use/"><strong>What is credible minimum deterrence?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Credible minimum deterrence is the principle on which India’s nuclear diplomacy is based. It underlines no first use (NFU) with an assured second strike capability and falls under minimal deterrence, as opposed to mutually assured destruction.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="nuclear diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-627981" height="592" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 592px) 100vw, 592px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-768x768.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-900x900.jpg 900w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview-1200x1200.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/India-Pakistan-Overview.jpg 1667w" width="592"/>Why do countries proliferate nuclear weapons?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Proliferation models centred on security concerns or dilemmas dominate nuclear literature.</li>
<li>Nuclear weapons provide an overwhelmingly destructive force that increases a state’s relative power in comparison to its neighbours.</li>
<li>It provides a powerful tool in an anarchic system where superpowers dominate other nation-states sovereignty.</li>
<li>Hence weaponizing helps establish a deterrence to prevent war.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why relook is needed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Possessing nuclear weapons can confer India increased leverage to conduct foreign policy in both regional and international contexts.</li>
<li>There are two ways in which the possession of nuclear weapons can affect a state’s conduct of foreign policy and diplomacy.</li>
<li>The first involves military and strategic signalling. This includes military-oriented functions of deterrence, coercion, and brinkmanship.</li>
<li>The second, deals with non-military affairs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It should be noted that India’s quest to be a “responsible nuclear state” has given it considerable diplomatic capital in the West.</li>
<li>It would be unfortunate for India to squander such gain owing to the lack of carefully considered foreign policy that leverages its nuclear status for its national interest.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s civil nuclear engagements with the global community have strengthened its position in the global civil nuclear order, there is a need for the country to push for greater engagements with more key suppliers and stakeholders to fulfill its military nuclear potential and assert its status as a responsible nuclear state.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. India has been a nuclear weapons state for 22 years. Has this affected India’s foreign policy in a direct manner? Express your views in context of the return of nuclear weapons on the global platform.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nuclear-diplomacy/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>