<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 22:12:59 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Vyommitra Humanoid to undergo pre-flight tests</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vyommitra-humanoid-pre-flight-tests/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Vyommitra, Gaganyaan Mission</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="vyommitra" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-645002" height="1333" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom.jpg 2000w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom-1980x1320.jpg 1980w" width="2000"/></strong></p>
<p>Vyommitra, the humanoid designed and developed by the ISRO to fly aboard unmanned test missions ahead of the Gaganyaan human space-flight mission, is undergoing pre-flight ground tests at the ISRO Inertial Systems Unit (IISU).</p>
<h4><strong>Vyommitra </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AI-based robotic system is developed at a robotics lab at the Vikram Sarabhai Space Centre (VSSC) at Thumba, Thiruvananthapuram.</li>
<li>Vyommitra will be used for an unmanned flight of ISRO’s GSLV III rocket in December 2020, which, along with a second unmanned flight in July 2021.</li>
<li>This will serve as the test of ISRO’s preparedness for its maiden manned space mission, Gaganyaan, being targeted for 2022 to mark 75 years of India’s independence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Functions of the humanoid</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Vyommitra, equipped with a head, two arms and a torso, is built to mimic crew activity inside the crew module of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gaganyaan-and-other-new-missions-in-2022/">Gaganyaan</a>.</li>
<li>Attaining launch and orbital postures, responding to the environment, generating warnings, replacing carbon dioxide canisters, and operating switches, monitoring of the crew module, receiving voice commands, and responding via speech (bilingual) are among the functions listed.</li>
<li>It will have a human-like face, with lips synchronized for movement to mimic speech.</li>
<li>Once it is fully developed, Vyommitra will be able to use the equipment on board the spacecraft’s crew module, like safety mechanisms and switches, as well as receive and act on commands sent from ground stations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the recent development?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The IISU has successfully integrated it with a computer “brain”, which enables it to “read” control panels aboard the unmanned test flights and communicate with the ISRO ground stations.</li>
<li>It has a certain level of intelligence.</li>
<li>It is intended to operate and read the display panels and communicate back to ground station using its own voice.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Gaganyaan Mission</h4>
<ul>
<li>Gaganyaan is crewed orbital spacecraft intended to be the formative spacecraft of the Indian Human Spaceflight Programme (IHSP).</li>
<li>The IHSP was initiated in 2007 by ISRO to develop the technology needed to launch crewed orbital spacecraft into low Earth orbit.</li>
<li>ISRO had been working on related technologies and it performed a <strong>Crew Module Atmospheric Re-entry Experiment</strong> and a <strong>Pad Abort Test</strong> for the mission.</li>
<li>If completed in meantime, India will become the fourth nation to conduct independent human spaceflight after Russia, US, and China.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vyommitra-humanoid-pre-flight-tests/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>NOPEC: the US bill to pressure the OPEC+ oil group</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nopec-us-bill-to-pressure-opec-plus/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NOPEC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Global oil prices manipulation by OPEC</p></div></div><p><img alt="nopec" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-645009" height="719" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nopec.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nopec.jpg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nopec-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nopec-1024x575.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nopec-768x431.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nopec-1200x674.jpg 1200w" width="1280"/></p>
<p>US legislation NOPEC which could open members of oil producing group <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-opec-3/">OPEC+</a> to antitrust lawsuits has emerged as a possible tool to tackle high fuel prices.</p>
<h4><strong>What is NOPEC?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>NOPEC stands for No Oil Producing and Exporting Cartels (NOPEC).</li>
<li>It is a bill to protect US consumers and businesses from engineered oil spikes.</li>
<li>But some analysts warn that implementing it could also have some dangerous unintended consequences.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why such a move by the US?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>OPEC+, which groups the Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) and allies including Russia, agreed to steep production cuts, curbing supply in an already tight market.</li>
<li>After the decision, the US decided to reduce the group’s control over energy prices.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Key feature of the NOPEC bill</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The bipartisan NOPEC bill would tweak US antitrust law to revoke the sovereign immunity that has protected OPEC+ members and their national oil companies from lawsuits.</li>
<li>If signed into law, the US attorney general would gain the option to sue the oil cartel or its members, such as Saudi Arabia, in federal court.</li>
<li>It is unclear exactly how a federal court could enforce judicial antitrust decisions against a foreign nation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Is such bill effective?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Previous versions of the NOPEC bill have failed amid resistance by oil industry groups, including the top US oil lobby groups.</li>
<li>Saudi Arabia has rebuffed repeated lobbying during visits by Biden officials not to cut production.</li>
<li>Instead, OPEC+ has agreed to cut output by the most since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Implications of NOPEC</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>NOPEC more or less is a knee-jerk reaction from the US against oil hegemony of the OPEC+.</li>
<li>If passed into law, it could lead to unintended blowback.</li>
<li>In 2019, for example, Saudi Arabia threatened to sell its oil in currencies other than the dollar if Washington passed a version of the NOPEC bill.</li>
<li>There is a possibility that other countries could take similar action on the US for withholding agricultural output to support domestic farming, for example.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nopec-us-bill-to-pressure-opec-plus/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Human Rights Council rejects debate on Xinjiang Abuses</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/xinjiang-china-abuses-unhrc-india-abstain/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Uighurs, Xinjiang</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>HR abuses in China</p></div></div><p><img alt="xinjiang" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-395897" height="374" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 456px) 100vw, 456px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/xing.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/xing.jpg 456w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/xing-300x246.jpg 300w" width="456"/></p>
<p>The UN Human Rights Council has voted against holding a debate on alleged abuses in China’s Xinjiang region after intense lobbying by Beijing, in a major setback for Western nations.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India and 10 other nations abstained.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who are the Uighurs?</strong></h4>
<p><strong><img alt="xinjiang" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-547953" height="400" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/uyghr.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/uyghr.jpg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/uyghr-300x200.jpg 300w" width="600"/></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There are about 12 million Uighurs, mostly Muslim, living in north-western China in the region of Xinjiang, officially known as the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region (XUAR).</li>
<li>The Uighurs speak their own language, similar to Turkish, and see themselves as culturally and ethnically close to Central Asian nations.</li>
<li>They make up less than half of the Xinjiang population.</li>
<li>In recent decades, there’s been a mass migration of Han Chinese (China’s ethnic majority) to Xinjiang, and the Uighurs feel their culture and livelihoods are under threat.</li>
<li>In the early 20th Century, the Uighurs briefly declared independence, but the region was brought under complete control of mainland China’s new Communist government in 1949.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Where is Xinjiang?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Xinjiang lies in the north-west of China and is the country’s biggest region.</li>
<li>Like Tibet, it is autonomous, meaning – in theory – it has some powers of self-governance. But in practice, both face major restrictions by the central government.</li>
<li>It is a mostly desert region, producing about a fifth of the world’s cotton.</li>
<li>It is also rich in oil and natural gas and because of its proximity to Central Asia and Europe is seen by Beijing as an important trade link.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the build-up to the Uighur crackdown?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Anti-Han and separatist sentiment rose in Xinjiang from the 1990s, flaring into violence on occasion.</li>
<li>In 2009 some 200 people died in clashes in Xinjiang, which the Chinese blamed on Uighurs who want their own state.</li>
<li>Xinjiang is now covered by a pervasive network of surveillance, including police, checkpoints, and cameras that scan everything from number plates to individual faces.</li>
<li>According to Human Rights Watch, police are also using a mobile app to monitor peoples’ behaviour, such as how much electricity they are using and how often they use their front door.</li>
<li>Since 2017 when President Xi Jinping issued an order saying all religions in China should be Chinese in orientation, there have been further crackdowns.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Chinese narrative</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>China says the crackdown is necessary to prevent terrorism and root out Islamist extremism and the camps are an effective tool for re-educating inmates in its fight against terrorism.</li>
<li>It insists that Uighur militants are waging a violent campaign for an independent state by plotting bombings, sabotage and civic unrest.</li>
<li>China has dismissed claims it is trying to reduce the Uighur population through mass sterilizations as “baseless”, and says allegations of forced labor are “completely fabricated”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why did India abstain from voting against China?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has traditionally voted against or abstained from such country-specific resolutions at the UNHRC.</li>
<li>It is understood that China’s presence within the UNHRC was a factor in the decision since any backing for the Xinjiang issue could have led to similar moves by China on other issues in India.</li>
<li>This is particularly in the context of the Kashmir issue.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this PYQ:</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Q.Very recently, in which of the following countries have lakhs of people either suffered from severe famine/acute malnutrition or died due to starvation caused by war/ethnic conflicts?</strong><br/>
(a) Angola and Zambia<br/>
(b) Morocco and Tunisia<br/>
(c) Venezuela and Colombia<br/>
(d) Yemen and South Sudan</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/xinjiang-china-abuses-unhrc-india-abstain/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India’s Rice Exports and food Insecurity</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/exports/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<h4><strong><img alt="Exports" class="alignnone wp-image-644956 size-full" height="720" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.04.10-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.04.10-1.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.04.10-1-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.04.10-1-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.04.10-1-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.04.10-1-1200x675.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>On August 8, India banned the exports of broken rice and imposed a 20 per cent duty on the exports of various grades of rice amid high cereal inflation and uncertainties with respect to domestic supply.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>This is surely not the first time an attempt is being made to ban wheat and rice exports.</li>
<li>It was also done in 2007-08, in the wake of the global financial crisis.</li>
<li>Perhaps government will also impose stocking limits on traders for a host of commodities, suspend<strong> </strong>futures trading in food items, and even conduct income tax raids on traders of food.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Exports" class="alignnone wp-image-644959 size-full" height="870" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1073px) 100vw, 1073px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.40.02-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.40.02-1.jpeg 1073w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.40.02-1-300x243.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.40.02-1-1024x830.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.40.02-1-768x623.jpeg 768w" width="1073"/>What is the current status of rice in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>World’s largest rice exporter:</strong> India has exported more than 20 MT of rice worth a record $9. 6 billion to more than 150 countries in 2021-22.It has been the world’s largest rice exporter of the grain in the last decade and has a share of around 44% global trade.</li>
<li><strong>Likely to fall in production:</strong> India’s rice production is likely to decline by 6 per cent t to 104.99 million tonnes in the kharif season due to a fall in paddy acreage amidst rainfall deficit in key producing states, including Jharkhand, Madhya Pradesh and West Bengal.</li>
<li><strong>Kharif season:</strong> Sowing in the kharif season begins with the onset of the southwest monsoon from June and harvesting from October onwards .About 85 per cent of India’s total production comes from this season.</li>
<li><strong>Deficient rainfall:</strong> West Bengal, the biggest rice producer amongst states, has received deficient rainfall in 15 of its 23 districts, raising the likelihood of crop loss. Uttar Pradesh, the second biggest producer of rice has received 42% less rainfall than benchmark. The rainfall deficiency in the other eastern states Bihar (-34%) and Jharkhand (-48%).</li>
<li><strong>Depleting stocks:</strong> There are concerns about rice stocks with the Food Corporation of India (FCI) depleting to a 10-year low level by April, 2023 year, if the free ration scheme is extended to the second half of the financial year. The government may have to impose some curbs on rice exports though minimum export price or an export tax if the scheme is extended.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why India’s rice export ban is cause for worry?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Thin world rice market and the impact on prices:</strong> Given that 90 per cent of production is consumed domestically, As a result, any small change in exports and imports has an enormous impact on prices, especially if it leads to panic buying of food grains by rich countries.</li>
<li><strong>Limited Import option:</strong> The stakes are higher as it is India’s largest agricultural crop. Unlike with wheat, the options for import in rice due to any production shortfall are limited, when India’s own share in the global trade of the cereal is more than 40%.</li>
<li><strong>Affect the credibility:</strong> The export uncertainties will affect the credibility of Indian exporters, create a disincentive for future exports, and will enable buyers to shift towards other major rice-exporting countries.</li>
<li><strong>Affect a section of farmers:</strong> Though Indian farmers in general lack market access, and hence do not take advantage of high market prices, the fall in prices may adversely affect a section of farmers who hope to get a better price for their produce through exports. The exporters who face the burden of the unfeasibility of exports may pass it on to farmers in the form of lower prices during procurement.</li>
<li><strong>Affect low-income and low middle-income Countries: </strong>India’s export restrictions will adversely affect several low-income and low-middle-income countries like Bangladesh, Senegal, Nepal and Benin, which are among the largest importers of Indian rice.</li>
<li><strong>Domestic prices and to safeguard food security</strong>: Frequent changes in export policies undoubtedly have long-term ramifications on domestic prices</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Exports" class="alignnone wp-image-644962 size-large" height="499" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.39.58-1024x499.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.39.58-1024x499.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.39.58-300x146.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.39.58-768x374.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.39.58.jpeg 1200w" width="1024"/>What are the Issues in India’s rice <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/can-agri-exports-be-made-more-sustainable/">export strategy?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Highest ever volume:</strong> India exported the highest-ever volume of 21 million metric tonnes (MMT) of rice in 2021-22 (FY22) in a global market of about 51.3 MMT, which amounts to about 41 per cent of global exports.</li>
<li><strong>Reduced price:</strong> Such large volumes of rice exports brought down global prices of rice by about 23 per cent in March (YoY), when all other cereal prices, be it wheat or maize, were going up substantially in global markets. In fact, in FY22, the unit value of exports of common rice was just $354/tonne, which was lower than the minimum support price (MSP) of rice.</li>
<li><strong>Below MSP buying or leakage from PMGKAY:</strong> This meant that rice exporters were either buying rice (paddy) from farmers and millersat below the MSP or that quite a substantial part of rice was given free under the PM Garib Kalyan Ann Yojana (PMGKAY) was being siphoned away for exports at prices below MSP.</li>
<li><strong>Artificial competitive advantage:</strong> Free electricity for irrigation in several states, most notably Punjab, and highly subsidised fertilisers, especially urea, create an artificial competitive advantage for Indian rice in global markets.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Problems with India’s rice cultivation</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lower yield:</strong> India’s rice yield is lower than the world average. However, India’s yield is better than Thailand and Pakistan but worse than Vietnam, China and the US.</li>
<li><strong>Higher cost of cultivation and price support</strong>: The cost of cultivation in India is also increasing, and hence there will be a need for a higher MSP to make production remunerative. This will exacerbate the pressure to re-think its price-support-backed food security mechanism.</li>
<li><strong>Water-intensive nature</strong>: India’s rice production likely to fall amidst the shortfall of rainfall in major rice producing states and increasing salinity of soil because of over usage of water. The water-intensive nature of rice cultivation, along with frequent export restrictions will adversely affect the long-run sustainability of rice production. In India, around 49 per cent of rice cultivation depends on groundwater which is depleting rapidly.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Exports" class="alignnone wp-image-644964 size-full" height="1280" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 755px) 100vw, 755px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-1.jpeg 755w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-1-177x300.jpeg 177w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-1-604x1024.jpeg 604w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-1-531x900.jpeg 531w" width="755"/>What is the link between Rice cultivation and ground water depletion?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Ground water depletion</strong>: In India, around 49 per cent of rice cultivation depends on groundwater which is depleting rapidly.</li>
<li><strong>Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) data</strong>: As per the latest data available from the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), agricultural water withdrawal as a percentage of total available renewable water resources has increased from 26.7 per cent in 1993 to 36 per cent in 2022.</li>
<li><strong>Virtual water trade (VWT):</strong> Rice exports are leading to an indirect export of water to other countries a phenomenon known as virtual water trade (VWT). The relative per capita water availability in India is lower than a majority of its major importing countries. The other major exporters of rice, such as Thailand and Vietnam, also have better per capita water availability in comparison to India.</li>
<li><strong>Renewable water resources: </strong>Out of 133 countries in which India has positive net rice exports, only 39 countries have relatively lower per capita renewable water resources. Out of these 39 countries, 12 countries are high-income countries with the ability to buy food at a higher price.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Depletion of groundwater resources and rising cost of cultivation may threaten rice production in the future. Adequate water saving measures in the form of widespread adoption of water saving practices like System of Rice Intensification (SRI) need to be taken to keep input requirements, costs and production sustainable.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>As many developing countries depend on Indian rice, rice export restrictions have raised food security concerns in the global market. </strong><strong>In this context discuss the causes and effects of India’s restrictions on rice export.</strong></p></blockquote>
<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/exports/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Corporate Social Responsibility(CSR) &amp; Social Justice</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/social/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CSR</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>corporate governance</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Social" class="alignnone wp-image-644974 size-full" height="853" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.30.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.30.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.30-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.30-1024x682.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.30-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.30-1200x800.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Since the establishment of the Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) regime in India under Section 135 of the Companies Act 2013, CSR spending in India has risen from RS.10,065 crore in 2014-15to Rs.24,865crore in 2020-21.But there is no data to verify whether this increase is commensurate with the increase in profits of Indian and foreign (having a registered arm in India) companies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Voluntary spending</strong>: Corporate social responsibility (CSR) is a form of international private business self-regulation which aims to contribute to societal goals of a philanthropic, activist, or charitable nature by engaging in or supporting volunteering or ethically oriented practices.</li>
<li><strong>Ministry Corporate Affairs: </strong>The National Corporate Social Responsibility Data Portal is an initiative by Ministry of Corporate Affairs, Government of India to establish a platform to disseminate Corporate Social Responsibility related data and information filed by the companies registered with it<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Companies Act, 2013</strong>: The Corporate Social Responsibility concept in India is governed by Section 135 of the Companies Act, 2013 (‘Act’), Schedule VII of the Act and Companies (CSR Policy) Rules, 2014 wherein the criteria has been provided for assessing the CSR eligibility of a company, Implementation and Reporting of their CSR Policies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/csr/"><img alt="Social" class="alignnone wp-image-644977 size-large" height="683" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.27-1024x683.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.27-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.27-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.27-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.27.jpeg 1200w" width="1024"/></a></strong></h4>
<h4><strong>How <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/csr/">CSR helps in achieving social justice</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li style="text-align: left;"><strong>Sustainable Goals: </strong>India having the most elaborated CSR mechanism and implementation strategy has started its journey to set a benchmark in attaining sustainability goals and stakeholder activism in nation building.</li>
<li><strong>Corporate philanthropy</strong>: company donations to charity, including cash, goods, and services, sometimes via a corporate foundation.</li>
<li><strong>Community volunteering</strong>: company-organized volunteer activities, sometimes while an employee receives pay for pro-bono work on behalf of a non-profit organization</li>
<li><strong>Socially-responsible business practices</strong>: ethically produced products that appeal to a customer segment.</li>
<li><strong>Corporate social marketing</strong>: Company-funded behaviour-change campaigns, Company-funded advocacy campaigns, donations to charity based on product sales.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why there is need to review the CSR?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Declining number: </strong>There was also a decline in the number of companies participating in CSR 25,103 in FY2019 to 17,007 in FY2021.</li>
<li><strong>Flaw in the law</strong>: If a company spends an amount in excess of the minimum 2%, as stipulated, the excess amount is liable to be set off against spending in the succeeding three financial years. Ideally, companies should have been shown courage to spend more than this.</li>
<li><strong>Own trusts: </strong>many private companies have registered their own foundations/trusts to which they transfer the statutory CSR budgets for utilisation. It is unclear if this is allowed under the Companies Act/CSR rules.</li>
<li><strong>Geographical bias: </strong>The first proviso to Section 135(5) of the Act is that the company should give preference to local areas/areas around it where it operates. This is logical. However, a report by Ashoka University’s Centre for Social Impact and Philanthropy says that 54% of CSR companies are concentrated in Maharashtra, Tamil Nadu, Karnataka, and Gujarat(receiving the largest CSR spends) while populous Uttar Pradesh and Madhya Pradesh receive little.</li>
<li><strong>Spending on environment: </strong>Item (iv) of Schedule VII of the Act deals with broader environmental issues to create a countervailing effect. However, an analysis of CSR spending (2014-18)reveals that while most CSR spending is in education (37%) and health and sanitation (29%), only 9% was spent on the environment even as extractive industries such as mining function in an environmentally detrimental manner in several States</li>
<li><strong>Incomplete information: </strong>The Standing Committee on Finance had observed that the information regarding CSR spending by companies is insufficient and difficult to access. As per the ‘Technical Guide on Accounting’ issued by the Institute of Chartered Accountants of India, a company is only required to mention its CSR spends, non-spend, under-spend, and overspend in the ‘Notes to Accounts’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Social" class="alignnone wp-image-644979 size-full" height="441" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 770px) 100vw, 770px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.28.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.28.jpeg 770w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.28-300x172.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.28-768x440.jpeg 768w" width="770"/>What are the suggestions to improve the mechanism of CSR?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Centralized platform: </strong>There is a need to curate a national level platform centralised by the MCA where all States could list their potential CSR admissible projects so that companies can assess where their CSR funds would be most impactful across India with, of course, preferential treatment to areas where they operate.</li>
<li><strong>India Investment Grid: </strong>Invest India’s ‘Corporate Social Responsibility Projects Repository’ on the India Investment Grid (IIG) can serve as a guide for such efforts. This model would be very useful for supporting deserving projects in the 112aspirational districts and projects identified by MPs under the Government’s Sansad AdarshGram Yojana.</li>
<li><strong>Increase environment spending: </strong>Companies need to prioritise environment restoration in the area where they operate, earmarking at least 25% for environment regeneration.</li>
<li><strong>Public participation: </strong>All CSR projects should be selected and implemented with the active involvement of communities, district administration and public representatives.</li>
<li><strong>Transparency: </strong>Recommendations by the high-level committee in 2018 should be incorporated in the current CSR framework to improve the existing monitoring and evaluation regime. These include strengthening the reporting mechanisms with enhanced disclosures concerning selection of projects, locations, implementing agencies, etc.; bringing CSR within the purview of statutory financial audit with details of CSR expenditure included in the financial statement of a company, and mandatory independent third party impact assessment audits.</li>
<li><strong>Monitoring by government: </strong>The MCA and the line departments need to exercise greater direct monitoring and supervision over CSR spend by companies through the line ministries (for public sector undertakings) and other industry associations(for non-public units) instead of merely hosting all information on the Ministry’s website.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Social" class="alignnone wp-image-644981 size-full" height="1000" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.33.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.33.jpeg 1000w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.33-300x300.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.33-150x150.jpeg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.33-768x768.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.33-900x900.jpeg 900w" width="1000"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Corporate social responsibility is an effective tool to address the social and income inequality. Present legal arrangements are toothless and based on voluntary actions. For an effective change CSR spending should be made more transparent and accountable.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question. </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Present arrangement of CSR is not yielding the desired result. Enlist the current weakness in CSR spending Suggest the changes needed for efficient implantation of CSR.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/social/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Moonlighting: Overemployment or Underpayment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/moonlighting/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>what is moonlighting.</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Impact of moonlighting on comapnies and employment.</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Moonlighting" class="alignnone wp-image-645000 size-full" height="337" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.03.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.03.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.03-300x79.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.03-1024x270.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.03-768x202.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.03-1200x316.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In July, Kotak Securities said in a study that at least 60% of 400 employees surveyed said they themselves had, or knew someone who had engaged in moonlighting.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is mean by moonlighting?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Moonlighting is a state where employees work for remuneration with entities other than their employers. It is not defined in any of the statutes in India. However, there are enactments that deal with double employment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Moonlighting" class="alignnone wp-image-644992 size-large" height="879" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.55-1-1024x879.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.55-1-1024x879.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.55-1-300x258.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.55-1-768x659.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.55-1-1049x900.jpeg 1049w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.55-1.jpeg 1080w" width="1024"/>How does it affect companies and what are latest examples?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Wipro</strong>: According to Wipro CEO, there is a lot of chatter about people moonlighting in the tech industry. This is cheating plain and simple. The company sacked 300 employees following the discovery that they were working for rival firms on the side, leading to conflict of interest.</li>
<li><strong>Infosys: </strong>Infosys has warned staff against moonlighting, saying it could lead to termination.</li>
<li><strong>Effect of WFH</strong>: Another software firm DXC Technologies said that moonlighting by employees was a challenge for employers but that wouldn’t affect its WFH (work from home) policy that has worked well for both the firm and its staff.</li>
<li><strong>Moonlighting policy: </strong>Swiggy announced a moonlighting policy’ that allows employees to pursue their passion for economic interests alongside their fulltime employment.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Moonlighting" class="alignnone wp-image-644995 size-full" height="416" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-1.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-1-300x98.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-1-1024x333.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-1-768x250.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-1-1200x390.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>What is the<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/back-in-news-gig-workers-rights/"> Legal status of moonlighting</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Factory act: </strong>Section 60 of the Factories Act deals with restriction on double employment stating that “No adult worker shall be required or allowed to work in any factory on any day on which he has already been working in any other factory, save in such circumstances as may be prescribed. However, this enactment is applicable only to employees working in factories.</li>
<li><strong>The Tamil Nadu Shops &amp; Establishments Act, 1947</strong>: There are State enactments which deal with employment of persons working in offices, banks, shops, etc. In Tamil Nadu, it is termed as The Tamil Nadu Shops &amp; Establishments Act, 1947. However, there is no provision wherein dealing with dual employment.</li>
<li><strong>Glaxo Laboratories (I) Limited vs Labour Court, Meerut and others</strong>: The apex court held that “The employer has hardly any extra territorial jurisdiction. He is not the custodian of general law and order situation or the Guru or mentor of his workmen for their well-regulated cultural advancement. If the power to regulate the behaviour of the workmen outside the duty hours and at any place wherever they may be was conferred upon the employer, contract of service may be reduced to contract of slavery.” This case was not specifically about moonlighting but the court’s observation gives us an idea as to how the law may view such cases.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Moonlighting" class="alignnone wp-image-645001 size-full" height="480" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59.jpeg 640w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-300x225.jpeg 300w" width="640"/>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>More earning</strong>: The Minister of State for Skill Development and Entrepreneurship, and Electronics and IT, said that employers should not to suppress employees who want to monetise, develop and demonstrate but also urged employees not to violate their agreements with employers.</li>
<li><strong>Working hours</strong>: Moonlighting is subject to law of the land. The sphere of employment cannot be extended by the employer beyond working hours and outside his place of employment.</li>
<li><strong>Socialistic view: </strong>The Courts of law in India dealing with employment are Writ Courts and Labour Courts, which exercise jurisdiction based on equity or fairness. Therefore, the Courts may lean in favour of the employee unless the contravention of the employee has led to serious prejudice and loss to the employer</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Employees are not the slaves of employers. What they do beyond the working hours is none of the business of employer unless it affects company financially or causes substantial damage to business. Government should bring the legal statute to regulate moonlighting and prevent the unjustified punishment of employees.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What is moonlighting? Why employees do moonlighting? Discuss the legal framework about moonlighting in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/moonlighting/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Amendments to Bharat Series Rules</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bharat-series-rules/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>BH Series</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="bharat" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-455446" height="565" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1204px) 100vw, 1204px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/bhs.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/bhs.jpg 1204w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/bhs-300x141.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/bhs-1024x481.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/bhs-768x360.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/bhs-1200x563.jpg 1200w" width="1204"/></p>
<p>The Ministry of Road Transport and Highway has issued a draft notification proposing new rules to further increase the scope of implementation of the BH series vehicle registrations.</p>
<h4><strong>Bharat series (BH-series)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There was a procedure of re-registration of a vehicle while moving to another state.</li>
<li>A vehicle bearing BH registration mark shall not require assignment of a new registration mark when the owner of the vehicle shifts from one State to another.</li>
<li>Format of Bharat series (BH-series) Registration Mark –</li>
</ul>
<p>Registration Mark Format:</p>
<ol>
<li>YY BH #### XX</li>
<li>YY – Year of first registration</li>
<li>BH- Code for Bharat Series</li>
<li>####- 0000 to 9999 (randomized)</li>
<li>XX- Alphabets (AA to ZZ)</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Why such move?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Station relocation occurs with both Government and private sector employees.</li>
<li>Such movements create a sense of unease in the minds of such employees with regard to transfer of registration from the parent state to another state.</li>
<li>Under section 47 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988, a person is allowed to keep the vehicle for not more than 12 months in any state other than the state where the vehicle is registered.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who can get this BH series?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>BH-series will be available on voluntary basis to Defense personnel, employees of Central Government/ State Government/ Central/ State PSUs and private sector companies/organizations.</li>
<li>The motor vehicle tax will be levied for two years or in multiple of two.</li>
<li>This scheme will facilitate free movement of personal vehicles across States/UTs of India upon relocation to a new State/UT.</li>
<li>After the completion of the fourteenth year, the motor vehicle tax shall be levied annually which shall be half of the amount which was charged earlier for that vehicle.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bharat-series-rules/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Places in news: Solomon Islands</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/solomon-islands-china/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Solomon Islands</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Chinese expansion in Pacific</p></div></div><p><img alt="solomon" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-494199" height="1532" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1600px) 100vw, 1600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon.jpg 1600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-300x287.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-1024x980.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-768x735.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-1536x1471.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-1200x1149.jpg 1200w" width="1600"/></p>
<p>Solomon Islands PM has assured Australia that his nation will not allow a Chinese military presence in its territory.</p>
<h4>Where is the Solomon Islands located?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Solomon Islands is a sovereign country consisting of six major islands and over 900 smaller islands in Oceania, to the east of Papua New Guinea and northwest of Vanuatu.</li>
<li>Its capital, Honiara, is located on the largest island, Guadalcanal.</li>
<li>It is part of the ethnically Melanesian group of islands in the Pacific and lies between Papua New Guinea and Vanuatu.</li>
<li>The country takes its name from the Solomon Islands archipelago, which is a collection of Melanesian islands that also includes the North Solomon Islands (a part of Papua New Guinea).</li>
<li>It excludes outlying islands, such as the Santa Cruz Islands and Rennell and Bellona.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Quick recap of its past</h4>
<ul>
<li>The islands, which were initially controlled by the British Empire during the colonial era, went through the hands of Germany and Japan.</li>
<li>It then went back to the UK after the Americans took over the islands from the Japanese during World War II.</li>
<li>The islands became independent in 1978 to become a constitutional monarchy under the British Crown, with a parliamentary system of government.</li>
<li>Nevertheless, its inability to manage domestic ethnic conflicts led to close security relations with Australia, which is the traditional first responder to any crisis in the South Pacific.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did China enter the picture?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Earlier this year, the Solomon Islands established a <strong>security agreement with China</strong>, saying it needed Beijing’s assistance with its domestic security situation.</li>
<li>But the <strong>announcement had rattled the west</strong>, esp. the US, Australia and others in the Indo-Pacific region.</li>
<li>The concerns were that the agreement could potentially lead to a <strong>Chinese military base on the island nation</strong> and a gain in power-projection capabilities.</li>
<li>At that time, following intense scrutiny, the Solomon Islands had <strong>denied</strong> that the agreement would allow China to establish a naval base.</li>
<li>The Island insisted that the agreement was only to <strong>assist the Solomon Islands with what he called “hard internal threats”.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the Solomon Islands’ stance?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The government has asked all partner countries with plans to conduct naval visits or patrols to put them on hold until a <strong>revised national mechanism</strong> is in place.</li>
<li>The revised national mechanism <strong>applied to all foreign vessels seeking access to the country’s ports</strong>.</li>
<li>The nation wanted to <strong>build up its</strong> <strong>own naval capacity</strong>.</li>
<li>It has some <strong>unfortunate experiences of foreign naval vessels entering its waters</strong> without any diplomatic clearance.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is behind China’s growing influence in the region?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There is no dispute that China has been rapidly increasing its presence and influence in the region for over three decades, particularly in the South Pacific.</li>
<li>Certainly Beijing views the Pacific Island region as an <strong>important component of its Belt and Road Initiative (BRI). </strong></li>
<li>Specifically, it sees the region as a critical air freight hub in its so-called <strong>Air Silk Road</strong>, which connects Asia with Central and South America.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Concerns of the West</h4>
<ul>
<li>The United States and its regional allies, such as Australia and New Zealand, are concerned that the China-Solomon Islands security pact allows Chinese naval vessels to replenish there.</li>
<li>That could open the <strong>door to a Chinese naval base</strong>, which would significantly extend China’s military reach in the South Pacific.”</li>
<li>It is likely that this security agreement between China and the Solomon Islands has been driven by, what the CFR calls, Beijing’s “<strong>sense of vulnerability</strong>” in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the rationale for the Solomon Islands’ increasing proximity to China?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Solomon Islands had cultivated strong ties with Taiwan, which ended with the emergence of the current government in Honiara.</li>
<li>In 2019, the regime change switched Taiwan for China.</li>
<li>This was supposedly after Beijing offered half a billion US dollars in financial aid, roughly five times what Taiwan spent on the islands in the past two decades.</li>
<li>It has been alleged by the pro-Taiwan Opposition that the incumbent government has been bribed by China.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is China interested in the Solomon Islands?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Isolating Taiwan:</strong> The Solomon Islands was one among the six Pacific island states which had official bilateral relations with Taiwan.</li>
<li><strong>Supporter in UN:</strong> The small Pacific island states act as potential vote banks for mobilising support for the great powers in international fora like the United Nations.</li>
<li><strong>Larger EEZ:</strong> These states have disproportionately large maritime Exclusive Economic Zones when compared to their small sizes.</li>
<li><strong>Natural resources:</strong> Solomon Islands, in particular, have significant reserves of timber and mineral resources, along with fisheries.</li>
<li><strong>Countering US:</strong> But more importantly, they are strategically located for China to insert itself between America’s military bases in the Pacific islands and Australia.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What does this mean for the established geopolitical configuration in the region?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Diminishing western influence:</strong> The Pacific islands, in the post-World War II scenario, were exclusively under the spheres of influence of the Western powers, in particular, the US, UK, France and Australia and New Zealand.</li>
<li><strong>Inserting into western hegemony:</strong> All of them have territorial possessions in the region, with the three nuclear powers among them having used the region as a nuclear weapons testing ground.</li>
<li><strong>Shifting of dependencies:</strong> The smaller island nations of the region are heavily dependent on them, especially Australia as it is a resident power.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/solomon-islands-china/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Aatmanirbhar in defence production: Where does India stand?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/atmanirbhar-in-defence-production/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Boosting indigenous defence production</p></div></div><p>India ranks fourth among 12 Indo-Pacific nations in self-reliant arms production capabilities, according to a study released this month by the Stockholm International Peace Research Institute (SIPRI).</p>
<h4><strong>Study on Defence production </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>China tops the list, Japan is second, South Korea is in third place, and Pakistan is at number 8.</li>
<li>The study, which measures self-reliance until 2020, is based on three indicators of self-reliance in each country:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong><u>Arms procurement</u></strong> — imports, licensed and domestic production as a proportion of the government’s total procurement of major conventional arms;</li>
<li><strong><u>Arms industry</u></strong> — the study presents the five largest arms companies in each country, where data are available, ranked by sales of arms and military services in 2020 to both domestic and export customers;</li>
<li><strong><u>Uncrewed maritime vehicles, the sea equivalent of drones</u></strong> — covering both uncrewed surface vehicles (USVs) and uncrewed underwater vehicles (UUVs), meant to provide a qualitative understanding of how countries are engaging domestic research institutes and firms to produce such cutting edge systems.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>How has China progressed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>China was the world’s fifth largest arms importer in 2016-20.</li>
<li>Its self-reliance policies, and its high economic growth in that period meant that the Chinese arms industry now increasingly fulfils the requirements of the People’s Liberation Army (PLA).</li>
<li>Its high volume of imports in absolute terms accounts for only 8 per cent of total procurement for the period, the lowest share for any of the 12 governments studied in this report.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is India still lagging behind?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India is ranked as the second-largest importer of arms for its armed forces in 2016-20.</li>
<li>India is highly dependent on imports of complete foreign major arms, including many produced under licence or as components for its domestic production.</li>
<li>Of India’s total volume of procurement in 2016–20, 84 per cent was of foreign origin.</li>
<li>Domestic arms companies provide only 16 per cent of its total procurement.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Steps taken by the Centre to boost defence production</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Licensing relaxation:</strong> Measures announced to boost exports since 2014 include simplified defence industrial licensing, relaxation of export controls and grant of no-objection certificates.</li>
<li><strong>Lines of Credit:</strong> Specific incentives were introduced under the foreign trade policy and the Ministry of External Affairs has facilitated Lines of Credit for countries to import defence product.</li>
<li><strong>Policy boost:</strong> The Defence Ministry has also issued a draft Defence Production &amp; Export Promotion Policy 2020.</li>
<li><strong>Budgetary allocation:</strong> In addition, a percentage of the capital outlay of the defence budget has been reserved for procurement from domestic industry.</li>
<li><strong>Defence Industrial Corridors:</strong> The government has also announced 2 dedicated Corridors in the States of TN and UP to act as clusters of defence manufacturing that leverage existing infrastructure, and human capital.</li>
<li><strong>Long-term vision:</strong> The vision of the government is to achieve a turnover of $25 bn including export of $5 bn in Aerospace and Defence goods and services by 2025.</li>
<li><strong>Push for self-reliance:</strong> The govt has identified the Defence and Aerospace sector as a focus area for the ‘Aatmanirbhar Bharat’ or Self-Reliant India initiative.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues retarding defence indigenization</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Excess reliance on Public Sector:</strong> India has four companies (Indian ordnance factories, Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL), Bharat Electronics Limited (BEL) and Bharat Dynamics Limited (BDL)) among the top 100 biggest arms producers of the world.</li>
<li><strong>Policy delays:</strong> In the past few years, the government has approved over 200 defence acquisition worth Rs 4 trillion, but most are still in relatively early stages of processing.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of Critical Technologies:</strong> Poor design capability in critical technologies, inadequate investment in R&amp;D and the inability to manufacture major subsystems and components hamper the indigenous manufacturing.</li>
<li><strong>Long gestation:</strong> The creation of a manufacturing base is capital and technology-intensive and has a long gestation period. By that time newer technologies make products outdated.</li>
<li><strong>‘Unease’ in doing business:</strong> An issue related to stringent labour laws, compliance burden and lack of skills, affects the development of indigenous manufacturing in defence.</li>
<li><strong>Multiple jurisdictions:</strong> Overlapping jurisdiction of the Ministry of Defence and Ministry of Industrial Promotion impair India’s capability of defence manufacturing.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of quality:</strong> The higher indigenization in few cases is largely attributed to the low-end technology.</li>
<li><strong>FDI Policy:</strong> The earlier FDI limit of 49% was not enough to enthuse global manufacturing houses to set up bases in India.</li>
<li><strong>R&amp;D Lacunae:</strong> A lip service to technology funding by making token allocations is an adequate commentary on our lack of seriousness in the area of Research and Development.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of skills:</strong> There is a lack of engineering and research capability in our institutions. It again leads us back to the need for a stronger industry-academia interface.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reducing import dependence:</strong> India was the world’s second-largest arms importer from 2014-18, ceding the long-held tag as the largest importer to Saudi Arabia, says 2019 SIPRI report.</li>
<li><strong>Security Imperative:</strong> Indigenization in defence is critical to national security also. It keeps intact the technological expertise and encourages spin-off technologies and innovation that often stem from it.</li>
<li><strong>Economic boost:</strong> <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indigenisation-in-defence-technologies-manufacturing-will-ensure-indias-strategic-autonomy/">Indigenization in defence</a> can help create a large industry which also includes small manufacturers.</li>
<li><strong>Employment generation:</strong> Defence manufacturing will lead to the generation of satellite industries that in turn will pave the way for a generation of employment opportunities.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/atmanirbhar-in-defence-production/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Stubble burning in Punjab at 3-year low</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/stubble-burning-in-punjab-at-3-year-low/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>GHGs relased by Stubble Burning</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Stubble Burning</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="stubble" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-645413" height="628" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/stubble.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/stubble.jpg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/stubble-300x147.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/stubble-1024x502.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/stubble-768x377.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/stubble-1200x589.jpg 1200w" width="1280"/></strong></p>
<p>Though early days, the number of crop fires reported out of Punjab are at a three-year low, suggest data from the Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) that tracks such fires via satellite.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Stubble Burning?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Stubble (parali) burning is a method of removing paddy crop residues from the field to sow wheat from the last week of September to November.</li>
<li>It is usually required in areas that use the combined harvesting method which leaves crop residue behind.</li>
<li>This practice mostly carried out in Punjab, Haryana and UP contributes solely to the grave winter pollution in the national capital.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Emissions from stubble burning</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The process of burning farm residue is one of the major causes of air pollution in parts of north India, deteriorating the air quality.</li>
<li>Stubble burning is a significant source of carbon dioxide (CO2), volatile organic compounds (VOCs), nitrogen oxides (NOx) and hydrocarbons (HC).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Despite emissions, why do farmers burn stubble?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Crop residue burning is practised by the farmers to <strong><u>prepare the land for the next cultivation</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The major reason behind the stubble burning is the <strong><u>short time available</u></strong> between rice harvesting and sowing of wheat as delay in sowing wheat affects the wheat crop.</li>
<li>Between the harvesting of the paddy crop and the sowing of the next crop, there is only a <strong><u>two to three weeks’ time window</u></strong> is left.</li>
<li>Even though farmers are aware that the burning of straw is harmful to health, they <strong><u>do not have alternatives</u></strong> for utilizing them effectively.</li>
<li>The farmers are ill-equipped to deal with waste because they <strong><u>cannot afford the new technology</u></strong> that is available to handle the waste material.</li>
<li>Therefore, stubble burning is <strong><u>considered one of the cheapest methods</u></strong> to clean the field after the harvesting season.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Impact of stubble burning</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Air Pollution:</strong> Stubble burning emits toxic pollutants in the atmosphere containing harmful gases like Carbon Monoxide (CO), methane (CH4), carcinogenic polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, volatile organic compounds (VOC). These pollutants disperse in the surroundings and eventually affect air quality and people’s health by forming a thick blanket of smog. Along with vehicular emissions, it affects the Air Quality Index (AQI) in the national capital and NCR.</li>
<li><strong>Soil degradation:</strong> Soil becomes less fertile and its nutrients are destroyed when the husk is burned on the ground. Organic content of soil is completely destroyed. Stubble burning generates heat that penetrates into the soil, causing an increase in erosion, loss of useful microbes and moisture.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Alternative solutions </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Power generation:</strong> The available paddy straw can be effectively used for power generation, which will go a long way towards overcoming the problem of disposal of crop residues and power deficit in the region.</li>
<li><strong>In-situ decomposition:</strong> Suitable machinery for collection, chopping and in situ incorporation of straw is required. We can use <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pusa-bio-decomposer/">Pusa Biodecomposer,</a> Biomethanation etc.</li>
<li><strong>Organic manuring:</strong> Convert the removed residues into enriched organic manure through composting.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Unless financial assistance is to be provided by the Centre for boosting farm mechanization, it is difficult to completely stop stubble burning.</li>
<li>States need to make alternative arrangements for the consumption of paddy straw into the soil as per the directions of the NGT.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/stubble-burning-in-punjab-at-3-year-low/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Classifying Merit and Non merit Freebies</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/freebie/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- Freebies issue</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Freebie" class="alignnone wp-image-645400 size-full" height="1025" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.30.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.30.jpeg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.30-300x285.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.30-1024x972.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.30-768x729.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.30-948x900.jpeg 948w" width="1080"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The debate that began with an RBI 2022 report on state finances followed by Prime Minister Narendra Modi’s comment on revdi culture aka freebies, has garnered substantial attention so much so that the Supreme Court is hearing on this issue. Freebies have now assumed more importance than ever.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are freebies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Freebies could be defined as non-merit subsidies. The term Freebies is not new; rather it is a prevalent culture in Indian politics (in the name of socialism).</li>
<li>The political parties are always trying to outdo each other in luring the Indian voters with freebies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Subsidies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Subsidies are money transfers (implicit or explicit) by the government in an attempt to drive prices artificially below market prices.</li>
<li>As a National Institute of Public Finance and Policy (NIPFP) study by Sudipto Mundle and Satadru Sirkar puts it, budget subsidies, in particular, are defined as the unrecovered cost of economic and social services.</li>
<li>However, all subsidies cannot be easily classified into merit or non-merit.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Freebie" class="alignnone wp-image-645402 size-full" height="881" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.43-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.43-1.jpeg 660w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.43-1-225x300.jpeg 225w" width="660"/>What are the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/making-sense-of-the-freebies-issue/">objectives behind providing freebies?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Welfare state</strong>: It could be said that providing freebies empowers the state to, first, deliver welfare as a welfare state should, by providing subsidised merit goods like health and education;</li>
<li><strong>Combating poverty</strong>: To help households combat poverty (especially in economically stressed times characterised by fewer job opportunities, lower incomes, high inflation, etc.) by providing subsidised public goods like food, electricity, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Populist spending</strong>: To appeal to the electorate through outright populist spending.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Question of classification between a merit and a non-merit freebies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Blur Boundary:</strong> The boundaries between the aforementioned objectives begin to blur when it comes to classifying one form of freebie as a merit or a non-merit subsidy.</li>
<li><strong>Few examples</strong>: Are corporate tax cuts non-merit subsidies or a measure to boost investment? 2. Is making bus rides free for women in the national capital a non-merit subsidy or a way to boost women’s mobility and labour-force participation? 3. Are free laptops to students in Tamil Nadu not a way to bridge the digital divide in education?</li>
<li><strong>Varying definition: </strong>The existing arguments develop an understanding that freebies cannot be defined in a finite context, and that the definition varies across space and economic conditions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Freebie" class="alignnone wp-image-645408 size-full" height="600" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.39.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.39.jpeg 800w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.39-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.39-768x576.jpeg 768w" width="800"/>How freebies impact revenue of the state?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Adverse impact on revenues:</strong> Regardless of which one gets classified as good or bad, freebies are simply expenditures or foregone revenues. Any freebie-induced debt burden could have an adverse effect on the state finances if, one, it hasn’t been properly accounted for through transparent budgeting procedures (including off-budget borrowings in debt calculations)</li>
<li><strong>Increase in Fiscal deficit:</strong> Either way, they lead to an increase in fiscal deficit whose financing could necessitate taking on debt. It threatens fiscal sustainability, i e, it limits the state’s ability to service its debt-related commitments without making an unrealistic fiscal adjustment<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Lack of data leading to leakages: </strong>The targeting of beneficiaries to ease the burden on the exchequer is one way to check these expenditures but lack of data has forced a situation wherein leakages and duplication of beneficiaries is commonplace.</li>
<li><strong>Jeopardises long-term growth and development: </strong>In the absence of adequate avenues of revenue mobilisation, any fiscal adjustment achieved by contracting critical expenditures on the social sector and capital formation further jeopardises long-term growth and development. The emanating risk of fiscal sustainability means a “revdi” today would take a toll on tomorrow’s generation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What could be the solution?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Setting up an independent fiscal council: </strong>Setting up an independent fiscal council that has been recommended by the FRBM Review Committee (2017), and recently constituted Finance Commissions too, including the 15th Finance Commission.</li>
<li><strong>Providing information and advisory:</strong> FRBM report says, the council will serve both an ex-ante role providing independent forecasts on key macro variables like real and nominal GDP growth, tax buoyancy, commodity prices as well as an ex-post monitoring role, and also serve as the institution to advise on triggering the escape clause and also specify a path of return.</li>
<li><strong>Monitoring finance: </strong>Such a council should work for the union as well as the states. Monitoring of finances and fiscal rules could also help ensure that states comply with a medium-term fiscal policy framework, which has been long argued for by economists.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Freebie" class="alignnone wp-image-645409 size-full" height="488" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.40.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.40.jpeg 608w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.40-300x241.jpeg 300w" width="608"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Freebies cannot be defined easily, and constitutionally, any state government should be empowered to spend the way it wants, provided the fiscal policy is sustainable. The message from the freebies debate is to make informed economic decisions whilst attending to key development objectives.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>There is nothing wrong in having social security programme that aims to lift the poor get out of poverty and empower the vulnerable sections of the society. In this context, where do you see the goal of sustainable economic development? Comment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/freebie/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India’s Dark Sky Reserve</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dark-sky-reserve/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Dark Sky Reserve</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Science tourism</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Dark Sky Reserve" class="alignnone wp-image-645423 size-full" height="907" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.35.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.35.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.35-300x213.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.35-1024x726.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.35-768x544.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.35-1200x850.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The union territory of Ladakh will host India’s first Dark Sky Reserve which will be set up in Hanle area in the next three months. The Dark Sky Reserve is being built as part of Ladakh’s high-altitude Changthang Wildlife Sanctuary.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Dark Sky Reserve (DSR)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Definition of Dark Sky Reserve</strong>: The International Dark Sky Association (IDSA) defines an international dark sky reserve (IDSR) as “a public or private land of substantial size (at least 700 km², or about 173,000 acres) possessing an exceptional or distinguished quality of starry nights and nocturnal environment, and that is specifically protected for its scientific, natural, educational, cultural heritage, and/or public enjoyment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Core Area of Dark Sky Reserve?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A dark sky reserve requires a “core” area that has clear sky without any light pollution, which can enable telescopes to see the sky in its natural darkness.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Dark Sky Reserve" class="alignnone wp-image-645426 size-full" height="614" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1170px) 100vw, 1170px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.40.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.40.jpeg 1170w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.40-300x157.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.40-1024x537.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.40-768x403.jpeg 768w" width="1170"/></strong></h4>
<h4>Why Ladakh is chosen as ideal location for DSR?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Ladakh is ideal for long-term observatories and dark-sky sites because of its large arid area, high elevation, and sparse population, extreme cold and minimum temperature drops to minus 40 degree celcius.</li>
<li>The Changthang wildlife Sanctuary, the DSR site is situated around 4,500 metres above sea level, which makes it a perfect host for telescopes.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who is managing India’s DSR?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Department of Science and Technology and Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA) in Bengaluru are providing support for the facility. The IIA already manages the Indian Astronomical Observatory (IAO) complex in Hanle, Ladakh.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the International standards for DSR?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>International Dark Sky Association’s Recognition: </strong>The IDSA recognizes and accredits dark-sky areas worldwide, in three categories. The Mont Mégantic Observatory in Quebec is the first such site to be recognized (in 2007) as an International Dark Sky Reserve.</li>
<li><strong>Categorical Certification: </strong>Individuals or groups can nominate a site for certification to the International Dark Sky Association (IDSA). There are five designated categories, namely International Dark Sky parks, communities, reserves, sanctuaries and Urban Night Sky Places.</li>
<li><strong>Global Recognition</strong>: The certification process is similar to that of a site being awarded the UNESCO World Heritage Site tag or getting recognised as a Biosphere Reserve. Between 2001 and January 2022, there have been 195 sites recognised as International Dark Sky Places globally, the IDSA said.</li>
<li><strong>Dark Sky Park: </strong>IDSA recognized Natural Bridges National Monument in Utah as the world’s first International Dark Sky Park.</li>
<li><strong>Dark Sky Sanctuary</strong>: In 2015, the IDSA introduced the term “Dark Sky Sanctuary” and designated the Elqui Valley of northern Chile as the world’s first International Dark Sky Sanctuary. The Gabriela Mistral Dark Sky Sanctuary is named after a Chilean poet.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Dark Sky Reserve" class="alignnone wp-image-645444 size-full" height="720" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.48.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.48.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.48-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.48-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.48-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.48-1200x675.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>What is <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-first-dark-sky-reserve-in-ladakh/">India’s objective with DSR</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>To promote AstroTourism: </strong>The primary objective of the proposed Dark Sky Reserve is to promote astronomy tourism in a sustainable and environment-friendly manner. Scientific methods will be used here to preserve the night sky from ever-increasing light pollution.</li>
<li><strong>To offer clear skies for observations</strong>: With metros, cities and peripheral areas experiencing light pollution and remaining constantly lit up, there are diminishing areas that offer a view of clear skies on cloudless nights.</li>
<li><strong>For training purpose: </strong>In the pilot phase, the Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA),has procured ten small and easy-to-handle telescopes and light-reflecting shields. IIA’s scientists and outreach experts will identify locals and train them to use these telescopes.</li>
<li><strong>Sky gazing and a boost for village economy:</strong> This will include basic sky gazing, identification of constellations, and locating the pole star, among others. These telescopes will be installed at the homestays, which is a popular option for tourist accommodation in Ladakh.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Dark Sky Reserve" class="alignnone wp-image-645446 size-full" height="452" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 678px) 100vw, 678px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.44.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.44.jpeg 678w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.44-300x200.jpeg 300w" width="678"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Dark Sky Reserve is likely to boost Astro tourism in India where there has been no such reserve. Once set up, the reserve will be the highest-located site in the country for infrared, gamma-ray, and optical telescopes<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. </strong><strong>What are the Dark Sky Reserves? How DRS will help in astronomical research and observations in India?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dark-sky-reserve/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Boosting India’s Cotton Production</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-cotton/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Cotton crop,Voluntary Sustainable Standards (VSS)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Textile industry,Voluntary Sustainable Standards (VSS)</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="India" class="alignnone wp-image-645443" height="272" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 595px) 100vw, 595px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.04.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.04.jpeg 1196w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.04-300x137.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.04-1024x468.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.04-768x351.jpeg 768w" width="595"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cotton, one of the most important crops, has a strategic role in India’s international agriculture play. India is the world’s third-largest exporter of cotton and the second-largest exporter of textiles, therefore, also contributing significantly to the country’s economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>All you need to know about the Cotton crop</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rainfall and Temperature: </strong>Sensitive to timing of rainfall and rainfall during harvest might lead to crop failure. Temperature required is around 20-30 degree c., while rainfall is about 75-100cm.</li>
<li><strong>Soil: </strong>Black soil ideally suited for cotton cultivation as it is rich in lime.cotton is vulnerable to pest attack.</li>
<li><strong>Humidity: </strong>Cotton cultivation requires more than 200 frost free days. Humidity during harvest is harmful.</li>
<li><strong>Oilcake</strong>: The cotton seeds are crushed for oil and the oilcake is an important animal fodder and also used as farm manure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="India" class="alignnone wp-image-645445 size-full" height="627" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1112px) 100vw, 1112px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.58.52.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.58.52.jpeg 1112w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.58.52-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.58.52-1024x577.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.58.52-768x433.jpeg 768w" width="1112"/></strong></h4>
<h4><strong>What is the Present status of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/challenges-facing-the-south-asian-textile-industry/">cotton in India?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India holds a 4% share of the U.S.$840 billion global textile and apparel market</li>
<li>India has been successful in developing backward links, with the aid of the Technical Upgradation Fund Scheme (TUFS), in the cotton and technical textiles industry.</li>
<li>However, India is yet to move into man-made fibres as factories still operate in a seasonal fashion.</li>
<li>Areas of cotton cultivation are Gujrat, Maharashtra, Telangana, Punjab, etc.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;"><em>Do you</em></strong><em style="font-size: 32px; font-weight: bold; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;"> k</em><em style="font-size: 32px; font-weight: bold; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">now? </em></p>
<p>The latest archaeological discovery in Mehrgarh puts the dating of early cotton cultivation and the use of cotton to 5000 BCE. The Indus Valley civilization started cultivating cotton by 3000 BCE. Cotton was mentioned in Hindu hymns in 1500 BCE.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="India" class="alignnone wp-image-645448 size-large" height="887" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.09-1024x887.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.09-1024x887.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.09-300x260.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.09-768x666.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.09-1038x900.jpeg 1038w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.09.jpeg 1080w" width="1024"/>What are the voluntary sustainable standards (VSS) in cotton?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Voluntary Sustainability Standards (VSS): </strong> Voluntary Sustainability Standards (VSS), which encapsulate certification schemes, labelling programmes, and private standards. The major VSS that are dominant in the sustainable cotton value chain today include Better Cotton Initiative (BCI), Organic Cotton, Fair trade Cotton, and Cotton Made in Africa.</li>
<li><strong>To achieve sustainable Goal: </strong>The global textile supply chain is undergoing a paradigm shift; it is pursuing environmental and social upgradation to meet the sustainability requirements imposed by global textile and home furnishing retailers, so as to mitigate the adverse impacts of climate change on cotton farmers and cotton cultivation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the benefits of VSS for India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enhance position in global cotton supply: </strong>Adapting to VSS is clearly beneficial for India. On the one hand, it will help it remain globally competitive in the cotton supply chain and strengthen its position in the export market, while on the other, it will help meet India’s SDG commitments.</li>
<li><strong>Takes India a step closer towards sustainable farming: </strong>India has made considerable progress in its transition towards a more sustainable cotton farming ecosystem. The total cotton area under VSS has reached 1.5 million hectares, contributing to 24 percent of the global VSS cotton area.</li>
<li><strong>Increases organic production of cotton: </strong>With approximately 0.2 million hectares of area for production, it is the largest producer of organic cotton, accounting for 50 percent of global organic cotton production, and the second-largest producer of ‘Better Cotton’, accounting for 16.5 percent of total Better Cotton production covering an area of 1.5 million hectares.</li>
<li><strong>Higher yeild</strong>: According to the BCI’s 2020 Impact Report for India, Better Cotton farmers have 9 percent higher yields and 18 percent higher profit than conventional farmers.</li>
<li><strong>Eco friendly production:</strong>The Thinkstep report 2018 on the Life Cycle Assessment of VSS Cotton conducted in Madhya Pradesh revealed a reduction of 50 percent in climate change impact, 59 percent in blue water consumption, 84 percent in ecotoxicity, and 100 percent eutrophication in organic over conventional cotton.</li>
<li><strong>To achieve SDG Targets</strong>: The VSS cotton growth story in India has already demonstrated its contribution towards the achievement of SDG targets for Zero Hunger (Goal 2), Clean Water and Sanitation (Goal 6), Responsible Consumption and Production (Goal 12), Life on Land (Goal 15), and Climate Action (Goal 16).</li>
<li><strong>NITI Aayog’s Assessment: </strong>VSS cotton delivers real, measurable outcomes according to priority indicators as outlined by NITI Aayog which maps India’s SDG goals. These indicators include changes in the extent of water bodies, improving groundwater withdrawal against availability, and rationalising nitrogen fertiliser.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="India" class="alignnone wp-image-645450 size-full" height="614" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.17.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.17.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.17-300x144.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.17-1024x491.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.17-768x368.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.17-1200x576.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India must scale up the VSS while aligning it with its SDG commitments since VSS in cotton ensures a better production system, sourcing methods, and consumption patterns while also influencing the lives of hundreds of millions.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. </strong><strong>What are the Voluntary Sustainable Standards (VSS)? Cotton production can be boosted in India using VSS method. Elaborate</strong>.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-cotton/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Chandrayaan-2 gauges sodium content on Moon’s surface</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/chandrayaan-2-sodium-moon-surface/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Chandrayaan-2</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="chandra" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-646151" height="439" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/moon.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/moon.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/moon-300x171.jpg 300w" width="768"/></p>
<p>Scientists from ISRO have mapped out the global distribution of sodium on the Moon’s surface using the CLASS instrument (Chandrayaan-2 large area soft X-ray spectrometer) onboard of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tasks-accomplished-by-the-chandrayaan-2/">Chandrayaan-2 mission</a>.</p>
<h4><strong>Why in news now?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>This is the first effort to provide a global-scale measurement of sodium on the lunar surface using X-ray fluorescent spectra.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Chandrayaan-2: A quick recap</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Chandrayaan-2 consisted of an Orbiter, Lander and Rover, all equipped with scientific instruments to study the moon.</li>
<li>The Orbiter would watch the moon from a 100-km orbit, while the Lander and Rover modules were to be separated to make a soft landing on the moon’s surface.</li>
<li>ISRO had named the Lander module as Vikram, after Vikram Sarabhai, the pioneer of India’s space programme, and the Rover module as Pragyaan, meaning wisdom.</li>
<li>The Orbiter part of the mission has been functioning normally. It is carrying eight instruments.</li>
<li>Each of these instruments has produced a handsome amount of data that sheds new light on the moon and offers insights that could be used in further exploration.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is X-Ray Fluorescence?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is commonly used to study the composition of materials in a non-destructive manner.</li>
<li>When the sun gives out solar flares, a large amount of X-ray radiation falls on the moon, triggering X-ray fluorescence.</li>
<li>The CLASS measures the energy of the X-ray photons coming from the moon and counts the total number.</li>
<li>The energy of the photons indicates the atom (for instance, sodium atoms emit X-ray photons of 1.04 keV) and the intensity is a measure of how many atoms are present.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How is it related to the history of moon?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sodium can be used as a tracer of the volatile history of the moon.</li>
<li>When compared to Earth, the moon is significantly depleted of volatile elements such as sodium.</li>
<li>The amount of volatiles on the moon today can be used to test formation scenarios of the Earth-Moon system.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/chandrayaan-2-sodium-moon-surface/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Early warning for heatwaves sees huge improvement</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/early-warning-for-heatwaves-sees-huge-improvement/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Heatwaves</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Heatwaves prediction</p></div></div><p><img alt="heatwave" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-646152" height="431" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 725px) 100vw, 725px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/heatwave.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/heatwave.jpg 725w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/heatwave-300x178.jpg 300w" width="725"/></p>
<p>Indian scientists have, for the first time, been able to predict heatwaves even one season in advance.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In a recent study, the India’s Ministry of Earth Sciences have documented for the first time that Indian heatwaves can be predicted even one season in advance.</li>
<li>They used 37 years (1981-2017) of hindcasts from the Monsoon Mission Coupled Climate Forecast Model (MMCFS).</li>
<li>It documented the seasonal predictions of frequency and duration of Indian heatwaves during April-June are very useful.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Heatwave and when is it declared?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Heatwaves occur over India between March and June.</li>
<li>IMD declares a heatwave event when the maximum (day) temperature for a location in the plains crosses 40 degrees Celsius.</li>
<li>Over the hills, the threshold temperature is 30 degrees Celsius.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How are they formed?</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="heatwave" class="alignnone wp-image-537965 size-full" height="533" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 461px) 100vw, 461px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/htwv.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/htwv.jpg 461w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/htwv-259x300.jpg 259w" width="461"/></p>
<ul>
<li>Heatwaves form when high pressure aloft (3,000–7,600 metres) strengthens and remains over a region for several days up to several weeks.</li>
<li>This is common in summer (in both Northern and Southern Hemispheres) as the jet stream ‘follows the sun’.</li>
<li>On the equator side of the jet stream, in the upper layers of the atmosphere, is the high pressure area.</li>
<li>Summertime weather patterns are generally slower to change than in winter. As a result, this upper level high pressure also moves slowly.</li>
<li>Under high pressure, the air subsides (sinks) toward the surface, warming and drying adiabatically, inhibiting convection and preventing the formation of clouds.</li>
<li>Reduction of clouds increases shortwave radiation reaching the surface.</li>
<li>A low pressure at the surface leads to surface wind from lower latitudes that brings warm air, enhancing the warming.</li>
<li>Alternatively, the surface winds could blow from the hot continental interior towards the coastal zone, leading to heat waves.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Following criteria are used to declare heatwave:</strong></h4>
<p>To declare heatwave, the below criteria should be met at least in 2 stations in a Meteorological subdivision for at least two consecutive days and it will be declared on the second day.</p>
<p><strong>a) Based on Departure from Normal</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Heat Wave:</strong> Departure from normal is 4.5°C to 6.4°C</li>
<li><strong>Severe Heat Wave:</strong> Departure from normal is &gt;6.4°C</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>b) Based on Actual Maximum Temperature (for plains only)</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Heat Wave:</strong> When actual maximum temperature ≥ 45°C</li>
<li><strong>Severe Heat Wave:</strong> When actual maximum temperature ≥47°C</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How long can a heatwave spell last?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A heatwave spell generally lasts for a <strong><u>minimum of four days</u></strong>.</li>
<li>On some occasions, it can <strong><u>extend up to seven or ten days</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The longest recorded heatwave spell, in recent years, was between 18 and 31 May 2015.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Impact of Heatwaves</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Heat Strokes:</strong> Very high temperatures or humid conditions pose an elevated risk of heat stroke or heat exhaustion.</li>
<li><strong>Increased healthcare costs:</strong> Effects from extreme heat are also associated with increased hospitalizations and emergency room visits, increased deaths from cardio-respiratory and other diseases, mental health issues, adverse pregnancy and birth outcomes, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Lesser work productivity:</strong> Extreme heat also lessens worker productivity, especially among the more than 1 billion workers who are exposed to high heat on a regular basis.</li>
<li><strong>Risk of wildfires:</strong> The heat domes act as fuel to wildfires, which destroys a lot of land area every year in countries like the US.</li>
<li><strong>Weather impacts:</strong> The condition also prevents clouds from forming, allowing for more radiation from the sun to hit the ground.</li>
<li><strong>Effect on Vegetation:</strong> The trapping of heat can also damage crops, dry out vegetation and result in</li>
<li><strong>Increased energy demands:</strong> The sweltering heat wave also leads to rise in energy demand, especially electricity, leading to pushing up rates.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Mitigating its impacts</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Adaptation to heatwaves can be effective to minimise the negative impacts.</li>
<li>This can be done by developing a comprehensive heat response plan that includes early warnings, awareness rising and technology intervention.</li>
<li>India has now a strong national framework for heat action plans involving the India Meteorological Department (IMD), the National and State disaster management authorities, and local bodies.</li>
<li>Early warning systems are an integral part of this heat action plan.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Seasonal forecasts should use a multi-model ensemble (MME) forecasting strategy.</li>
<li>Short-range ensemble forecasts should use higher-resolution global models, initialized with observed soil moisture data, which are available from microwave satellites and IMD’s soil moisture network.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/early-warning-for-heatwaves-sees-huge-improvement/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Freezing of Election Symbols</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/freezing-of-election-symbols/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Election symbols</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>In an interim order the Election Commission of India (ECI) froze the well-known ‘bow and arrow’ election symbol of a political party in Maharashtra.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the EC order?</strong></h4>
<p>In the operative part of its order, the ECI said that-</p>
<ol>
<li>Neither of the two groups shall be permitted to use the name of the party.</li>
<li>Neither group shall be permitted to use the symbol ‘Bow &amp; Arrow’.</li>
<li>Both groups shall be known by such names as they may choose.</li>
</ol>
<h4>EC’s powers in Election Symbol Dispute</h4>
<ul>
<li>The question of a split in a political party outside the legislature is dealt by Para 15 of the Symbols Order, 1968.</li>
<li>It states that the Election Commission of India’s (ECI) may take into account all the available facts and circumstances and undertake a test of majority.</li>
<li>The decision of the ECI shall be binding on all such rival sections or groups emerged after the split.</li>
<li>This applies to disputes in recognized national and state parties.</li>
<li>For splits in registered but unrecognized parties, the EC usually advises the warring factions to resolve their differences internally or to approach the court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did the EC deal with such matters before the Symbols Order came into effect?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Before 1968, the EC issued notifications and executive orders under the Conduct of Election Rules, 1961.</li>
<li>The most high-profile split of a party before 1968 was that of the CPI in 1964.</li>
<li>A breakaway group approached the ECI in December 1964 urging it to recognize them as CPI(Marxist). They provided a list of MPs and MLAs of Andhra Pradesh, Kerala and West Bengal who supported them.</li>
<li>The ECI recognized the faction as CPI(M) after it found that the votes secured by the MPs and MLAs supporting the breakaway group added up to more than 4% in the 3 states.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Options for ECI</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ECI in all likelihood can freeze the symbol so that neither of the two sides is able to use it until a final decision is made.</li>
<li>EC hearings are long and detailed and may take at least six months.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What was the first case decided under Para 15 of the 1968 Order?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It was the first split in the Indian National Congress in 1969.</li>
<li>Indira Gandhi’s tensions with a rival group within the party came to a head with the death of President Dr Zakir Hussain on May 3, 1969.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Is there a way other than the test of the majority to resolve a dispute over election symbols?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In almost all disputes decided by the EC so far, a clear majority of party delegates/office bearers, MPs and MLAs have supported one of the factions.</li>
<li>Whenever the EC could not test the strength of rival groups based on support within the party organization (because of disputes regarding the list of office bearers), it fell back on testing the majority only among elected MPs and MLAs.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What happens to the group that doesn’t get the parent party’s symbol?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The EC in 1997 did not recognize the new parties as either state or national parties.</li>
<li>It felt that merely having MPs and MLAs is not enough, as the elected representatives had fought and won polls on tickets of their parent (undivided) parties.</li>
<li>The EC introduced a new rule under which the splinter group of the party — other than the group that got the party symbol — had to register itself as a separate party.</li>
<li>It could lay claim to national or state party status only on the basis of its performance in the state or central elections after registration.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/freezing-of-election-symbols/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Pilot launch of E-Rupee</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/e-rupee-pilot-launch/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>E-Rupee (CBDC)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Rolling out of digital Rupee</p></div></div><p>The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) has indicated that it will soon commence limited pilot launches of e-rupee (e`), or <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/rstv-archive-central-bank-digital-currency/">Central Bank Digital Currency (CBDC)</a> or digital rupee, for specific use cases.</p>
<h4><strong>What’s RBI’s plan?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>RBI has hinted at two broad categories for the use of e-rupee — retail and wholesale — taking the payment system in the country to a new level.</li>
<li>Hence the common people and businesses will be able to use the digital currency seamlessly for various transactions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is E-Rupee?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>E-rupee is the same as a fiat currency and is exchangeable one-to-one with the fiat currency.</li>
<li>Only its form is different.</li>
<li>It can be accepted as a medium of payment, legal tender and a safe store of value.</li>
<li>The digital rupee would appear as liability on a central bank’s balance sheet.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the types of E-Rupee?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Based on the usage and the functions performed by the digital rupee and considering the different levels of accessibility, CBDC can be demarcated into two broad categories:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>General purpose (retail) (CBDC-R):</strong> It is an electronic version of cash primarily meant for retail transactions. It will be potentially available for use by all — private sector, non-financial consumers and businesses — and can provide access to safe money for payment and settlement as it is a direct liability of the central bank.</li>
<li><strong>Wholesale (CBDC-W):</strong> It is designed for restricted access to select financial institutions. It has the potential to transform the settlement systems for financial transactions undertaken by banks in the government securities (G-Sec) segment, inter-bank market and capital market more efficiently and securely in terms of operational costs, use of collateral and liquidity management.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What are the forms of CBDC?</strong></h4>
<p>The central bank says e-rupee, or CBDC, can be structured as <strong><u>token-based</u></strong> or <strong><u>account-based</u></strong>.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Token-based CBDC:</strong> It would be a bearer instrument like banknotes, meaning whosoever holds the tokens at a given point in time would be presumed to own them. In this, the person receiving a token will verify that his ownership of the token is genuine. It is viewed as a preferred mode for CBDC-R as it would be closer to physical cash.</li>
<li><strong>Account-based CBDC:</strong> It would require maintenance of record of balances and transactions of all holders of the CBDC and indicate the ownership of the monetary balances. In this case, an intermediary will verify the identity of an account holder. This system can be considered for CBDC-W.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What’s the model for issuance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There are two models for issuance and management of CBDCs under the RBI’s consideration — direct model (single tier model) and indirect model (two-tier model).</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Direct model:</strong> Here the central bank will be responsible for managing all aspects of the digital rupee system such as issuance, account-keeping and transaction verification.</li>
<li><strong>Indirect model:</strong> It would be one where the central bank and other intermediaries (banks and any other service providers), each play their respective role. In this model, the central bank will issue CBDC to consumer’s indirectly through intermediaries and any claim by consumers will be managed by the intermediary.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Advantages of e-rupee</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The key motivations for exploring the issuance of CBDC in India among others include reduction in operational costs involved in physical cash management.</li>
<li>It would foster financial inclusion, bringing resilience, efficiency and innovation in the payments system.</li>
<li>It will add efficiency to the settlement system and boost innovation in cross-border payments space.</li>
<li>It can provide the public with uses that any private virtual currencies can provide, without the associated risks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Can e-rupee be transacted in offline mode?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The offline functionality as an option will allow CBDC to be transacted without the internet and thus enable access in regions with poor or no internet connectivity.</li>
<li>It will also create digital footprints of the unbanked population in the financial system, which will facilitate the easy availability of credit to them.</li>
<li>However, the RBI feels in the offline mode, the risk of ‘double-spending’ will exist because it will be technically possible to use a CBDC unit more than once without updating the common ledger of CBDC.</li>
<li>But it can be mitigated to a larger extent by technical solutions and appropriate business rules including monetary limits on offline transactions.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/e-rupee-pilot-launch/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>GDP and The Rising Interest Rates</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gdp/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>GDP and basic economic concepts</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Inflation and effect of rising Interate rates.</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="GDP" class="alignnone wp-image-646085 size-full" height="1075" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.17-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.17-1.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.17-1-300x252.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.17-1-1024x860.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.17-1-768x645.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.17-1-1072x900.jpeg 1072w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.17-1-1200x1008.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While cutting down India’s GDP growth to 6.5 per cent for 2022-23, the World Bank noted that this was largely due to a deteriorating global scenario. But, even at 6.5 per cent, India will still be a global growth out-performer this year.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Gross Domestic Product (GDP)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>GDP is the value of all final goods and services produced by the normal residents as well as non-residents in the domestic territory of the country but does not includes Net Factor Income from Abroad.</li>
<li>The important point to remember is whatever is produced in India, whether by an Indian or foreign national is part of Indian GDP.</li>
<li>GDP = Consumption + Gross Private Investment + Government Expenditure + Net Exports</li>
<li>Net Exports= Exports – Imports.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="GDP" class="alignnone wp-image-646087 size-full" height="1216" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.21.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.21.jpeg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.21-266x300.jpeg 266w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.21-909x1024.jpeg 909w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.21-768x865.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.21-799x900.jpeg 799w" width="1080"/>What is <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/issues-with-indias-gdp-data/">India’s Current GDP</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian Economy stands at $3.53 trillion in FY22</li>
<li>India’s gross domestic product (GDP) grew 8.7% in FY22.</li>
<li>India has overtaken Britain to become the world’s fifth largest economyand as per IMF projections, only USA, China, Japan, and Germany are now ahead of India in terms of the volume of the national economy.</li>
<li>As per its estimates, India would be a $3.54 trillion economy at the end of 2022 compared to the UK’s $3.38 trillion. India’s economy has been growing at a much faster rate in both real and nominal rates than that of the UK over a long period of time.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em><strong>DO YOU KNOW</strong></em></p>
<p>India, still a developing nation but it is the third-largest economy globally when it comes to Purchasing power parity (PPP). This country has approximately 6.7 percent of the world’s GDP, compared to America’s 16 percent.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>An examination of GDP growth data for India </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>India’s growth trajectory: </strong>India’s growth cycles are in sync with those of the advanced economies. What this implies is that India cannot avoid the short-term pain of deceleration in the developed countries. Increasing global interconnectivity only accentuates this effect.</li>
<li><strong>Divergent Rate of GDP Growth:</strong> The long-term trend rate of GDP growth of advanced economies and India is divergent. For India, it has moved up over time, while for advanced economies it is the other way.</li>
<li><strong>Domestic factors:</strong> Domestic inflation dynamics and financial conditions will also influence growth outcomes. On the other hand, the long-term trend rate of growth will be influenced by many factors including efficiency-enhancing reforms.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="GDP" class="alignnone wp-image-646089 size-full" height="936" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 723px) 100vw, 723px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.17.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.17.jpeg 723w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.17-232x300.jpeg 232w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.17-695x900.jpeg 695w" width="723"/>Near-term prospects for India’s GDP growth in the backdrop of ongoing geopolitical events</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>A complex interplay of geopolitical events and its impact: </strong></li>
<li>High inflation and sharp rate hike has turned the global environment gloomier more so for calendar 2023 than 2022. As economies moved past the pandemic in early 2022, geopolitical risks emerged and have only escalated since then.</li>
<li>S&amp;P Global has recently marked down global growth to 3.1 per cent and 2.4 per cent for 2022 and 2023 respectively.</li>
<li><strong>Impact of Global slowdown:</strong></li>
<li>Typically, Global slowdowns soften crude and commodity prices, which ease the burden on India’s imports. However, the ongoing geopolitical stress is likely to limit the decline in their prices. OPEC’s recent move to cut oil output is an example of how geopolitics is shaping oil prices.</li>
<li>Impact of a slowing global economy on exports will overshadow the mild positive impulse from the rupee depreciating.</li>
<li><strong>Volatility of crude oil and commodity prices leading to inflation:</strong></li>
<li>From the beginning of this fiscal, geopolitical developments have had an outsized impact on India’s inflation, particularly the wholesale price inflation, which continues to be in double digits and spills over to consumer prices.</li>
<li>The Russia-Ukraine conflict has created volatility for several agricultural commodities. Exporter nations have then imposed trade restrictions. While commodity prices have come off from their highs, volatility and uncertainty about their price trajectory continue.</li>
<li><strong>Systematic rise in interest rates and its impact on rupee:</strong></li>
<li>The four-decade high inflation is forcing systemically important central banks such as the Fed and European Central Bank (ECB) to raise interest rates faster and by bigger magnitudes than anticipated earlier.</li>
<li>Such hikes in the US have raised the spectrum of currency depreciation and imported inflation for India. Although the rupee’s depreciation had been quite orderly so far thanks to the Reserve Bank of India’s deft interventions, the downward pressure has intensified again with the rupee breaching 82/$ last week.</li>
<li>A weaker rupee will only make imports expensive. Domestic pressures on food inflation from freak weather events and a lopsided monsoon are keeping consumer inflation high.</li>
<li><strong>Impact on India’s Exports:</strong></li>
<li>In the backdrop of slowing economy, India’s exports, which have already started contracting. A 1 per cent decline in global GDP is associated with a 2.3 per cent reduction in exports. But every 1 per cent depreciation in the real effective exchange rate leads to a 1 per cent increase in exports.</li>
<li>The World Trade Organization has already lowered global trade volume growth forecasts.</li>
<li><strong>Impact on Consumption linked sectors:</strong></li>
<li>Sectors such as textiles (readymade garments and home furnishings) and leather are already facing lower export orders. Engineering and electronics goods are also getting hit.</li>
<li>Since the domestic growth momentum remains strong, imports are sticky and continue to grow.</li>
<li><strong>Widening trade deficit leading to Current account deficit(CAD)</strong>:</li>
<li>During April-September this year, while exports have grown by 15.5 per cent, imports grew by 37.8 per cent.</li>
<li>A rising CAD requires more capital flows to finance it. The availability of this in the current risk-off scenario would be a challenge. Thus the rupee is likely to remain volatile with a depreciation bias in the near term.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="GDP" class="alignnone wp-image-646095 size-full" height="450" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.23.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.23.jpeg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.23-300x225.jpeg 300w" width="600"/>Way ahead</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Rising interest rates and slowing external demand will be the growth dampeners in the foreseeable future.</li>
<li>We see downside risks to our GDP growth forecast of 7.3 per cent and 6.5 per cent for the current and next year respectively.</li>
<li>During upturns, the growth is overestimated, while in downturns, it’s the other way around. Therefore, forecasts at this juncture will have a short shelf life and a wider confidence interval.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Slowdown in global growth has an immediate impact on India’s exports, further widening the trade deficit and affecting domestic growth. In this context, discuss the role of central bank in keeping inflation low.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gdp/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Is Private Capital Formation Declining?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/is-private-capital-formation-declining/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Corporate Investment, employment and growth</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Capital" class="alignnone wp-image-646134 size-full" height="418" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 734px) 100vw, 734px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-11.40.51.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-11.40.51.jpeg 734w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-11.40.51-300x171.jpeg 300w" width="734"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In a meeting held with the country’s corporate leaders, Finance Minister Nirmala Sitharaman drew attention to an important aspect of the economy today. She rightly flagged concerns about sluggish corporate investment, despite the government’s business friendly stance, including a reduction in the corporate tax<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is mean by Corporate Investment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Corporate investment is an investment that is made by companies rather than by governments or individual people. Corporate investing simply means investing the profits / surplus cash of your business, instead of drawing it as income or holding it in cash bank accounts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is mean by <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/public-capex-plan-key-to-long-term-growth-fm/">Capital Investment</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Capital investment is the acquisition of physical assets by a company for use in furthering its long-term business goals and objectives. Real estate, manufacturing plants, and machinery are among the assets that are purchased as capital investments.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Capital" class="alignnone wp-image-646129 size-large" height="1024" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1022px) 100vw, 1022px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-11.23.38-1022x1024.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-11.23.38-1022x1024.jpeg 1022w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-11.23.38-300x300.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-11.23.38-150x150.jpeg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-11.23.38-768x769.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-11.23.38-899x900.jpeg 899w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-11.23.38-1200x1202.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-11.23.38.jpeg 1278w" width="1022"/>What is the Present situation of corporate Investment in Indian Economy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Gross capital formation</strong> (<strong>GCF): </strong>Over 90% of GCF consists of fixed investments.The National Accounts Statistics provides disaggregation of gross capital formation (GCF) by sectors, type of assets and modes of financing.</li>
<li><strong>Share of Private investment: </strong>Private investment accounts for close to 75% of total capital formation in the economy. Its revival therefore is essential for sustained growth of the economy.</li>
<li><strong>No change in investment distribution</strong>: The investment distribution has hardly changed over the last decade, with the public sector’s share remaining 20%.</li>
<li><strong>Fall in share of agriculture and industry</strong>: Between 2014-15 and 2019-20, the shares of agriculture and industry in fixed capital formation/GDP fell from 7.7% and 33.7% to 6.4% and 32.5%, respectively.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Capital" class="alignnone wp-image-646131 size-large" height="721" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.25-1024x721.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.25-1024x721.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.25-300x211.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.25-768x540.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-09.04.25.jpeg 1026w" width="1024"/>Why Private capital formation is declining in the economy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low productivity of companies: </strong>Very low productivity of capital for Indian companies at 2-3% despite the cost tailwinds in FY21 due to the pandemic shock.</li>
<li><strong>Low Government spending: </strong>Despite the bump-up in capital allocations by government (30% YoY) the progress towards improving the mix of government spending towards capital outlay has been moderate.</li>
<li><strong>Dismal Public capital formation: </strong>Capex as % of total spending has increased marginally to 16.5%, and its impact on overall capital formation has been less than 4% of GDP; overall public sector capital formation has remained low at 7% of GDP (vs 9% in FY08).</li>
<li><strong>No crowding in: </strong>While total government revenue spending in nominal terms remained higher compared to our framework (averaging at 12% YoY during FY11-FY21), the real growth has been modest, averaging at 5.8%. Thus, amid the declining trade/GDP ratio, weak private capex, rising unemployment and several shocks the crowding in role of fiscal expansion has been missing.</li>
<li><strong>Declining savings rate: </strong>India’s saving rate continues to decline at 30% (37% FY08), along with sharply lower household savings rate (19.3% in FY20, 24% at the peak) and household financial savings rate (7.8% vs 10.5%). Domestic savings explains 98% of domestic invests &amp; it should precede a private capex cycle.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Capital" class="alignnone wp-image-646136 size-full" height="620" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 494px) 100vw, 494px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-2.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-2.jpeg 494w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-2-239x300.jpeg 239w" width="494"/>Why is there a Conducive environment for private investment in the Indian Economy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Improved financial condition: </strong>There has been considerable improvement in external balance position, including CAD turning surplus in FY21 at 0.9% of GDP, steep rise in RBI’s forex buffer. Favourable financial conditions have enabled fund raising by many sectors, including banks.</li>
<li><strong>Deleveraging of corporate balance sheets</strong>: There is a sharp decline in debt/equity ratio of the non-financial sector for BSE500 companies (constant set of companies existing since 1998) to 63% in FY21 from 92% in FY20.</li>
<li><strong>Declining NPA’s: </strong>Higher capital base of banks (CAR at 15.8% in FY21), lower NPAs (7.5% of advances) and deleveraged corporate balance sheets are necessary buffer for private capex revival and ability of banks to fund it.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The present scenario is indicative of high-risk aversion among banks and companies. While there has been some positive progress in FY21 towards private capex inflection point, there are a few crucial laps to finish before it decisively breaks from the 13 years of decline. A big push on demand recovery backed either by public spending or positive global spill over will be necessary in shortening the revival process</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Discuss the current status of private capital formation in India. What factors in the Indian economy create a conducive environment for private capital investment?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/is-private-capital-formation-declining/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Reinventing the United Nations</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/united-nations/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UN</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>United nations and India's Role.</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="United Nations" class="alignnone wp-image-646156 size-full" height="853" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.14.35.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.14.35.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.14.35-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.14.35-1024x682.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.14.35-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.14.35-1200x800.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The United Nations Secretary General (UNSG), António Guterres, made a candid assessment of global governance. He addressed the United Nations General Assembly and said the “world is in big trouble, gridlocked in colossal global dysfunction, even the G20 is in the trap of geopolitical divides”.</li>
<li>In a splintering world, we need to create mechanisms of dialogue to heal divides and only by acting as one, we can nurture fragile shoots of hope for a coalition of the world.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>History of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-birth-of-united-nations/">evolution of United Nations (UN)</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The League of Nations set up in 1920, was the first intergovernmental organisation with the aim to promote international cooperation and outlived its utility with World War II.</li>
<li>The United Nations claims to be the one place where all the world’s nations can discuss common problems and find shared solutions that benefit all of humanity.</li>
<li>Now, 75 years later, rising conflict situations suggest it is time to go back to first principles of the Charter.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="United Nations" class="alignnone wp-image-646157 size-full" height="853" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.14.34.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.14.34.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.14.34-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.14.34-1024x682.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.14.34-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.14.34-1200x800.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Why UN is at inflection point?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>A Club outside UN: </strong>The G7 Summit, held in June, endorsed the goals of a cooperative international Climate Club to accelerate climate action outside the UN.</li>
<li><strong>Nonworking of WTO: </strong>The dispute settlement mechanism of the WTO without the quorum of its members has rendered the institution dysfunctional.</li>
<li><strong>Failed promises: </strong>Despite the G7 having accepted the need for transfer of funds at Rio in 1992, because of their role in creating the climate crisis, the promise made in 2009 to provide at least$100 billion per year in climate finance remains unfulfilled.</li>
<li><strong>The China challenge: </strong>China has opted for rival set of multilateral institutions. China’s Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) seeks to achieve policy, infrastructure, trade, financial, and people to people connectivity by building a new platform for international cooperation to create new drivers of shared development, and covers half the world population with one third the GDP and investment of $930billion.</li>
<li><strong>Challenge of non traditional security: </strong> China’s Global Development Initiative 2021, and linked Global Security Initiative, 2022, is developing a conceptual frame responding to an urbanising world, i.e., digital governance and non- traditional security, which the international system has not covered.</li>
<li><strong>A divide within the UN: </strong>More significant than the clash of institutions reflecting the deepening divide between the Atlantic powers and the Russia-China combine is the diffusion of wealth, technology and power. The ‘rest’, despite threats, are now capable of not taking sides and are looking for leadership within the United Nations, for what the UNSG characterised as “coalition of the world”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="United Nations" class="alignnone wp-image-646155 size-full" height="400" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.11.29-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.11.29-1.jpeg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.11.29-1-300x300.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.11.29-1-150x150.jpeg 150w" width="400"/>What measures could be taken to move ahead ?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reject the Binary Approach: </strong>Strategists in major powers see the world in binary terms around rules. In a multipolar world, the question is the kind of rules needed for human wellbeing and whether principles would serve the purpose better.</li>
<li><strong>Adjusting the competing Institutions: </strong>The time is ripe for a big idea that both keeps away from the current multilateral focus on global rules, amount of aid and inviolability of IPR’s as well as recognises a role for competing institutions as countries can now secure the best terms themselves without bargaining.</li>
<li><strong>Universal Wellbeing at the core</strong>: Just as the ‘Rio principles’ continue to guide climate change, vasudhaiva kutumbakam, or ‘world as one family’, focusing on comparable levels of wellbeing can be the core of a set of universal socioeconomic principles for a dialogue between the states.</li>
<li><strong>Climate as uniting force</strong>: To the current global consensus around equitable sustainable development, Prime Minister Narendra Modi has added a clearer societal purpose to flesh out a universal Civilizational principle. He emphasised Lifestyle for Environment’ seeing climate change as a societal process and combating it devoid of trade-offs characteristic of the Climate Treaty. He has also offered India’s payments and linked digital D technology without IPR restrictions.</li>
<li><strong>Adressing the common concerns</strong>: In terms of felt needs of the majority rather than interests and concerns of the powerful will shift the focus of a much slimmed down United Nations squarely to human wellbeing, and not as an add on.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="United Nations" class="alignnone wp-image-646160 size-full" height="360" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.32.17.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.32.17.jpeg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.32.17-300x100.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.32.17-1024x341.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-10-at-12.32.17-768x256.jpeg 768w" width="1080"/>What role India can play?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s Presidency of the Group of 20, UN Security Council (UNSC)in 2022, and the Shanghai Cooperation Organisation (SCO) in 2023 when major powers are not even talking to each other and India alone, now the fifth largest economy, is interacting with each of them, presents a historic opportunity.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">Conclusion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>United Nations, however dysfunctional, the only global platform for world governance. No country would gain by falling UN. Even if we dissolve UN, there is no alternative than reinventing the UN again. India’s and global interest lie in preserving the UN rather than dismantling of UN.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.What are the reasons for declining credibility of UN? What role India can play to strengthen the UN?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/united-nations/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>