<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 01:03:59 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>What it will take to fulfill India’s Solar Power Dream?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-it-will-take-to-fulfill-indias-solar-power-dream/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Solar energy targets of India</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>From less than 10 MW in 2010, India has added significant PV capacity over the past decade, achieving over 50 GW by 2022.</p>
<h4>Solar energy in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>Solar photovoltaics (PV) has driven India’s push towards the adoption of cleaner energy generation technologies.</li>
<li><strong><u>India is targeting about 500 GW by 2030</u></strong>, of renewable energy deployment, out of which ~280 GW is expected from solar PV.</li>
<li>This necessitates the deployment of nearly 30 GW of solar capacity every year until 2030.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Key components</h4>
<ul>
<li>A typical solar PV value chain consists of first fabricating polysilicon ingots which need to be transformed into thin Silicon wafers that are needed to manufacture the PV mini-modules.</li>
<li>The mini-modules are then assembled into market-ready and field-deployable modules.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Various challenges</h4>
<p>There are challenges that need to be overcome for the sustainability of the PV economy.</p>
<p><strong>(1) PV Modules</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Indian solar deployment or installation companies <strong><u>depend heavily on imports</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It currently <strong><u>imports 100% of silicon wafers and around 80% of cells</u></strong> even at the current deployment levels.</li>
<li>India currently <strong><u>does not have enough module</u></strong> and cell manufacturing capacity.</li>
<li>India’s current solar module <strong><u>manufacturing capacity is limited to ~15 GW per year</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>demand-supply gap widens</u></strong> as we move up the value chain — for example, India only produces ~3.5 GW of cells currently.</li>
<li>India has <strong><u>no manufacturing capacity</u></strong> for solar wafers and polysilicon ingots.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Field deployment</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Also, out of the 15 GW of module manufacturing capacity, <strong><u>only 3-4 GW of modules</u></strong> are <strong><u>technologically competitive and worthy of deployment</u></strong> in grid-based projects.</li>
<li>India remains dependent on the import of solar modules for field deployment.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Size and technology</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Most of the Indian industry is currently tuned to handling M2 wafer size, which is roughly 156 x 156 mm2, while the global industry is already moving towards M10 and M12 sizes, which are 182 x 182 mm2 and 210 x 210 mm2 respectively.</li>
<li>The bigger size has an advantage in terms of silicon cost per wafer, as this effectively means lower loss of silicon during ingot to wafer processing.</li>
<li>In terms of cell technology, most of the manufacturing still uses Al-BSF technology, which can typically give efficiencies of ~18-19% at the cell level and ~16-17% at the module level.</li>
<li>By contrast, cell manufacturing worldwide has moved to PERC (22-23%), HJT(~24%), TOPCON (23-24%) and other newer technologies, yielding module efficiency of &gt;21%.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Land issue</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Producing more solar power for the same module size means more solar power from the same land area.</li>
<li>Land, the most expensive part of solar projects, is scarce in India — and Indian industry has no choice but to move towards newer and superior technologies as part of expansion plans.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Raw materials supply</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is a <strong><u>huge gap on the raw material supply</u></strong> chain side as well.</li>
<li>Silicon wafer, the most expensive raw material, is not manufactured in India.</li>
<li>India will have to work on technology tie-ups to make the right grade of silicon for solar cell manufacturing — and since &gt;90% of the world’s solar wafer manufacturing currently happens in China.</li>
<li>It is not clear how and where India will get the technology.</li>
<li>Other key raw materials such as <strong><u>metallic pastes of silver and aluminium</u></strong> to form the electrical contacts too, <strong><u>are almost 100% imported</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Thus, <strong><u>India is more of an assembly hub than a manufacturing</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Lack of investment</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India has hardly invested in this sector which can help the industry to try and test the technologies in a cost-effective manner.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Current govt policy</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>government has identified this gap</u></strong>, and is rolling out various policy initiatives to push and motivate the industry to <strong><u>work towards self-reliance</u></strong> in solar manufacturing, both for cells and modules.</li>
<li>Key initiatives include:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>40% duty on the import of modules and</li>
<li>25% duty on the import of cells, and</li>
<li>Production Linked Incentive (PLI) scheme to support manufacturing capex</li>
<li>Compulsion to procure modules only from an approved list of manufacturers (ALMM) for projects that are connected to state/ central government grids</li>
<li>Only India-based manufacturers have been approved</li>
</ol>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s path to become a manufacturing hub for the same <strong><u>requires more than just putting some tax barriers and commercial incentives</u></strong> in the form of PLI schemes, etc.</li>
<li>It will warrant <strong><u>strong industry-academia collaboration</u></strong> in an innovative manner to start developing home-grown technologies which could, in the short-term.</li>
<li>It needs to <strong><u>work with the industry</u></strong> to provide them with trained human resource, process learnings, root-cause analysis through right testing and, in the long term, develop India’s own technologies.</li>
<li>High-end technology development requires <strong><u>substantial investment</u></strong> in several clusters which operate in industry-like working and management conditions, appropriate emoluments, and clear deliverables.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-it-will-take-to-fulfill-indias-solar-power-dream/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>UN slams Sri Lanka’s rights record</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/un-slams-sri-lanka-rights-record/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UNHRC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economic crisis in Sri Lanka</p></div></div><p>Linking Sri Lanka’s past on human rights record to its current economic crisis, the UN Human Rights Chief on said “impunity” for human rights abuses, economic crimes, and corruption was the underlying reason for the country’s collapse.</p>
<h4>UNHRC report on Sri Lanka</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/united-nations-human-rights-council-unhrc/">UNHRC</a> report warned that Sri Lanka’s failure to address human rights violations and war crimes committed in the past had put the country on a “dangerous path”.</li>
<li>It rose that this could lead to a “recurrence” of policies and practices that gave rise to the earlier situation.</li>
<li>It flagged the accelerating militarization of civilian governmental functions, a reversal of important constitutional safeguards, political obstruction of accountability, intimidation of civil society, and the use of anti-terrorism laws.</li>
<li>The shrinking space for independent media and civil society and human rights organizations are also themes in the report.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Resolution 30/1</h4>
<ul>
<li>The resolution 30/1 launched in 2015 deals with promoting reconciliation, accountability and human rights in Sri Lanka.</li>
<li>It extended an opportunity to make good on its promises for justice and offered extensive support to accomplish that objective.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Sri Lanka’s intention</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is more than Sri Lanka has failed to – and doesn’t intend to — take the necessary, decisive, and sustainable steps necessary to achieve domestic justice and reconciliation.</li>
<li>Sri Lanka has officially sought India’s help to muster support against the resolution, which it has described as “unwanted interference by powerful countries”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where India comes in</h4>
<ul>
<li>The UNHRC is scheduled to hold an “interactive” session on Sri Lanka where the report was to be discussed, and member countries were to make statements.</li>
<li>Country-specific resolutions against Sri Lanka have regularly come up at the UNHRC in the last decade.</li>
<li>New Delhi voted against Sri Lanka in 2012 and abstained in 2014. It was spared the dilemma in 2015 when Sri Lanka joined resolution 30/1.</li>
<li>With elections coming up in Tamil Nadu, and PM declaring on a recent visit that he was the first Indian leader to visit Jaffna, Sri Lanka has begun reading the tea leaves.</li>
<li>Whichever way it goes, the resolution is likely to resonate in India-Sri Lanka Relations and for India internally, in the run-up to the Assembly elections in Tamil Nadu.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/un-slams-sri-lanka-rights-record/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the PM SHRI Scheme?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-pm-shri-scheme/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PM Shri Schools</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632164" height="398" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 394px) 100vw, 394px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pmshri-297x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pmshri-297x300.jpg 297w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pmshri.jpg 630w" width="394"/></p>
<p>Prime Minister has announced that under the PM SHRI Scheme, as many as 14,500 schools will be “upgraded” across India to showcase the components of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-national-education-policy-2020-higher-education-and-regional-languages/">National Education Policy, 2020</a>.</p>
<h4>What is the PM SHRI scheme?</h4>
<ul>
<li>According to the Ministry of Education, the <strong><u>centrally sponsored scheme</u></strong> will be called PM SHRI Schools (PM Schools for Rising India).</li>
<li>Under it, as many as 14,500 schools across states and Union Territories will be redeveloped to reflect the key features of the NEP, 2020.</li>
<li>The plan was first discussed with the education ministers of states and UTs during a conference organised by the Ministry of Education in June at Gandhinagar in Gujarat.</li>
<li>While there are exemplary schools like Navodaya Vidyalayas, Kendriya Vidyalayas, the PM SHRI will act as “NEP labs”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the key features of NEP in school education?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The NEP envisages a curricular structure and teaching style divided into various stages – foundational, preparatory, middle and secondary.</li>
<li>The foundational years (pre-school and grades I, II) will involve play-based learning.</li>
<li>At the preparatory level (III-V), light textbooks are to be introduced along with some formal classroom teaching. Subject teachers are to be introduced at the middle level (VI-VIII).</li>
<li>The secondary stage (IX-XII) will be multidisciplinary in nature with no hard separation between arts and sciences or other disciplines.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is a centrally sponsored scheme?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A centrally sponsored scheme is one where the cost of implementation is likely to split in the 60:40 ratio among the Union government and the states/Union Territories.</li>
<li>For instance, the mid-day meal scheme (PM Poshan) or the PM Awas Yojana are examples of centrally sponsored schemes.</li>
<li>In the case of the Northeastern states, Himachal Pradesh, Uttarakhand, Jammu and Kashmir and UTs without legislatures, the Centre’s contribution can go up to 90 per cent.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How will PM SHRI schools be different from Kendriya Vidyalayas or Jawahar Navodaya Vidyalayas?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Kendriya Vidyalayas or Jawahar Navodaya Vidyalayas come entirely under the Centre’s Ministry of Education. They are fully funded by the Union government under Central Sector Schemes.</li>
<li>While KVs largely cater to children of Union government employees posted in states and UTs, JNVs were set up to nurture talented students in rural parts of the country.</li>
<li>In contrast, PM SHRI schools will be an upgrade of existing schools run by the Centre, states, UTs and local bodies.</li>
<li>This essentially means that PM SHRI schools can either be KVs, JNVs, state government schools or even those run by municipal corporations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where will the PM SHRI schools come up?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Centre has not yet released the list of schools that have been chosen for this purpose.</li>
<li>It has however announced that the PM SHRI schools will also “offer mentorship” to other schools in their vicinity.</li>
<li>These schools will be equipped with modern infrastructure including labs, smart classrooms, libraries, sports equipment, art room etc.</li>
<li>It shall also be developed as green schools with water conservation, waste recycling, energy-efficient infrastructure and integration of organic lifestyle in curriculum.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-pm-shri-scheme/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Bangladesh favours early solution for Teesta Dispute</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/teesta-water-sharing-issue/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Teesta River</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India-Bangladesh Relations</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-575770" height="586" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 524px) 100vw, 524px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/tist.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/tist.jpg 524w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/06/tist-268x300.jpg 268w" width="524"/></p>
<p>India and Bangladesh should resolve all bilateral issues, including the differences over the waters of the Teesta, at an early date, said Bangladesh PM on her visit to India.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Bangladeshi PM is on a visit to India.</li>
<li>Both ministers discussed the long-standing disputes over Teesta river water sharing.</li>
<li>The two sides shared 54 rivers that required both nations to work together and share “environmental responsibility” in areas such as the Sundarbans.</li>
</ul>
<h4>About Teesta River</h4>
<ul>
<li>Teesta River is a 315 km long river that rises in the eastern Himalayas, flows through the Indian states of Sikkim and West Bengal through Bangladesh and enters the Bay of Bengal.</li>
<li>It is a tributary of the Brahmaputra (known as Jamuna in Bangladesh), flowing through India and Bangladesh.</li>
<li>It originates in the Himalayas near Chunthang, Sikkim and flows to the south through West Bengal before entering Bangladesh.</li>
<li>Originally, it continued southward to empty directly into the Padma River but around 1787 the river changed its course to flow eastward to join the Jamuna river.</li>
<li>The Teesta Barrage dam helps to provide irrigation for the plains between the upper Padma and the Jamuna.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the dispute about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The point of contention between India and Bangladesh is mainly the lean season flow in the Teesta draining into Bangladesh.</li>
<li>The river covers nearly the entire floodplains of Sikkim while draining 2,800 sq km of Bangladesh, governing the lives of hundreds of thousands of people.</li>
<li>For West Bengal, Teesta is equally important, considered the lifeline of half-a-dozen districts in North Bengal.</li>
<li>Bangladesh has sought an “equitable” distribution of Teesta waters from India, on the lines of the Ganga Water Treaty of 1996, but to no avail.</li>
<li>The failure to ink a deal had its fallout on the country’s politics, putting the ruling party of PM Sheikh Hasina in a spot.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>Q.The hydrological linkages between India and Bangladesh are a product of geography and a matter of shared history. Discuss this statement in line with the Teesta water sharing dispute.</p></blockquote>
<h4>The deal</h4>
<ul>
<li>Following a half-hearted deal in 1983, when a nearly equal division of water was proposed, the countries hit a roadblock. The transient agreement could not be implemented.</li>
<li>Talks resumed after the Awami League returned to power in 2008 and the former Indian PM Manmohan Singh visited Dhaka in 2011.</li>
<li>In 2015, PM Modi’s visit to Dhaka generated more ebullient lines: deliberations were underway involving all the stakeholders to conclude the agreement as soon as possible.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues from the Indian side</h4>
<ul>
<li>It remains an unfinished project and one of the key stakeholders — West Bengal CM is yet to endorse the deal.</li>
<li>Her objection is connected to “global warming. Many of the glaciers on the Teesta basin have retreated.</li>
<li>The importance of the flow and the seasonal variation of this river is felt during the lean season (from October to April/May) as the average flow is about 500 million cubic metres (MCM) per month.</li>
<li>The CM opposed an arrangement in 2011, by which India would get 42.5% and Bangladesh 37.5% of the water during the lean season, and the plan was shelved.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why does this deal matters?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India and Bangladesh have resolved border problems through the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/land-boundary-agreement-lba-with-bangladesh/">Land Boundary Agreement of 2015</a>.</li>
<li>However, both nations have locked horns over the sharing of multiple rivers that define the borders and impact lives and livelihoods on both sides.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/teesta-water-sharing-issue/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Alcohol Laws in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/alcohol-laws-in-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Alcohol laws</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The most ambitious Delhi’s Alcohol Policy 2021-22 which brought in big discounts for consumers was scrapped on July 31 amid allegations of corruption and irregularities in the drafting and implementation of the policy.</p>
<p>After scrapping the new policy, the Delhi government decided to bring back the ‘<strong><u>old excise regime</u></strong>’ that was in force before.</p>
<blockquote><p>Definitely! We shall not nit-pick the old vs. new policy. Let us generally understand how alcohol is regulated in India.</p></blockquote>
<h4>Alcohol laws of India: A backgrounder</h4>
<ul>
<li>The legal drinking age in India and the laws which regulate the sale and consumption of alcohol vary significantly from state to state.</li>
<li>In India, consumption of alcohol is prohibited in the states of Bihar, Gujarat, Nagaland and Mizoram.</li>
<li>There is partial ban on alcohol in some districts of Manipur.</li>
<li>All other Indian states permit alcohol consumption but fix a legal drinking age, which ranges at different ages per region.</li>
<li>In some states the legal drinking age can be different for different types of alcoholic beverage.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Regulation</h4>
<ul>
<li>Alcohol is a subject in the <strong><u>State List</u></strong> under the Seventh Schedule of the Constitution of India.</li>
<li>Therefore, the <strong><u>laws governing alcohol vary from state to state</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Liquor in India is generally sold at liquor stores, restaurants, hotels, bars, pubs, clubs and discos but not online.</li>
<li>Some states, like Kerala and Tamil Nadu, prohibit private parties from owning liquor stores making the state government the sole retailer of alcohol in those states.</li>
<li>In some states, liquor may be sold at groceries, departmental stores, banquet halls and/or farm houses.</li>
<li>Some tourist areas have special laws allowing the sale of alcohol on beaches and houseboats.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Drunk driving law</h4>
<ul>
<li>The blood alcohol content (BAC) legal limit is 0.03% or 0.03 mg alcohol in 100 ml blood.</li>
<li>On 1 March 2012, the Union Cabinet approved proposed changes to the Motor Vehicle Act.</li>
<li>Higher penalties were introduced, including fines from ₹2,000 to ₹10,000 and imprisonment from 6 months to 4 years.</li>
<li>Different penalties are assessed depending on the blood alcohol content at the time of the offence.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Dry days</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dry days are specific days when the sale of alcohol is not permitted.</li>
<li>Most of the Indian states observe these days on major national festivals/occasions such as Republic Day (26 January), Independence Day (15 August) and Gandhi Jayanti (2 October).</li>
<li>Dry days are also observed during elections in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Taxation on Alcohol</h4>
<ul>
<li>Most states levy either Value added Tax (VAT) or Excise duty or both.</li>
<li>Excise duty is a tax levied to discourage the consumption of a product.</li>
<li>It is calculated on a per-unit basis. Meaning, if you buy 1 litre of liquor, you pay a fixed excise duty of Rs 15.</li>
<li>Value-added Tax is charged in the proportion of the product. If a bottle costs Rs 100, and the state levies 10 percent VAT, the price rises to Rs 110.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Tax rates in States</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 29 states/UTs in India approach liquor taxation differently.</li>
<li>For instance, Gujarat has banned its citizens from consuming liquor since 1961.</li>
<li>But outsiders with special licenses can still buy.</li>
<li>Puducherry, on the other hand, earns most of its revenue from alcohol trading.</li>
<li>Bihar has prohibited alcohol consumption entirely, meaning the state’s revenue from liquor consumption is nil.</li>
<li>Its neighbour, Uttar Pradesh, earns the most excise duty on liquor.</li>
<li>The state does not levy VAT but a special duty on liquor, collecting funds for particular purposes.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Do you know?</strong></h4>
<p>Andhra Pradesh, Telangana, Kerala, Karnataka, and Tamil Nadu consume as much as 45 percent of the liquor sold in the country.</p>
<p>Nationally, Maharashtra charges the highest rate but draws only a portion of its revenue from its sales.</p></blockquote>
<h4>Why alcohol isn’t banned everywhere?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Taxes from alcohol sales roughly form a quarter of state revenues.</li>
<li>If this stream suddenly stops, states have to compulsorily cut some important spending.</li>
<li>Also, moderate alcohol consumption may provide some health benefits.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/alcohol-laws-in-india/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>In news: Sutlej-Yamuna Link (SYL) Canal</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sutlej-yamuna-link-syl-canal-ias/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>SYL Canal</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Interstate water disputes</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632166" height="438" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 409px) 100vw, 409px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/sutlej-280x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/sutlej-280x300.jpg 280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/sutlej.jpg 670w" width="409"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court drew an assurance from the State of Punjab that it will meet the Haryana counterpart within this month to discuss the construction of the Sutlej-Yamuna Link (SYL) Canal which has been languishing for two decades.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The observations came after the Centre complained that Punjab had “refrained” from coming to the negotiating table to engage in talks with Haryana over the issue.</li>
<li>The construction of Punjab’s portion of the canal had led to <strong><u>militant attacks in the 1980s</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The issue had also been a political thorn for successive governments in Punjab, so much so that it led to the State’s unilateral enactment of the <strong><u>controversial Punjab Termination of Water Agreements Act of 2004. </u></strong></li>
<li>This law was, however, <strong><u>struck down by a Constitution Bench in 2016</u></strong>, dashing the hopes of Punjab’s farmers to reclaim lands acquired for the SYL canal project.</li>
</ul>
<h4>About Sutlej-Yamuna Link (SYL) Canal</h4>
<ul>
<li>Satluj Yamuna Link Canal or SYL as it is popularly known, is an under-construction 214-kilometer long canal in India to connect the Sutlej and Yamuna rivers.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the SYL canal issue?</h4>
<ul>
<li>At the time of reorganization of Punjab in 1966, the issue of sharing of river waters between both the states emerged.</li>
<li>Punjab refused to share waters of Ravi and Beas with Haryana stating it was against the riparian principle.</li>
<li>Before the reorganization, in 1955, out of 15.85 MAF of Ravi and Beas, the Centre had allocated 8 MAF to Rajasthan, 7.20 MAF to undivided Punjab, 0.65MAF to Jammu and Kashmir.</li>
<li>Out of 7.20 MAF allocated, Punjab did not want to share any water with Haryana.</li>
<li>In March 1976, when the Punjab Reorganization Act was implemented, the Centre notified fresh allocations, providing 3.5 MAF To Haryana.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Inception of the canal project</h4>
<ul>
<li>Later, in 1981, the water flowing down Beas and Ravi was revised and pegged at 17.17 MAF, out of which 4.22 MAF was allocated to Punjab, 3.5 MAF to Haryana, and 8.6 MAF to Rajasthan.</li>
<li>Finally, to provide this allocated share of water to southern parts of Haryana, a canal linking the Sutlej with the Yamuna, cutting across the state, was planned.</li>
<li>Finally, the construction of 214-km SYL was started in April 1982, 122 km of which was to run through Punjab and the rest through Haryana.</li>
<li>Haryana has completed its side of the canal, but work in Punjab has been hanging fire for over three decades.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why has the SYL canal come up again now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The issue is back on centre stage after the Supreme Court directed the CMs of Punjab and Haryana to negotiate and settle the SYL canal issue.</li>
<li>The apex court asked for a meeting at the highest political level to be mediated by the Centre so that the states reach a consensus over the completion of the SYL canal.</li>
<li>The meeting remained inconclusive with the Centre expressing the view that the construction of the SYL canal should be completed. But Punjab CM refused categorically.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Punjab’s resentment with the project</h4>
<ul>
<li>The dispute is based on the <strong><u>bloody history around the SYL canal</u></strong>. The trouble-torn days of terrorism in Punjab started in the early 1980s when work on the SYL started.</li>
<li>Punjab feels it utilized its precious groundwater resources to grow the crop for the entire country and should not be forced to share its waters as it faces desertification.</li>
<li>It is feared that once the construction of the canal restarts, the youth may start feeling that the state has been discriminated against.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Punjab CM fears Pakistan and secessionist organisations could exploit</u></strong> this and foment trouble in the state.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Water crisis in Punjab</h4>
<ul>
<li>Punjab is facing severe water crisis due to over-exploitation of its underground aquifers for the wheat/paddy monocycle.</li>
<li>According to the Central Underground Water Authority’s report, its underground water is over-exploited to meet the agriculture requirements in about 79 per cent area of the state.</li>
<li>Out of 138 blocks, 109 are “over-exploited”, two are “critical” five are “semi-critical” and only 22 blocks are in “safe” category.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Punjab expects a new tribunal</h4>
<ul>
<li>The state wants a tribunal seeking a fresh time-bound assessment of the water availability.</li>
<li>The state has been saying that till date there has been no adjudication or scientific assessment of Punjab river waters.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this PYQ:</strong></h4>
<p> </p>
<p><strong> Which one of the following pairs is not correctly matched? (CSP 2017)</strong></p>
<p>Dam/Lake River</p>
<p>(a) Govind Sagar: Satluj</p>
<p>(b) Kolleru Lake: Krishna</p>
<p>(c) Ukai Reservoir: Tapi</p>
<p>(d) Wular Lake: Jhelum</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sutlej-yamuna-link-syl-canal-ias/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SC asks Centre, States to allay EWS Quota concerns</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-asks-centre-states-ews-quota-concerns/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>EWS Quota , 103rd Amendment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632163" height="385" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 426px) 100vw, 426px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ews-300x271.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ews-300x271.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ews.jpg 481w" width="426"/></p>
<p>A five-judge Constitution Bench led by CJI U.U. Lalit are hearing petitions challenging the 10% quota for the economically weaker sections (EWS) and an Andhra Pradesh law that grants reservation to Muslims.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The five-judge Bench, led by CJI, is considering the validity of the 103rd Constitutional Amendment.</li>
<li>The said amendment provides the 10% reservation to economically weaker sections (EWS) of society in government jobs and educational institutions.</li>
<li>Economic reservation was introduced by amending Articles 15 and 16 and adding clauses empowering the State governments to provide reservation on the basis of economic backwardness.</li>
</ul>
<h4>EWS Quota: A backgrounder</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 10% reservation was introduced through the 103rd Constitution Amendment and enforced in January 2019.</li>
<li>It added Clause (6) to Article 15 to empower the Government to introduce special provisions for the EWS among citizens except those in the classes that already enjoy reservation.</li>
<li>It allows reservation in educational institutions, both public and private, whether aided or unaided, excluding those run by minority institutions, up to a maximum of 10%.</li>
<li>It also added Clause (6) to Article 16 to facilitate reservation in employment.</li>
<li>The new clauses make it clear that the EWS reservation will be in addition to the existing reservation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of the quota</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Constitution initially allowed special provisions only for the socially and educationally backward classes.</li>
<li>The Government introduced the concept of EWS for a new class of affirmative action program for those not covered by or eligible for the community-based quotas.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the court’s questions about the criteria?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reduction within general category:</strong> The EWS quota remains a controversy as its critics say it reduces the size of the open category, besides breaching the 50% limit on the total reservation.</li>
<li><strong>Arbitrariness over income limit:</strong> The court has been intrigued by the income limit being fixed at ₹8 lakh per year. It is the same figure for excluding the ‘creamy layer’ from OBC reservation benefits.</li>
<li><strong>Socio-economic backwardness:</strong> A crucial difference is that those in the general category, to whom the EWS quota is applicable, do not suffer from social or educational backwardness, unlike those classified as the OBC.</li>
<li><strong>Metropolitan criteria:</strong> There are other questions as to whether any exercise was undertaken to derive the exceptions such as why the flat criterion does not differentiate between metropolitan and non-metropolitan areas.</li>
<li><strong>OBC like criteria:</strong> The question the court has raised is that when the OBC category is socially and educationally backward and, therefore, has additional impediments to overcome.</li>
<li><strong>Not based on relevant data:</strong> In line with the Supreme Court’s known position that any reservation or norms for exclusion should be based on relevant data.</li>
<li><strong>Breaches reservation cap:</strong> There is a cap of 50% on reservation as ruled in the Indira Sawhney Case. The principle of balancing equality ordains reservation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the current status of the EWS quota?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The reservation for the EWS is being implemented by the Union Government for the second year now.</li>
<li>Recruitment test results show that the category has a lower cut-off mark than the OBC, a point that has upset the traditional beneficiaries of reservation based on caste.</li>
<li>The explanation is that only a small number of people are currently applying under the EWS category — one has to get an income certificate from the revenue authorities — and therefore the cut-off is low.</li>
<li>However, when the number picks up over time, the cut-off marks are expected to rise.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Practical issues with EWS Quota</h4>
<p>The EWS quota will come in for judicial scrutiny soon. But it’s not only a matter for the judiciary, India’s Parliament should revisit the law too.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hasty legislation:</strong> This law was passed in haste. It was passed in both the houses within 48 hours, and got presidential approval the next day.</li>
<li><strong>Minority appeasement:</strong> It is widely argued that the law was passed to appease a certain section of upper-caste society and to suppress the demands for minority reservations.</li>
<li><strong>Morality put to question: </strong>Imagine! A constitutional amendment has been made with few hours of deliberation and without consultation of the targeted group. This is certainly against constitutional morality and propriety.</li>
<li><strong>Substantial backing is missing:</strong> This amendment is based on a wrong or unverified premise. This is at best a wild guess or a supposition because the government has not produced any data to back this point.</li>
<li><strong>Under-reservation of Backward Classes:</strong> The assertion is based on the fact that we have different data to prove the under-representation of SC, ST, OBCs. That implies that ‘upper’ castes are over-represented (with 100 minus reservation).</li>
<li><strong>Rationale of 10%:</strong> There is one more problem in this regard. The SC and ST quota is based on their total population. But the rationale for the 10 per cent quota was never discussed.</li>
<li><strong>Principle of Equality:</strong> Economic backwardness is quite a fluid identity. It has nothing to do with historic wrongdoings and liabilities caused to the Backward Classes.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Preserving the merit: </strong>We cannot rule out the sorry state of economic backwardness hampering merit in our country.</li>
<li><strong>Rational critera: </strong>There has to be collective wisdom to define and measure the economic weakness of certain sections of the society in order to shape the concept of economic justice.</li>
<li><strong>Judicial guidance: </strong>Judicial interpretation will pave the wave forward for deciding the criterion for EWS Quota.</li>
<li><strong>Targetted beneficiaries. </strong>The centre needs to resort to more rational criteria for deciding the targeted beneficiary of this reservation system. Caste Census data can be useful in this regard.</li>
<li><strong>Income study: </strong>The per capita income or GDP or the difference in purchasing power in the rural and urban areas, should be taken into account while a single income limit was formulated for the whole country.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Reservation is a constitutional scheme to ensure the participation of backward classes shoulder to shoulder with all citizens in the nation-building process.</li>
<li>The EWS quota with above discussed ambiguities is the subversion of the constitutional scheme for reservation.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-asks-centre-states-ews-quota-concerns/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the idea of Climate Reparation?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-idea-of-climate-reparation/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Climate reparation</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632165" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 100vw, 542px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-1024x684.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-768x513.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-1536x1025.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-1200x801.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-1980x1322.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation.jpg 2000w" width="542"/></p>
<p>Facing the worst <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-urban-deluge-floods/">flooding disaster</a> in its history, <strong><u>Pakistan has begun demanding reparations</u></strong>, or compensation, from the rich countries that are mainly responsible for causing climate change.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>On the face of it, Pakistan’s demand for reparations appears to be a long shot, but the principles being invoked are fairly <strong><u>well-established in environmental jurisprudence</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In fact, <strong><u>Pakistan is not alone</u></strong> in making this demand.</li>
<li>Almost the entire developing world has for years been insisting on setting up an <strong><u>international mechanism for financial reparation</u></strong> for loss and damage caused by climate disasters.</li>
<li>The issue has <strong><u>come up repeatedly at international negotiations</u></strong> for climate change, and on other platforms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Climate Reparation?</h4>
<ul>
<li>At its heart, the demand for compensation for loss and damage from climate disasters is an extension of the universally acknowledged <strong><u>“Polluter Pays” principle</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This makes the polluter liable for paying not just for the cost of remedial action, but also for <strong><u>compensating the victims of environmental damage caused by their actions.</u></strong></li>
<li>Climate justice is based on the <strong><u>notion of not being punished for someone else’s bad behaviour</u></strong>, but it does not sanction additional bad behaviour.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who are responsible for climate change?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the climate change framework, the burden of <strong><u>responsibility falls on those rich countries that have contributed most of the greenhouse gas emissions since 1850</u></strong>, generally considered to be the beginning of the industrial age.</li>
<li>The United States and the European Union, including the UK, account for over 50% of all emissions during this time.</li>
<li>If Russia, Canada, Japan, and Australia too are included, the combined contribution goes past 65%, or almost two-thirds of all emissions.</li>
<li>Historical responsibility is important because carbon dioxide remains in the atmosphere for hundreds of years, and it is the <strong><u>cumulative accumulation of carbon dioxide</u></strong> that causes global warming.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What about developing countries?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A country like India, currently the third largest emitter, <strong>accounts for only 3% of historical emissions</strong>.</li>
<li>China, which is the world’s biggest emitter for over 15 years now, has contributed about <strong><u>11% to total emissions since 1850.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>Why need climate reparations?</h4>
<ul>
<li>While the <strong><u>impact of climate change</u></strong> is global, it is much more <strong><u>severe on the poorer nations</u></strong> because of their geographical locations and weaker capacity to cope.</li>
<li>Countries that have had negligible contributions to historical emissions and <strong><u>have severe limitations of resources</u></strong> are the ones that face the most devastating impacts of climate change.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Institutional mechanism for Climate Reparations</h4>
<h4>(1) United Nations</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>UN Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC)</u></strong>, the 1994 international agreement that lays down the broad principles of the global effort to fight climate change.</li>
<li>It explicitly acknowledges this <strong><u>differentiated responsibility of nations</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It makes it very clear that <strong><u>rich countries must provide both the finance and the technology to the developing nations</u></strong> to help them tackle climate change.</li>
<li>It is this mandate that later evolved into the <strong><u>$100 billion amount that the rich countries agreed to provide</u></strong> every year to the developing world.</li>
<li>While this promise is <strong><u>yet to be met</u></strong>, this $100 billion per year amount is not meant for loss and damage.</li>
<li>Climate disasters were not a regular occurrence in 1994, and as such the <strong><u>UNFCCC does not make a mention of loss and damage. </u></strong></li>
<li>This particular demand emerged much later, and faced <strong><u>stiff resistance from the developed nations</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(2) Warsaw International Mechanism (WIM)</h4>
<ul>
<li>The WIM for Loss and Damages, set up in 2013, was the <strong><u>first formal acknowledgment</u></strong> of the need to <strong><u>compensate developing countries struck by climate disasters</u></strong>.</li>
<li>However, the <strong><u>progress</u></strong> on this front has been painfully <strong><u>slow</u></strong>.</li>
<li><strong><u>No funding mechanism</u></strong>, or even a promise to provide funds, has come about.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Pushback from Developed Countries</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is not hard to understand why the developed countries are dead against compensation claims.</li>
<li>They are struggling to put together even the $100 billion per year flow that they had <strong><u>reluctantly agreed to provide.</u></strong></li>
<li>Further, loss and damage claims can easily spiral into billions of dollars, or even more.</li>
<li>The report said that the United States alone is estimated to have “inflicted more than $1.9 trillion in damages to other countries” due to its emissions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with loss assessment</h4>
<ul>
<li>There are practical difficulties in estimating <strong><u>how much a country has actually suffered</u></strong> due to the actions of others.</li>
<li>To begin with, it has to be established that the <strong><u>disaster was caused by climate change</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Then there are <strong><u>non-economic losses</u></strong> as well, including <strong><u>loss of lives</u></strong>, <strong><u>displacement</u></strong> and <strong><u>migration</u></strong>, <strong><u>health impacts</u></strong>, and <strong><u>damage to cultural heritage</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Then there is this other step about assessing how much of the losses are due to the event itself, and <strong><u>what could be attributed to misgovernance</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>A lot of background work is going on to create the framework in which it would be possible to quantify the compensation due to an affected country.</li>
<li>What Pakistan has done, through its demands for reparations, is to call attention to this often neglected aspect.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-idea-of-climate-reparation/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Electricity Amendment Bill 2022 – Addressing the transition and equity</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/electricity/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of the bill</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>electricity reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="electricity" class="alignnone wp-image-629013" height="343" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download.jpeg" width="558"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Concerns of states on some provisions of the new Electricity Bill are justified. But the legislation proposes welcome correctives to longstanding problems of the power sector.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Important provisions of the bill</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Payment security</strong>: The Bill provides that electricity will not be scheduled or despatched if adequate payment security is not provided by the discom.   The central government may prescribe rules regarding payment security.</li>
<li><strong>Contract enforcement</strong>: The Bill empowers the CERC and SERCs to adjudicate disputes related to the performance of contracts.  These refer to contracts related to the sale, purchase, or transmission of electricity.  Further, the Commissions will have powers of a Civil Court.</li>
<li><strong>Renewable purchase obligation</strong>: The Act empowers SERCs to specify renewable purchase obligations (RPO) for discoms.  RPO refers to the mandate to procure a certain percentage of electricity from renewable sources.  The Bill adds that RPO should not be below a minimum percentage prescribed by the central government.  Failure to meet RPO will be punishable with a penalty between 25 paise and 50 paise per kilowatt of the shortfall.</li>
<li><strong>Selection committee for SERCs</strong>: Under the Act, the Chairperson of the Central Electricity Authority or the Chairperson of the CERC is one of the members of the selection committee to recommend appointments to the SERCs.  Under the Bill, instead of this person, the central government will nominate a member to the selection committee.  The nominee should not be below the rank of Additional Secretary to the central government.</li>
<li><strong>Composition of Commissions and APTEL</strong>: The Bill increases the number of members (including the chairperson) in SERCs from three to four.  Further, at least one member in both the CERC and SERCs must be from law background.  Under the Act, Appellate Tribunal for Electricity (APTEL) consists of a chairperson and three other members.  The Bill instead provides that the APTEL will have three or more members, as may be prescribed by the central government.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>State apprehensions of the bill </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multi state license: </strong>The clause pertaining to applicants seeking a distribution licence in more than one state. It states that the Central Electricity Regulatory Commission (CERC), and not the SERC, will grant the licence. This is problematic because a SERC is likely to be more aware of the field-level conditions in a state than its central counterpart.</li>
<li><strong>Centre can bypass state: </strong>The Bill has a provision empowering the Centre to give directions directly to the SERCs. Till now, the CERC received instructions from the Centre and the SERCs were under the state. The new Bill enables the Centre to bypass state governments. It’s not surprising that this is a matter of concern for the states.</li>
<li><strong>Direct appointment by centre:</strong> The Bill states that the SERC chairperson will now be a nominee of the central government and will be an additional secretary-level official. This gives the impression that the Centre is trying to control the appointments to the SERCs<strong>. </strong></li>
</ul>
<div class="mceTemp"></div>
<p><img alt="electricity" class="alignnone wp-image-629016" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 481px) 100vw, 481px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy-300x208.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy-300x208.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy.jpg 650w" width="481"/></p>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/power-sector-reforms/"><strong>Why the bill is important? </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Compensation clause: </strong>The Bill states that if power purchase agreement PPAs are renegotiated, the affected party has to be compensated within 90 days from the date of submission of the petition.</li>
<li><strong>Uniformity in tariffs revision:</strong> New tariffs have to be made applicable from the beginning of the financial year. New tariffs often come into force in the middle of the financial year (due to delays in the issuing of orders by SERCs). This means that discoms do not earn their full revenues leading to cash flow problems.</li>
<li><strong>Easy tariff petition processing now:</strong> The Bill has proposed a reduction in the time for processing tariff petitions from 120 days to 90 days.</li>
<li><strong>Suo moto jurisdiction</strong>: Regulatory commissions have been given suo motu jurisdiction if tariff petitions are not filed within 30 days of the stipulated time. This too is a step in the right direction.</li>
<li><strong>More teeth to load dispatcher: </strong>the Bill proposes to give more teeth to the national load dispatcher. We need to strengthen the load dispatcher for the smooth functioning of the grid, especially with a huge renewable capacity where intermittency of generation is a major issue in the offing.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The rollout of the proposed amendments through a consensus-based approach would go a long way in overhauling the weakest link in the nation’s power supply chain.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Electricity Bill 2022 is a remedy worse than the disease afflicting India’s power sector. Critically analyse.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/electricity/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Effecting the Ban on Single-Use Plastics</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/effecting-the-ban-on-single-use-plastics/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Single use plastics</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Need for plastic waste management</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-629408" height="234" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 355px) 100vw, 355px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-300x198.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-300x198.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1024x675.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-768x506.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1536x1013.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1200x791.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1980x1306.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban.jpg 2000w" width="355"/></p>
<p>Since July 1, 2022, India has banned the manufacture, import, stocking, distribution, sale, and use of single-use plastics (SUP) items with low utility and high littering potential.</p>
<h4>What are single-use plastics?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Single-use plastics, often also referred to as <strong><u>disposable plastics</u></strong>, are commonly used for plastic packaging and include items intended to be <strong><u>used only once</u></strong> before they are thrown away or recycled.</li>
<li>These include, among other items, grocery bags, food packaging, bottles, straws, containers, cups and cutlery.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why are single-use plastics harmful?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The purpose of single-use plastics is to use them once or for a short period of time before disposing of them. Plastic waste has drastic impacts on the environment and human health.</li>
<li>There is a greater likelihood of single-use plastic products <strong><u>ending up in the sea</u></strong> than reusable ones.</li>
</ul>
<h4>SUP ban in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has taken resolute steps to mitigate pollution caused by littered single-use plastics.</li>
<li>A number of items are banned, including earbuds with plastic sticks, balloon sticks, plastic flags, candy sticks, ice cream sticks, polystyrene (thermocol) for decorations, plates, cups, glasses, cutlery such as forks, spoons, knives, straws etc.</li>
<li>India has also banned plastic or PVC banners less than 100 micron, stirrers, etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the impact on the environment?</h4>
<p><strong>[A] Solid Waste generation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The disposal of plastics is one of the least recognized and most highly problematic areas of plastic’s ecological impact.</li>
<li>Ironically, one of plastic’s most desirable traits: its <strong>durability and resistance to decomposition</strong>, is also the source of one of its greatest liabilities when it comes to the disposal of plastics.</li>
<li>A very small amount of total plastic production (less than 10%) is effectively recycled; the remaining plastic is sent to landfills.</li>
<li>It is destined to remain entombed.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>[B] Ecological Impact</strong></p>
<p><strong>(i) Groundwater and soil pollution</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Plastic is a material made to last forever, and due to the same chemical composition, plastic cannot biodegrade; it breaks down into smaller and smaller pieces.</li>
<li>When buried in a landfill, plastic lies untreated for years.</li>
<li>In the process, toxic chemicals from plastics drain out and seep into groundwater, flowing downstream into lakes and rivers.</li>
<li>The seeping of plastic also causes soil pollution and have now started resulting in presence of micro plastics in soil.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(ii) Water Pollution</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The increased presence of plastic on the ocean surface has resulted in more serious problems.</li>
<li>Since most of the plastic debris that reaches the ocean remains floating for years as it does not decompose quickly, it leads to the dropping of oxygen level in the water.</li>
<li>It has severely affected the survival of marine species.</li>
<li>When oceanic creatures and even birds consume plastic inadvertently, they choke on it which causes a steady decline in their population.</li>
<li>In addition to suffocation, ingestion, and other macro-particulate causes of death in larger birds, fish, and mammals.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>[C] Health Hazards</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Burning of plastic results into formation of a class of flame retardants called as Halogens.</li>
<li>Collectively, these harmful chemicals are known to cause the following severe health problems: cancer, neurological damage, endocrine disruption, birth defects and child developmental disorders etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Ban elsewhere</h4>
<ul>
<li>India is not the first country to ban single-use plastics.</li>
<li>Bangladesh became the first country to ban thin plastic bags in 2002; New Zealand banned plastic bags in July 2019.</li>
<li>China had issued a ban on plastic bags in 2020 with a phased implementation.</li>
<li>As of July 2019, 68 countries have plastic bag bans with varying degrees of enforcement.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the plastic waste management rules in India?</h4>
<ul>
<li>With effect from September 30, 2021 India has the Plastic Waste Management Amendment Rules, 2021.</li>
<li>It prohibited the manufacture, import, stocking, distribution, sale, and use of plastic carry bags whose thickness is less than 75 microns.</li>
<li>From December 31, 2022, plastic carry bags whose thickness is less than 120 microns will be banned.</li>
<li>It means that the ban does not cover all plastic bags; however, it requires the manufacturers to produce plastic bags thicker than 75 microns which was earlier 50 microns.</li>
<li>As per the notification, the standard shall be increased to 120 microns in December this year.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the role of the manufacturer?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In addition, the Ministry of Environment, Forests, and Climate Change notified the Plastic Waste Management Amendment Rules, 2022 on February 16, 2022.</li>
<li>Extended Producer Responsibility (EPR) is the responsibility of a producer for the environmentally sound management of the product until the end of its life.</li>
<li>The guidelines provide a framework to strengthen the circular economy of plastic packaging waste, promote the development of new alternatives to plastic packaging and provide the next steps for moving towards sustainable plastic packaging by businesses.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Various steps taken</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian government has taken steps to promote innovation and create an ecosystem for accelerated adoption and availability of alternatives across the country.</li>
<li>To ensure the effective enforcement of the ban, national and State-level control rooms will be established, as well as special enforcement teams for the purpose of checking the illegal sale and use of single-use plastics.</li>
<li>To prevent the movement of banned single-use plastic items between States and Union Territories, border checkpoints have been established.</li>
<li>In an effort to empower citizens to help curb the plastic menace, the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB) has launched a grievance redressal application.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the challenges?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ban will succeed only if all stakeholders participate enthusiastically and engage in effective engagement and concerted actions.</li>
<li>However, if we look back at our past, almost 25 Indian States previously banned plastic at the state level.</li>
<li>However, these bans had a very limited impact in reality because of the widespread use of these items.</li>
<li>Now the challenge is to see how the local level authorities will enforce the ban in accordance with the guidelines.</li>
<li>Banned items such as earbuds with plastic sticks, plastic sticks for balloons, etc., are non-branded items and it is difficult to find out who the manufacturer is and who is accountable.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>The consumer needs to be informed about the ban through advertisements, newspaper or TV commercials, or on social media.</li>
<li>In order to find sustainable alternatives, companies need to invest in research and development.</li>
<li>The solution to the plastic pollution problem is not the responsibility of the government alone, but of industries, brands, manufacturers and most importantly consumers.</li>
<li>Finding alternatives to plastic seems a little difficult, however, greener alternatives to plastic may be considered a sustainable option.</li>
<li>For example, compostable and bio-degradable plastic, etc., may be considered as an option.</li>
<li>While the total ban on the use of plastic sounds a great idea, its feasibility seems difficult at this hour, especially in the absence of workable alternatives.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/effecting-the-ban-on-single-use-plastics/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Fruit Fly: Novel method to study Nuclear Matrix</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nuclear Matrix</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627770" height="489" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 566px) 100vw, 566px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly.jpg 665w" width="566"/></p>
<p>Now, using a novel method, Indian researchers have established a way of studying the nuclear matrix of the fruit fly (Drosophila melanogaster) without removing the nucleus from the embryo.</p>
<h4>Nuclear Matrix of fruit flies</h4>
<ul>
<li>Every cell that makes up an organism contains a copy of its genome.</li>
<li>This genome is packaged in special ways with the help of a structure known as the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>The nuclear matrix gives an organisation and architecture to the nucleus.</li>
<li>A familiar figure, the nuclear matrix of fruit flies, for instance, has been studied for many years, mainly by isolating it in nuclei that have been taken out from fruit fly embryos.</li>
<li>This allows comparative study of nuclear matrix in different cells within the embryo, giving a boost for fruit fly genetics.</li>
<li>Two of the most recent papers on this work have been published in the journals Nucleus and Molecular and Cell Proteomics.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What exactly is Nuclear Matrix?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The nuclear matrix is like a scaffolding.</li>
<li>Using biochemical means, if the nucleus is taken out and treated with an enzyme that digests all the DNA.</li>
<li>It is then washed with a solution of high salt concentration so that viable DNA proteins or protein-protein interactions are removed.</li>
<li>What is then left is a fibrous meshwork of proteins called the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>This is like a building from which all movables have been sucked out, leaving only the beams, ceiling, and walls, plug points, etc.</li>
<li>Analogous to the building, the nuclear matrix creates the architecture in which the genome is packaged.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why study them?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Studying the nuclear matrix is, therefore, very important to get a better picture of how precisely development progresses every time a new individual is born.</li>
<li>We have 220 different types of cells in the body, but all contain identical genomes.</li>
<li>The same genome sequence is present in neurons, where it works for thinking; in the liver, the same sequence enacts metabolism; and in the intestine, it works to digest.</li>
<li>So, this information is packaged differently in different cell types.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Revisiting the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-627767" height="188" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-768x481.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji.jpg 885w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has referred to a three-judge Bench a series of petitions seeking a judicial direction that political parties who make wild promises should also reveal in their poll manifestos where they will get the money to pay for them.</p>
<p>The reference is a shift from the court’s own stand in the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs Tamil Nadu judgment of 2013.</p>
<h4>Hefty promises: A no lesser corrupt practice</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the <strong><u>Balaji case judgment</u></strong>, a Division Bench of the Supreme Court had held that making promises in election manifestos <strong><u>do not amount to a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> under Section 123 of the Representation of People Act (RP).</li>
<li>However, the Supreme Court is now worried that <strong><u>freebies promised</u></strong> by political parties to win elections could <strong><u>bleed the public exchequer dry</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Court said that parties who form the government riding the wave created by their pre-poll promises of free gifts are bleeding the State finances dry.</li>
<li>Parties actually try to <strong><u>fulfil their outlandish promises using public money</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Supreme Court has therefore decided to revisit the Balaji verdict.</p>
<h4>What triggered the Balaji case?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The course of events started in 2006, during the run-up to the Tamil Nadu Assembly elections.</li>
<li>A party released its election manifesto announcing a scheme of free distribution of colour television sets (CTVs) to each and every household if voted to power.</li>
<li>The party swept to power in the polls and decided to implement its scheme and portioned off ₹750 crore from the budget for the project.</li>
<li>The government finally distributed 30,000 TV sets across the State.</li>
<li>In 2011, the rival party also announced its election manifesto with free gifts to “equalise” the gifts offered.</li>
<li>It promised grinders, mixies, electric fans, laptop computers, four gram gold thalis, a cheque of ₹50,000 for women’s marriage, green houses, 20 kg of rice to ration card holders and free cattle and sheep.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Balaji case</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji, a resident of Tamil Nadu, challenged the schemes introduced by the parties in the Madras High Court.</li>
<li>He said that the <strong><u>expenditure was incurred by the State from the exchequer</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This was “<strong><u>unauthorised, impermissible and ultra vires the constitutional mandates</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>High Court dismissed his case</u></strong>, following which he had moved the apex court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did the case play out?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji argued that <strong><u>the State cannot act</u></strong> in furtherance of “<strong><u>eccentric principles of socialistic philanthropy</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>He argued that the promises of <strong><u>free distribution of non-essential commodities</u></strong> in an election manifesto amounts to electoral bribe under Section 123 of the RP Act.</li>
<li>Money can be taken out of the Consolidated Fund of the State <strong><u>only for “public purposes”</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>distribution of goods to certain sections</u></strong> of people was <strong><u>violative of Article 14 of the Constitution</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Argument provided against the Balaji Case</h4>
<ul>
<li>In response, the State of Tamil Nadu countered that <strong><u>promises do not constitute corrupt practice. </u></strong></li>
<li>Political parties are not the State and ‘<strong><u>freebies’ is a nebulous term which has no legal status</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises implemented by the party after forming the government is an <strong><u>obligation under the Directives Principles of State Policy</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The State is only doing its duty to promote the <strong><u>welfare of its people</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises are <strong><u>implemented by framing various schemes/guidelines/eligibility</u></strong> criteria etc. as well as <strong><u>with the approval of the legislature. </u></strong></li>
<li>Thus, it <strong><u>cannot be construed as a waste of public money</u></strong> or be prohibited by any statute or scheme.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Outcome of the Judgement</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court’s judgment held that <strong><u>promises by a political party cannot constitute a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> on its part.</li>
<li>It would be <strong><u>“misleading” to generalize</u></strong> that all promises in the election manifesto would amount to corrupt practice.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>manifesto is a statement of the policy</u></strong> for a political party.</li>
<li>The question of implementing the manifesto arises only if the political party forms a government.</li>
<li>It is the promise of a future government and not of an individual candidate.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Scope for revisiting the judgment</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court agreed that <strong><u>freebies create an “uneven playing field”.</u></strong></li>
<li>It had asked the Election Commission of India to <strong><u>consult political parties</u></strong> and issue guidelines on the election manifesto and make it a <strong><u>part of the Model Code of Conduct</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the Court’s move to review the Balaji judgment significant?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In its order, the court foresees that “freebies may create a situation wherein the <strong><u>State governments cannot provide basic amenities due to lack of funds</u></strong> and the State is pushed towards imminent bankruptcy”.</li>
<li>The court said it wants a <strong><u>transparent debate</u></strong> before the three-judge Bench on whether an “enforceable” judicial order can stop political parties from promising and distributing ‘irrational freebies’.</li>
<li>The case is unique as the Supreme Court is exploring <strong><u>whether judicial parameters can be set on a purely political act of promising freebies.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Dynamic leadership of Bose should always be remembered</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bose/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Indian national army particuars</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Modern Indian history developments</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="bose" class="alignnone wp-image-632639" height="397" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 430px) 100vw, 430px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bosenehru-300x277.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bosenehru-300x277.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bosenehru.jpg 654w" width="430"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the year of ‘Azadi Ka Amrit Mahotsav’, the nation pays tribute to Subhas Bose on September 8 as his statue rises tall next to India Gate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Crux of this article in simple words</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The transfer of power to India took place on August 15, 1947. Had Bose and his Indian National Army (INA) succeeded, India would have attained freedom, not inherited it through a transfer of power.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Brief of historical account of his career</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bose was the ninth child in 14 and the sixth son to Janakinath Bose, a lawyer from the Kayasth caste.</li>
<li>He passed matriculation in 1913 from Cuttack and joined the Presidency College in Kolkata (then Calcutta).</li>
<li>The teachings of Swami Vivekananda and Ramakrishna Paramhansa led to a spiritual awakening in Bose at the young age of 15.</li>
<li>Subhash Chandra Bose reached Singapore on July 2, 1943, at the invitation of Rash Behari Bose. He took charge as the President of the Indian Independence League and took over as the leader for East Asia.</li>
<li>On October 23 1943, with the help of the Japanese Army, Netaji declared war on the United States and Britain.</li>
<li>He was fondly called Netaji and was arrested 11 times in his freedom struggle and died under mysterious circumstances in an air crash over Taipei.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="bose" class="alignnone wp-image-632641" height="246" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 467px) 100vw, 467px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-4-300x158.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-4-300x158.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-4.jpeg 310w" width="467"/>His vision for INA march in India </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Creating revolutionary conditions: </strong>Bose had hoped to capture Imphal. That would give the INA a large number of Indian soldiers. Once this was achieved, fighting in India would create revolutionary conditions.</li>
<li><strong>Organization of INA divisions at border: </strong>When the fighting commenced, the INA had only one division stationed on India’s borders. Another was on the move towards Burma. And the third was in the process of formation. All three divisions were expected to be in Burma by the time Imphal fell.</li>
<li><strong>Rapid invasion from north east:</strong> Bose was confident of raising three more divisions from among the Indian troops that would fall to him after the capture of Imphal. With six divisions, the INA would be the single largest force in the region. The rapid advance into India would create the right conditions for the Indian army to switch sides along with the people of the Northeast.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/history-of-popular-slogans-raised-during-freedom-struggle/"><strong>His famous quotes for value addition</strong></a></p>
<p>“It is our duty to pay for our liberty with our own blood.”</p>
<p>“No great change in history has ever been achieved by discussions”</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="bose" class="alignnone wp-image-632642" height="288" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 540px) 100vw, 540px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bose-300x160.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bose-300x160.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bose-768x409.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bose.jpg 782w" width="540"/>Azad Hind Radio</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>This radio station was created to encourage countrymen to fight for freedom under the leadership of Subhas Chandra Bose.</li>
<li>The radio station used to broadcast news at weekly intervals in various languages like English, Hindi, Tamil, Punjabi, Urdu, etc.</li>
<li>The main aim for the formation of the Azad Hind Radio was to counter the broadcast of allied radio stations and to fill Indian nationals with pride and motivation to fight for freedom.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The Rani Jhansi Regiment</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Netaji Subhas Chandra Bose was a firm believer of women’s power and women were also greatly inspired by his words.</li>
<li>He had always wanted to form an only women’s regiment and his dream came to fruition with the formation of the Rani Jhansi Regiment on 12th July 1943.</li>
<li>About 170 women cadets joined the force and their training camp was set in Singapore.</li>
<li>They were given ranks according to their educational background.</li>
<li>By November of 1943, this unit had more than 300 cadets as camps were also established in Rangoon and Bangkok.</li>
<li>The women cadets were given military and combat training, weapons training, and route marches. Some of them were also chosen for advanced training and some were also chosen for training as a nurse.</li>
<li>The Rani Jhansi Regiment mainly worked as care and relief givers.</li>
<li>The unit later disbanded after the fall of Rangoon and the withdrawal of the Azad Hind Government.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bose maintained that the Congress leaders wanted freedom in their lifetime. He believed that no revolutionary leader had the right to expect that. A movement, a fight, had to be passed on. Expecting freedom in one’s lifetime was bound to lead to compromises.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Netaji Subhas Bose was an exceptional leader who turned his vision into action. Critically analyse. </strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bose/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>[pib] CoE – SURVEI standardizes Drone images for land Survey</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/survei-standardizes-drone-images-for-land-survey/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CoE-SURVEI</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Centre of Excellence on Satellite and Unmanned Remote Vehicle Initiative (CoE-SURVEI) has developed an Artificial Intelligence-based software which can automatically detect change on the ground, including unauthorised constructions and encroachments in a time series using satellite imagery.</p>
<h4>CoE-SURVEI</h4>
<ul>
<li>The CoE-SURVEI, established by Directorate General Defence Estates at National Institute of Defence Estates Management, leverages the latest technologies in survey viz. satellite imagery, drone imagery and geo-spatial tools for effective land management and urban planning.</li>
<li>This change detection software has been developed by CoE-SURVEI in collaboration with knowledge partner Bhabha Atomic Research Centre (BARC), Visakhapatnam.</li>
<li>Presently, the tool uses National Remote Sensing Centre (NRSC) Cartosat-3 imagery with trained software.</li>
<li>The changes are detected by analysing satellite imagery of different time periods.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where is it used?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The application has been used by CoE in 62 Cantonments and a comparison has been done with the ground position in a recent period.</li>
<li>The software facilitates better control of unauthorised activities, ensures accountability of field staff and helps in reducing corrupt practices.</li>
<li>The CoE-SURVEI has also developed tools for vacant land analysis and 3D image analysis of hill cantonments</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/survei-standardizes-drone-images-for-land-survey/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Rajpath, Central Vista lawns renamed ‘Kartavya Path’</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rajpath-renamed-kartavya-path/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Kartavya Path</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632651" height="243" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 445px) 100vw, 445px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kartavya-300x164.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kartavya-300x164.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kartavya-768x419.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kartavya.jpg 954w" width="445"/></p>
<p>Rajpath and <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/back-in-news-central-vista-project-2/">Central Vista Lawns</a> in the national capital will now be known as “Kartavya Path”, the New Delhi Municipal Council (NDMC) announces.</p>
<h4>Updating to Kartavya Path</h4>
<ul>
<li>The entire stretch and the area from the Netaji statue under the Grand Canopy to the Rashtrapati Bhavan will be known as Kartavya Path.</li>
<li>Kartavya Path, which will be opened to the public at the end of the official function, will exhibit landscapes, lawns with walkways, added green spaces, refurbished canals, amenity blocks, improved signages and vending kiosks.</li>
<li>New pedestrian underpasses, improved parking spaces, new exhibition panels, and upgraded night lighting are some other features that will enhance the public experience.</li>
<li>It also includes a number of sustainability features like solid waste management, storm-water management, recycling of used water, rainwater harvesting, water conservation and energy-efficient lighting systems, among others.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Kingsway to Rajpath</h4>
<ul>
<li>Called Kingsway during British rule, the three-km stretch was built as a ceremonial boulevard by Edwin Lutyens and Herbert Baker, the architects of New Delhi, more than a hundred years ago.</li>
<li>The capital of the Raj moved to New Delhi from Calcutta in 1911, and construction continued for several years thereafter.</li>
<li>Lutyens conceptualised the modern imperial city centred on a “ceremonial axis”, which was named Kingsway in honour of the then Emperor of India, George V.</li>
<li>He visited Delhi during the Durbar of 1911, where he formally proclaimed the decision to move the capital.</li>
<li>The nomenclature followed that of the Kingsway in London, an arterial road built in 1905, which was named in honour of King Edward VII, the father of George V.</li>
<li>Following Independence, the road was given its Hindi name, Rajpath, on which the Republic Day parades took place over the decades that followed.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why sudden renaming?</h4>
<ul>
<li>During his address from the Red Fort on August 15, Modi had stressed on the abolition of symbols of colonialism.</li>
<li>The new name and look of Rajpath, as well as the installation of the 28-foot statue of Netaji under the Grand Canopy under which a statue of George V once stood, are meant to represent that spirit of the proud new India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of all recent event</h4>
<ul>
<li>The construction of the Central Vista Redevelopment Project began in February 2021, with the new Parliament building and redevelopment of the Central Vista Avenue in the first phase.</li>
<li>The aim is to build an iconic avenue that truly befits the New India, the government has said about the Rs 608 crore Central Vista Avenue project.</li>
<li>It symbolizes a shift from erstwhile Rajpath being an icon of power to Kartavya Path being an example of public ownership and empowerment.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rajpath-renamed-kartavya-path/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>CSR needs positive reforms to support NGO’S</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/csr/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of funding</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>corporate governance</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="CSR" class="alignnone wp-image-632655" height="240" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 459px) 100vw, 459px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-300x157.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-300x157.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-1024x536.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-768x402.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-1536x804.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-2048x1072.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-1200x628.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-1980x1036.jpg 1980w" width="459"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The evolving role of CSR in funding NGOs</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is NGO?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A non-governmental organization is an organization that generally is formed independent from government. They are typically non-profit entities, and many of them are active in humanitarianism or the social sciences; they can also include clubs and associations that provide services to their members and others.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/a-case-against-punishing-non-compliance-of-csr-guidelines/"><strong>What is CSR?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Corporate social responsibility CSR is a form of international private business self-regulation which aims to contribute to societal goals of a philanthropic, activist, or charitable nature by engaging in or supporting volunteering or ethically oriented practices.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why NGO’s are important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When COVID-19 spurred a nationwide lockdown in India in 2020, a grave need for localised social support emerged. Giving, both private and public, flowed to NGOs working towards combating pandemic-induced challenges such as loss of livelihood for vulnerable communities, food banks, and health and medical support.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>CSR key fact</strong></p>
<p><em>All companies with a net worth of Rs 500 crore or more, a turnover of Rs 1,000 crore or more, or net profit of Rs 5 crore or more, are required to spend 2 per cent of their average profits of the previous three years on CSR activities every year<strong>.</strong></em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="CSR" class="alignnone wp-image-632656" height="429" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-768x768.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-900x900.jpg 900w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-1200x1200.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-1980x1980.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118.jpg 2000w" width="429"/>Issues with CSR funding to NGO</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>No organization development: </strong>CSR funders mostly contribute little or no money to organisational development and limit what they pay for indirect costs to a fixed rate often below 5%. 2020 primary research showed that NGOs’ indirect costs range from 5% to 55%, depending on their mission and operating model, much as a corporate’s sales and administration costs vary significantly by industry and product.</li>
<li><strong>Regulatory framework:</strong> These practices are partly a consequence of CSR funders’ focus on regulatory compliance amendments to the CSR law in 2021 include substantial financial penalties for noncompliance.</li>
<li><strong>Errors on safety:</strong> Many CSRs make errors on safety with the unintended consequence of leaving an NGO with unpaid bills or worse still, drawing on its scarce core funding from other donors to pay for these essential costs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="CSR" class="alignnone wp-image-632657" height="237" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-1.jpeg" width="405"/>How to improve CSR governance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increase transparency: </strong>Transparency is the ultimate trust-builder, and should be considered a guiding principle for any socially responsible company. This concept should apply to goals, ongoing initiatives, and ultimate progress or results.</li>
<li><strong>Focus on equity: </strong>Equity is a vital lens through which to evaluate business practices and CSR strategy, at both a micro and macro level. Not only is ensuring that program furthers social and racial justice a cornerstone of the very essence of corporate responsibility, but study after study establishes that improved diversity and inclusion leads to better outcomes for everyone from increased innovation and competitiveness, to stronger ethics and team culture.</li>
<li><strong>Deepen community connections: </strong>Deepening your organization’s connection to those on the other side of your CSR projects will have far-reaching benefits. These could likely include developing a more impactful program, as you strengthen your understanding of the needs of the community served.</li>
<li><strong>Encourage creativity</strong>: Creativity as a principle may feel out of place in a discussion of how to improve CSR. Yet it’s a concept increasingly invoked in philanthropic thought leadership, and for good reason.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The idea is to move beyond signing cheques to recognising that, ultimately, what’s good for Indian society is also good for business.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. why the role of CSR is becoming important in NGO funding? What are the issues with CSR? Discuss the way forward.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/csr/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Concrete supply chain is needed for nutritional security</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/supply-chain/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Food security</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="supply chain" class="alignnone wp-image-632662" height="303" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 491px) 100vw, 491px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hd2g1flc_wheat-export-ban-pti_625x300_16_May_22-300x185.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hd2g1flc_wheat-export-ban-pti_625x300_16_May_22-300x185.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hd2g1flc_wheat-export-ban-pti_625x300_16_May_22-1024x630.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hd2g1flc_wheat-export-ban-pti_625x300_16_May_22-768x473.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hd2g1flc_wheat-export-ban-pti_625x300_16_May_22-1200x739.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hd2g1flc_wheat-export-ban-pti_625x300_16_May_22.jpg 1230w" width="491"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Disruption of supply chains due to Ukraine war has implications for India’s food security</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is supply chain in simple words?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A supply chain is the network of all the individuals, organizations, resources, activities and technology involved in the creation and sale of a product.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Is supply chain management related to agriculture?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Agribusiness, supply chain management (SCM) implies managing the relationships between the businesses responsible for the efficient production and supply of products from the farm level to the consumers to meet consumers’ requirements reliably in terms of quantity, quality and price.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="supply chain" class="alignnone wp-image-632663" height="267" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupplyChain_FQU0520-1024x607-1-300x178.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupplyChain_FQU0520-1024x607-1-300x178.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupplyChain_FQU0520-1024x607-1-768x455.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupplyChain_FQU0520-1024x607-1.jpg 1024w" width="450"/>What are two types of food chain?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Agriculture food supply chains for fresh agricultural products: </strong>(such as fresh vegetables, flowers, fruit). In general, these chains may comprise growers, auctions, wholesalers, importers and exporters, retailers and speciality shops and their input and service suppliers. Basically, all of these stages leave the intrinsic characteristics of the product grown or produced untouched. The main processes are the handling, conditioned storing, packing, transportation and especially trading of these goods.</li>
<li><strong>Agriculture food supply chains for processed food products: </strong>(such as portioned meats, snacks, juices, desserts, canned food products). In these chains, agricultural products are used as raw materials for producing consumer products with higher added value. In most cases, conservation and conditioning processes extend the shelf-life of the products<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/food-procurement-and-distribution/"><strong><img alt="supply chain" class="alignnone wp-image-632665" height="249" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 442px) 100vw, 442px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513-768x433.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513-1200x676.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513.jpg 1598w" width="442"/>Supply chain issues </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Shelf-life constraints for raw materials, intermediates and finished products and changes in product quality level while progressing the supply chain (decay).</li>
<li>High volume, low variety (although the variety is increasing) production systems.</li>
<li>Importance of production planning and scheduling focusing on high capacity utilization.</li>
<li>Highly sophisticated capital-intensive machinery leading to the need to maintain capacity utilization.</li>
<li>Variable process yield in quantity and quality due to biological variations, seasonality, random factors connected with weather, pests and other biological hazards.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What should we do to ensure nutritional security?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Strengthening and shortening food supply chains</strong>: reinforcing regional food systems, food processing, agricultural resilience and sustainability in a climate-changing world will require prioritising research and investments along these lines.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure</strong>: Lastly, infrastructure and institutions supporting producers, agripreneurs and agricultural micro, small and medium enterprises (MSMEs) in their production value chain are central to the transition.</li>
<li><strong>Potential for crop diversification</strong>: Data compiled in the agro-climatic zones reports of the Indian Council of Agricultural Research and the erstwhile Planning Commission of India reveal enormous potential for crop diversification and precision for enhanced crop productivity based on soil type, climate (temperature and rainfall), and captive water resources.</li>
<li><strong>Holistic policy approach: </strong>In the context of the intensifying economic, environmental and climate challenges and crisis, the need of the hour is a good theory of transition encompassing the spatial, social and scientific dimensions, supported by policy incentives and mechanisms for achieving a sustainable, resilient and food secure agriculture<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Agro-climatic approach: </strong>An agro-climatic approach to agricultural development is important for sustainability and better nutrition.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Transparency:</strong> The Indian government could ensure more transparency on food stocks and regulate the private sector.</li>
<li><strong>Set restriction on hoarding:</strong> For that, there is a need to set restrictions on the reserves that the private sector can hold, as they often tend to hoard food stocks to later sell at a profit.</li>
<li><strong>Speculation should be regulated</strong>: This will help prevent the opaqueness of private sector reserves, which often fuels speculation by large international financial actors.</li>
<li><strong>Positional limits:</strong> Internationally, positional limits could be set on speculators but that would require a multilateral accord, a topic which should be on the agenda at the next G-20 meeting.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What role supply chain play in nutritional security? Discuss the constraints in supply chain along with way forward.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/supply-chain/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Mandatory requirements for Packaged Commodities</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mandatory-packaged-commodities/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Rule for Packaged Commodities</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632653" height="420" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 372px) 100vw, 372px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/package-266x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/package-266x300.jpg 266w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/package.jpg 563w" width="372"/></p>
<p>The Department of Consumer Affairs, Legal Metrology Division has notified a draft amendment to the Legal Metrology (Packaged Commodities) Rules 2011 making some compulsions.</p>
<h4>Discrepancies over Packaged Commodities</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Division has observed that many manufacturers/packagers/importers <strong><u>do not clearly label necessary declarations or prime constituents</u></strong> on the front of packaged commodities.</li>
<li>It is common for consumers to assume that brands’ claims are accurate, but such <strong><u>claims are usually misleading.</u></strong></li>
<li>Such disclosure are deemed essential in order <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/five-new-rights-you-get-as-a-consumer/">to protect consumer rights</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the mandatory provisions under the Legal Metrology (Packaged Commodities) Rules, 2011?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is mandatory under the Rules, to ensure a number of declarations, such as the:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Name and address of the manufacturer/packer/importer,</li>
<li>Country of origin,</li>
<li>Common or generic name of the commodity,</li>
<li>Net quantity,</li>
<li>Month and year of manufacture</li>
<li>Maximum Retail Price (MRP) and</li>
<li>Consumer care information.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>As a consumer-oriented policy, all pre-packaged commodities should also be inspected.</li>
<li>Rule 9(1)(a) provides that the declaration on the package must be legible and prominent.</li>
<li>The consumers’ ‘right to be informed’ is violated when important declarations are not prominently displayed on the package.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the proposed amendments?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As many <strong><u>blended food and cosmetic products</u></strong> are sold on the market, the <strong><u>key constituents need to be mentioned</u></strong> on the product packaging.</li>
<li>Additionally, the front side of the package must contain the <strong><u>percentage of the composition of the unique selling proposition (USP). </u></strong></li>
<li>Also, packages displaying key constituents must display a <strong><u>percentage of the content</u></strong> used to make the product.</li>
<li>The new amendments has suggested that <strong><u>at least two prime components should be declared on the package’s front side</u></strong> along with the brand name.</li>
<li>Currently, manufacturers list the ingredients and nutritional information only on the <strong><u>back of the packaging</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This declaration <strong><u>must also include the percentage/quantity of the USPs of the product</u></strong> in the same font size as the declaration of the USPs. However, mechanical or electrical commodities are excluded from this sub-rule.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Consumer Rights</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632652" height="317" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 436px) 100vw, 436px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/consumer-300x218.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/consumer-300x218.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/consumer.jpg 554w" width="436"/></p>
<p>Consumer right is an insight into what rights consumer holds when it comes to the seller who provides the goods.</p>
<p>In general, the consumer rights in India are listed below:</p>
<p><strong>(1) Right to Safety</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Means right to be protected against the marketing of goods and services, which are hazardous to life and property.</li>
<li>The purchased goods and services should not only meet their immediate needs, but also fulfil long term interests.</li>
<li>Before purchasing, consumers should insist on the quality of the products as well as on the guarantee of the products and services. They should preferably purchase quality marked products such as ISI, AGMARK, etc.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Right to be Informed</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Means right to be informed about the quality, quantity, potency, purity, standard and price of goods so as to protect the consumer against unfair trade practices.</li>
<li>Consumer should insist on getting all the information about the product or service before making a choice or a decision.</li>
<li>This will enable him to act wisely and responsibly and also enable him to desist from falling prey to high pressure selling techniques.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Right to Choose</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Means right to be assured, wherever possible of access to variety of goods and services at competitive price. In case of monopolies, it means right to be assured of satisfactory quality and service at a fair price.</li>
<li>It also includes right to basic goods and services. This is because unrestricted right of the minority to choose can mean a denial for the majority of its fair share.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Right to be Heard</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Means that consumer’s interests will receive due consideration at appropriate forums. It also includes right to be represented in various forums formed to consider the consumer’s welfare.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Right to Seek redressal</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Means right to seek redressal against unfair trade practices or unscrupulous exploitation of consumers. It also includes right to fair settlement of the genuine grievances of the consumer.</li>
<li>Consumers must make complaint for their genuine grievances. Many a times their complaint may be of small value but its impact on the society as a whole may be very large.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Right to Consumer Education</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Means the right to acquire the knowledge and skill to be an informed consumer throughout life.</li>
<li>Ignorance of consumers, particularly of rural consumers, is mainly responsible for their exploitation.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mandatory-packaged-commodities/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Positive Secularism is allowed: Student to SC in hijab case</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/positive-secularism-hijab-case/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Secularism in India</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Hijab Row</p></div></div><p>India believes in ‘positive secularism’ based on tolerance of all religious faiths and not ‘negative secularism’ followed in countries like France which holds that display of religion in public is offensive, said a student from Karnataka who has challenged the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-freedom-of-religion-and-attire/">ban on wearing hijab</a> to school.</p>
<h4>What is Positive Secularism?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Secularism is most commonly defined as the separation of religion from civic affairs and the state.</li>
<li>It may be broadened to a similar position seeking to remove or to minimize the role of religion in any public sphere.</li>
<li>Positive secularism is where the state plays an enabler role in the exercise of fundamental rights and the religious freedoms of all communities.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What did the petitioner argue?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The petitioner replied that the Constitution itself says that all religions have to be treated with equal respect.</li>
<li>It said that the Supreme Court has also held in the <strong><u>Aruna Roy Judgment</u></strong> that there should be no discrimination on the ground of any religion.</li>
<li>It went on to say that the State should show <strong>‘<u>reasonable accommodation</u>’</strong> of Muslim students’ right to wear hijab to school as a part of her <strong><u>right to expression, religion and dignity</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Circumstances where hijab can be prohibited in school</h4>
<p>The State can only restrict her right in three circumstances, the petition highlighted.</p>
<ol>
<li>One, to protect <strong><u>public order, morality and health</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Two, to <strong><u>protect another fundamental right</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Three, if such a <strong><u>restriction is authorised by a law</u></strong> made to regulate or restrict any economic, financial, political or secular activity which may be associated with religious practice or to provide for social welfare and reform.</li>
</ol>
<h4>What was the judgment announced by Karnataka HC?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The HC held that wearing hijab is <strong><u>not an essential religious practice</u></strong> in Islam and is not, therefore, protected under by the right to freedom of religion guaranteed by Article 25 of the Constitution.</li>
<li>The court said it was a <strong><u>reasonable restriction that was constitutionally permissible</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Bench also upheld the <strong><u>legality of the order prescribing guidelines for uniforms</u></strong> in schools and pre-university colleges under the provisions of the Karnataka Education Act, 1983.</li>
<li>The court said that <strong><u>school uniform will cease to be a uniform if hijab is also allowed</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="YzKC1QOxQZ"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-freedom-of-religion-and-attire/">[Burning Issue] Freedom of religion and attire</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="YzKC1QOxQZ" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-freedom-of-religion-and-attire/embed/#?secret=SFcf1ZbYEF#?secret=YzKC1QOxQZ" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Burning Issue] Freedom of religion and attire” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/positive-secularism-hijab-case/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India-Bangla Trade, now set for CEPA boost</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-bangla-trade-now-set-for-cepa-boost/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CEPA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Bilateral trade agreements</p></div></div><p><img alt="cepa" class="alignnone wp-image-632677" height="283" sizes="(max-width: 502px) 100vw, 502px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cepa-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cepa-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cepa.jpg 687w" width="502"/></p>
<p>India and Bangladesh will soon commence negotiations on a Bilateral Comprehensive Economic Partnership Agreement (CEPA).</p>
<h4>Glimpse of bilateral trade between India and Bangladesh</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2021-22, Bangladesh has emerged as the <strong><u>largest trade partner for India</u></strong> in South Asia and the <strong><u>fourth largest destination for Indian exports worldwide.</u></strong></li>
<li>India is <strong><u>Bangladesh’s second biggest trade partner</u></strong>, and its largest export market in Asia.</li>
<li>Despite Covid-19 related disruptions, bilateral trade grew at an unprecedented rate of almost 44 per cent from $10.78 billion in 2020-21 to $18.13 billion in 2021-22.</li>
<li>India’s main exports to Bangladesh are raw cotton, non-retail pure cotton yarn, and electricity, and its main imports from the country are pure vegetable oils, non-knit men’s suits, and textile scraps.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is CEPA?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The partnership agreement or cooperation agreement is more comprehensive than an Free Trade Agreement (FTA).</li>
<li>CECA/CEPA also looks into the regulatory aspect of trade and encompasses an agreement covering the regulatory issues.</li>
<li>CECA has the widest coverage. CEPA covers negotiation on the trade in services and investment and other areas of economic partnership.</li>
<li>It may even consider negotiation in areas such as trade facilitation and customs cooperation, competition, and IPR.</li>
<li>India has signed CEPAs with South Korea and Japan.</li>
</ul>
<h4>CEPA objectives</h4>
<ul>
<li>While informal talks on CEPA have been happening since 2018, officials said that the <strong><u>pandemic has brought urgency. </u></strong></li>
<li><strong><u>Chinese investments were an initial trigger</u></strong> for India, but New Delhi and Dhaka want to step up the pace following the economic shock faced by the two economies.</li>
<li>The CEPA is likely to focus on trade in goods, services, and investment, with a key objective being the <strong><u>reduction of the trade gap between the two countries</u></strong>.</li>
<li>As Bangladesh prepares to graduate into a <strong><u>developing nation by 2026</u></strong> — after which <strong><u>it may no longer qualify for trade benefits</u></strong> that it currently enjoys as a least-developed country — it is keen to clinch the CEPA in a year.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the existing frameworks?</h4>
<p>The current institutional frameworks for trade and investment include:</p>
<ul>
<li>During the visit of Prime Minister Modi to Bangladesh in June 2015, the <strong><u>bilateral trade agreement</u></strong> between the two countries was renewed for a period of five years with a provision for auto renewal.</li>
<li>Under the provisions of the <strong><u>South Asian Free Trade Area (SAFTA)</u></strong>, Bangladesh extends preferential tariffs to Indian exports of products outside the ‘sensitive list’ of 993 items.</li>
<li>In 2011, India announced <strong><u>duty-free, quota-free access to Bangladesh</u></strong> for all tariff lines except tobacco and alcohol.</li>
<li>An <strong><u>Agreement on Promotion and Protection of Investments</u></strong> has been in force since 2011.</li>
<li><strong><u>Joint Interpretative Notes</u></strong> to the agreement were signed during the visit of the Indian Finance Minister to Bangladesh in October 2017.</li>
<li>To facilitate trade and transit through inland waterways, a <strong><u>Protocol on Inland Waterways Trade and Transit (PIWTT)</u></strong> has been in place since 1972. It was renewed in 2015.</li>
<li><strong><u>Direct sea movement of containerized/ bulk/ dry cargo</u></strong> began after the signing of a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) on Coastal Shipping in June 2015.</li>
<li>MoUs were signed in 2015 on the <strong><u>use of the </u></strong><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bangladesh-offers-chittagong-port-for-use-to-india/"><strong>Chittagong</strong></a><strong><u> and Mongla Ports</u></strong> for Movement of Goods to and from India.</li>
<li>The MoU on <strong><u>Border Haats </u></strong>on the India-Bangladesh border was renewed in April 2017 during the visit of Prime Minister Hasina to India. Currently, four Border Haats — two each in Meghalaya (Kalaichar and Balat) and Tripura (Srinagar and Kamalasagar) — are functional.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Types of Trade Agreements</h4>
<p><strong>(1) Free Trade Agreement </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>A FTA is a pact between two or more nations to reduce barriers to imports and exports among them.</li>
<li>Under a free trade policy, goods and services can be bought and sold across international borders with little or no government tariffs, quotas, subsidies, or prohibitions to inhibit their exchange.</li>
<li>The concept of free trade is the opposite of trade protectionism or economic isolationism.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Preferential Trade Agreement</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In this type of agreement, two or more partners give preferential right of entry to certain products.</li>
<li>This is done by reducing duties on an agreed number of tariff lines.</li>
<li>Here a positive list is maintained i.e. the list of the products on which the two partners have agreed to provide preferential access.</li>
<li>Tariff may even be reduced to zero for some products even in a PTA.</li>
<li>India signed a PTA with Afghanistan.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Comprehensive Economic Partnership Agreement</strong></p>
<p>Discussed above.</p>
<p><strong>(4) Comprehensive Economic Cooperation Agreement</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>CECA generally cover negotiation on trade tariff and Tariff rate quotas (TRQs) rates only.</li>
<li>It is not as comprehensive as CEPA.</li>
<li>India has signed CECA with Malaysia.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Framework Agreement</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Framework agreement primarily defines the scope and provisions of orientation of the potential agreement between the trading partners.</li>
<li>It provides for some new area of discussions and set the period for future liberalisation.</li>
<li>India has previously signed framework agreements with the ASEAN, Japan etc.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Early Harvest Scheme</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>An Early Harvest Scheme (EHS) is a precursor to an FTA/CECA/CEPA between two trading partners. For example, early harvest scheme of RCEP has been rolled out.</li>
<li>At this stage, the negotiating countries identify certain products for tariff liberalization pending the conclusion of actual FTA negotiations.</li>
<li>An Early Harvest Scheme is thus a step towards enhanced engagement and confidence building.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-bangla-trade-now-set-for-cepa-boost/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>