<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 08:18:42 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>It seems that inflation may hover around 7 percent</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/inflation-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>types of inflation</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>inflation overview</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="inflation" class="alignnone wp-image-637649" height="341" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1.jpg 1200w" width="647"/> </strong><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It seems that inflation may hover around 7 per cent despite RBI’s tightening of monetary policy in the months to come.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a simple definition for inflation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Inflation is an increase in the level of prices of the goods and services that households buy. It is measured as the rate of change of those prices. Typically, prices rise over time, but prices can also fall (a situation called deflation).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Inflation Rate</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Inflation Rate is the percentage change in the price level from the previous period. If a normal basket of goods was priced at Rupee 100 last year and the same basket of goods now cost Rupee 120, then the rate of inflation this year is 20%.</li>
<li>Inflation Rate= {(Price in year 2 – Price in year 1)/ Price in year 1} *100</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="inflation" class="alignnone wp-image-637678" height="350" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 841px) 100vw, 841px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-1-300x125.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-1-300x125.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-1-768x319.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-1.jpg 842w" width="841"/>Types of Inflation</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Creeping Inflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Creeping or mild inflation is when prices rise 3% a year or less. This kind of mild inflation makes consumers expect that prices will keep going up. That boosts demand. Consumers buy now to beat higher future prices. That’s how mild inflation drives economic expansion.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Walking Inflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>This type of strong, or pernicious, inflation is between 3-10% a year. It is harmful to the economy because it heats up economic growth too fast. People start to buy more than they need, just to avoid tomorrow’s much higher prices. This drives demand even further so that suppliers can’t keep up. More important, neither can wages. As a result, common goods and services are priced out of the reach of most people.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Galloping Inflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>When inflation rises to 10% or more, it wreaks absolute havoc on the economy. Money loses value so fast that business and employee income can’t keep up with costs and prices. Foreign investors avoid the country, depriving it of needed capital. The economy becomes unstable, and government leaders lose credibility. Galloping inflation must be prevented at all costs.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Hyperinflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Hyperinflation is when prices skyrocket more than 50% a month. It is very rare. In fact, most examples of hyperinflation have occurred only when governments printed money to pay for wars. Examples of hyperinflation include <strong>Germany</strong>in the 1920s, <strong>Zimbabwe</strong> in the 2000s, and <strong>Venezuela</strong> in the 2010s. The last time America experienced hyperinflation was during its civil war.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Core Inflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The core inflation rate measures rising prices in everything except food and energy. That’s because gas prices tend to escalate now and then. Higher gas costs increase the price of food and anything else that has large transportation costs.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Consumer Price Index</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>CPI is used to monitor changes in the cost of living over time. When the CPI rises, the average Indian family has to spend more on goods and services to maintain the same standard of living. The economic term used to define such a rising prices of goods and services is Inflation.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Whole sale Price Index</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>WPI is used to monitor the cost of goods and services bought by producer and firms rather than final consumers. The WPI inflation captures price changes at the factory/wholesale level.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>GDP Deflator</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Another important measure of calculating standard of living of people is GDP Deflator. GDP Deflator is the ratio of nominal GDP to real GDP. The nominal GDP is measured at the current prices whereas the real GDP is measured at the base year prices. Therefore, GDP Deflator reflects the current level of prices relative to prices in a base year. Example, In India the base year of calculating deflator is 2011-12.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="inflation" class="alignnone wp-image-637631" height="297" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 100vw, 527px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_Rate_0_1200x768-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_Rate_0_1200x768-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_Rate_0_1200x768-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_Rate_0_1200x768.jpeg 770w" width="527"/>Factors fuelling inflation in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Falling rupee:</strong> Inflation is here to stay because it has much to do with the decline in value of the rupee that has fallen to its lowest, which makes imports of oil and gas more expensive.</li>
<li><strong>Ukraine crisis:</strong> The war in Ukraine has the same effect and pushes the price of some food items upward.</li>
<li><strong>Poor inflation management:</strong> With inflation, as measured by the consumer price index, in August going back to 7 per cent, and the wholesale price index coming in at 12.4 per cent, one thing is clear India is not out of the woods on inflation management.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Rising inflation have these implications</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Impact on the poor:</strong> This upsurge of inflation is affecting the poor more because some of the commodities whose prices are increasing the most represent a larger fraction of the budget of the most vulnerable sections of society.</li>
<li><strong>Rising inequality:</strong> As a result, inequalities which were already on the rise are increasing further. Recently, the State of Inequality in India report showed that an Indian making Rs 3 lakh a year belonged to the top 10 per cent of the country’s wage earners.<strong> </strong></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inequality in healthcare: </strong>India’s spending on healthcare is among the lowest in the world. Decent level of healthcare is available only to the ones who can afford it because of increasing out-of-pocket expenditure the payment made directly by individuals for the health service, not covered under any financial protection scheme. Overall, these out-of-pocket expenses on healthcare are 60 per cent of the total expenditure on public health in India, which is one of the highest in the world.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong><img alt="inflation" class="alignnone wp-image-637701" height="358" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 643px) 100vw, 643px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200.jpg 1200w" width="643"/>Need for bold steps on three fronts to tackle inflation</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Unless bold and innovative steps are taken at least on three fronts, GDP growth and inflation both are likely to be in the range of 6.5 to 7.5 per cent in 2022-23.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>1] Tightening of loose<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/monetary-economics-barter-system-definition-function-and-evolution-of-money/"> monetary policy:</a></strong> The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) is mandated to keep inflation at 4 per cent, plus-minus 2 per cent.</p>
<ul>
<li>The RBI has already started the process of tightening monetary policy by raising the repo rate, albeit a bit late.</li>
<li>It is expected that by the end of 2022-3, the repo rate will be at least 5.5 per cent, if not more.</li>
<li>It will still stay below the likely inflation rate and therefore depositors will still lose the real value of their money in banks with negative real interest rates.</li>
<li>That only reflects an inbuilt bias in the system — in favour of entrepreneurs in the name of growth and against depositors, which ultimately results in increasing inequality in the system.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2] Prudent fiscal policy:</strong> Fiscal policy has been running loose in the wake of Covid-19 that saw the fiscal deficit of the Union government soar to more than 9 per cent in 2020-21 and 6.7 per cent in 2021-22, but now needs to be tightened.</p>
<ul>
<li>Government needs to reduce its fiscal deficit to less than 5 per cent, never mind the FRMB Act’s advice to bring it to 3 per cent of GDP.</li>
<li>However, it is difficult to achieve when enhanced food and fertiliser subsidies, and cuts in duties of petrol and diesel will cost the government at least Rs 3 trillion more than what was provisioned in the budget.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>3] Rational trade policy:</strong> Export restrictions/bans go beyond agri-commodities, even to iron ore and steel, etc. in the name of taming inflation.</p>
<ul>
<li>But abrupt export bans are poor trade policy and reflect only the panic-stricken face of the government.</li>
<li>A more mature approach to filter exports would be through a gradual process of minimum export prices and transparent export duties for short periods of time, rather than abrupt bans, if at all these are desperately needed to favour consumers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Though the government is opting for market-based economics, currently, India needs a mixed solution that comprises price stability via government channels and subsidies.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>What are the fuelling factors for inflation? Discuss what steps should be taken to tackle inflation.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/inflation-2/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Geopolitics follows the geoeconomics and not vice-versa</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/geoeconomics/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>international relations</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="geoeconomics" class="alignnone wp-image-637721" height="347" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 699px) 100vw, 699px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-300x149.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-300x149.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-1024x508.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-768x381.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-1200x595.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1.jpg 1269w" width="699"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Over the recent years India’s manoeuvres in indo-pacific have highlighted the India’s geopolitical and ambitions. Pandemic and Chinese incursion in Ladakh forced India to move fast to achieve its geopolitical ends. However missing link in India’s endeavour is geoeconomics.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is mean by geopolitics and geo-economics?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Geopolitics:</strong> is defined as the struggle over the control of geographical entities with an international and global dimension, and the use of such geographical entities for political advantage.</li>
<li><strong>Geo-economics:</strong> is defined as the combination of economic and geographic factors relating to international trade and a governmental policy guided by geoeconomics.</li>
<li>Geopolitics and geoeconomics are sometimes used interchangeably.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the strategy to pursue geopolitical goals in indo-pacific?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has managed to emerge as a major pivot of the global Indo-Paciﬁc grand strategic imagination.</li>
<li>Avoided the temptations to militarise/securitise the Quad (Australia, Japan, India and the United States).</li>
<li>Which has ensured that the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) states do not feel uneasy by the ever-increasing balance of power articulations in the Indo-Pacific</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="geoeconomics" class="alignnone wp-image-637722" height="323" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Geoeconomics-in-a-Globalized-World-300x166.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Geoeconomics-in-a-Globalized-World-300x166.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Geoeconomics-in-a-Globalized-World.jpg 525w" width="584"/>What is the missing link in India’s geopolitical strategy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The missing link in geoeconomics is India’s decision to take to the Indo-Paciﬁc and Quad in a big way.</li>
<li>While unwilling to join two of the region’s key multilateral trading agreements goes to show that geoeconomics and geopolitics are imagined and pursued parallelly in New Delhi, not as complimenting each other.</li>
<li>The most recent example is India’s refusal to join the trade pillar of the Indo-Paciﬁc Economic Framework (IPEF) while deciding to join the three other pillars of the IPEF supply chains, tax and anti-corruption, and clean energy.</li>
</ul>
<p>India also withdrew from <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/back-in-news-india-asean-relations/">ASEAN</a> led <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/regional-comprehensive-economic-partnership-rcep/">RCEP.</a></p>
<h4><strong>Is the lack of geoeconomic bad for foreign policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The absence of the world’s fifth largest economy from various regional trading platforms will invariably boost China’s geo-economic hegemony in Asia.</li>
<li>Staying out of IPEF is a bad idea is because for India, it would be hard to integrate itself into the regional and global supply chains without being a part of important regional multilateral trading agreements.</li>
<li>We have no option but to address some of the deeper challenges plaguing the investment and business environment in India.</li>
<li>If India is indeed serious about its maritime grand strategy, which cannot be solely military in nature, it needs to get the states in the region to create economic stakes in India (something China has done cleverly and consistently) and vice-versa.</li>
<li>Another impact of India’s hesitation about joining regional multilateral trading arrangements is its potential regional economic isolation. The less India engages with the region economically, and the more China does so, and given the Sino-Indian rivalry, India might risk getting economically isolated in the broader region.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Geo-economics: is defined as the combination of economic and geographic factors relating to international trade and a governmental policy guided by geoeconomics. Geopolitics and geoeconomics are sometimes used interchangeably." class="alignnone wp-image-637723" height="397" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 634px) 100vw, 634px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-1024x640.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-1536x960.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-2048x1280.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-1200x750.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-1980x1238.jpg 1980w" width="634"/>What can be done?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>New Delhi should: </strong>rethink its geoeconomic choices if it is serious about enhancing its geopolitical inﬂuence in the region. Given that India has not closed the door on the trade pillar of the IPEF, we have an opportunity to rethink our position.</li>
<li><strong>India should: </strong>also rethink its decision not to join the RECP and seek to join the Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Paciﬁc Partnership (CPTPP) from which the U.S. walked out and China is seeking to join.</li>
<li><strong>India should: </strong>also proactively lobby to become a part of the Minerals Security Partnership, the U.S.-led 11-member grouping to secure supply chains of critical minerals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the words of external affairs minister Dr. Jaishankar,” geopolitics follows the geoeconomics and not vice-versa”. Geoeconomics is inclusive of geoeconomics. India should integrate itself in multilateral trading platforms and leverage its big market to bargain the best deal for itself.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Indias pursuit of geopolitics is futile without inclusion of geoeconomics. Comment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/geoeconomics/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Without social justice constructive women empowerment is a futile exercise here is why</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-empowerment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Women empowerment</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637728" height="341" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609-768x447.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609.jpg 1000w" width="585"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Despite notable progress in closing the gender pay gap over time in India, the gap remains high by international standards. Asymmetries still abound in the country’s labor market stopping women empowerment .</li>
<li>Time to reassess the progress made in to close the Gender pay gap.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The third International Equal Pay Day is observed globally on September 18, 2022.</li>
<li>It is a United Nations-recognized event to highlight the issue of gender pay gap.</li>
<li>International Labor Organization’s “Global Wage Report 2020–21” which suggests the crisis inflicted massive downward pressure on wages and disproportionately affected women’s total wages compared to</li>
<li>This greater wage reduction for women means that the pre-existing gender pay gap has widened.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637732" height="325" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200.jpg 1200w" width="584"/>Covid-19 Impact</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While it is difficult to tell exactly what the economic damage from the global covid-19 pandemic has been, it is clear that its impact has been uneven, with women being among the worst affected in terms of their income security.</li>
<li>Many women reverted to full-time care of children and the elderly during the pandemic, foregoing their livelihoods to do so.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is gender pay gap?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The gender pay gap or gender wage gap measures the difference between the average earnings of women and men in the workforce.</li>
<li>In simple term it is a measure of what women are paid relative to men.</li>
<li>Women are generally found to be paid less than men.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is the gender pay gap?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Education: </strong>low investment o girl education<strong>, </strong>Girl children are kept out of schools, or made drop out of school at early age, girl is considered as burden on family in many societies.</li>
<li><strong>workforce </strong>: even if they are educated they are not allowed to work by their families, very limited or no decision making power, lack of women friendly work environment, discriminatory practices at workplaces.</li>
<li><strong>Household:</strong> early marriage , responsibilities of the household at early age , spending more times on domestic chores,</li>
<li><strong>Healthcare: </strong>malnutrition, anemia, Maternity, child care, looking after health of the elderly family members etc.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p>These are some of the reasons which affect education, skills, experience and the career prospectus of women as compared to men and contribute to widen the gender wage gap.</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637730" height="297" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 100vw, 527px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India.jpg 1919w" width="527"/>Discrimination as factor</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A part of gender pay gap attributed to education, skills or experience, a large part of the gender pay gap can still purely because of discrimination based on one’s gender or sex.</li>
<li>Gender-based discriminatory practices include: lower wages paid to women for work of equal value; undervaluation of women’s work in highly feminized occupations and enterprises, and motherhood pay gap lower wages for mothers compared to non-mother.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637734" height="466" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 837px) 100vw, 837px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1.jpg 1200w" width="837"/>Status in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The gender pay gap in India is among the widest in the world.</li>
<li>Indian women earned, on an average, 48% less compared to their male counterparts in 1993-94</li>
<li>According to labor force survey data of the National Sample Survey Office (NSSO) gap declined to 28% in 2018-19.</li>
<li>Periodic Labor Force Survey (PLFS) 2020-21 show an increase in the gap by 7% between 2018-19 and 2020-21.</li>
<li>Recently, the World Economic Forum (WEF) ranked India at 135 out of 146 countries in its Global Gender Gap (GGG) Index for 2022.</li>
<li>According to the estimates of the World Inequality Report 2022, in India, men earn 82 per cent of the labor income whereas women earn 18 per cent of it.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637731" height="392" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 696px) 100vw, 696px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8477553337_67c076bed2_o-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8477553337_67c076bed2_o-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8477553337_67c076bed2_o.jpg 639w" width="696"/>Steps taken by India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Minimum Wages Act in 1948</strong>: It is an act of parliament<strong>, </strong>aimed at statutory fixation of minimum wages that must be paid to skilled and unskilled labours. Payment of wages below the minimum wage rate amounts to forced labour.</li>
<li><strong>Equal Remuneration Act in 1976: </strong>This act of parliament provides for the payment of equal remuneration to men and women workers for the prevention of discrimination. It helps in bridging the gap between unequal remuneration faced by the women of our country.</li>
<li><strong>Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA) 2005:</strong> MGNREGA contributed to the rapid rise in overall rural and agricultural wages in the country. It benefited rural women workers and helped reduce the gender pay gap, both directly and indirectly. Directly, by raising the pay levels of women workers and indirectly to women involved in agricultural occupations through higher earnings.</li>
<li><strong>The Maternity Benefit (Amendment) Act 2017</strong>: has increased the duration of paid maternity leave available for women employees to 26 weeks from 12 weeks for all women working in establishments employing 10 or more workers. This is expected to reduce the motherhood pay gap among mothers in the median and high end wage earners working in the formal economy also it will help in women empowerment.</li>
<li><strong>Skill India Mission</strong>: To equip women with market-relevant skills to bridge the learning to-livelihood gap and the gender pay gap.</li>
<li>In 2019, India carried out comprehensive reforms in both the legislation and enacted the Code on Wages.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While the gender pay gap is slowly narrowing, acceleration and bold actions to prevent the widening of gender pay gap is the need of the hour.</li>
<li>Equal pay for work of equal value is necessary to close the gender pay gap.</li>
<li>Closing the gender pay gap is key to achieving <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/women-empowerment-issues-jobsreservation-education/">social justice for working women</a>, as well as economic growth for the nation as a whole</li>
<li>Without social justice women empowerment is a futile exercise.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Define gender equality .Equal pay for equal work is necessary to bridge the gender pay gap India .Comment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-empowerment/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the PM PRANAM Scheme?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-pm-pranam-scheme/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PM PRANAM Scheme</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India's fertilizer subsidy</p></div></div><p>In order to reduce the use of chemical fertilisers by incentivising states, the Union government plans to introduce a new scheme – PM PRANAM, which stands for PM Promotion of Alternate Nutrients for Agriculture Management Yojana.</p>
<h4>What is the PM PRANAM scheme?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The proposed scheme intends to reduce the subsidy burden on chemical fertilisers.</li>
<li>This burden if uneased, is expected to increase to Rs 2.25 lakh crore in 2022-2023, which is 39% higher than the previous year’s figure of Rs 1.62 lakh crore.</li>
<li>The scheme will not have a separate budget and will be financed by the “savings of existing fertiliser subsidy” under schemes run by the Department of fertilisers.</li>
</ul>
<p>Subsidies under the PRANAM</p>
<ul>
<li>Further, 50% subsidy savings will be passed on as a grant to the state that saves the money and that 70% of the grant provided under the scheme can be used for asset creation related to technological adoption of alternate fertilisers.</li>
<li>It would create alternate fertiliser production units at village, block and district levels.</li>
<li>The remaining 30% grant money can be used for incentivising farmers, panchayats, farmer producer organisations and self-help groups that are involved in the reduction of fertiliser use and awareness generation.</li>
<li>The government will compare a state’s increase or reduction in urea in a year, to its average consumption of urea during the last three years.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How much fertiliser does India require?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The kharif season (June-October) is critical for India’s food security, accounting for nearly half the year’s production of foodgrains, one-third of pulses and approximately two-thirds of oilseeds.</li>
<li>A sizable amount of fertiliser is required for this season.</li>
<li>The Department of Agriculture and Farmers Welfare assesses the requirement of fertilisers each year before the start of the cropping season, and informs the Ministry of Chemical and fertilisers to ensure the supply.</li>
<li>The amount of fertiliser required varies each month according to demand, which is based on the time of crop sowing, which also varies from region to region.</li>
<li>For example, the demand for urea peaks during June-August period, but is relatively low in March and April, and the government uses these two months to prepare for an adequate amount of fertiliser for the kharif season.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the scheme being introduced?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Due to <strong><u>increased demand for fertiliser</u></strong> in the country over the past 5 years, the overall expenditure by the government on subsidy has also increased.</li>
<li>The final figure of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-enhances-subsidy-for-non-urea-fertilizers/"><strong>fertiliser subsidy</strong></a> touched Rs 1.62 lakh crore in 2021-22.</li>
<li>The total requirement of four fertilisers — Urea, DAP (Di-ammonium Phosphate), MOP (Muriate of potash), NPKS (Nitrogen, Phosphorus and Potassium) — increased by 21% between 2017-2018 and 2021-2022, from 528.86 lakh metric tonnes (LMT) to 640.27 LMT.</li>
<li>PM PRANAM, which seeks to reduce the use of chemical fertiliser, will likely <strong><u>reduce the burden on the exchequer. </u></strong></li>
<li>The proposed scheme is also in line with the government’s focus on promoting the <strong><u>balanced use of fertilisers or alternative fertilisers</u></strong> in the last few years.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ:</h4>
<p><strong>Q.What are the advantages of fertigation in agriculture? (CSP 2020)</strong></p>
<p>1.Controlling the alkalinity of irrigation water is possible.<br/>
2.Efficient application of Rock Phosphate and all other phosphatic fertilizers is possible.<br/>
3.Increased availability of nutrients to plants is possible.<br/>
4.Reduction in the leaching of chemical nutrients is possible.</p>
<p><strong>Select the correct answer using the code given below:</strong><br/>
(a) 1, 2 and 3 only</p>
<p>(b) 1,2 and 4 only</p>
<p>(c) 1,3 and 4 only</p>
<p>(d) 2, 3 and 4 only</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-pm-pranam-scheme/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the Plant Treaty?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-plant-treaty/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Plant treaty</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p> </p>
<p>The ninth session of the governing body of the International Treaty on Plant Genetic Resources for Food and Agriculture (ITPGRFA) has recently begun in New Delhi.</p>
<h4><strong>Theme of this years event</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The theme of the meeting is ‘Celebrating the Guardians of Crop Diversity: Towards an Inclusive Post-2020 Global Biodiversity Framework’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Plant Treaty?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The International Treaty on Plant Genetic Resources for Food and Agriculture (ITPGRFA) was adopted by the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations November 3, 2001.</li>
<li>It was signed in 2001 in Madrid, and entered into force on 29 June 2004.</li>
<li>It is the first legally-binding international instrument to formally acknowledge the enormous contribution of indigenous people and small-holder farmers as traditional custodians of the world’s food crops.</li>
<li>It also calls on nations to protect and promote their rights to save and use the seeds they have taken care of for millennia.</li>
<li>The parties to this treaty have come together after nearly three years to discuss governance of agricultural biodiversity and global food security.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Objectives of the treaty<br/>
</strong></h4>
<p>The treaty aims at:</p>
<ol>
<li>Guaranteeing food security through the conservation</li>
<li>Exchange and sustainable use of the world’s plant genetic resources for food and agriculture (PGRFA)</li>
<li>Fair and equitable benefit sharing arising from its use, as well as</li>
<li>Recognition of farmers’ rights.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Key feature: Annex 1 Crops</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The treaty has implemented a Multilateral System (MLS) of access and benefit sharing, among those countries that ratify the treaty, for a list of 64 of some of the most important food and forage crops essential for food security and interdependence.</li>
<li>The genera and species are listed in Annex 1 to the treaty. The treaty facilitates the continued open exchange of food crops and their genetic materials.</li>
<li>The list of plant genetic material included in the Multilateral System of the Treaty is made of major food crops and forages.</li>
<li>The Forages are also divided in legume forages and grass forages.</li>
<li>They were selected taking into account the criteria of food security and country interdependence</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-plant-treaty/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SC quota for Dalit Muslims and Christians</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-quota-for-dalit-muslims-and-christians/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Quota benefits for religious convertees</p></div></div><p>The Centre is likely to soon decide on setting up a national commission to study the social, economic and educational status of Dalits who converted to religions other than Hinduism, Buddhism and Sikhism.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Several petitions are pending before the Supreme Court seeking Scheduled Caste (SC) reservation benefits for Dalits who converted to Christianity or Islam.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Dalit Convertees and Quota Benefits<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The original rationale behind giving reservation to Scheduled Castes was that these sections had suffered from the social evil of untouchability, which was practised among Hindus.</li>
<li>Under Article 341 of the Constitution, the President may specify the castes, races or tribes or parts of or groups within castes, races or tribes which shall…be deemed to be Scheduled Castes.</li>
<li>The first order under this provision was issued in 1950, and covered only Hindus.</li>
<li>Following demands from the Sikh community, an order was issued in 1956, including Sikhs of Dalit origin among the beneficiaries of the SC quota.</li>
<li>In 1990, the government acceded to a similar demand from Buddhists of Dalit origin, and the order was revised to state: “No person who professes a religion different from the Hindu, the Sikh or the Buddhist religion shall be deemed to be a member of Scheduled Caste.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Does this religion-based bar apply to converted STs and OBCs as well?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It does not.</li>
<li>The Department of Personnel and Training (DoPT) website states, “The rights of a person belonging to a Scheduled Tribe are independent of his/her religious faith.”</li>
<li>Following the implementation of the Mandal Commission report, several Christian and Muslim communities have found place in the Central and state lists of OBCs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What efforts have been made to include Muslims and Christians of Dalit origin among SCs?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>After 1990, a number of Private Member’s Bills were brought in Parliament for this purpose.</li>
<li>In 1996, a government Bill called The Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Orders (Amendment) Bill was drafted, but in view of a divergence of opinions, the Bill was not introduced in Parliament.</li>
<li>Then government headed by PM Manmohan Singh set up two important panels:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Ranganath Misra Commission:</strong> The National Commission for Religious and Linguistic Minorities, popularly known as the Ranganath Misra Commission, in October 2004 and</li>
<li><strong>Sachar Committee:</strong> A seven-member high-level committee headed by former Chief Justice of Delhi High Court Rajinder Sachar to study the social, economic, and educational condition of Muslims in March 2005.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What did they recommend?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Sachar Committee Report</u></strong> observed that the social and economic situation of Dalit Muslims and Dalit Christians did not improve after conversion.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Ranganath Misra Commission</u></strong>, which submitted its report in May 2007, recommended that SC status should be completely de-linked from religion and Scheduled Castes should be made fully religion-neutral like Scheduled Tribes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reception to these recommendations</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The report was tabled in Parliament in 2009, but its recommendation was <strong><u>not accepted</u></strong> in view of inadequate field data and corroboration with the actual situation on the ground.</li>
<li>Few studies, commissioned by the National Commission for Minorities, was also <strong><u>not considered reliable due to insufficient data.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What lies ahead?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Based on the recommendations of the Ranganath Misra Commission, there are some <strong><u>petitions pending before the Supreme Cour</u></strong>t, seeking reservation benefits for Christians and Muslims of Dalit orgin.</li>
<li>In the last hearing, a three-judge Bench gave the Solicitor General of India three weeks’ time to present the stand of the Union government on the issue.</li>
<li>The next hearing is awaited.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-quota-for-dalit-muslims-and-christians/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Significance of Ethereum’s Merge for the future of cryptocurrencies</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/significance-of-ethereums-merge-for-the-future-of-cryptocurrencies/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ethereum Merge Event</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Cryptyocurrencies</p></div></div><p><img alt="merge" class="alignnone wp-image-637900" height="212" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 370px) 100vw, 370px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merge-300x172.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merge-300x172.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merge.jpg 721w" width="370"/></p>
<p>Ethereum’s shift of its consensus algorithm from proof-of-work (PoW) to environment-friendly proof-of-stake (PoS) in an event called ‘The Merge’ recently took place.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>One would wonder if the Merge Event has actually any relation to any corporate merger or acquisition!</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>What is Ethereum?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Ethereum is one of the most used platforms by developers to build decentralised apps (dApps), smart contracts, and even crypto tokens.</li>
<li>The platform’s currency, Ether is only second to Bitcoin (BTC) in terms of market capitalisation.</li>
<li>The change in the way Ethereum builds the blockchain comes with not just environmental consequences, but also major cyber and financial security implications.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Merge?  </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Merge is an upgrade to the way transactions are validated on the Ethereum blockchain.</li>
<li>It moves the network proof-of-work (PoW) system to proof-of-stake (PoS) system, which is designed to be more environmentally sustainable and faster.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does PoS and PoW refer to?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>PoS and PoW are consensus mechanisms through which transactions on blockchains are validated.</li>
<li>PoW consumes more energy since it allows all miners on a network to try and validate a transaction.</li>
<li>As a result, more computers attack a transaction and hence consume more energy.</li>
<li>PoS removes miners from the equation, replacing them with entities called ‘validators’.</li>
<li>These validators put up a stake (at least 32ETH) in order to gain the right to validate transactions. Only the top stakeholders are rewarded for their work.</li>
<li>Their stakes are held in a central wallet, and they are penalized for mistakes or frauds.</li>
<li>Common centres for mining included China (before a near total crypto ban), the US, Russia, and Kazakhstan — countries with cheap electricity rates and colder climates.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is there a need for a new mechanism?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Power Saving</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Decentralised transactions are processed on blockchains using consensus mechanisms.</li>
<li>Ethereum’s former method, ‘proof-of-work’, which is also used by Bitcoin, needs powerful mining hardware that consumes a lot of electricity and generates enormous amounts of heat.</li>
<li>This energy is then used to process extremely difficult mathematical puzzles, the solution of which would let new transactions be added to the blockchain so as to reward the miners with crypto.</li>
<li>Many environmentalists, policy makers, and regulators have strongly criticised the impact of Bitcoin mining on local communities.</li>
<li>Ethereum’s website admitted that their crypto’s total annualised power consumption nearly matches that of Finland while its carbon footprint is comparable to Switzerland.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Global Crackdown</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>For some time, European countries even mulled a crypto mining ban, while China actually carried out a nationwide crackdown on crypto miners, sending them fleeing overseas.</li>
<li>Probably as a response to the backlash, Ethereum has decided to switch to a ‘proof-of-stake’ consensus mechanism.</li>
<li>The crypto owners will stake their own coins in order to serve as collateral and help process new blockchain transactions, in return for rewards.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Significance of the merge</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="merge" class="alignnone wp-image-637902" height="224" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 391px) 100vw, 391px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merge-ether-300x172.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merge-ether-300x172.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merge-ether.jpg 669w" width="391"/></p>
<ul>
<li>According to the Ethereum Foundation, the Merge will reduce overall energy consumption of the Ethereum network by 99.95%.</li>
<li>Blockchains have a short history so far, but in that history, the Merge has become one of the most widely publicized and awaited events.</li>
<li>It has been in the works for six years and 15 September marked the end of that build-up.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Which other cryptocurrencies are changing to proof-of-stake now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>For now, no other top coin is planning an Ethereum-style Merge.</li>
<li>After Bitcoin, Dogecoin [DOGE] is the largest proof-of-work based cryptocurrency.</li>
<li>It was initially created as a joke by its founders. After that comes Ethereum Classic [ETC], formerly part of Ethereum before a community schism.</li>
<li>Ethereum Classic has made it clear that it is loyal to the proof-of-work mechanism.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/significance-of-ethereums-merge-for-the-future-of-cryptocurrencies/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Death Penalty: SC moots fair hearing</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/death-penalty-sc-moots-fair-hearing/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Death penalty debate</p></div></div><p><strong> <img alt="death" class="alignnone wp-image-637901" height="305" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/death-300x204.png" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/death-300x204.png 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/death.png 461w" width="449"/></strong></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has referred to a Constitution Bench the question of how to provide accused in death penalty cases a “meaningful, real and effective” hearing of their mitigating circumstances before a trial judge.</p>
<h4><strong>Death Penalty: A backgrounder</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-debate-over-capital-punishment/">Capital punishment</a>, sometimes called death penalty, is execution of an offender sentenced to death after conviction by a court of law for a criminal offense.</li>
<li>It should be distinguished from extrajudicial executions carried out without due process of law.</li>
<li>The term death penalty is sometimes used interchangeably with capital punishment, though imposition of the penalty is not always followed by execution, because of the possibility of commutation to life imprisonment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>When is it awarded?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The term “Capital Punishment” stands for most severe form of punishment.</li>
<li>It is the punishment which is to be awarded for the most heinous, grievous and detestable crimes against humanity.</li>
<li>While the definition and extent of such crimes vary, the implication of capital punishment has always been the death sentence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Special factors on the death penalty jurisprudence in India</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(a) Increase in Sexual Offences</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The report on death penalty published by NLU Delhi shows that the rate of awarding capital punishment to the offences of rape with murder is much higher than other offences.</li>
<li>There is no doubt that rape is one of the most heinous crimes.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(b) Sedition and waging War against India</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India has seen many cases of treason, terrorism and seditious activities.</li>
<li>It is in fact the most vulnerable state for such crimes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Judicial observations related to Death Penalty</strong></h4>
<p>The Supreme Court has always said that the death sentence should be given rarely.</p>
<p><strong><u>Judgments against:</u></strong></p>
<p><strong>(a) Mithu vs State of Punjab (1983):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court ruled that the mandatory death penalty is unconstitutional.</li>
<li>It struck down Section 303 in the IPC, which entailed a mandatory death sentence for a person who commits murder while serving a life term in another case.</li>
<li>The Supreme Court ruled Section 303 violated Articles 14 (right to equality) and 21 (right to life) since an unreasonable distinction was sought to be made between two classes of murders.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(b) State of Punjab vs Dalbir Singh (2012):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Similarly, the Supreme Court ruled that mandatory death penalty as punishment for crimes under Section 27 (3) of the Arms Act, 1959, was unconstitutional.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(c) Channulal Verma vs State of Chhattisgarh (2018):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In Channulal, the Supreme Court, through Justice Kurian Joseph noted that the time was appropriate to review the constitutionality of the death penalty and take into consideration reformative aspects of punishment</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><u>Judgments in favour:</u></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In Jagmohan Singh vs State of UP’ (1973), then in ‘Rajendra Prasad vs State of UP’ (1979), and finally in ‘<strong><u>Bachan Singh vs State of Punjab’ (1980)</u></strong> the Supreme Court affirmed the constitutional validity of the death penalty.</li>
<li>It said that if capital punishment is provided in the law and the procedure is a fair, just and reasonable one, the death sentence can be awarded to a convict.</li>
<li>This will, however, only be in the “rarest of rare” cases, and the courts should render “special reasons” while sending a person to the gallows.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Avenues available to a Death-Row Convict</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Confirmation by HC:</strong> After a trial court awards the death penalty, the sentence must be confirmed by a High Court. The sentence cannot be executed till the time the High Court confirms it, either after deciding the appeal filed by the convict, or until the period allowed for preferring an appeal has expired.</li>
<li><strong>Review Petition:</strong> If the High Court confirms the death penalty and it is also upheld by the Supreme Court, a convict can file a review petition.</li>
<li><strong>Curative Petition:</strong> If the review petition is rejected, the convict can file a curative petition for reconsideration of the judgment.</li>
<li><strong>Mercy Petition: </strong>Under Article 72 of the Indian Constitution, the President shall have the power to grant pardons, reprieves, respites, or remissions of punishments or to suspend, remit or commute the sentence of any convicted person.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Debate over Death Penalty</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Arguments in favor:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Forfeiture of life:</strong> Supporters of the death penalty believe that those who commit murder, because they have taken the life of another, have forfeited their own right to life.</li>
<li><strong>Moral indignation of the victim:</strong> It is a just form of retribution, expressing and reinforcing the moral indignation not only of the victim’s relatives but of law-abiding citizens in general.</li>
<li><strong>Highest form of Justice:</strong> For heinous crimes such as the Nirbhaya Gangrape Case, no other punishment could have deterred the will of the convicts.</li>
<li><strong>Deterrent against crime:</strong> Capital punishment is often justified with the argument that by executing convicted murderers, we will deter would-be murderers from killing people.</li>
<li><strong>Proportional punishment:</strong> The guilty people deserve to be punished in proportion to the severity of their crime.</li>
<li><strong>Prevailing lawlessness:</strong> The crimes we are now witnessing cannot be addressed by simple punishments. We are seeing horrific attacks on women, young girls, minority communities and Dalits etc.</li>
<li><strong>Prevention of crime is non-existent:</strong> Despite of stringent regulations, it is certainly visible that some crimes can never be prevented in our society.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Arguments against</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Eye for an eye:</strong> Reformative justice is more productive, that innocent people are often killed in the search for retribution, and that “an eye for an eye makes the whole world blind.</li>
<li><strong>Deterrence is a myth:</strong> Death penalty is not a deterrent to capital crimes state that there is no evidence to support the claim that the penalty is a deterrent.</li>
<li><strong>Political tool of suppression:</strong> The authorities in some countries, for example Iran and Sudan, use the death penalty to punish political opponents.</li>
<li><strong>Reverence for life’ principle: </strong>Death penalty is an immoral punishment since humans should not kill other humans, no matter the reasons, because killing is killing.</li>
<li><strong>Stigma against killing:</strong> With the introduction of lethal injection as execution method, medical professionals participate in executions. Many professionals have now refused to administer such deaths.</li>
<li><strong>Skewed justice systems:</strong> In many cases recorded by Amnesty International, people were executed after being convicted in grossly unfair trials, on the basis of torture-tainted evidence and with inadequate legal representation.</li>
<li><strong>Discriminatory nature:</strong> The weight of the death penalty is disproportionally carried by those with less advantaged socio-economic backgrounds or belonging to a racial, ethnic or religious minority.</li>
<li><strong>Penalizing the innocents:</strong> The risk of executing the innocent precludes the use of the death penalty. Our colonial history has witnessed many such executions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other issues with such executions</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(a) Socio-Economic Factors</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The recent statistics shows that the death row prisoners in India are more from the backward classes of the society.</li>
<li>The death row prisoners belong to backward classes and religious minorities and the majority of convicts’ families are living in adjunct poverty.</li>
<li>These people who are backward both in economic and social respects, are not in a position to here expensive lawyers and get proper representation in the Court.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(b) Delayed Execution</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The law provides for a long process before the execution of the convicts actually takes place.</li>
<li>The unexplained delay in execution can be a ground for commutation of death penalty, and an inmate, his or her kin, or even a public-spirited citizen could file a writ petition seeking such commutation.</li>
<li>Their trials are often cruelly forced to endure long periods of uncertainty about their fate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward: Law Commission recommendations on death penalty</strong></h4>
<p>The Law Commission of India in its 262<sup>nd</sup> Report (August 2015) recommended that:</p>
<ul>
<li>Death penalty be <strong><u>abolished for all crimes other than terrorism related offences and waging war</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Measures such as police reforms, witness protection scheme and victim compensation scheme should be taken up expeditiously by the government.</li>
<li>It felt that time has come for India to move towards abolition of the death penalty. However the concern is often raised that abolition of death penalty for terrorism-related offences and waging war, will affect national security.</li>
</ul>
<p>Further, the Commission sincerely hopes that the movement towards absolute abolition will be swift and irreversible</p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/death-penalty-sc-moots-fair-hearing/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Teachers with a passion for the profession are foundational to the positive educational change</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/teacher-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>TET</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>quality education</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="teacher" class="alignnone wp-image-633160" height="204" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 482px) 100vw, 482px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1789299_orig-300x127.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1789299_orig-300x127.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1789299_orig.jpg 425w" width="482"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Success of new education policy depends on how we recruit and assesss teachers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the issue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Recruitment of well-qualified teachers into the schooling system is the first prerequisite to ensure that students receive quality education.</li>
<li>However, teacher recruitment processes in the country are not adequately streamlined. There are diverse recruitment processes across regions, school stages, and school types central, state, and private schools.</li>
<li>This, in turn, leads to multiple criteria and processes for hiring teachers, thereby bringing a wide disparity in teacher quality across institutions and regions.</li>
<li>Many of the processes are also sub-optimal in measuring the competency of a candidate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Teacher hiring mechanism in place </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>One of the most common and widely-taken tests to ensure eligibility for recruitment is the Teacher Eligibility Test (TET), conducted at both the state (STET) and central levels (CTET).</li>
<li>TET is the equivalent of the licensure tests that are undertaken by teacher candidates in various countries.</li>
<li>However, in India, the test is required only for government school teacher recruitment at the elementary stage (Class 1-8).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="teacher" class="alignnone wp-image-633161" height="273" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 366px) 100vw, 366px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Competent-teachers-300x224.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Competent-teachers-300x224.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Competent-teachers-768x573.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Competent-teachers.jpg 800w" width="366"/>Issues</strong> <strong>in hiring mechanism </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>TET has been critiqued time and again for various reasons. These include low pass percentages, poor test quality, lengthy test papers and a serious lack of alignment with teacher preparation programmes.</li>
<li>The test was in the news recently because of the teachers’ recruitment scam in West Bengal.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="teacher" class="alignnone wp-image-633162" height="344" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 387px) 100vw, 387px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S0883035521001129-gr5-300x267.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S0883035521001129-gr5-300x267.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S0883035521001129-gr5.jpg 621w" width="387"/>What we need?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>A coherent strategy:</strong> to tie together the various tests and processes such as TET, teacher recruitment tests, classroom demonstrations and teacher interviews. This will enable a holistic assessment of teacher competence.</li>
<li><strong>Understanding what is competence</strong>: Framing a common understanding of what qualifies as teacher competence. Simply speaking, teacher competence can be understood as the core knowledge, skills, and dispositions expected of a teacher to effectively contribute to the teaching-learning process.</li>
<li><strong>Multiple methods of assessment</strong>: To evaluate several other skills and dispositions, one requires multiple methods of assessment including classroom demonstrations and teacher interviews. These assessments could help gauge skills like effective dissemination of a concept and selection of appropriate resources and learning materials.</li>
<li><strong>Teacher’s aptitude</strong>: Most importantly, such processes should help evaluate a teacher’s empathy towards students. Respecting learner diversity and skills in building a participative/democratic classroom culture are crucial requisites of a teacher. The recruitment process should assess the teacher’s aptitude in this respect.</li>
<li><strong>A comprehensive competency framework</strong>: That details the skills a teacher should have. This could be derived from a teacher education curriculum rooted in policy perspectives of the day. For instance, in the case of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-national-education-policy-2020-higher-education-and-regional-languages/">NEP</a>, the curriculum could be geared towards imparting training in classroom practices that make learning joyful.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Long-term benefits to adopting such a holistic model of teacher recruitment</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Better parity</strong>: It will ensure better parity in the quality of teachers recruited across the country.</li>
<li><strong>Equitable education</strong>: Will contribute to equitable education for students from diverse sections of society.</li>
<li><strong>Credibility is ensured</strong>: The recruitment process will also become credible if it is rooted in a framework that outlines the core competencies of becoming a teacher.</li>
<li><strong>Reduction in coaching centres:</strong> At the systemic level, this may also lead to a reduction in coaching centres as the assessment processes will be non-standardised and cannot be easily gleaned from coaching materials and guidebooks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Teachers with a passion for the profession are foundational to the positive educational change envisaged by the NEP. Setting up clear benchmarks of quality and well-designed recruitment processes hold the key to ensuring better teaching-learning outcomes.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you think on teacher’s quality today? Explain how dynamic teacher recruitment process will enhance teacher’s quality.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/teacher-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The great Indian thirst: The story of India’s water stress</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/water-stress/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>various water reports</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>water conservation</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="water stress" class="alignnone wp-image-636154" height="315" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 559px) 100vw, 559px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vsemirnyi-den-vody-2017-nrwf-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vsemirnyi-den-vody-2017-nrwf-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vsemirnyi-den-vody-2017-nrwf-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vsemirnyi-den-vody-2017-nrwf.jpeg 770w" width="559"/></strong><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>United Nations World Water Development Report of 2022 has expressed global concern over the sharp rise in freshwater withdrawal from streams, lakes, aquifers and human made reservoirs, significant water stress and also water scarcity being experienced in diﬀerent parts of the world.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who publishes the UNs world water development report?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The United Nations World Water Development Report (WWDR) is published by UNESCO, on behalf of UN-Water and its production is coordinated by the UNESCO World Water Assessment Program (WWAP).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the level of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-water-crisis/#:~:text=Nearly%20600%20million%20Indians%20faced,million%20people%2C%20the%20study%20noted.">water stress</a> in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Global Drought Risk and Water Stress map (2019)</strong>: It shows that major parts of India, particularly west, central and parts of peninsular India are highly water stressed and experience water scarcity.</li>
<li><strong>Composite Water Management Index (2018):</strong> Released by Niti Aayog indicates that more than 600 million people are facing acute water stress.</li>
<li><strong>India is the world’s largest extractor of groundwater</strong>: Accounting for 25 per cent of the total. 70 percent of our water sources are contaminated and our major rivers are dying because of pollution.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="water stress" class="alignnone wp-image-636155" height="304" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 456px) 100vw, 456px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-768x511.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478.jpg 976w" width="456"/>Why is Rural to Urban transfer of water becoming an issue in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rising urban population: </strong>According to Census 2011, the urban population in India accounted for 34% of total population. It is estimated that the urban population component in India will cross the 40% mark by 2030 and the 50% mark by 2050 according to World Urbanization Prospects, 2018.</li>
<li><strong>Water use in the urban areas: </strong>Water use in the urban sector has increased as more and more people shift to urban areas. Per capita use of water in these centers rises, which will continue to grow with improved standards of living.</li>
<li><strong>Shifting of water source in Urban areas: </strong>As the city grows and water management infrastructures develop, dependence shifts to surface water from groundwater. <strong>For example:</strong> In Ahmedabad, more than 80% of water supply used to be met from groundwater sources till the mid-1980s. Due to such overexploitation of groundwater the depth to groundwater level reached 67 meters in confined aquifers. The city now depends on the Narmada canal for the bulk of its water supply.</li>
<li><strong>Dependence of urban areas on rural areas for water source and rural-urban disputes over water: </strong>Cities largely depend on rural areas for raw water supply, which has the potential to ignite the rural-urban dispute. For example: Nagpur and Chennai face the problem of rural-urban water disputes.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong><img alt="water stress" class="alignnone wp-image-636156" height="336" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 596px) 100vw, 596px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Water1-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Water1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Water1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Water1.jpg 800w" width="596"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/kaveri-river-water-dispute/">Reasons for disputes</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Diversion of resource</strong>: Water is transported to urban areas at the expense of rural areas. Due to the high population in urban areas the water requirement for daily use is very high.</li>
<li><strong>High demand of water for industrial purposes: </strong>In urban areas the water is heavily used in industries creating water stress.</li>
<li><strong>High Agriculture dependence:</strong> In the rural areas water is used mainly for irrigation purposes and due to heavy dependence on agriculture the water is very essential in rural areas.</li>
<li><strong>Water pollution</strong>: In cities, most of this water is in the form of grey water with little recovery or reuse, eventually contributing to water pollution.</li>
<li><strong>Bad governance</strong>: Politicization of water for vote bank and skewed distribution of water particular regions For example: Andhra and Telangana.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="water stress " class="alignnone wp-image-636157" height="387" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-1536x1025.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-1980x1321.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo.jpg 2048w" width="581"/>Climate change exacerbate the rural-urban disputes</strong><strong> </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Affecting rainfall pattern: </strong>Climate change affects the amount of rainfall in the region which is the prime source of both surface water and groundwater.</li>
<li><strong>Increase rate of evaporation over surface water:</strong> because of high temperature the surface waters of lakes, rivers, canals etc. face high evaporation water loss.</li>
<li><strong>Melting of glaciers: </strong>glaciers are the sources for perennial rivers of India. Due to global warming, glaciers are melting and hence affecting the perennial nature of rivers.</li>
<li><strong>Frequent droughts:</strong> It affects the groundwater recharge process and drying of surface waters which creates shortage of water. It exacerbate the rural-urban conflict.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A system perspective and catchment scale based approach are necessary to link reallocation of water with wider discussions on development, infrastructure investment, fostering an rural-urban partnership and adopting an integrated approach in water management.</li>
<li>The government cannot manage the water crisis alone. It will take the combined efforts of civil society, the private sector including the public at large to meet the challenge.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Rural and urban areas use water from the same stock, i.e., the water resources of the country. Therefore, it is important to strive for a win- win situation by securing the interests of both urban and rural areas. Good Governance is the key to achieve such a win-win situation.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question Q.</strong></p>
<p><strong>How the rising water stress and growing urbanization in India is fuelling rural-urban conflict over water issues? Also highlight the role of climate change in exacerbating these conflicts. Elaborate.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/water-stress/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Here is how HDI has performed in last 3 decades</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hdi/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of report</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>human development</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="HDI" class="alignnone wp-image-636168" height="345" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 448px) 100vw, 448px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-300x231.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-300x231.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-1024x787.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-768x590.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-1171x900.jpg 1171w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant.jpg 1200w" width="448"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India, belonging to the medium HDI category, shows dimensional inequalities similar to or slightly below the average figures in the category, except in the case of education where it is high and closer to the low HDI countries. The inequalities in health and education are more than twice that of the very high and high HDI categories.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The bad news for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/human-development-report-by-undp/">India is that its global HDI rank has slipped</a> from 129 in 2019 to 131 in 2020 and to 132 in 2021-22.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the meaning of human development?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Human development is defined as the process of enlarging people’s freedoms and opportunities and improving their well-being. Human development is about the real freedom ordinary people have to decide who to be, what to do, and how to live.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is meant by Human Development Index?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The HDI is a summary measure of human development. The HDI is a summary composite measure of a country’s average achievements in three basic aspects of human development: health, knowledge and standard of living.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who publishes HDI?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Human Development Report (HDR) is an annual Human Development Index report published by the Human Development Report Office of the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="HDI" class="alignnone wp-image-636170" height="338" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3.jpg 960w" width="600"/>Dimensions of the Human Development Index</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Long and healthy life: </strong>The long and healthy life dimension is measured by life expectancy at birth. The life expectancy at birth is a statistical measure that an average individual is expected to live based on certain demographic factors such as the year of birth and current age.</li>
<li><strong>Education</strong>: This is a second dimension in the HDI. The indicators of education are the expected years of schooling and the mean years of schooling. According to the UN, the average maximum years of schooling is 18 years, while the mean maximum years of schooling is 15 years.</li>
<li><strong>Standard of living: </strong>The standard of living is usually measured by the gross national income (GNI) per capita. The GNI indicates the total domestic and foreign output created by the residents of a certain country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the 4 indicators of HDI?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Mean years of schooling</li>
<li>Expected years of schooling</li>
<li>Life expectancy at birth</li>
<li>Gross national income (GNI) per capita</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Which Countries Have the Highest HDI?</strong></p>
<p>In the latest HDI ranking, from 2022, Switzerland finished first with an HDI value of 0.962.</p></blockquote>
<p><img alt="HDI" class="wp-image-636173" height="339" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 509px) 100vw, 509px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook.jpg 1536w" width="509"/></p>
<h4><strong>Issues in HDI</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) An incomplete indicator</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Human development is incomplete without human freedom and that while the need for qualities judgement is clear; there is no simple quantitative measure available yet to capture the many aspects of human freedom.</li>
<li>HDI also does not specifically reflect quality of life factors, such as empowerment movements or overall feelings of security or happiness.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Limited idea of development</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The HDI is not reflecting the human development idea accurately.</li>
<li>It is an index restricted to the socio-economic sphere of life; the political and civil spheres are in the most part kept separate.</li>
<li>Hence there is a sub-estimation of inequality among countries, which means that this dimension is not being taken into consideration appropriately.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) A vague concept</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Concerning data quality and the exact construction of the index HDI is conceptually weak and empirically unsound.</li>
<li>This strong critic comes from the idea that both components of HDI are problematic. The GNP in developing countries suffers from incomplete coverage, measurement errors and biases.</li>
<li>The definition and measurement of literacy are different among countries and also, this data has not been available since 1970 in a significant number of countries.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Data quality issues</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The HDI, as a combination of only four relatively simple indicators, doesn’t only raise a questions what other indicators should be included, but also how to ensure quality and comparable input data.</li>
<li>It is logical that the UNDP try to collect their data from international organizations concentrating in collecting data in specific fields.</li>
<li>Quality and trustworthiness of those data is disputable, especially when we get the information from UN non-democratic members, as for example Cuba or China.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) A tool for mere comparison</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The concept of HDI was set up mainly for relative comparison of countries in one particular time.</li>
<li>HDI is much better when distinguishing between countries with low and middle human development, instead of countries at the top of the ranking.</li>
<li>Therefore, the original notion was not to set up an absolute ranking, but let’s quite free hands in comparison of the results.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Development has to be greener</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The human development approach has not adequately incorporated environmental conditions which may threaten long-term achievements on human development. The most pervasive failure was on environmental sustainability.</li>
<li>However, for the first time in 2020, the UNDP introduced a new metric to reflect the impact caused by each country’s per-capita carbon emissions and its material footprint.</li>
<li>This is Planetary Pressures-adjusted HDI or PHDI. It measured the amount of fossil fuels, metals and other resources used to make the goods and services it consumes.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(7) Wealth can never equate welfare</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Higher national wealth does not indicate welfare. GNI may not necessarily increase economic welfare; it depends on how it is spent.</li>
<li>For example, if a country spends more on military spending – this is reflected in higher GNI, but welfare could actually be lower.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Importance of HDI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multidimensionality</strong>: It is one of the few multidimensional indices as it includes indicators such as literacy rate, enrolment ratio, life expectancy rate, infant mortality rate, etc.</li>
<li><strong>True yardstick</strong>: It acts as a true yardstick to measure development in real sense.</li>
<li><strong>Helps in measuring a nation’s well-being:</strong> Unlike per capital income, which only indicates that a rise in per capital income implies economic development; HDI considers many other vital social indicators and helps in measuring a nation’s well-being.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Value addition line</strong></p>
<p><em>People are the real wealth of a nation. The basic objective of development should be to create an enabling environment for people to live long, healthy and creative lives. This may appear to be a simple truth.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To sum up, the introduction of the HDI three decades ago was an early attempt to address the shortcomings in conventional measures of wellbeing.</li>
<li>The HDI has continued to attract widespread attention and motivates the work of activists, scholars and political leaders around the world.</li>
<li>The HDI compels us to ask what matters more, the quantitative expansion of an economy, or the qualitative improvement in the capabilities of society.</li>
<li>Indeed the revival of interest in this subject at the highest levels of government is the need of the hour.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you understand by human development? Critically analyse the human development index given by UNDP.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hdi/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why we need to build a framework for best global digital governance affirmation</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/digital-governance/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<h4><strong><img alt="digital governance" class="alignnone wp-image-637976" height="444" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/CRN_Services_Portfolio_Technology_696-300x200.jpg" width="667"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In an interview earlier this month, Telecom Minister Ashwini Vaishnaw spoke about a comprehensive policy roadmap for India’s digital economy and digital governance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is digital governance ?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Electronic governance or e-governance can be defined as the usage of Information and Communication Technology (ICT) by the government to provide and facilitate government services, exchange of information, communication transactions and integration of various standalone systems and services.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is “global digital governance”?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Global digital governance encompasses the norms, institutions, and standards that shape the regulation around the development and use of these technologies. Digital governance has long-term commercial and political implications.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is it important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The main objective of e-governance is to provide a friendly, affordable, and efficient interface between a government and its people. It is about ensuring greater transparency, accountability and objectivity, resulting in cost-effective and high-quality public service.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the three domains of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/interactions-between-main-groups-in-e-governance-action-plan-for-india/">e-governance</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>E-administration</strong>: improving government processes</li>
<li><strong>E-services</strong>: connecting individual citizens with their government</li>
<li><strong>E-society</strong>: building interactions with and within civil society.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="digital governance" class="alignnone wp-image-637977" height="422" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 546px) 100vw, 546px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital-India-and-E-governance-300x232.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital-India-and-E-governance-300x232.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital-India-and-E-governance.jpg 529w" width="546"/>Is there a historical parallel to governing key economic sectors globally?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Digital economy is not unprecedented:</strong> Sectors critical to the global economy are subject to international cooperation frameworks and pacts. Therefore, the idea of setting up a single multilateral organization with a mandate to govern the digital economy is not unprecedented.</li>
<li><strong>The International Commission for Air Navigation (ICAN): </strong>Global aviation has been regulated since 1903 when the International Commission for Air Navigation (ICAN) first met, subsequently replaced by the International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO) in 1947.</li>
<li><strong>Bank for International Settlements (BIS): </strong>Similarly, the modern international banking system is governed by the Bank for International Settlements (BIS), an institution initially set up in the interwar period in 1930 to oversee Germany’s reparations to the Allies under the Treaty of Versailles. The BIS acquired a more global mandate beginning in the 1950s and is now partially responsible for global financial stability.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who are the key players in the global contest for digital governance</strong>?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>China seeks to champion the concept of cyber sovereignty: </strong>An authoritarian vision drives the first model. Most notably, China is emerging as the standard-bearer for this model with its desire to “reinvent the internet.” China seeks to champion the concept of “cyber sovereignty,” allowing countries to control access to the internet, censor content, and institute data localization requirements, as a pretext to protecting individual national interests.</li>
<li><strong>European Union’s General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR): </strong>Which provides a more democratic concept for digital governance. This model primarily seeks to protect the privacy and rights of internet users and online content consumers. Adopted with the overwhelming support of the European Parliament in 2014, the GDPR came into effect in May 2018, giving firms that rely on digital technologies the opportunity to modify their data usage and privacy policies. The adoption of the GDPR has been a turning point for global internet governance as consumers gained unprecedented control over their data in a manner that preserved freedom and openness online.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="digital governance" class="alignnone wp-image-637978" height="434" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 591px) 100vw, 591px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Syn-19-1-300x220.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Syn-19-1-300x220.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Syn-19-1.jpg 662w" width="591"/>Why global digital governance is important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Minimum rights and protections for platform workers</strong>: Under the G20, the International Labour Organisation has already placed a proposal in the employment working group for digital labour platforms to develop an international governance system determining minimum rights and protections for platform workers.</li>
<li><strong>Implementation of central bank digital currency projects: </strong>Similarly, on digital money, a reincarnated Bretton Woods is being advocated to address the distrust in private currencies and to coordinate the implementation of central bank digital currency projects.</li>
<li><strong>Digital taxation:</strong> Finally, in the deeply contested area of digital taxation, the OECD facilitated Base Erosion and Profit Shifting (BEPS) negotiations and helped arrive at a global solution.</li>
<li><strong>Digital sovereignty:</strong> The internet is splintering and digital sovereignty is now commonplace; yet, there is no better time for countries to come together and build a framework for global digital governance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="digital governance" class="alignnone wp-image-637981" height="357" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/E-Governance-Kya-Hai-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/E-Governance-Kya-Hai-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/E-Governance-Kya-Hai-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/E-Governance-Kya-Hai.jpg 1000w" width="570"/>What are the big 5 tech companies called?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Big Five tech giants—Apple, Amazon, Google (Alphabet), Meta, and Microsoft.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The rapid digitalisation of the world along with a new focus on trust in the global supply chains for digital products and services presents tremendous opportunities for India and its youth.  It is now up to all of us to engage in a collective “sabka prayas” to realise New India’s economic potential.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. The rapid digitalisation of the world along with a new focus on trust in the global supply chains for digital products and services presents tremendous opportunities for India. Comment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/digital-governance/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Supreme Court’s basic structure doctrine in a new context</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/basic-structure/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Various judgements on basic structure</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Features of constitution</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="basic structure" class="alignnone wp-image-637988" height="285" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 506px) 100vw, 506px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BASIC-STRUCURE-DOCTRINE-IN-INDIAN-CONSTITUTION-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BASIC-STRUCURE-DOCTRINE-IN-INDIAN-CONSTITUTION-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BASIC-STRUCURE-DOCTRINE-IN-INDIAN-CONSTITUTION.jpg 560w" width="506"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The basic structure doctrine constitutes a high watermark in the assertion of the Supreme Court’s judicial power in the teeth of a determined majoritarian regime.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is basic structure of Constitution?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The basic structure doctrine is one of the fundamental judicial principles connected with the Indian Constitution. The doctrine of the basic structure holds that there is a basic structure to the Indian Constitution, and the Parliament of India cannot amend the basic features.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the significance of the basic structure in the Constitution of India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The doctrine of basic structure is nothing but a judicial innovation to ensure that the power of amendment is not misused by Parliament. The idea is that the basic features of the Constitution of India should not be altered to an extent that the identity of the Constitution is lost in the process.08-Dec-2021</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Courts are empowered under our Constitution to invalidate not only executive orders, but also legislative enactments that violate any part of the Fundamental Rights guaranteed in Part III of the Constitution (Bill of Rights).</li>
<li>But as to whether they are also empowered to adjudicate on the validity of constitutional amendments passed with the requisite special majority and following the procedure prescribed in Article 368 the Constitution is silent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="basic structure" class="alignnone wp-image-637989" height="412" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 731px) 100vw, 731px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r.jpeg 770w" width="731"/>Historical developments on evolution of basic structure doctrine </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Constitution provided a mechanism for parliament to amend the constitution in the form of article 368 but the nature and scope of this amending power was questioned in Supreme Court on multiple occasions. Supreme Court gave a series of judgement which ultimately culminated in probably the most landmark judgement Basic structure doctrine judgement.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Shankari Prasad Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Sajjan Singh Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Golakh Nath Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Kesvananda Bharati Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Minerva Mills case</strong></li>
<li><strong>I.R. Koelhi</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Constitutional Provisions</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>1st amendment and 9th schedule</strong></li>
<li><strong>24th amendment</strong></li>
<li><strong>42nd amendment</strong></li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<p>His holiness, Kesavananda bharati, challenged before the supreme court, the validity of 29th CAA which inserted some laws in 9th schedule and affected property of his Hindu Mutt.</p>
<h4><strong>What else was at stake?</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li>Supreme Court (R. C. Cooper case) had struck down bank nationalization act of 1969 which had nationalized 14 major banks for illusory compensation though it conceded parliament’s right to nationalise banks in national interest.</li>
<li>Supreme Court had struck down abolition of privy purses which was a betrayal of solemn promise to erstwhile kings by Sardar Patel.</li>
</ol>
<p>Supreme Court could do all this as it had held in 1967 in Golaknath case that fundamental rights could not be abridged.</p>
<p>Before returning back to Kesavananda, Let’s take a look at the relevant provisions of the constitution and Supreme Court interpretation of the same.</p>
<ul>
<li>Art 13(2) – Any LAW abridging fundamental rights mentioned in part 3 shall be null and void to the extent of contravention</li>
<li>Art 368 -Procedure to amend the constitution.</li>
<li>Art 19(f) – freedom to acquire hold on and dispose off property.</li>
<li>Art 31 – right to property</li>
</ul>
<p>Both the rights were subject to reasonable restriction in public interest and restriction were subject to judicial review.</p>
<p>Soon after the coming into force of the constitution, states enacted land reform acts #Zamindars challenged them. #Patna high court declared Bihar act as unconstitutional for violating right to property #interim parliament passed 1st CAA.</p>
<ol>
<li>ART 31B created 9th schedule. Laws inserted under it by constitutional amendment were immune to judicial review.</li>
</ol>
<p>Other provisions not imp for this article but imp for exams –</p>
<ol>
<li>Reasonable restrictions against freedom of expression under art 19.</li>
<li>To nullify judgment in State of Madras v. Champakam Dorairajan and giving effect to art 46 (promoting educational and economic interests of weaker sections) amplified article 15 (3)</li>
</ol>
<p>Zamindars didn’t like it, not one bit. And here comes the 1st salvo</p>
<h4><strong>Shankari Prasad v Union of India</strong></h4>
<p>Challenged 1st CAA. What was the court’s judgment?</p>
<ol>
<li>Difference b/w constituent power and ordinary legislative power i.e. amendment not law for the purpose of article 13</li>
<li>art 13 and 368 in conflict # apply DOCTRINE OF HARMONIOUS CONSTRUCTION # ART 13 not applicable to art 368</li>
</ol>
<p>Govt 1-0 Zamindars</p>
<p>Govt passed 17th amendment and inserted more laws under 9th schedule ‘</p>
<p>Zamindars fired another salvo-</p>
<h4><strong>Sajjan Singh vs state of rajasthan</strong></h4>
<p>Supreme Court sang Shankari prasad song again</p>
<p>Govt 2-0 jamindars</p>
<p>But Justice Mudholkar was of the view that the every Constitution has certain features which are basic in nature and those features cannot be changed.</p>
<p>2 minority judgements…. utter confusion. And you can see seeds of basic structure were sown here.</p>
<p>Zamindars fired 3rd salvo</p>
<h4><strong>Golaknath v. State of Punjab</strong></h4>
<p>11 judge bench overturned earlier 2 verdicts by a slender majority of 6-5</p>
<p>Really? What was the logic given here?</p>
<ol>
<li>Nothing to suggest constituent power to be separate from legislative power and even if distinct, amending power not same as constituent power which is given only to constituent assembly i.e. amendment is law and subject to article 13</li>
<li>Fundamental rights so sacrosanct and transcendental that they cannot be abridged even if whole parliament unanimously decided to abridge them.</li>
</ol>
<p>But it validated all previous land reform acts as nullifying them would create utter confusion</p>
<p>Govt angry – Zamindars angry</p>
<p>New landlords happy.</p>
<p>Loss – loss to defendants as well as petitioner.</p>
<p>Madam Indira was in power and she did not like this. Not one bit.</p>
<p>Along came 24th amendment to neutralize GOLAKNATH JUDGEMENT</p>
<ol>
<li>Art 13 inapplicable to art 368</li>
<li>Art 368 provided powers as well as procedure to amend the constitution</li>
<li>Parliament by way of addition, variation or repeal can amend any provision of constitution</li>
<li>President shall give assent to CA bills ( VERY VERY IMP FOR PRELIMS )</li>
</ol>
<p>But madam Indira wouldn’t just stop here as Cooper judgment (Bank nationalization ) also had to be neutralized.</p>
<p>Smarting from this setback, Madam Indira (the parliament, herself) passed 24th CAA to neutralise GOLAKNATH judgement. But there was also a small matter of reversing Copper judgment in bank nationalisation case so parliament passed 25th CAA.</p>
<ol>
<li>Art 19f delinked from 31, in effect parliament deciding compensation amount payable instead of courts.</li>
<li>Art 31c  -inserted under which – art 39b and c, most socialist of DPSPs (equitable distribution and prevention of concentration of wealth respectively) precede over 7 freedoms (art 19 ), equality (14), property (31)</li>
<li>Parliament’s power to determine if policy is to give effect to 39b and c not subject to judicial review.</li>
</ol>
<p>29th CAA had put Kerala land reform act under 9th schedule and his holiness challenged the provisions and all hell broke loose.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Now the 4th salvo</p>
<h4><strong><img alt="basic structure" class="alignnone wp-image-637990" height="345" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 616px) 100vw, 616px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1-300x168.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1-300x168.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1-768x431.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1.jpg 896w" width="616"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/kesavananda-bharati-case-1973-the-judgment-that-upheld-basic-structure-of-indias-constitution/">Kesvanada Bharati Case</a></strong></h4>
<p>A 13 judge bench is constituted and what does it do!</p>
<ol>
<li>Overturned Golaknath i.e. amendment not law, fundamental rights amendable, no implied limit under art 368 i.e. CAA 24 constitutional</li>
<li>Art 25 invalid to the extent it takes away judicial review i.e. 39 b and c above 14, 19 and 31 but subject to judicial review</li>
</ol>
<p>Most imp decision of all by slimmest of all 7-6 majority stated Parliament can amend any provision of the Constitution but the basic structure should not be destroyed, damaged or abrogated.</p>
<p>What’s the logic?</p>
<ol>
<li>Expression amendment did not encompass defacing the constitution such that it lost its identity.</li>
<li>In the garb of amendment parliament can not rewrite the constitution.</li>
</ol>
<p>Court gave relief to govt but reserved for itself power to review all amendment not just those that violate fundamental rights.</p>
<p>Aftermath</p>
<p>Indira Gandhi didn’t like the judgement one  bit. She (via the president) superseded 3 judges to appoint justice A.N. Ray as CJI.</p>
<p>Knives had been drawn and the battle was gonna be very bloody –</p>
<ul>
<li>Navnirman movement of JP (Jayprakash<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jayaprakash_Narayan" rel="noopener" target="_blank">)</a> had gathered steam, Indira was on the back foot and along came the judgement of Allahabad High Court convicting Indira of corrupt electoral practices. Election was declared null and void and  6 years ban to contest election was imposed on her.</li>
<li>Supreme Court stayed it and allowed her to remain PM but not to draw salary or speak or vote in parliament.</li>
<li>Darkest chapter in democracy’ 21 month emergency was declared on 25th June 1975 without even consulting cabinet (44th amendment made it mandatory for the president to have written advice of cabinet to declare emergency)</li>
</ul>
<p>Indira Gandhi wasn’t to sit quiet.</p>
<p>CAA 39th – election of president, VP, PM and speaker beyond judicial review</p>
<p>Clownish Rajnarayan challenged the CAA 39.</p>
<h4><strong>Indira Gandhi v/s Raj Narain Case</strong></h4>
<p>For the 1st time Supreme Court applied basic structure doctrine and considered free and fair election and rule of law to be part of basic structure. #amending act invalidated.</p>
<p>Note here that 4 of the 5 judges on the bench had given dissenting judgment in Bharati case but still applied the same doctrine for Supreme Court judgment becomes law until overruled by bigger bench (art 141).</p>
<p>Then how did Indira continue to be prime minister and contest election again and not get banned for 6 years?</p>
<p>Supreme court accepted retrospective amendment to electoral law i.e. electoral malpractice of Indira was no longer a corrupt practice.</p>
<p>Find out for fun the charges against Mrs. Gandhi for which she was convicted and what a popular British magazine had to say about the judgement.</p>
<p>Along came the mini constitution i.e 42nd amendment act TO ELIMINATE IMPEDIMENTS TO THE GROWTH OF THE CONSTITUTION –</p>
<ol>
<li>PART 4a fundamental duties</li>
<li>Socialist,secular and integrity word to preamble</li>
<li>New <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/indepth-understanding-of-the-directive-principles-of-state-policy/">DPSP</a>s were added</li>
</ol>
<p>And for the purpose of this article amendment to article 368 nullifying basic structure doctrine by adding amendments can’t be challenged in courts and parliament possessing unlimited power of amendment</p>
<ol start="4">
<li>All DPSPs to take precedence over all fundamental rights not just 39b and 39c.</li>
</ol>
<p>And Minerva Textile mills of Karnataka fired the 5th and the last salvo</p>
<h4><strong>Minerva Mills v Union of India</strong></h4>
<p>SC unanimously struck down amendment to article 368 holding limited amending power and judicial review to be part of basic structure.</p>
<p>Court held that constitution is founded on the bedrock of balance b/w FRs and DPSPs. Goals set out by DPSPs have to be achieved without abrogation of means provided by FRs.</p>
<p>What’s the logic?</p>
<p>If a donee was vested with limited power, it could not be exercised to control that very power power and convert into unlimited one.</p>
<p>Or</p>
<p>If a genie grants u 3 wishes, it is understood u can not, as one of the wish, ask for unlimited number of wishes!</p>
<p>Janta govt comes to power and 44th CAA deletes art 31 (b) right to property and 19 (f) freedom to acquire, hold and dispose of property as they were not considered part of basic structure</p>
<p>Right to property now a constitutional right under art 300A.</p>
<p>9th schedule and judicial review</p>
<h4><strong>I.R.Coelho vs state of TN</strong></h4>
<p>Supreme Court held that acts placed under 9th schedule after basic structure subject would be subject to judicial review to the extent of those acts violating basic structure of constitution.</p>
<p>Impact of basic structure doctrine.</p>
<p>It certainly saved Indian democracy from degenerating into authoritarian regime during those testing times but it has also given immense untold unbridled power to Supreme Court and made it the most powerful court in the world.</p>
<p>As we would later see in the NJAC Verdict (let’s call it 4th judges case), Supreme Court applied this doctrine, many would say for wrong reasons to strike down the act and kept for itself the power to appoint brother judges. In the original constitution only fetters on the power of parliament was art 13.</p>
<p>Relevance –  It was delivered at the time of single party rule both at the centre and most of the states. In the era of coalition politics no govt is going to wield so much power to destroy the constitution and then there is ever present danger of tyranny of unelected.</p>
<p>But only legitimate way to overturn the verdict would be a 15 judge bench so don’t hold your breath for that.</p>
<p>Now is the time for some thought questions</p>
<p>#1. Consider these 2 statements –</p>
<ol>
<li>Any LAW that is ordinary law violating provisions of constitution would be declared null and void to the extent of contravention.</li>
<li>Any LAW violating art 13 would be declared null and void</li>
</ol>
<p>Both statements are true…..If amendments were not law, what was the purpose of art 13 (2) other laws would anyway be declared unconstitutional!</p>
<p>#2. Is basic structure doctrine relevant in the present political scenario where no single party is unlikely to enjoy majority in both the houses?</p>
<p>#3. What should be the limits to amending power of parliament? Do u think for very substantial amendments instead of courts, people by way of referendum should determine whether amendment should go through or not?</p>
<p>#4. Whatever happens to original intent theory that constitutional courts have to interpret constitution in accordance with the implied intentions of founding fathers and there is enough evidence to suggest founding fathers thoughtfully kept FRs sacrosanct to prevent their abrogation or as we would see in a later article how supreme court by creative interpretation virtually changed procedure established by law in art 21 to due process of law while founding fathers deliberately kept expression as procedure established by law.</p>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>By restraining the amending powers of legislative organ of State, it provided basic Rights to Citizens which no organ of State can overrule. Being dynamic in nature, it is more progressive and open to changes in time unlike the rigid nature of earlier judgements.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. What do you understand by basic structure of constitution? Trace evolution of basic structure in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/basic-structure/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The hijab case and the doctrine of essentiality</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/doctrine-of-essentiality-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of doctrine of essentiality</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>judicial reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="doctrine of essentiality" class="alignnone wp-image-638019" height="496" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 755px) 100vw, 755px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/19hijab-1140302-1661758240-300x197.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/19hijab-1140302-1661758240-300x197.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/19hijab-1140302-1661758240-1024x671.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/19hijab-1140302-1661758240.jpg 1200w" width="755"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A two-judge Bench of the Supreme Court of India is presently hearing arguments on the correctness of a Karnataka High Court judgment that upheld the ban on the use of the hijab by students in Karnataka which raises question on doctrine of essentiality.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> </strong><strong>What is ‘doctrine of essentiality’? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A seven-judge Bench of the Supreme Court invented the doctrine of “essentiality” in the Shirur Mutt case in 1954. The court held that the term “religion” will cover all rituals and practices “integral” to a religion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Importance doctrine of essentiality</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the legal framework, the doctrine of essentiality is a doctrine that has evolved to protect the religious practices that are essential or integral and does not violate any fundamental right. India being a secular country has discrete religious beliefs and to deny any is to violate the freedom of religion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why hijab is not an essential practice?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Wearing of hijab (head scarf) by Muslim women does not form a part of essential religious practices in Islamic faith and it is not protected under the right to freedom of religion guaranteed under Article 25 of the Constitution of India, the High Court of Karnataka declared on March 15 2022.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="doctrine of essentiality" class="alignnone wp-image-638020" height="366" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 594px) 100vw, 594px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/r04jg7b8_hijab-row-protest_650x400_15_February_22-300x185.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/r04jg7b8_hijab-row-protest_650x400_15_February_22-300x185.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/r04jg7b8_hijab-row-protest_650x400_15_February_22.jpg 650w" width="594"/>Is hijab essential part of Islam?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Qur’an instructs Muslim women and men to dress modestly, and for some, the hijab is worn by Muslim girls and women to maintain modesty and privacy from unrelated males. According to the Encyclopedia of Islam and Muslim World, modesty concerns both men’s and women’s “gaze, gait, garments, and genitalia”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How do you identify essential religion practice?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Court observed that in order to determine whether or not a particular practice is an essential part of religion, the test must be whether the absence of the practice itself</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/op-ed-snap-the-warp-and-weft-of-religious-liberty/"><strong>Meaning of Article 26</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Freedom to manage religious affairs Subject to public order, morality and health, every religious denomination or any section thereof shall have the right.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="doctrine of essentiality" class="alignnone wp-image-638021" height="417" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 626px) 100vw, 626px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1.jpg 1200w" width="626"/>Examples of the essential religious practices test</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While these issues are largely understood to be community-based, there are instances in which the court has applied the test to individual freedoms as well.</li>
<li>In a 2004 ruling, the Supreme Court held that the Ananda Marga sect had no fundamental right <strong>to <u>perform the Tandava dance in public</u></strong> streets since it did not constitute an essential religious practice of the sect.</li>
<li>For example, in 2016, the Supreme Court upheld the discharge of an airman from the Indian Air Force <strong>for <u>keeping a beard</u>.</strong></li>
<li>It distinguished the case of a Muslim airman from that of Sikhs who are allowed to keep a beard.</li>
<li>In 2015, the Supreme Court restored <strong>the<u> Jain religious practice of Santhara/Sallekhan</u>a</strong> (a ritualistic fast unto death) by staying an order of the Rajasthan HC.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="doctrine of essentiality" class="alignnone wp-image-637989" height="336" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 596px) 100vw, 596px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r.jpeg 770w" width="596"/>What is the Supreme Court’s judgement on Doctrine of Essentiality?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The doctrine of “essentiality” was invented by a seven-judge Bench of the Supreme Court in the ‘Shirur Mutt’ case in 1954.</li>
<li>It is a contentious doctrine evolved by the court to protect only such religious practices which were essential and integral to the religion.</li>
<li>The court held that the term “religion” will cover all rituals and practices “integral” to a religion, and took upon itself the responsibility of determining the essential and non-essential practices of a religion.</li>
<li>Referring to the Ayodhya case, the Constitution Bench had ruled in 1994 that A mosque is not an essential part of the practice of the religion of Islam and namaz (prayer) by Muslims can be offered anywhere, even in open.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How has the doctrine been used in subsequent years?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ‘essentiality doctrine’ of the Supreme Court has been criticised by several constitutional experts.</li>
<li>Scholars of constitutional law have argued that the essentiality/integrality doctrine has tended to lead the court into an area that is beyond its competence, and given judges the power to decide purely religious questions.</li>
<li>As a result, over the years, courts have been inconsistent on this question — in some cases they have relied on religious texts to determine essentiality.</li>
<li>In others it relied on the empirical behaviour of followers, and in yet others, based on whether the practice existed at the time the religion originated.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues over the doctrine</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the beginning, the court engaged with the question of whether untouchability, manifested in restrictions on entry into temples, was an “essential part of the Hindu religion”.</li>
<li>After examining selected Hindu texts, it came to the conclusion that untouchability was not an essential Hindu practice.</li>
<li>The idea of providing constitutional protection only to those elements of religion which the court considers “essential” is problematic as it assumes that one element or practice of religion is independent of other elements or practices.</li>
<li>So, while the essentiality test privileges certain practices over others, it is, in fact, all practices taken together that constitute a religion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does essentiality square up against religious freedom?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Freedom of religion was meant to guarantee freedom to practice one’s beliefs based on the concept of “inward association” of man with God.</li>
<li>The apex court in ‘Ratilal Panachand Gandhi vs The State of Bombay and Ors’ (March 18, 1954) acknowledged that “every person has a fundamental right to entertain such religious beliefs as may be approved by his judgment or conscience”.</li>
<li>The framers of the Constitution wanted to give this autonomy to each individual. Scholars have argued that the essentiality test impinges on this autonomy.</li>
<li>The apex court has itself emphasised autonomy and choice in its Privacy (2017), 377 (2018), and Adultery (2018) judgments.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Its effect on society</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Narrowing of safeguards to religious customs:</strong> It has allowed the Court to narrow the extent of safeguards available to religious customs by directly impinging on the autonomy of groups to decide for themselves what they deem valuable, violating, in the process, their right to ethical independence.</li>
<li><strong>Negated legislation that might otherwise enhance the cause of social</strong> <strong>justice</strong>: It has also negated legislation that might otherwise enhance the cause of social justice by holding that such laws cannot under any circumstances encroach on matters integral to the practice of a religion. For example, in 1962, the Court struck down a Bombay law that prohibited excommunications made by the Dai of the Dawoodi Bohra community when it held that the power to excommunicate is an essential facet of faith and that any measure aimed at social welfare cannot reform a religion out of its existence.</li>
<li><strong>A principle of anti-exclusion:</strong> Its application would require the Court to presume that a practice asserted by a religious group is, in fact, essential to the proponents of its faith. But regardless of such grounding, the Constitution will not offer protection to the practice if it excludes people on grounds of caste, gender, or other discriminatory criteria.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>For now, any Court hearing a matter touching upon a matter of faith has the unenviable task of acting not merely as an expert on law but also as an expert on religion.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Every person has a fundamental right to entertain such religious beliefs as may be approved by his judgment or conscience. Critically examine in context of doctrine of essentiality.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/doctrine-of-essentiality-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Backsliding on climate action</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/backsliding-on-climate-action/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Paris agreement</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Climate change</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>Europe is staring at a recession and its appetite for climate action is waning.</p>
<h4>Developed countries moving away from commitment</h4>
<ul>
<li>Countries in Europe led by Germany, Austria and the Netherlands are cranking up their coal plants again.</li>
<li>Fossil fuels are making a comeback and countries are rejecting the European Union (EU)’s plan to reduce natural gas consumption by 15%. Dutch, Polish and other European farmers are protesting against emission cuts from agriculture.</li>
<li>In the U.S. too, the Senate and the Supreme Court have struck blows to climate action.</li>
<li>And in the U.S. too, prices of fuel started increasing last year, not just this year.</li>
<li>Fossil fuels are making a quiet comeback, since the strength of the U.S. is its oil and gas industry.</li>
<li>That is why we have just witnessed a ‘re-calibration’ of U.S. policy towards the Gulf.</li>
<li>Coal, oil and gas are not going anywhere in the developed world; they are, in fact, making a comeback.</li>
<li>The West had rushed to draw down on fossil fuels even before technology for renewables were in place.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Global peaking issue</h4>
<ul>
<li>Article 4 of the Paris Agreement defines ‘Global Peaking’ thus: “In order to achieve the long-term temperature goal set out in Article 2, Parties aim <strong>to reach global peaking</strong> of greenhouse gas emissions as soon as possible, recognizing that peaking will take longer for developing country Parties.”</li>
<li>The developed countries, given their historical emissions, will have to peak first.</li>
<li>That’s why the reference is to<strong> ‘global peaking’</strong> and not ‘individual peaking’.</li>
<li>From this, it logically follows that when developing country parties peak later than developed countries, they will also achieve net zero later than developed countries.</li>
<li>Consequently, it is the logical conclusion of the Article 4 of the Paris Agreement that when we consider net zero, we should only consider ‘global net zero’ and not ‘individual net zero’ for 2050.</li>
<li>The statement calls on developed countries to do a net negative on mitigation by 2050 rather than just “net zero”, if they are serious about fighting climate change.</li>
<li>In effect, the West needs to do a net minus and not just net zero.</li>
<li>Thanks to the efforts of India, the phrase used in the 2021 summit-level declarations at both G-20 and Quad is ‘global net zero’. We need to build on this understanding.</li>
<li>India stands as beacon of hope in renewables.</li>
<li>It is time for all developing countries, especially the small island developing states, to make sure that the developed world doesn’t backslide on its commitments on mitigation yet again.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward for developing countries</h4>
<ul>
<li>With countries of the developed world almost sure to renege on their 2030 Paris Agreement commitments, countries of the developing world must do everything to hold the countries of the developed world to their commitments.</li>
<li>The Western nations have already started reinterpreting the Paris Agreement and look to downgrade their commitments.</li>
<li>The concept of net zero is being cleverly misinterpreted.</li>
<li> To bring this to the attention of the Global South, India, China and eight other countries from Africa, Asia and Latin America made a cross-regional statement on ‘global net zero’ on June 7 at the UN on World Environment Day.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>COP 27 in Egypt gives us that opportunity to hold their feet to the fire. It is time for the developed world to make net minus pledges. If we don’t collectively push for it, we will be collectively pushed back.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/backsliding-on-climate-action/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is a Triple-Dip La Nina?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-triple-dip-la-nina/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Triple Dip La-Nina</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="nina" class="alignnone wp-image-356942" height="197" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 444px) 100vw, 444px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/enso-300x133.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/enso-300x133.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/enso.jpg 708w" width="444"/></p>
<p>Parts of the world are expected to experience severe weather for the rest of the year and into 2023, as part of a rare “triple dip La Nina” event, according to the World Meteorological Organization (WMO).</p>
<h4><strong>El Nino and La Nina</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While El Niño (Spanish for ‘little boy’), the more common expression, is the abnormal surface warming observed along the eastern and central regions of the Pacific Ocean (the region between Peru and Papua New Guinea).</li>
<li>The La Niña (Spanish for ‘little girl’) is an abnormal cooling of these surface waters.</li>
<li>Together, the El Niño (Warm Phase) and La Niña (Cool Phase) phenomena are termed as El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO).</li>
<li>These are large-scale ocean phenomena which influence the global weather — winds, temperature and rainfall. They have the ability to trigger extreme weather events like droughts, floods, hot and cold conditions, globally.</li>
<li>Each cycle can last anywhere between 9 to 12 months, at times extendable to 18 months — and re-occur after every three to five years.</li>
<li>Meteorologists record the sea surface temperatures for four different regions, known as Niño regions, along this equatorial belt.</li>
<li>Depending on the temperatures, they forecast either as an El Niño, an ENSO neutral phase, or a La Niña.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> What is the “Triple-Dip” La Nina? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A “triple-dip” La Nina is a <strong><u>multiyear cooling of the surface temperature of the equatorial Pacific Ocean</u></strong>, which can cause droughts, fierce winds and heavy rainfall.</li>
<li>According to WMO, the current La Nina is projected to span three consecutive northern hemisphere winters. It began in September 2020.</li>
<li>If it continues for the next six months, it will be the first “triple-dip” La Nina event of the 21st century, WMO says.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How rare is this triple-dip?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is exceptional to have three consecutive years with a la Nina event.</li>
<li>Its cooling influence is temporarily slowing the rise in global temperatures – but it will not halt or reverse the long-term warming trend.</li>
<li>La Nina’s are usually preceded by El Nino, a weather pattern that warms the surface of the eastern tropical Pacific Ocean.</li>
<li>However, an El Nino event did not occur before the current La Nina.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Has it happened before? Will it happen again?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>La Nina’s occurred several times between 1903 to 2010 and 2010 to 2012.</li>
<li>This would be the first “triple-dip” La Nina this century.</li>
<li>However, it is not unprecedented for the weather pattern to last more than nine months to a year, which is typical for a La Nina.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Evaluating the likely impact</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the Indian context, La Nina is associated with good rainfall during the monsoon season.</li>
<li>This is the opposite of El Nino which is known to suppress monsoon rainfall.</li>
<li>Thus, a continued spell of La Nina could lead to expectation of another year of good, or normal, rainfall during the monsoon.</li>
<li>Until now, the monsoon season this year has produced 7% more rain compared to normal. Last year, the seasonal rainfall was almost 100%.</li>
<li>But, even though powerful, ENSO condition is only one of the several factors affecting monsoon rainfall in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Impact on rainfall</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is no one-on-one correlation between the ENSO condition and the amount of rainfall.</li>
<li>Also, the influence of ENSO is at a macro level.</li>
<li>There are wide variations in rainfall at the local level, which are getting exacerbated by climate change.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Differential impacts of this triple-dip event</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The continuance of La Nina further into 2023 is not bad news from the Indian standpoint. But it is not the same for many other regions where La Nina has very different impacts.</li>
<li>In most parts of the <strong><u>United States</u></strong>, for example, La Nina is associated with <strong><u>very dry winters</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In <strong><u>Australia and Indonesia</u></strong>, and generally in the tropical region, La Nina is expected to bring <strong><u>more rainfall.</u></strong></li>
<li>The <strong><u>excessive rainfall in Pakistan</u></strong>, which is experiencing its worst flooding disaster, can also be blamed in part on La Nina.</li>
<li>It said that the persistence of La Nina was most likely to result in a worsening of the <strong><u>drought in Africa</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is its climate change link?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Every</u></strong><u> <strong>unusual weather event these days is attributed to climate change</strong></u>, but science is not conclusive right now.</li>
<li>The occurrences of El Nino or La Nina are not very regular.</li>
<li>Sometimes they emerge every two years, at other times there has been a gap of even seven years.</li>
<li>Historical records do not go very far in the past.</li>
<li>As a result, the natural variability of ENSO is not understood very clearly.</li>
<li>And when the natural variability itself is not clear, the influence of global warming is difficult to quantify.</li>
<li>But there is clearer evidence of another kind of linkage with global warming.</li>
<li>During La Nina years, the colder surfaces allow the oceans to absorb more heat from the atmosphere.</li>
<li>Consequently, the air temperatures tend to go down, producing a cooling effect.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-triple-dip-la-nina/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Southwest Monsoon begins early Withdrawal/Retreat</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/monsoon-begins-early-withdrawal-retreat/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Retreat of Monsoon</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The southwest monsoon rainfall, 7% more than normal, has started to withdraw.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Monsoon Withdrawal/Retreat?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In India, retreating <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/various-terms-related-to-indian-monsoon/">monsoon</a> is the withdrawal of south-west monsoon winds from North India.</li>
<li>The withdrawal is gradual and takes about three months.</li>
<li>With the retreat of the monsoons, the clouds disappear and the sky becomes clear. The day temperature starts falling steeply.</li>
<li>Monsoon rains weaken all over India except few southeastern states.</li>
<li>It is helpful in Rabi crop cultivation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Factors affecting the retreat</strong></h4>
<p>Two predominant factors cause the phenomenon:</p>
<p><strong>(1) Land topography</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>First, the low mountain range in each region runs from north to south, shielding it from west-bound winds that trigger summer monsoon.</li>
<li>After summer, the range aids in the ‘orographic lift’ or rising of east-bound air mass from a lower to higher elevation, forming clouds and resulting in rain.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Atmospheric convection</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The second factor is atmospheric convection or vertical movement of air.</li>
<li>As the earth is heated by the sun, different surfaces absorb different amounts of energy and convection may occur where the surface heats up very rapidly.</li>
<li>As the surface warms, it heats the overlying air, which gradually becomes less dense than the surrounding air and begins to rise.</li>
<li>This condition is more favorable from September to February because of the role played by sea surface temperature or water temperature.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Immediate factors influencing withdrawal</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The withdrawal of the monsoon is based on meteorological conditions such as-</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Anti-cyclonic circulation (dry air that is the opposite of a cyclone)</li>
<li>Absence of rain in the past five days and</li>
<li>Dry weather conditions over the region</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>When does it occur?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The monsoon withdrawal is a long-drawn process and extends into mid-October, though the <strong><u>IMD considers September 30 to be the final day</u></strong> of the season over India.</li>
<li>The rain after that is categorised as “<strong><u>post-monsoon</u></strong>” rainfall.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ:</h4>
<p><strong>Q.The seasonal reversal of winds is the typical characteristic of:</strong></p>
<p>(a) Equatorial climate</p>
<p>(b) Mediterranean climate</p>
<p>(c) Monsoon climate</p>
<p>(d) All of the above climates</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="I4EHflyfgs"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/various-terms-related-to-indian-monsoon/">Various terms related to Indian Monsoon</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="I4EHflyfgs" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/various-terms-related-to-indian-monsoon/embed/#?secret=U6HYHuUCWH#?secret=I4EHflyfgs" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“Various terms related to Indian Monsoon” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/monsoon-begins-early-withdrawal-retreat/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The heavy rainfall and the crazy Banglore flood: A case to study</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/flood/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>urban floods mitigation</p></div></div><h4><img alt="flood" class="alignnone wp-image-638490" height="321" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734.jpg 1600w" width="570"/>Context</h4>
<ul>
<li>The recent events of heavy downpours in short period of time and the recent example of Banglore flood, highlights how cities in India and elsewhere need to adapt to climate change as it brings more extreme rainfall in the future.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is heavy downpour?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A downpour or cloudburst is a sudden and unexpected heavy fall of rain.</li>
<li>It is usually local in nature and of brief duration. Most so-called cloudbursts occur in connection with thunderstorms.</li>
<li>Heavy downpour in short period causes flood, damage to buildings and infrastructure can disrupt transport, communications and connectivity, loss of crops and livestock.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The heavy rainfall and the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/floods/">Banglore flood</a> causes </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rise in built up area: </strong>Lakes and natural depressions may not always fill up during many monsoons so the people who are unaware of hydrology tempts to build and buy in the catchment areas of water-bodies, which will be disastrous when it rains heavily as there is rise in the quantity.</li>
<li><strong>Water-logging: </strong>rainwater and sewage water are forced to build up, which results in water-logging. The highway acts as a dam for the water ,Garbage frequently clogs drains, which limits the flow of sewage, and they are too small to support the weight of the expanding population.</li>
<li><strong>Physical shrinkage of water-bodies</strong>: Destruction of lakes is a major issue .lakes can store the excess water and regulate the flow of water however the pollution of natural water bodies and converting them for development purposes has increased the risks of floods<strong>. </strong>Unplanned growth, Rise in population<strong>, </strong>rise in the built up areas along streams, canals, around the lakes, leaving no storage capacity.</li>
<li><strong>Compromised runoff potential and health hazards</strong>: Choked and encroached drains and lakes, ill designed infrastructure and missing pipes compromising run off potential. Not only the physical quantity of the runoff that poses a hazard. When polluted drains and lakes overflow, the flood can pose a health hazard especially to vulnerable and exposed marginal communities living in informal settlements.</li>
<li><strong>Zero or limited ability to allow infiltration of water: </strong>Encroachments in and around wetlands and green lands harming the natural way of water infiltration and ground water recharge.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of vision in rain water harvesting: </strong>Ignorance towards the tradition rain water harvesting techniques and no or limited vision for creating new systems of rain water harvesting. Exceptionally heavy monsoon rains have been exacerbated by poor urban planning in the Indian tech hub, showing the need for improved water systems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="flood" class="alignnone wp-image-638492" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 641px) 100vw, 641px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/deccan-Herald-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/deccan-Herald-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/deccan-Herald.jpg 708w" width="641"/>What are the reasons behind the frequent floods in urban areas?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Meteorological factors</strong>: change in the weather patterns, increase in the temperature leading to heavy rainfall, sudden downpour, cloudburst, thunderstorms, hailstorms etc.</li>
<li><strong>Hydrological factors</strong>: Natural surface infiltration rate, soil moisture level, presence or absence of Overbank flows, Presence of impervious cover, the occurrence of high tides impeding the drainage in coastal cities.</li>
<li><strong>Man-Made factors: </strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Unplanned urbanization: </strong>Unplanned settlement is one of the main cause of urban flooding. Blocking of natural drainage pathways through construction activity and encroachment on catchment areas, streams, rivers, lakebeds. Reduced infiltration and ground water recharge of water, destruction of lakes, Land-use changes (e.g. surface sealing due to urbanization, deforestation) increase runoff and sedimentation. Inefficiency or non-maintenance of infrastructure etc.</li>
<li><strong>Outdated Drainage systems</strong>: The old and ill-maintained drainage system is one of the main factor making cities in India vulnerable to flooding</li>
<li><strong>Encroachments on and around water-bodies: </strong>Illegal Habitations started growing into towns and cities alongside rivers and watercourses. As a result of this, the capacity of the natural drains has decreased, resulting in flooding.</li>
<li><strong>Climate Change: </strong>Climate change due to various anthropogenic events has led to extreme weather events, increasing temperature which resulting in heavy rainfall in one part while drought and dry spells in other.</li>
<li><strong>Poor Solid Waste Management System:</strong> Indiscriminate disposal of solid waste, poor waste management system, clogging drains because of accumulation of non-biodegradable wastes are major concerns. Domestic, commercial and industrial waste and dumping of it into the drains also contribute significantly to reducing their capacities.</li>
<li><strong>Reduced Seepage:</strong> use of hard and non-porous construction material making the soil impervious, reducing the seepage capability in no of cities in India.</li>
<li><strong>Weak Implementation and lack of awareness:</strong>Even with provisions of rainwater harvesting, sustainable urban drainage systems, etc, in regulatory mechanisms like the Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA), adoption at user end as well as enforcement agencies remains weak.</li>
<li><strong>No Community Participation:</strong>Flood control measures planned without participation of the affected community are unsustainable as they do not meet the needs of relevant stakeholders.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to prevent the urban floods and prevent losses?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Developing climate Resilient Infrastructure:</strong> using permeable material for roads and pavement, green roofs and harvesting systems in buildings. To reduce the burden of road infrastructure in cities Outer Ring Road should be explored. Innovative approaches like Sponge Cities wetland restoration, flushing systems using collected rooftop water, public spaces as flexible water retention facilities can be applied to Indian urban areas.</li>
<li><strong>Use of technology in Early Warning Systems and Communication: </strong>Early-warning systems using sensors across waterbodies and drains, and a network of communication for hotspots of emerging flood risk in the wet-season should be put in place. Providing real-time data where traditional systems fail. Tools such as predictive precipitation modelingcan help do that and are also able to link it with the adaptive capacity of urban land use.</li>
<li><strong>Proper management and regular upgrade of Urban Drainage System:</strong> drains need to be cleaned on a regular basis to permit the free flow of water .Proper management of the drainage system is necessary to ensure that the water does not get stored in one place. Watershed management and emergency drainage plan should be clearly enunciated in policy.</li>
<li><strong>Rainwater Harvesting</strong>: It will serve the twin purposes of lowering the peak runoff and raising the groundwater table. Many municipal corporations in India have already made rainwater harvesting compulsory<strong>. </strong></li>
<li><strong>Conservation of Water Bodies: </strong>Urban water bodies like lakes, tanks, and ponds also play a very important role in the management of urban flooding by reducing the flood water run-off by capturing it.</li>
<li><strong>Holistic approach: </strong>Improved monitoring, forecasting, and decision-support systems. Find out the different method for improving the preparedness for urban flooding.</li>
<li><strong>Responsibility on every stakeholder: </strong>Locally, citizens, local ward officials and staff will need to work together to minimize dumping of solid waste and garbage in storm-water drains. As this is a socio –political problem, public participation awareness and responsibility of citizen is the need of the hour. To develop a long-lasting solution, all parties must acknowledge the issues and adopt a thorough strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What we as citizens can do on a personal level to prevent the urban environment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Raising voice at all available forums and platforms</li>
<li>Making politicians and bureaucrats accountable</li>
<li>Refuse to buy a house in the encroached lands.</li>
<li>Applying methods of rain water harvesting on individual level.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Exceptionally heavy monsoon rains have been exacerbated by poor urban planning in the Indian tech hub, showing the need for improved water systems.</li>
<li>Urbanization is a global and inevitable process, and with cities as engines of the economy, built-up areas will continue to grow. But we need to draw upon these experiences and the growing perils of climate change and extreme rain events and change course.</li>
<li>According to UN projections, by 2050 more than 68% of the world’s population could be concentrated in urban areas.</li>
<li>In this context, resilience-based strategies should be adopted to improve the capacity to handle the crisis arising out of climate change.</li>
<li>Wetlands are the kidneys of the earth, let’s keep it healthy.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What are the factors causing flood in the urban cities? What are the measures to prevent the urban flooding keeping in mind the sustainable development? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/flood/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Multilateralism will open pandora of opportunities for India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/multilateralism/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>SCO and QUAD</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>multilateralism</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="multilateralism" class="alignnone wp-image-638494" height="399" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 599px) 100vw, 599px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/brics-621x414-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/brics-621x414-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/brics-621x414-1.jpg 621w" width="599"/>Context</strong></h4>
<p>India may give up its strategic balancing of China and West if the Ukraine war weakens Russia. Because for major defence supplies India is dependent on Russia.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/growing-salience-of-multilateralism/"><strong>What is the concept of multilateralism?</strong></a></p>
<ul>
<li>Process of organizing relations between groups of three or more states. Beyond that basic quantitative aspect, multilateralism is generally considered to comprise certain qualitative elements or principles that shape the character of the arrangement or institution.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is SCO?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Shanghai Cooperation Organization (SCO) is a Eurasian political, economic and security organization.</li>
<li><strong>Global share:</strong> In terms of geographic scope and population, it is the world’s largest regional organization, covering approximately 60% of the area of Eurasia, 40% of the world population, and more than 30% of global GDP.</li>
<li><strong>Members</strong>: The SCO currently comprises eight Member States. They are- China, India, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Russia, Pakistan, Tajikistan and Uzbekistan.</li>
<li><strong>Headquarters</strong>: Beijing, China.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is QUAD?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (QSD), commonly known as the Quad.</li>
<li>It is a strategic security dialogue.</li>
<li><strong>Members</strong>: Australia, India, Japan, and the United States.</li>
<li><strong>Origin</strong>: The dialogue was initiated in 2007.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="multilateralism" class="alignnone wp-image-638498" height="562" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 538px) 100vw, 538px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-287x300.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-287x300.jpeg 287w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-978x1024.jpeg 978w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-768x804.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-860x900.jpeg 860w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2.jpeg 1200w" width="538"/>Which factors forced India to have more engagements with QUAD?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Chinese threat has been largely responsible in shaping New Delhi’s Indo Pacific Policy.</li>
<li>The China’s Belt and Road initiative and the growing China’s presence in India’s neighborhood- as evident from China’s investment not only in Pakistan and Myanmar, but also in Nepal and Sri Lanka. Because of such activities India felt encircled.</li>
<li>The very launch of the QUAD initiative was the reaction to China’s assertiveness in the Indo Pacific region.</li>
<li>India agreed to upgrade the quad meeting at the ministerial level only after the gunmen attack of 2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How India is maintaining balance between the West and China-Russia Alliance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Plurilateralism</strong>: India continued to believe in <strong>plurilateralism</strong>, a doctrine elucidated by external affairs Minister S Jaishankar in his book <strong>‘The Indian Way</strong>’.</li>
<li><strong>Member of both QUAD and SCO</strong>: Along with QUAD, India also took membership of SCO. It means India dealing with the USA and Japan on one side and Russia and China on the other.</li>
<li><strong>Simultaneously dealing with many powers: </strong>India is engaging with competing powers like the USA, China, the EU or Russia at the same time.</li>
<li><strong>Multipolar world: </strong>India stands in favor of a <strong>multipolar world</strong> where the plurality of power centers would allow her to play one pole against the other. In this context, New Delhi wants Russia to remain an important player.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="multilateralism" class="alignnone wp-image-638500" height="353" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 602px) 100vw, 602px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-300x176.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-300x176.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1.jpg 637w" width="602"/><br/>
What are India’s concerns regarding the West created world order?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The stand on Multilateralism goes together with India’s reservations (not being completely satisfied) against the West’s past hegemony and the international orders that were established after 1945.</li>
<li>MEA S Jaishankar emphasises that the West has imposed norms on the world that need to be dismantled. He says, “The key of western durability till now is the set of institutions and practices that it progressively but firmly established in the period of its dominance”.</li>
<li>The world order and the institutions are created and supported by the West by narratives that serve the West well, while diminishing its competitors.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the steps taken by India to deal with the West created world order and institutions ?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s engagement with the other regional organizations like BRICS, SCO, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Doctrine of Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam: </strong>India’s foreign policy has been based on the philosophy of Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam.</li>
<li><strong>UN Reforms:</strong> Efforts towards bringing reforms in the UNs.</li>
<li><strong>Shift from Non-Alignment to Multi-Alignment:</strong> Multi-alignment is the very essence of India’s foreign policy and the economic policy of India today. Promotion of multilateralism by engaging with many poles simultaneously.</li>
<li><strong>Various Multilateral initiatives: </strong>India has taken the lead in promoting various multilateral initiatives like International Solar Alliance, proposing CCIT for combating terrorism, Asia-Africa Growth corridor.</li>
<li><strong>Collaborating with Like-minded Countries: </strong>India could work closely with the <strong>Alliance for Multilateralism </strong>(an initiative launched by Germany and France) to shape both the alliance itself and the reform agenda at large.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is Russia important for India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Military supplies</strong>: India is heavily dependent on Russia for its military supplies with more than two-third of its weapons coming from Russia. For example: S-400 is the recent supply to India by Russia.</li>
<li><strong>Balancing China:</strong> Russia is important for India to balance China. More isolation of Russia may push Russia closer to China.</li>
<li><strong>To promote multilateralism</strong>: To maintain multilateral world order Russia is a major player or partner for India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A multilateral world order with power decentralized between all the regions and all the economic strata is critical for any sustainable model of peace and prosperity to be gained. The UN and similar bodies must recognize the need of the hour and must reform or else they will perish in yet another set of protectionism, distrust, and possible large-scale military conflicts like Russia- Ukraine.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What are the concerns of India regarding the present world order created by the West? </strong><strong>How can India promote multilateralism by playing a balancing role between the QUAD and the SCO?  What is the importance of Russia for India in the present global situation? Explain.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/multilateralism/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>On reservations for disempowered Dalit Christians and Muslims, a question of government’s intent</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dalit/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>social justice</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="dalit" class="alignnone wp-image-638560" height="367" sizes="(max-width: 551px) 100vw, 551px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1457603210-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1457603210-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1457603210.jpeg 555w" width="551"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Union government intends to appoint a national commission to study the status of Dalits (ex “untouchable” castes) belonging to the Muslim and Christian communities. Aim of study to check the socio-economic condition of Muslims and Christian Dalits on par with Hindu, Sikh, Buddhist Dalits.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Current reservation policy</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At present, scheduled caste reservation is applicable only to schedule caste (Dalit) belongs to Hindu, Sikh, Buddhist. Currently it is unavailable for schedule caste belongs to Muslims and Christians.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why Muslim and Christian Dalit needs reservation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2008 review-study commissioned by the National Commission of Minorities (NCM) and housed in the Sociology Department of <a href="https://indianexpress.com/section/cities/delhi/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Delhi</a> The remit of the study was to conduct a comprehensive review of already existing social-scientific evidence that might offer answers to three questions.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>What is the contemporary status of Dalit Muslims (DMs) and Dalit Christians (DCs) in terms of their material well-being and social status?</li>
<li>How does their situation compare with that of: a) non-Dalits of their own communities, and b) Dalits of other communities?</li>
<li>Do the caste disabilities suffered by these groups justify state intervention?</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong><img alt="dalit" class="alignnone wp-image-638564" height="308" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 547px) 100vw, 547px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537.jpg 777w" width="547"/>What were the findings of study?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The study reviewed two main kinds of available evidence, ethnographic-descriptive and macro-statistical, in addition to semi-academic NGO reports and publications.</li>
<li>The survey of ethnographic materials began with the finding that the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-caste-system/">existence of caste divisions</a> – including the presence of ex-untouchable castes recognised as such – among both Muslims and Christians – was beyond dispute.</li>
<li>DMs and DCs were identified and segregated much like their counterparts in the Hindu or Sikh communities.</li>
<li>Evidence was tabulated on five forms of caste-based social discrimination – the practice untouchability; enforced ban on inter-marriage; occupational segregation; social and cultural segregation and finally, economic discrimination.</li>
<li>The most common instances were separate mosques or churches (or hierarchically segregated seating); separate burial grounds; strict prohibition on inter-marriage with very severe punishments (sometimes extending to murder) for breaking this taboo; and general avoidance of social interaction and cooperation.</li>
<li>The main findings were that DMs are clearly the worst off among all Dalits, while DCs are somewhat better off than other Dalits except Sikh Dalits (who are by far the best off, especially in the rural sector).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why DMs and DCs doesn’t have reservation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The courts accept that “caste survives conversion” but complain about the lack of reliable data. No recognition, no data; no data, no recognition.</li>
<li>Informal guesstimates (based on the 2001 Census and the 2004-05 NSSO survey) place the proportion of DMs at 1 per cent or less of the Muslim population, and DCs as anything between 40-50 per cent of the Christian population of India.</li>
<li>As per the 2011 Census, Muslims are 14.2 per cent and Christians 2.3 per cent of our population. Taken together, DMs and DCs are likely to form less than 2 per cent of the total Dalit population of India, more than 90 per cent of which is Hindu.</li>
<li>According to experts Adding DMs and DCs will not rock the boat of reservation, since the increment will be roughly one-fifth of the 10 per cent reservation readily granted to the upper castes as the Economically Weaker Sections.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What efforts have been made to include Muslims and Christians of Dalit origin among SCs?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>After 1990, a number of Private Member’s Bills were brought in Parliament for this purpose.</li>
<li>In 1996, a government Bill called The Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Orders (Amendment) Bill was drafted, but in view of a divergence of opinions, the Bill was not introduced in Parliament.</li>
<li>Then government headed by PM Manmohan Singh set up two important panels:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Ranganath Misra Commission:</strong> The National Commission for Religious and Linguistic Minorities, popularly known as the Ranganath Misra Commission, in October 2004 and</li>
<li><strong>Sachar Committee:</strong> A seven-member high-level committee headed by former Chief Justice of Delhi High Court Rajinder Sachar to study the social, economic, and educational condition of Muslims in March 2005.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What did they recommend?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Sachar Committee Report</u></strong> observed that the social and economic situation of Dalit Muslims and Dalit Christians did not improve after conversion.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Ranganath Misra Commission</u></strong>, which submitted its report in May 2007, recommended that SC status should be completely de-linked from religion and Scheduled Castes should be made fully religion-neutral like Scheduled Tribes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="dalit" class="alignnone wp-image-638566" height="321" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 609px) 100vw, 609px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244.jpg 1200w" width="609"/>Reception to these recommendations</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The report was tabled in Parliament in 2009, but its recommendation was <strong><u>not accepted</u></strong> in view of inadequate field data and corroboration with the actual situation on the ground.</li>
<li>Few studies, commissioned by the National Commission for Minorities, was also <strong><u>not considered reliable due to insufficient data.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Schedule caste community from all religion India suffers from same fate of untouchability. Change of religion unfortunately, have change their social status. If 70+ year of reservation of Dalit in Hindu haven’t substantially change their social destiny, we have to think beyond reservation for social dignity and economic empowerment of schedule castes in India.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Reservation policy in India is religion based and not based on overall social discrimination. Comment in the context of demand for Dalit reservation extension to Christians and Muslims Dalits.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dalit/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>