<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 19:10:56 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Centre raises credit limit under ECLGS</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/eclgs-centre-raises-credit-limit/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>ECLGS Scheme</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Ministry of Finance has raised the credit limit for airlines under the Emergency Credit Line Guarantee Scheme (ECLGS), making them eligible for a sum equivalent to 100% of their outstanding debt, up to a maximum of ₹1,500 crore.</p>
<h4><strong>Boost for Aviation sector</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Earlier, airlines were eligible to borrow up to 50% of their credit outstanding up to ₹400 crore.</li>
<li>This is the second time the government has liberalized the scheme for the aviation sector.</li>
<li>The scheme introduced for medium and small enterprises during the outbreak of the COVID-19 pandemic was extended till March 2023 and its guarantee cover expanded by ₹50,000 crore to ₹5 lakh crore.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is ECLGS?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Under the Scheme, 100% guarantee coverage to be provided by National Credit Guarantee Trustee Company Limited (NCGTC) for additional funding of up to Rs. 3 lakh crore to eligible MSMEs and interested MUDRA borrowers.</li>
<li>The credit will be provided in the form of a Guaranteed Emergency Credit Line (GECL) facility.</li>
<li>The Scheme would be applicable to all loans sanctioned under GECL Facility during the period from the date of announcement of the Scheme to 31.10.2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Aims and objectives</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Scheme aims at mitigating the economic distress faced by MSMEs by providing them additional funding in the form of a fully guaranteed emergency credit line.</li>
<li>The main objective is to provide an incentive to Member Lending Institutions (MLIs), i.e., Banks, Financial Institutions (FIs) and NBFCs to increase access to, and enable the availability of additional funding facility to MSME borrowers.</li>
<li>It aims to provide a 100 per cent guarantee for any losses suffered by them due to non-repayment of the GECL funding by borrowers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Salient features of ECGLS<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The entire funding provided under GECL shall be provided with a 100% credit guarantee by NCGTC to MLIs under ECLGS.</li>
<li>Tenor of the loan under Scheme shall be four years with a moratorium period of one year on the principal amount.</li>
<li>No Guarantee Fee shall be charged by NCGTC from the Member Lending Institutions (MLIs) under the Scheme.</li>
<li>Interest rates under the Scheme shall be capped at 9.25% for banks and FIs, and at 14% for NBFCs.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/eclgs-centre-raises-credit-limit/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Nobel for work on Click Chemistry</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nobel-for-work-on-click-chemistry/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Click Chemistry</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="click" class="alignnone wp-image-644553 size-full" height="2362" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 2362px) 100vw, 2362px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-1.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-1.jpg 2362w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-1-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-1-2048x2048.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-1-900x900.jpg 900w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-1-1200x1200.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nobel-1-1980x1980.jpg 1980w" width="2362"/></p>
<p>Scientists Carolyn R. Bertozzi, Morten Meldal and K. Barry Sharpless won the 2022 Nobel Prize in Chemistry on for discovering reactions that let molecules snap together to create desired compounds and that offer insight into cell biology.</p>
<h4><strong>What the scientists worked on?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sharpless came up with the term ‘<strong><u>Click Chemistry’</u></strong> and worked extensively on it,</li>
<li>Meldal came up with a special chemical structure called ‘<strong><u>Triazole’</u></strong> which has many significant applications, and</li>
<li>Bertozzi took the next step of developing click reactions that could work inside living organisms — <strong><u>‘bioorthogonal’ reactions</u></strong> take place living systems without interfering with native biochemical processes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Click Chemistry?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Chemists often try to recreate complex chemical molecules found in nature, and this has applications, among other things, in the field of medicine – how to target and block pathogens in cells.</li>
<li>However, this process can be complicated and time-consuming.</li>
<li>Instead of trying to wrangle reluctant carbon atoms into reacting with each other, Barry Sharpless encouraged his colleagues to start with smaller molecules that already had a complete carbon frame.</li>
<li>If chemists choose simple reactions – where there is a strong intrinsic drive for the molecules to bond together – they avoid many of the side reactions, with a minimal loss of material.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Applications of click chemistry</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Meldal through his experiments came up with the useful chemical structure called triazoles, whch are stable and are found in pharmaceuticals, dyes and agricultural chemicals.</li>
<li>He also found that the reaction he used could bind together numerous different molecules.</li>
<li>Bertozzi, using the work of Sharpless and Meldal, came up with an efficient and innovative method to map glycans, which are carbohydrate-based polymers made by all living organisms.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nobel-for-work-on-click-chemistry/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>In news: Criterion for SC status</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/criterion-for-sc-status/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>SC status and related issues</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has sought the most recent position of the Union government on a batch of petitions challenging the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order of 1950, which allows only members of Hindu, Sikh and Buddhist religions to be recognised as SCs.</p>
<h4><strong>The Constitution Order of 1950</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When enacted, the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order of 1950, initially provided for recognising only Hindus as SCs.</li>
<li>It was then aimed to address the social disability arising out of the practice of untouchability.</li>
<li>The Order was amended in 1956 to include Dalits who had converted to Sikhism and once more in 1990 to include Dalits who had converted to Buddhism.</li>
<li>Both amendments were aided by the reports of the <strong><u>Kaka Kalelkar Commission</u></strong> in 1955 and the High Powered Panel (HPP) on Minorities, SCs and STs in 1983 respectively.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What about Christians?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Union government in 2019 rejected the possibility of including Dalit Christians as members of SCs.</li>
<li>This decision was rooted on the exclusion on an Imperial Order of 1936 of the then colonial government, which had first classified a list of the Depressed Classes and specifically excluded “Indian Christians” from it.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why are Dalit Christians excluded?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>SC status is meant for communities suffering from social disabilities arising out of the practice of <strong><u>untouchability that was prevalent in Hindu and Sikh communities</u></strong>.</li>
<li>SC status for everyone would significantly <strong><u>swell the population of SCs</u></strong> across the country thus trivializing the purpose itself.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why neo-Buddhists are included in SC quota?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The amendment to include Buddhist converts as SCs was passed in 1990.</li>
<li>Like Dalit Buddhists, Dalits who converted to Islam or Christianity belonged to different sets of caste groups and not just one.</li>
<li>As a result of this, they cannot be categorised as a “single ethnic group”, which is required by Clause (2) of Article 341 for inclusion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Major concerns of including other religions</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sanction of untouchability:</strong> The practice of “untouchability” was a feature of Hindu religion and its branches. This would imply that India was trying to “impose its caste system” upon Christians and Muslims.</li>
<li><strong>Undue internationalization:</strong> Allowing the inclusion of Dalit Muslims and Dalit Christians as SCs could result in being misunderstood internationally.</li>
<li><strong>Reviving casteism:</strong> Christians and Muslims of Dalit origin had lost their caste identity by way of their conversion and that in their new religious community, the practice of untouchability is not prevalent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Is there a case for inclusion?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The petitions arguing for inclusion have cited several independent Commission reports that have documented the existence of caste and caste inequalities among Indian Christians and Indian Muslims.</li>
<li>Even after conversion, members who were originally from SCs continued to experience the same social disabilities.</li>
<li>This was substantiated in the First Backward Classes Commission’s report in 1953, the HPP report on SCs, STs, and Minorities in 1983, the Mandal Commission Report, etc.</li>
<li>However, these reports do not have enough empirical evidence to support their claims.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is the issue debated?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Non-deserving beneficiaries:</strong> The proposition that caste identity is lost upon conversion, noting that even in Sikhism and Buddhism, casteism is not present and yet they have been included as SCs.</li>
<li><strong>Continued discrimination:</strong> The above-mentioned reports argue that caste-based discrimination continues even after conversion, hence entitling these communities to SC status.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/criterion-for-sc-status/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Parliamentary Committees, their leaders, and their role in law-making</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/parliamentary-committee-significance/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Parliamentary Committess</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>A recent revamp of the Standing Committees of Parliament could potentially worsen the relations between the government and opposition parties.</p>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Of the 22 committees announced, the erstwhile ruling party has the post of chairperson in only one, and the opposition party from West Bengal has none.</li>
<li>The ruling party has the chairmanship of the important committees on Home, Finance, IT, Defence and External Affairs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Committees of Parliament?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A Parliamentary Committee is a panel of MPs that is appointed or elected by the House or nominated by the Speaker, and which works under the direction of the Speaker.</li>
<li>It presents its report to the House or to the Speaker.</li>
<li>Parliamentary Committees have their origins in the British Parliament.</li>
<li>They draw their authority from Article 105, which deals with the privileges of MPs, and Article 118, which gives Parliament authority to make rules to regulate its procedure and conduct of business.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What do they do?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Legislative business begins when a Bill is introduced in either House of Parliament.</li>
<li>But the process of lawmaking is often complex, and Parliament has limited time for detailed discussions.</li>
<li>Also, the political polarisation and shrinking middle ground has been leading to inconclusive debates in Parliament.</li>
<li>As a result of this, a great deal of legislative business ends up taking place in the Parliamentary Committees instead.</li>
<li>The aim is to increase Parliamentary scrutiny, and to give members more time and a wider role in examining important legislation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the various Committees of Parliament?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Broadly, Parliamentary Committees can be classified into Financial Committees, Departmentally Related Standing Committees, Other Parliamentary Standing Committees, and Ad hoc Committees.</li>
<li>The Financial Committees include the Estimates Committee, Public Accounts Committee, and the Committee on Public Undertakings.</li>
<li>These committees were constituted in 1950.</li>
<li>Seventeen Departmentally Related Standing Committees came into being in 1993, when Shivraj Patil was Speaker of Lok Sabha.</li>
<li>They aimed to examine budgetary proposals and crucial government policies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Composition of these committees</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The number of Committees was subsequently increased to 24.</li>
<li>Each of these Committees has 31 members — 21 from Lok Sabha and 10 from Rajya Sabha.</li>
<li>Ad hoc Committees are appointed for a specific purpose.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How are the Committees constituted?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There are 16 Departmentally Related Standing Committees for Lok Sabha and eight for Rajya Sabha; however, every Committee has members from both Houses.</li>
<li>Lok Sabha and Rajya Sabha panels are headed by members of these respective Houses.</li>
<li>Among the important Lok Sabha panels are: Agriculture; Coal; Defence; External Affairs; Finance; Communications &amp; Information Technology; Labour; Petroleum &amp; Natural Gas; and Railways.</li>
<li>The important Rajya Sabha panels include Commerce; Education; Health &amp; Family Welfare; Home Affairs; and Environment.</li>
<li>There are other Standing Committees for each House, such as the Business Advisory Committee and the Privileges Committee.</li>
<li>The Presiding Officer of each House nominates members to these panels. A Minister is not eligible for election or nomination to Financial Committees, and certain Departmentally Related Committees.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Appointing of chairmen </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The appointment of heads of the Committees is also done in a similar way. By convention, the main Opposition party gets the post of PAC chairman; it is currently with the Congress.</li>
<li>Chairmanship of some key committees has been allocated to opposition parties in the past. However, this pattern has changed in the latest rejig.</li>
<li>The heads of the panels schedule their meetings.</li>
<li>They play a clear role in preparing the agenda and the annual report, and can take decisions in the interest of the efficient management of the Committee.</li>
<li>The chairperson presides over the meetings and can decide who should be summoned before the panel.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How do they work?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bills that are referred to Committees often return to the House with significant value-addition.</li>
<li>The Committees look into the demands for grants of Ministries/departments, examine Bills pertaining to them, consider their annual reports, and look into their long-term plans and report to Parliament.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Ad hoc Committees?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Ad hoc Committees cease to exist after they have completed the task assigned to them, and have submitted a report to the House.</li>
<li>The principal Ad hoc Committees are the Select and Joint Committees on Bills.</li>
<li>Committees like the Railway Convention Committee, Committee on Food Management and Security in Parliament House Complex, etc. also come under the category of Ad hoc Committees.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What about Joint Parliamentary Committee (JPC)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Parliament can also constitute a JPC with a special purpose, with members from both Houses, for detailed scrutiny of a subject or Bill.</li>
<li>Also, either of the two Houses can set up a Select Committee with members from that House.</li>
<li>JPCs and Select Committees are usually chaired by ruling party MPs, and are disbanded after they have submitted their report.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need all these committees?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The time to speak on a Bill is allocated according to the size of the party in the House.</li>
<li>MPs often do not get adequate time to put forward their views in Parliament, even if they are experts on the subject.</li>
<li>Committees are small groups with relatively less demands on their time; in these meetings, every MP gets a chance and the time to contribute to the discussion.</li>
<li>Parliament has only around 100 sittings a year; Committee meetings are independent of Parliament’s calendar.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How do discussions/ debates here differ from those in Parliament?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The discussions are confidential and off-camera.</li>
<li>Political Party affiliations usually do not come in the way of MPs speaking their minds in ways they are unable to do in Parliament.</li>
<li>The Committees work closely with multiple Ministries, and facilitate inter-ministerial coordination.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How important are the recommendations of the Committees?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Reports of Departmentally Related Standing Committees are <strong><u>recommendatory in nature</u></strong>.</li>
<li>However, suggestions by the Select Committees and JPCs — which have a majority of MPs and heads from the ruling party — are accepted more frequently.</li>
<li>They are not binding on the government, but they <strong><u>do carry significant weight</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In the past, governments have accepted suggestions given by the Committees and incorporated them into the Bills.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Significance of Parliamentary committees</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Many MPs concede that “real discussions” happen inside the Committees.</li>
<li>The former US President Woodrow Wilson had observed that “Congress in session is Congress on public exhibition, whilst Congress in its committee rooms is Congress at work”.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ:</h4>
<p><strong>Q.With reference to the Parliament of India which of the following Parliamentary Committees scrutinizes and reports to the House whether the powers to make regulations, rules, sub rules, bylaws, etc. conferred by the Constitution or delegated by the Parliament are being properly exercised by the Executive within the scope of such delegation? </strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p>(a) Committee on Government Assurances</p>
<p>(b) Committee on Subordinate Legislation</p>
<p>(c) Rules Committee</p>
<p>(d) Business Advisory Committee</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/parliamentary-committee-significance/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Marital rape, MTP Act and the Society</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/marital-rape/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>MTP Act.</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Abortion rights,Persistence of marital rape and need for its criminalization</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Marital rape" class="alignnone wp-image-644505 size-full" height="807" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 962px) 100vw, 962px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.03.12.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.03.12.jpeg 962w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.03.12-300x252.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.03.12-768x644.jpeg 768w" width="962"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The recent Supreme court judgment expands the definition of rape to marital rape for the MTP Act. Marital rape is still not criminalised. If society does not accept “marital rape” as even a moral offence, how will a woman convince doctors to terminate her pregnancy based on the exception provided by the SC’s verdict.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>B</strong><strong>ackground</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court has held that all women, irrespective of their marital status, are entitled to safe and legal abortion till 24 weeks of pregnancy under the Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Abortion in India has been a legal right under various circumstances for the last 50 years since the introduction of the<strong> </strong>Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act in 1971</li>
<li>The Act was amended in 2003 to enable women’s access to safe and legal abortion services.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Marital rape" class="alignnone wp-image-644502 size-full" height="344" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 899px) 100vw, 899px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.03.21.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.03.21.jpeg 899w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.03.21-300x115.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.03.21-768x294.jpeg 768w" width="899"/>What are the Changes in <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-legal-and-safe-abortion/">Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act,</a> 2021?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>The gestation limit</strong>: The gestation limit for abortions has been raised from the earlier ceiling of 20 weeks to 24 weeks, but only for special categories of pregnant women such as rape or incest survivors. But this termination would need the approval of two registered doctors.</li>
<li><strong>Doctor’s approval: </strong>All pregnancies up to 20 weeks require one doctor’s approval. The earlier law, the MTP Act 1971, required one doctor’s approval for pregnancies up to 12 weeks and two doctors’ for pregnancies between 12 and 20 weeks.</li>
<li><strong>Contraceptive failure: </strong>Women can now terminate unwanted pregnancies caused by contraceptive failure, regardless of their marital status. Earlier the law specified that only a “married woman and her husband” could do this.</li>
<li><strong>In case of fetal disability</strong>:  There is also no upper gestation limit for abortion in case of fetal disability if so decided by a medical board of specialist doctors, which state governments and union territories’ administrations would set up.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is marital rape?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Marital rape is the act of sexual intercourse with one’s spouse without her consent.</li>
<li>It is no different manifestation of domestic violence and sexual abuse.</li>
<li>It is often a chronic form of violence for the victim which takes place within abusive relations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Marital rape" class="alignnone wp-image-644509 size-full" height="401" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 764px) 100vw, 764px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.03.26.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.03.26.jpeg 764w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-03-at-07.03.26-300x157.jpeg 300w" width="764"/>Statistics on Marital rape in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>The NFHS-5 survey (2019-21):</strong></li>
<li>The survey said that 32% of ever-married women have suffered spousal physical, sexual, or emotional violence, and 27% have suffered at least one form of violence.</li>
<li>Twenty-nine percent of ever- married women have experienced spousal physical violence and 14% have suffered emotional violence.</li>
<li>The form of sexual violence most commonly reported by women is that their husband used physical force to have sexual intercourse when they did not want to (5%).</li>
<li>Four per cent reported that their husband forced them with threats or in other ways to perform sexual acts they did not want to and 3% of them reported that their husband forced them to perform any sexual acts they did not want to.</li>
<li>Women in rural areas are more likely (34%) than women in urban areas (27%) to experience one or more forms of spousal violence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why modern India still not accepting marital rape as a rape?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Definition: </strong>The definition of rape codified in Section 375 of the Indian Penal Code (IPC) includes all forms of sexual assault involving non-consensual intercourse with a woman.</li>
<li><strong>Non-Criminalization</strong>: Non-Criminalization of marital rape in India emanates from Exception 2 to Section 375.</li>
<li><strong>Exemption:</strong> Section 375 defines rape and lists seven notions of consent which, if vitiated, would constitute the offence of rape by a man. However, the provision contains a crucial exemption, Sexual intercourse or sexual acts by a man with his own wife, the wife not being under eighteen years of age, is not rape.</li>
<li><strong>Marriage as perpetual consent</strong>: As per current law, a wife is presumed to deliver perpetual consent to have sex with her husband after entering marital relations. The concept of marital rape in India is the epitome of what we call an “implied consent”. Marriage between a man and a woman here implies that both have consented to sexual intercourse, and it cannot be otherwise.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the link between marital rape and MTP Act?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>The distinction and the cultural ethos:</strong> Married women have a different world attire, jewellery, rituals compared to widows or unmarried or deserted women .So is the right to sexual intercourse. In contrast, unmarried women do not have a right to sex. So what does the right to terminate pregnancy mean for them</li>
<li><strong>Ownership of women’s sexuality:</strong> Unmarried women cannot have sex, married women cannot say no to sex because men own women’s sexuality<strong>.</strong> Husbands can use the legal remedy of restitution of conjugal rights against runaway wives. Ownership is integral here</li>
<li><strong>Cause of Disharmony:</strong> An unmarried woman does not have an owner. It causes confusion and disorder. Women’s sexuality is seen as a cause of disharmony.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Marital rape" class="alignnone wp-image-644506 size-full" height="338" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.40.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.40.jpeg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.40-300x169.jpeg 300w" width="600"/>Why marital rape must be a crime?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Associated physical violence:</strong> Rape by a spouse, partner or ex-partner is more often associated with physical violence.</li>
<li><strong>Mental harassment:</strong> There is research showing that marital rape can be more emotionally and physically damaging than rape by a stranger.</li>
<li><strong>Compulsive relationship:</strong> Marital rape may occur as part of an abusive relationship.</li>
<li><strong>Revengeful nature:</strong> Furthermore, marital rape is rarely a one-time event, but a repeated if not frequent occurrence.</li>
<li><strong>Obligation on women:</strong> In the case of marital rape the victim often has no choice but to continue living with their spouse.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Present regulations in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian Penal Code criminalizes rape in most cases, although marital rape is not illegal when the woman is over the age of 18.</li>
<li>However, until 2017, men married to those between 15 and 18 could not be convicted of rape.</li>
<li>Marital rape of an adult wife, who is unofficially or officially separated, is a criminal offence punishable by 2 to 7 year in prison; it is not dealt by normal rape laws which stipulate the possibility of a death sentence.</li>
<li>According to the Protection of Women From Domestic Violence Act (2005), other married women subject to such crime by their husband may demand for financial compensation.</li>
<li>They also have the right to continue to live in their marital household if they wish, or may approach shelter or aid homes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sanctioning marital rape is an acknowledgment of the woman’s right to self-determination (i.e., control of all matters relating to her body.</li>
<li>The recent judgment on the MTP Act has extended the definition of rape to marital rape which is a big step in the right direction.</li>
<li>However in a society with strong social norms and value systems every stakeholder should have more than a legitimate motive. It has to play an important role.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>While abortion is available under legal regulations in the country, Discuss the relationship between the Medical Termination of Pregnancy Act and Marital Rape.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/marital-rape/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysing Insolvency and bankruptcy Code</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/insolvency/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>what is IBC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>IBC reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Insolvency" class="alignnone wp-image-644504 size-full" height="579" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 997px) 100vw, 997px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.38.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.38.jpeg 997w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.38-300x174.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.38-768x446.jpeg 768w" width="997"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Speaking at the Sixth anniversary of the insolvency and bankruptcy Board of India (IBBI) on October 1, Union Finance Minister Nirmala Sitharaman said that the country could not afford to lose the “sheen” of its insolvency law, the Insolvency and Bankruptcy code(IBC)</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Insolvency?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Simply speaking, insolvency is a financial state of being one that is reached when you are unable to pay off your debts on time.</li>
<li>Insolvency is essentially the state of being that prompts one to file for bankruptcy. An entity a person, family, or company becomes insolvent when it cannot pay its lenders back on time.</li>
<li>Typically, those who become insolvent will take certain steps toward a resolution. One of the most common solutions for insolvency is bankruptcy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Bankruptcy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bankruptcy, on the other hand, is a legal process that serves the purpose of resolving the issue of insolvency.</li>
<li>Bankruptcy is a legal declaration of one’s inability to pay off debts. When one files for bankruptcy, one obliges to pay off what is owed with help from the government.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Insolvency" class="alignnone wp-image-644508 size-full" height="344" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.38-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.38-1.jpeg 500w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.38-1-300x206.jpeg 300w" width="500"/>What is Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code (IBC)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In a growing economy, a healthy credit flow and generation of new capital are essential.</li>
<li>When a company or business turns insolvent or “sick”, it begins to default on its loans.</li>
<li>In order for credit to not get stuck in the system or turn into bad loans, it is important that banks or creditors are able to recover as much as possible from the defaulter, as quickly as they can.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why the IBC introduced?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increasing Non ­Performing Assets: </strong>In 2016, at a time when India’s Non Performing Assets and debt defaults were piling up, and older loan recovery mechanisms were performing badly, the IBC was introduced to overhaul the corporate distress resolution regime in India.</li>
<li><strong>Time bound mechanism: </strong>To consolidate previously available laws to create a time bound mechanism with a creditor­ in­ control model as opposed to the debtor ­in ­possession system.</li>
<li><strong>Two positive outcomes: </strong>When insolvency is triggered under the IBC, there can be just two outcomes: resolution or liquidation. liquidation means the process of winding up a corporation or incorporated entity</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Insolvency" class="alignnone wp-image-644510 size-large" height="576" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.41-1024x576.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.41-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.41-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.41-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.41-1200x675.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.41.jpeg 1280w" width="1024"/>Importance of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/effective-and-efficient-the-insolvency-and-bankruptcy-code/">Insolvency and bankruptcy code</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Resolution: </strong>First objective is finding a way to save a business through restructuring, change in ownership, mergers etc.</li>
<li><strong>Maximising the value: </strong>The second objective is to maximise the value of assets of the corporate debtor  maximise the value .</li>
<li><strong>Credit facility: </strong>To promote entrepreneurship, availability of credit, and balancing the interests of all stakeholders.</li>
<li><strong>Easy exit: </strong>The Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code would provide such an environment to ensure easy exit for sick companies and help the country to improve its position in ease of doing business.</li>
<li><strong>Speedy winding up</strong>: The bankruptcy code will make it easier for companies to wind up failed businesses and bring India on a par with developed nations in terms of resolving bankruptcy issues.</li>
<li><strong>Time bound disposal: </strong>Timeliness is key here so that the viability of the business or the value of its assets does not deteriorate further. It minimizes the problem of delay as there are strict timelines within which the case has to be disposed off. Quick disposal of cases will maximize the recovery amount.</li>
<li><strong>Information database:</strong> It prepares a database to provide information on the insolvency status of individuals. In addition to this, specialized insolvency professionals helps in guiding through the process.</li>
<li><strong>Easy process of claim:</strong> Easy process of claim by the creditors also encourages financial institutions to extend credit facilities thus strengthening the financial markets with increased availability of credit for business.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the challenges before IBC?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Weak Resolution: </strong>IBBI data for the 3,400 cases admitted under the IBC in the last six years, more than 50% of the cases ended in liquidation, and only 14% could find a proper resolution.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing deadlines:</strong> The IBC was thus initially given a 180 day deadline to complete the resolution process, with a permitted 90 day extension. It was later amended to make the total timeline for completion 330 days is almost a year.</li>
<li>In FY22, it took 772 days to resolve cases involving companies that owed more than 1,000 crore. The average number of days it took to resolve such cases increased rapidly over the past five years.</li>
<li><strong>On Haircuts (Debts that banks forgo):</strong>The Parliamentary Standing Committee on Finance pointed out in 2021 that in the five years of the IBC, creditors on an average had to bear an 80% haircut in more than 70% of the cases.</li>
<li>As per The Hindu Data Team, in close to 33 of 85 companies so far that owed more than 1,000 crore, lenders had to take above 90% haircuts. In case of the resolution of the Videocon Group for instance, creditors bore a haircut of 95.3%.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Insolvency" class="alignnone wp-image-644512 size-large" height="852" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.39-1-1024x852.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.39-1-1024x852.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.39-1-300x250.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.39-1-768x639.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-08.29.39-1.jpeg 1080w" width="1024"/>What  are experts saying?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Addressing the delays: </strong>In order to address the delays, the Parliamentary Standing Committee suggested that the time taken to admit the insolvency application and transfer control of the company to a resolution process, should not be more than 30 days after filing the case.</li>
<li><strong>New mechanism</strong>: The IBBI has also called for a new yardstick to measure haircuts. It suggested that haircuts not be looked at as the difference between the creditor’s claims and the actual amount realized but as the difference between what the company brings along when it enters IBC and the value realized.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code is a comprehensive and systemic process, which gives a quantum leap to the functioning of the credit market. However, it is the need of the hour to find new and innovative alternatives to make this system comprehensible and address the challenge of delay and resolution.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code (IBC) is a comprehensive and systemic process, which gives a quantum leap to the functioning of the credit market. Discuss the challenges and way ahead in the resolution mechanism of IBC</strong>.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/insolvency/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Governor: 1st essential part of State Legislature</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/governor/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Role of Governors in State</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with role of Governor</p></div></div><h4><img alt="Governor" class="alignnone wp-image-644527 size-full" height="618" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 994px) 100vw, 994px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.37.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.37.jpeg 994w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.37-300x187.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.37-768x477.jpeg 768w" width="994"/><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In Tamil Nadu, the Governor forwarded the Bill for exemptio from the National Eligibility cum Entrance Test (NEET) to the President after considerable delay.</li>
<li>In Kerala the situation has become a bit curious with the Governor publicly announcing that he would not give assent to the Lokayukta Amendment Bill and the Kerala University Amendment Bill. Such actions by Governors throw the legislative programmes of governments out of gear because of the uncertainty surrounding the assent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Role of Governor in Legislature?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Integral part: </strong>A Bill passed by the State Assembly becomes law only after it is assented to by the Governor.The Governor being a part of the State legislature, the process of law making is complete only when he signs it, signifying his assent.</li>
<li><strong>Established practice: </strong>In all democratic countries, similar provision exists in their constitutions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Governor" class="alignnone wp-image-644528 size-full" height="415" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 739px) 100vw, 739px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.36.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.36.jpeg 739w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.36-300x168.jpeg 300w" width="739"/> What is the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/governors-powers-and-friction-with-states/">Power of Governor Vis-e-vis legislature?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>What Article 200 says</strong>: The Constitution provides certain options for the Governor to exercise when a Bill reaches him from the Assembly.</li>
<li><strong>There are four possible scenarios:</strong></li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Assent: </strong>He may give assent.</li>
<li><strong>Reconsider: </strong>He can send it back to the Assembly requesting it to reconsider some provisions of the Bill, or the Bill itself. In this case, if the Assembly passes the Bill without making any change and sends it back to the Governor, he will have to give assent to it.</li>
<li><strong>Reserve: </strong>The third option is to reserve the Bill for the consideration of the President.</li>
<li><strong>Withhold: </strong>The fourth option, of course, is to withhold the assent.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What are the Legislative practice in other democracies ?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>UK: </strong>The royal assent is necessary for a Bill to be passed by Parliament to become law and the crown has the power to withhold assent. But it is a dead letter.</li>
<li><strong>No power of veto: </strong>By practice and usage there is no power of veto exercised by the crown in England now. Moreover, refusal of royal assent on the ground that the monarchy strongly disapproves of the Bill or that the Bill is very controversial is treated as unconstitutional.</li>
<li><strong>USA: </strong>In the United States, the President is empowered by the Constitution to refuse assent and return a Bill to the House but if the Houses again pass it with two thirds of each House the Bill becomes law.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Governor" class="alignnone wp-image-644530 size-full" height="768" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.35.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.35.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.35-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.35-768x576.jpeg 768w" width="1024"/>Why there is an ambiguity over the role of governors in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Role of the governor: </strong>The question of whether a Governor is permitted by the Constitution to cause uncertainty in the matter of giving assent to the Bills passed by State legislatures assumes great importance.</li>
<li><strong>Presidential Assent: </strong>The provision concerned makes it clear that a Bill can be reserved for the consideration of the President only if the Governor forms an opinion that the Bill would endanger the position of the High Court by whittling away its powers. The Constitution does not mention any other type of Bill which is required to be reserved for the consideration of the President. Nevertheless, the courts have conceded a certain discretion to the Governors in the matter of sending Bills to the President.</li>
<li><strong>Constitution is silent: </strong>the Constitution does not mention the grounds on which a Governor may withhold assent to a Bill.</li>
<li><strong>No remedy</strong>: The Indian Constitution, however, does not provide any such remedy as that of USA or UK . The courts too have more or less accepted the position that if the Governor withholds assent, the Bill will go. Thus, the whole legislative exercise will become fruitless. It does not square with the best practices in old and mature democracies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Court mandated legislative practice?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>According to Article 361</strong>: The Constitution prohibits the court from initiating proceedings against a Governor or the President for any act done in exercise of their powers. They enjoy complete immunity from court proceedings. It is in fact a unique situation where a government is placed in a situation of having to challenge a Governor’s action of withholding assent to a Bill.</li>
<li><strong>Reasons: </strong>Governor while declaring that he withholds assent will have to disclose the reason for such refusal.</li>
<li><strong>No Arbitrary actions: </strong>Being a high constitutional authority, the Governor cannot act in an arbitrary manner</li>
<li><strong>Unconstitutional: </strong>If the grounds for refusal disclose mala fide or extraneous considerations or ultravires, the Governor’s action of refusal could be struck down as unconstitutional.</li>
<li><strong>Rameshwar Prasad and Others. vs Union of India case</strong>: The Court held: “the immunity granted by Article 361(1) does not, however, take away the power of the Court to examine the validity of the action including on the ground of malafides”.</li>
<li><strong>Pocket veto: </strong>since the Constitution does not fix any timeline for the Governor to decide the question of assent, he can wait for any length of time without doing anything. This is illogical and militates against the constitutional scheme in respect of law making by the legislatures.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Governor" class="alignnone wp-image-644540" height="1066" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.33.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.33.jpeg 413w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-06-at-11.27.33-169x300.jpeg 169w" width="600"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The legislature reflects the will of the people and is the constitutionally designated body to make laws. If the Governor who does not reflect in any way the aspirations of the people of the State refuses assent, and thereby defeats the legislative programme of the elected government, it would be against the spirit of the Constitution.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Governor is the connecting link between state and central executive. Discuss the duties of Governor with respect to state legislature? Why Governor tilt more towards centre than state?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/governor/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Vyommitra Humanoid to undergo pre-flight tests</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vyommitra-humanoid-pre-flight-tests/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Vyommitra, Gaganyaan Mission</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="vyommitra" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-645002" height="1333" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom.jpg 2000w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/vyom-1980x1320.jpg 1980w" width="2000"/></strong></p>
<p>Vyommitra, the humanoid designed and developed by the ISRO to fly aboard unmanned test missions ahead of the Gaganyaan human space-flight mission, is undergoing pre-flight ground tests at the ISRO Inertial Systems Unit (IISU).</p>
<h4><strong>Vyommitra </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AI-based robotic system is developed at a robotics lab at the Vikram Sarabhai Space Centre (VSSC) at Thumba, Thiruvananthapuram.</li>
<li>Vyommitra will be used for an unmanned flight of ISRO’s GSLV III rocket in December 2020, which, along with a second unmanned flight in July 2021.</li>
<li>This will serve as the test of ISRO’s preparedness for its maiden manned space mission, Gaganyaan, being targeted for 2022 to mark 75 years of India’s independence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Functions of the humanoid</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Vyommitra, equipped with a head, two arms and a torso, is built to mimic crew activity inside the crew module of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gaganyaan-and-other-new-missions-in-2022/">Gaganyaan</a>.</li>
<li>Attaining launch and orbital postures, responding to the environment, generating warnings, replacing carbon dioxide canisters, and operating switches, monitoring of the crew module, receiving voice commands, and responding via speech (bilingual) are among the functions listed.</li>
<li>It will have a human-like face, with lips synchronized for movement to mimic speech.</li>
<li>Once it is fully developed, Vyommitra will be able to use the equipment on board the spacecraft’s crew module, like safety mechanisms and switches, as well as receive and act on commands sent from ground stations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the recent development?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The IISU has successfully integrated it with a computer “brain”, which enables it to “read” control panels aboard the unmanned test flights and communicate with the ISRO ground stations.</li>
<li>It has a certain level of intelligence.</li>
<li>It is intended to operate and read the display panels and communicate back to ground station using its own voice.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Gaganyaan Mission</h4>
<ul>
<li>Gaganyaan is crewed orbital spacecraft intended to be the formative spacecraft of the Indian Human Spaceflight Programme (IHSP).</li>
<li>The IHSP was initiated in 2007 by ISRO to develop the technology needed to launch crewed orbital spacecraft into low Earth orbit.</li>
<li>ISRO had been working on related technologies and it performed a <strong>Crew Module Atmospheric Re-entry Experiment</strong> and a <strong>Pad Abort Test</strong> for the mission.</li>
<li>If completed in meantime, India will become the fourth nation to conduct independent human spaceflight after Russia, US, and China.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vyommitra-humanoid-pre-flight-tests/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>NOPEC: the US bill to pressure the OPEC+ oil group</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nopec-us-bill-to-pressure-opec-plus/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NOPEC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Global oil prices manipulation by OPEC</p></div></div><p><img alt="nopec" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-645009" height="719" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nopec.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nopec.jpg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nopec-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nopec-1024x575.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nopec-768x431.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/nopec-1200x674.jpg 1200w" width="1280"/></p>
<p>US legislation NOPEC which could open members of oil producing group <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-opec-3/">OPEC+</a> to antitrust lawsuits has emerged as a possible tool to tackle high fuel prices.</p>
<h4><strong>What is NOPEC?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>NOPEC stands for No Oil Producing and Exporting Cartels (NOPEC).</li>
<li>It is a bill to protect US consumers and businesses from engineered oil spikes.</li>
<li>But some analysts warn that implementing it could also have some dangerous unintended consequences.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why such a move by the US?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>OPEC+, which groups the Organization of the Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) and allies including Russia, agreed to steep production cuts, curbing supply in an already tight market.</li>
<li>After the decision, the US decided to reduce the group’s control over energy prices.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Key feature of the NOPEC bill</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The bipartisan NOPEC bill would tweak US antitrust law to revoke the sovereign immunity that has protected OPEC+ members and their national oil companies from lawsuits.</li>
<li>If signed into law, the US attorney general would gain the option to sue the oil cartel or its members, such as Saudi Arabia, in federal court.</li>
<li>It is unclear exactly how a federal court could enforce judicial antitrust decisions against a foreign nation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Is such bill effective?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Previous versions of the NOPEC bill have failed amid resistance by oil industry groups, including the top US oil lobby groups.</li>
<li>Saudi Arabia has rebuffed repeated lobbying during visits by Biden officials not to cut production.</li>
<li>Instead, OPEC+ has agreed to cut output by the most since the start of the COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Implications of NOPEC</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>NOPEC more or less is a knee-jerk reaction from the US against oil hegemony of the OPEC+.</li>
<li>If passed into law, it could lead to unintended blowback.</li>
<li>In 2019, for example, Saudi Arabia threatened to sell its oil in currencies other than the dollar if Washington passed a version of the NOPEC bill.</li>
<li>There is a possibility that other countries could take similar action on the US for withholding agricultural output to support domestic farming, for example.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nopec-us-bill-to-pressure-opec-plus/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Human Rights Council rejects debate on Xinjiang Abuses</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/xinjiang-china-abuses-unhrc-india-abstain/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Uighurs, Xinjiang</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>HR abuses in China</p></div></div><p><img alt="xinjiang" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-395897" height="374" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 456px) 100vw, 456px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/xing.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/xing.jpg 456w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/xing-300x246.jpg 300w" width="456"/></p>
<p>The UN Human Rights Council has voted against holding a debate on alleged abuses in China’s Xinjiang region after intense lobbying by Beijing, in a major setback for Western nations.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India and 10 other nations abstained.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who are the Uighurs?</strong></h4>
<p><strong><img alt="xinjiang" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-547953" height="400" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/uyghr.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/uyghr.jpg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/uyghr-300x200.jpg 300w" width="600"/></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There are about 12 million Uighurs, mostly Muslim, living in north-western China in the region of Xinjiang, officially known as the Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region (XUAR).</li>
<li>The Uighurs speak their own language, similar to Turkish, and see themselves as culturally and ethnically close to Central Asian nations.</li>
<li>They make up less than half of the Xinjiang population.</li>
<li>In recent decades, there’s been a mass migration of Han Chinese (China’s ethnic majority) to Xinjiang, and the Uighurs feel their culture and livelihoods are under threat.</li>
<li>In the early 20th Century, the Uighurs briefly declared independence, but the region was brought under complete control of mainland China’s new Communist government in 1949.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Where is Xinjiang?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Xinjiang lies in the north-west of China and is the country’s biggest region.</li>
<li>Like Tibet, it is autonomous, meaning – in theory – it has some powers of self-governance. But in practice, both face major restrictions by the central government.</li>
<li>It is a mostly desert region, producing about a fifth of the world’s cotton.</li>
<li>It is also rich in oil and natural gas and because of its proximity to Central Asia and Europe is seen by Beijing as an important trade link.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the build-up to the Uighur crackdown?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Anti-Han and separatist sentiment rose in Xinjiang from the 1990s, flaring into violence on occasion.</li>
<li>In 2009 some 200 people died in clashes in Xinjiang, which the Chinese blamed on Uighurs who want their own state.</li>
<li>Xinjiang is now covered by a pervasive network of surveillance, including police, checkpoints, and cameras that scan everything from number plates to individual faces.</li>
<li>According to Human Rights Watch, police are also using a mobile app to monitor peoples’ behaviour, such as how much electricity they are using and how often they use their front door.</li>
<li>Since 2017 when President Xi Jinping issued an order saying all religions in China should be Chinese in orientation, there have been further crackdowns.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Chinese narrative</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>China says the crackdown is necessary to prevent terrorism and root out Islamist extremism and the camps are an effective tool for re-educating inmates in its fight against terrorism.</li>
<li>It insists that Uighur militants are waging a violent campaign for an independent state by plotting bombings, sabotage and civic unrest.</li>
<li>China has dismissed claims it is trying to reduce the Uighur population through mass sterilizations as “baseless”, and says allegations of forced labor are “completely fabricated”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why did India abstain from voting against China?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has traditionally voted against or abstained from such country-specific resolutions at the UNHRC.</li>
<li>It is understood that China’s presence within the UNHRC was a factor in the decision since any backing for the Xinjiang issue could have led to similar moves by China on other issues in India.</li>
<li>This is particularly in the context of the Kashmir issue.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this PYQ:</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Q.Very recently, in which of the following countries have lakhs of people either suffered from severe famine/acute malnutrition or died due to starvation caused by war/ethnic conflicts?</strong><br/>
(a) Angola and Zambia<br/>
(b) Morocco and Tunisia<br/>
(c) Venezuela and Colombia<br/>
(d) Yemen and South Sudan</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/xinjiang-china-abuses-unhrc-india-abstain/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India’s Rice Exports and food Insecurity</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/exports/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<h4><strong><img alt="Exports" class="alignnone wp-image-644956 size-full" height="720" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.04.10-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.04.10-1.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.04.10-1-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.04.10-1-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.04.10-1-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.04.10-1-1200x675.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>On August 8, India banned the exports of broken rice and imposed a 20 per cent duty on the exports of various grades of rice amid high cereal inflation and uncertainties with respect to domestic supply.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>This is surely not the first time an attempt is being made to ban wheat and rice exports.</li>
<li>It was also done in 2007-08, in the wake of the global financial crisis.</li>
<li>Perhaps government will also impose stocking limits on traders for a host of commodities, suspend<strong> </strong>futures trading in food items, and even conduct income tax raids on traders of food.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Exports" class="alignnone wp-image-644959 size-full" height="870" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1073px) 100vw, 1073px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.40.02-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.40.02-1.jpeg 1073w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.40.02-1-300x243.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.40.02-1-1024x830.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.40.02-1-768x623.jpeg 768w" width="1073"/>What is the current status of rice in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>World’s largest rice exporter:</strong> India has exported more than 20 MT of rice worth a record $9. 6 billion to more than 150 countries in 2021-22.It has been the world’s largest rice exporter of the grain in the last decade and has a share of around 44% global trade.</li>
<li><strong>Likely to fall in production:</strong> India’s rice production is likely to decline by 6 per cent t to 104.99 million tonnes in the kharif season due to a fall in paddy acreage amidst rainfall deficit in key producing states, including Jharkhand, Madhya Pradesh and West Bengal.</li>
<li><strong>Kharif season:</strong> Sowing in the kharif season begins with the onset of the southwest monsoon from June and harvesting from October onwards .About 85 per cent of India’s total production comes from this season.</li>
<li><strong>Deficient rainfall:</strong> West Bengal, the biggest rice producer amongst states, has received deficient rainfall in 15 of its 23 districts, raising the likelihood of crop loss. Uttar Pradesh, the second biggest producer of rice has received 42% less rainfall than benchmark. The rainfall deficiency in the other eastern states Bihar (-34%) and Jharkhand (-48%).</li>
<li><strong>Depleting stocks:</strong> There are concerns about rice stocks with the Food Corporation of India (FCI) depleting to a 10-year low level by April, 2023 year, if the free ration scheme is extended to the second half of the financial year. The government may have to impose some curbs on rice exports though minimum export price or an export tax if the scheme is extended.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why India’s rice export ban is cause for worry?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Thin world rice market and the impact on prices:</strong> Given that 90 per cent of production is consumed domestically, As a result, any small change in exports and imports has an enormous impact on prices, especially if it leads to panic buying of food grains by rich countries.</li>
<li><strong>Limited Import option:</strong> The stakes are higher as it is India’s largest agricultural crop. Unlike with wheat, the options for import in rice due to any production shortfall are limited, when India’s own share in the global trade of the cereal is more than 40%.</li>
<li><strong>Affect the credibility:</strong> The export uncertainties will affect the credibility of Indian exporters, create a disincentive for future exports, and will enable buyers to shift towards other major rice-exporting countries.</li>
<li><strong>Affect a section of farmers:</strong> Though Indian farmers in general lack market access, and hence do not take advantage of high market prices, the fall in prices may adversely affect a section of farmers who hope to get a better price for their produce through exports. The exporters who face the burden of the unfeasibility of exports may pass it on to farmers in the form of lower prices during procurement.</li>
<li><strong>Affect low-income and low middle-income Countries: </strong>India’s export restrictions will adversely affect several low-income and low-middle-income countries like Bangladesh, Senegal, Nepal and Benin, which are among the largest importers of Indian rice.</li>
<li><strong>Domestic prices and to safeguard food security</strong>: Frequent changes in export policies undoubtedly have long-term ramifications on domestic prices</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Exports" class="alignnone wp-image-644962 size-large" height="499" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.39.58-1024x499.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.39.58-1024x499.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.39.58-300x146.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.39.58-768x374.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-06.39.58.jpeg 1200w" width="1024"/>What are the Issues in India’s rice <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/can-agri-exports-be-made-more-sustainable/">export strategy?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Highest ever volume:</strong> India exported the highest-ever volume of 21 million metric tonnes (MMT) of rice in 2021-22 (FY22) in a global market of about 51.3 MMT, which amounts to about 41 per cent of global exports.</li>
<li><strong>Reduced price:</strong> Such large volumes of rice exports brought down global prices of rice by about 23 per cent in March (YoY), when all other cereal prices, be it wheat or maize, were going up substantially in global markets. In fact, in FY22, the unit value of exports of common rice was just $354/tonne, which was lower than the minimum support price (MSP) of rice.</li>
<li><strong>Below MSP buying or leakage from PMGKAY:</strong> This meant that rice exporters were either buying rice (paddy) from farmers and millersat below the MSP or that quite a substantial part of rice was given free under the PM Garib Kalyan Ann Yojana (PMGKAY) was being siphoned away for exports at prices below MSP.</li>
<li><strong>Artificial competitive advantage:</strong> Free electricity for irrigation in several states, most notably Punjab, and highly subsidised fertilisers, especially urea, create an artificial competitive advantage for Indian rice in global markets.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Problems with India’s rice cultivation</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lower yield:</strong> India’s rice yield is lower than the world average. However, India’s yield is better than Thailand and Pakistan but worse than Vietnam, China and the US.</li>
<li><strong>Higher cost of cultivation and price support</strong>: The cost of cultivation in India is also increasing, and hence there will be a need for a higher MSP to make production remunerative. This will exacerbate the pressure to re-think its price-support-backed food security mechanism.</li>
<li><strong>Water-intensive nature</strong>: India’s rice production likely to fall amidst the shortfall of rainfall in major rice producing states and increasing salinity of soil because of over usage of water. The water-intensive nature of rice cultivation, along with frequent export restrictions will adversely affect the long-run sustainability of rice production. In India, around 49 per cent of rice cultivation depends on groundwater which is depleting rapidly.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Exports" class="alignnone wp-image-644964 size-full" height="1280" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 755px) 100vw, 755px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-1.jpeg 755w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-1-177x300.jpeg 177w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-1-604x1024.jpeg 604w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.12-1-531x900.jpeg 531w" width="755"/>What is the link between Rice cultivation and ground water depletion?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Ground water depletion</strong>: In India, around 49 per cent of rice cultivation depends on groundwater which is depleting rapidly.</li>
<li><strong>Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) data</strong>: As per the latest data available from the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), agricultural water withdrawal as a percentage of total available renewable water resources has increased from 26.7 per cent in 1993 to 36 per cent in 2022.</li>
<li><strong>Virtual water trade (VWT):</strong> Rice exports are leading to an indirect export of water to other countries a phenomenon known as virtual water trade (VWT). The relative per capita water availability in India is lower than a majority of its major importing countries. The other major exporters of rice, such as Thailand and Vietnam, also have better per capita water availability in comparison to India.</li>
<li><strong>Renewable water resources: </strong>Out of 133 countries in which India has positive net rice exports, only 39 countries have relatively lower per capita renewable water resources. Out of these 39 countries, 12 countries are high-income countries with the ability to buy food at a higher price.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Depletion of groundwater resources and rising cost of cultivation may threaten rice production in the future. Adequate water saving measures in the form of widespread adoption of water saving practices like System of Rice Intensification (SRI) need to be taken to keep input requirements, costs and production sustainable.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>As many developing countries depend on Indian rice, rice export restrictions have raised food security concerns in the global market. </strong><strong>In this context discuss the causes and effects of India’s restrictions on rice export.</strong></p></blockquote>
<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/exports/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Corporate Social Responsibility(CSR): A Vehicle of Achieving Social Justice</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/social/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CSR</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>corporate governance</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Social" class="alignnone wp-image-644974 size-full" height="853" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.30.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.30.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.30-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.30-1024x682.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.30-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.30-1200x800.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Since the establishment of the Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) regime in India under Section 135 of the Companies Act 2013, CSR spending in India has risen from RS.10,065 crore in 2014-15to Rs.24,865crore in 2020-21.But there is no data to verify whether this increase is commensurate with the increase in profits of Indian and foreign (having a registered arm in India) companies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Voluntary spending</strong>: Corporate social responsibility (CSR) is a form of international private business self-regulation which aims to contribute to societal goals of a philanthropic, activist, or charitable nature by engaging in or supporting volunteering or ethically oriented practices.</li>
<li><strong>Ministry Corporate Affairs: </strong>The National Corporate Social Responsibility Data Portal is an initiative by Ministry of Corporate Affairs, Government of India to establish a platform to disseminate Corporate Social Responsibility related data and information filed by the companies registered with it<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Companies Act, 2013</strong>: The Corporate Social Responsibility concept in India is governed by Section 135 of the Companies Act, 2013 (‘Act’), Schedule VII of the Act and Companies (CSR Policy) Rules, 2014 wherein the criteria has been provided for assessing the CSR eligibility of a company, Implementation and Reporting of their CSR Policies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/csr/"><img alt="Social" class="alignnone wp-image-644977 size-large" height="683" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.27-1024x683.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.27-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.27-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.27-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.27.jpeg 1200w" width="1024"/></a></strong></h4>
<h4><strong>How <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/csr/">CSR helps in achieving social justice</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li style="text-align: left;"><strong>Sustainable Goals: </strong>India having the most elaborated CSR mechanism and implementation strategy has started its journey to set a benchmark in attaining sustainability goals and stakeholder activism in nation building.</li>
<li><strong>Corporate philanthropy</strong>: company donations to charity, including cash, goods, and services, sometimes via a corporate foundation.</li>
<li><strong>Community volunteering</strong>: company-organized volunteer activities, sometimes while an employee receives pay for pro-bono work on behalf of a non-profit organization</li>
<li><strong>Socially-responsible business practices</strong>: ethically produced products that appeal to a customer segment.</li>
<li><strong>Corporate social marketing</strong>: Company-funded behaviour-change campaigns, Company-funded advocacy campaigns, donations to charity based on product sales.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why there is need to review the CSR?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Declining number: </strong>There was also a decline in the number of companies participating in CSR 25,103 in FY2019 to 17,007 in FY2021.</li>
<li><strong>Flaw in the law</strong>: If a company spends an amount in excess of the minimum 2%, as stipulated, the excess amount is liable to be set off against spending in the succeeding three financial years. Ideally, companies should have been shown courage to spend more than this.</li>
<li><strong>Own trusts: </strong>many private companies have registered their own foundations/trusts to which they transfer the statutory CSR budgets for utilisation. It is unclear if this is allowed under the Companies Act/CSR rules.</li>
<li><strong>Geographical bias: </strong>The first proviso to Section 135(5) of the Act is that the company should give preference to local areas/areas around it where it operates. This is logical. However, a report by Ashoka University’s Centre for Social Impact and Philanthropy says that 54% of CSR companies are concentrated in Maharashtra, Tamil Nadu, Karnataka, and Gujarat(receiving the largest CSR spends) while populous Uttar Pradesh and Madhya Pradesh receive little.</li>
<li><strong>Spending on environment: </strong>Item (iv) of Schedule VII of the Act deals with broader environmental issues to create a countervailing effect. However, an analysis of CSR spending (2014-18)reveals that while most CSR spending is in education (37%) and health and sanitation (29%), only 9% was spent on the environment even as extractive industries such as mining function in an environmentally detrimental manner in several States</li>
<li><strong>Incomplete information: </strong>The Standing Committee on Finance had observed that the information regarding CSR spending by companies is insufficient and difficult to access. As per the ‘Technical Guide on Accounting’ issued by the Institute of Chartered Accountants of India, a company is only required to mention its CSR spends, non-spend, under-spend, and overspend in the ‘Notes to Accounts’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Social" class="alignnone wp-image-644979 size-full" height="441" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 770px) 100vw, 770px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.28.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.28.jpeg 770w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.28-300x172.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.28-768x440.jpeg 768w" width="770"/>What are the suggestions to improve the mechanism of CSR?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Centralized platform: </strong>There is a need to curate a national level platform centralised by the MCA where all States could list their potential CSR admissible projects so that companies can assess where their CSR funds would be most impactful across India with, of course, preferential treatment to areas where they operate.</li>
<li><strong>India Investment Grid: </strong>Invest India’s ‘Corporate Social Responsibility Projects Repository’ on the India Investment Grid (IIG) can serve as a guide for such efforts. This model would be very useful for supporting deserving projects in the 112aspirational districts and projects identified by MPs under the Government’s Sansad AdarshGram Yojana.</li>
<li><strong>Increase environment spending: </strong>Companies need to prioritise environment restoration in the area where they operate, earmarking at least 25% for environment regeneration.</li>
<li><strong>Public participation: </strong>All CSR projects should be selected and implemented with the active involvement of communities, district administration and public representatives.</li>
<li><strong>Transparency: </strong>Recommendations by the high-level committee in 2018 should be incorporated in the current CSR framework to improve the existing monitoring and evaluation regime. These include strengthening the reporting mechanisms with enhanced disclosures concerning selection of projects, locations, implementing agencies, etc.; bringing CSR within the purview of statutory financial audit with details of CSR expenditure included in the financial statement of a company, and mandatory independent third party impact assessment audits.</li>
<li><strong>Monitoring by government: </strong>The MCA and the line departments need to exercise greater direct monitoring and supervision over CSR spend by companies through the line ministries (for public sector undertakings) and other industry associations(for non-public units) instead of merely hosting all information on the Ministry’s website.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Social" class="alignnone wp-image-644981 size-full" height="1000" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.33.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.33.jpeg 1000w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.33-300x300.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.33-150x150.jpeg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.33-768x768.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.33-900x900.jpeg 900w" width="1000"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Corporate social responsibility is an effective tool to address the social and income inequality. Present legal arrangements are toothless and based on voluntary actions. For an effective change CSR spending should be made more transparent and accountable.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question. </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Present arrangement of CSR is not yielding the desired result. Enlist the current weakness in CSR spending Suggest the changes needed for efficient implantation of CSR.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/social/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Moonlighting: Overemployment or Underpayment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/moonlighting/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>what is moonlighting.</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Impact of moonlighting on comapnies and employment.</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Moonlighting" class="alignnone wp-image-645000 size-full" height="337" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.03.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.03.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.03-300x79.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.03-1024x270.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.03-768x202.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.09.03-1200x316.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In July, Kotak Securities said in a study that at least 60% of 400 employees surveyed said they themselves had, or knew someone who had engaged in moonlighting.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is mean by moonlighting?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Moonlighting is a state where employees work for remuneration with entities other than their employers. It is not defined in any of the statutes in India. However, there are enactments that deal with double employment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Moonlighting" class="alignnone wp-image-644992 size-large" height="879" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.55-1-1024x879.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.55-1-1024x879.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.55-1-300x258.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.55-1-768x659.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.55-1-1049x900.jpeg 1049w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.55-1.jpeg 1080w" width="1024"/>How does it affect companies and what are latest examples?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Wipro</strong>: According to Wipro CEO, there is a lot of chatter about people moonlighting in the tech industry. This is cheating plain and simple. The company sacked 300 employees following the discovery that they were working for rival firms on the side, leading to conflict of interest.</li>
<li><strong>Infosys: </strong>Infosys has warned staff against moonlighting, saying it could lead to termination.</li>
<li><strong>Effect of WFH</strong>: Another software firm DXC Technologies said that moonlighting by employees was a challenge for employers but that wouldn’t affect its WFH (work from home) policy that has worked well for both the firm and its staff.</li>
<li><strong>Moonlighting policy: </strong>Swiggy announced a moonlighting policy’ that allows employees to pursue their passion for economic interests alongside their fulltime employment.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Moonlighting" class="alignnone wp-image-644995 size-full" height="416" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-1.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-1-300x98.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-1-1024x333.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-1-768x250.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-1-1200x390.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>What is the<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/back-in-news-gig-workers-rights/"> Legal status of moonlighting</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Factory act: </strong>Section 60 of the Factories Act deals with restriction on double employment stating that “No adult worker shall be required or allowed to work in any factory on any day on which he has already been working in any other factory, save in such circumstances as may be prescribed. However, this enactment is applicable only to employees working in factories.</li>
<li><strong>The Tamil Nadu Shops &amp; Establishments Act, 1947</strong>: There are State enactments which deal with employment of persons working in offices, banks, shops, etc. In Tamil Nadu, it is termed as The Tamil Nadu Shops &amp; Establishments Act, 1947. However, there is no provision wherein dealing with dual employment.</li>
<li><strong>Glaxo Laboratories (I) Limited vs Labour Court, Meerut and others</strong>: The apex court held that “The employer has hardly any extra territorial jurisdiction. He is not the custodian of general law and order situation or the Guru or mentor of his workmen for their well-regulated cultural advancement. If the power to regulate the behaviour of the workmen outside the duty hours and at any place wherever they may be was conferred upon the employer, contract of service may be reduced to contract of slavery.” This case was not specifically about moonlighting but the court’s observation gives us an idea as to how the law may view such cases.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Moonlighting" class="alignnone wp-image-645001 size-full" height="480" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59.jpeg 640w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-07-at-09.08.59-300x225.jpeg 300w" width="640"/>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>More earning</strong>: The Minister of State for Skill Development and Entrepreneurship, and Electronics and IT, said that employers should not to suppress employees who want to monetise, develop and demonstrate but also urged employees not to violate their agreements with employers.</li>
<li><strong>Working hours</strong>: Moonlighting is subject to law of the land. The sphere of employment cannot be extended by the employer beyond working hours and outside his place of employment.</li>
<li><strong>Socialistic view: </strong>The Courts of law in India dealing with employment are Writ Courts and Labour Courts, which exercise jurisdiction based on equity or fairness. Therefore, the Courts may lean in favour of the employee unless the contravention of the employee has led to serious prejudice and loss to the employer</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Employees are not the slaves of employers. What they do beyond the working hours is none of the business of employer unless it affects company financially or causes substantial damage to business. Government should bring the legal statute to regulate moonlighting and prevent the unjustified punishment of employees.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What is moonlighting? Why employees do moonlighting? Discuss the legal framework about moonlighting in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/moonlighting/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Amendments to Bharat Series Rules</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bharat-series-rules/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>BH Series</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="bharat" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-455446" height="565" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1204px) 100vw, 1204px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/bhs.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/bhs.jpg 1204w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/bhs-300x141.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/bhs-1024x481.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/bhs-768x360.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/bhs-1200x563.jpg 1200w" width="1204"/></p>
<p>The Ministry of Road Transport and Highway has issued a draft notification proposing new rules to further increase the scope of implementation of the BH series vehicle registrations.</p>
<h4><strong>Bharat series (BH-series)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There was a procedure of re-registration of a vehicle while moving to another state.</li>
<li>A vehicle bearing BH registration mark shall not require assignment of a new registration mark when the owner of the vehicle shifts from one State to another.</li>
<li>Format of Bharat series (BH-series) Registration Mark –</li>
</ul>
<p>Registration Mark Format:</p>
<ol>
<li>YY BH #### XX</li>
<li>YY – Year of first registration</li>
<li>BH- Code for Bharat Series</li>
<li>####- 0000 to 9999 (randomized)</li>
<li>XX- Alphabets (AA to ZZ)</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Why such move?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Station relocation occurs with both Government and private sector employees.</li>
<li>Such movements create a sense of unease in the minds of such employees with regard to transfer of registration from the parent state to another state.</li>
<li>Under section 47 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988, a person is allowed to keep the vehicle for not more than 12 months in any state other than the state where the vehicle is registered.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who can get this BH series?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>BH-series will be available on voluntary basis to Defense personnel, employees of Central Government/ State Government/ Central/ State PSUs and private sector companies/organizations.</li>
<li>The motor vehicle tax will be levied for two years or in multiple of two.</li>
<li>This scheme will facilitate free movement of personal vehicles across States/UTs of India upon relocation to a new State/UT.</li>
<li>After the completion of the fourteenth year, the motor vehicle tax shall be levied annually which shall be half of the amount which was charged earlier for that vehicle.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bharat-series-rules/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Places in news: Solomon Islands</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/solomon-islands-china/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Solomon Islands</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Chinese expansion in Pacific</p></div></div><p><img alt="solomon" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-494199" height="1532" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1600px) 100vw, 1600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon.jpg 1600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-300x287.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-1024x980.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-768x735.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-1536x1471.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/solmon-1200x1149.jpg 1200w" width="1600"/></p>
<p>Solomon Islands PM has assured Australia that his nation will not allow a Chinese military presence in its territory.</p>
<h4>Where is the Solomon Islands located?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Solomon Islands is a sovereign country consisting of six major islands and over 900 smaller islands in Oceania, to the east of Papua New Guinea and northwest of Vanuatu.</li>
<li>Its capital, Honiara, is located on the largest island, Guadalcanal.</li>
<li>It is part of the ethnically Melanesian group of islands in the Pacific and lies between Papua New Guinea and Vanuatu.</li>
<li>The country takes its name from the Solomon Islands archipelago, which is a collection of Melanesian islands that also includes the North Solomon Islands (a part of Papua New Guinea).</li>
<li>It excludes outlying islands, such as the Santa Cruz Islands and Rennell and Bellona.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Quick recap of its past</h4>
<ul>
<li>The islands, which were initially controlled by the British Empire during the colonial era, went through the hands of Germany and Japan.</li>
<li>It then went back to the UK after the Americans took over the islands from the Japanese during World War II.</li>
<li>The islands became independent in 1978 to become a constitutional monarchy under the British Crown, with a parliamentary system of government.</li>
<li>Nevertheless, its inability to manage domestic ethnic conflicts led to close security relations with Australia, which is the traditional first responder to any crisis in the South Pacific.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did China enter the picture?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Earlier this year, the Solomon Islands established a <strong>security agreement with China</strong>, saying it needed Beijing’s assistance with its domestic security situation.</li>
<li>But the <strong>announcement had rattled the west</strong>, esp. the US, Australia and others in the Indo-Pacific region.</li>
<li>The concerns were that the agreement could potentially lead to a <strong>Chinese military base on the island nation</strong> and a gain in power-projection capabilities.</li>
<li>At that time, following intense scrutiny, the Solomon Islands had <strong>denied</strong> that the agreement would allow China to establish a naval base.</li>
<li>The Island insisted that the agreement was only to <strong>assist the Solomon Islands with what he called “hard internal threats”.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the Solomon Islands’ stance?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The government has asked all partner countries with plans to conduct naval visits or patrols to put them on hold until a <strong>revised national mechanism</strong> is in place.</li>
<li>The revised national mechanism <strong>applied to all foreign vessels seeking access to the country’s ports</strong>.</li>
<li>The nation wanted to <strong>build up its</strong> <strong>own naval capacity</strong>.</li>
<li>It has some <strong>unfortunate experiences of foreign naval vessels entering its waters</strong> without any diplomatic clearance.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is behind China’s growing influence in the region?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There is no dispute that China has been rapidly increasing its presence and influence in the region for over three decades, particularly in the South Pacific.</li>
<li>Certainly Beijing views the Pacific Island region as an <strong>important component of its Belt and Road Initiative (BRI). </strong></li>
<li>Specifically, it sees the region as a critical air freight hub in its so-called <strong>Air Silk Road</strong>, which connects Asia with Central and South America.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Concerns of the West</h4>
<ul>
<li>The United States and its regional allies, such as Australia and New Zealand, are concerned that the China-Solomon Islands security pact allows Chinese naval vessels to replenish there.</li>
<li>That could open the <strong>door to a Chinese naval base</strong>, which would significantly extend China’s military reach in the South Pacific.”</li>
<li>It is likely that this security agreement between China and the Solomon Islands has been driven by, what the CFR calls, Beijing’s “<strong>sense of vulnerability</strong>” in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the rationale for the Solomon Islands’ increasing proximity to China?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Solomon Islands had cultivated strong ties with Taiwan, which ended with the emergence of the current government in Honiara.</li>
<li>In 2019, the regime change switched Taiwan for China.</li>
<li>This was supposedly after Beijing offered half a billion US dollars in financial aid, roughly five times what Taiwan spent on the islands in the past two decades.</li>
<li>It has been alleged by the pro-Taiwan Opposition that the incumbent government has been bribed by China.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is China interested in the Solomon Islands?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Isolating Taiwan:</strong> The Solomon Islands was one among the six Pacific island states which had official bilateral relations with Taiwan.</li>
<li><strong>Supporter in UN:</strong> The small Pacific island states act as potential vote banks for mobilising support for the great powers in international fora like the United Nations.</li>
<li><strong>Larger EEZ:</strong> These states have disproportionately large maritime Exclusive Economic Zones when compared to their small sizes.</li>
<li><strong>Natural resources:</strong> Solomon Islands, in particular, have significant reserves of timber and mineral resources, along with fisheries.</li>
<li><strong>Countering US:</strong> But more importantly, they are strategically located for China to insert itself between America’s military bases in the Pacific islands and Australia.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What does this mean for the established geopolitical configuration in the region?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Diminishing western influence:</strong> The Pacific islands, in the post-World War II scenario, were exclusively under the spheres of influence of the Western powers, in particular, the US, UK, France and Australia and New Zealand.</li>
<li><strong>Inserting into western hegemony:</strong> All of them have territorial possessions in the region, with the three nuclear powers among them having used the region as a nuclear weapons testing ground.</li>
<li><strong>Shifting of dependencies:</strong> The smaller island nations of the region are heavily dependent on them, especially Australia as it is a resident power.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/solomon-islands-china/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Aatmanirbhar in defence production: Where does India stand?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/atmanirbhar-in-defence-production/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Boosting indigenous defence production</p></div></div><p>India ranks fourth among 12 Indo-Pacific nations in self-reliant arms production capabilities, according to a study released this month by the Stockholm International Peace Research Institute (SIPRI).</p>
<h4><strong>Study on Defence production </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>China tops the list, Japan is second, South Korea is in third place, and Pakistan is at number 8.</li>
<li>The study, which measures self-reliance until 2020, is based on three indicators of self-reliance in each country:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong><u>Arms procurement</u></strong> — imports, licensed and domestic production as a proportion of the government’s total procurement of major conventional arms;</li>
<li><strong><u>Arms industry</u></strong> — the study presents the five largest arms companies in each country, where data are available, ranked by sales of arms and military services in 2020 to both domestic and export customers;</li>
<li><strong><u>Uncrewed maritime vehicles, the sea equivalent of drones</u></strong> — covering both uncrewed surface vehicles (USVs) and uncrewed underwater vehicles (UUVs), meant to provide a qualitative understanding of how countries are engaging domestic research institutes and firms to produce such cutting edge systems.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>How has China progressed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>China was the world’s fifth largest arms importer in 2016-20.</li>
<li>Its self-reliance policies, and its high economic growth in that period meant that the Chinese arms industry now increasingly fulfils the requirements of the People’s Liberation Army (PLA).</li>
<li>Its high volume of imports in absolute terms accounts for only 8 per cent of total procurement for the period, the lowest share for any of the 12 governments studied in this report.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is India still lagging behind?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India is ranked as the second-largest importer of arms for its armed forces in 2016-20.</li>
<li>India is highly dependent on imports of complete foreign major arms, including many produced under licence or as components for its domestic production.</li>
<li>Of India’s total volume of procurement in 2016–20, 84 per cent was of foreign origin.</li>
<li>Domestic arms companies provide only 16 per cent of its total procurement.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Steps taken by the Centre to boost defence production</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Licensing relaxation:</strong> Measures announced to boost exports since 2014 include simplified defence industrial licensing, relaxation of export controls and grant of no-objection certificates.</li>
<li><strong>Lines of Credit:</strong> Specific incentives were introduced under the foreign trade policy and the Ministry of External Affairs has facilitated Lines of Credit for countries to import defence product.</li>
<li><strong>Policy boost:</strong> The Defence Ministry has also issued a draft Defence Production &amp; Export Promotion Policy 2020.</li>
<li><strong>Budgetary allocation:</strong> In addition, a percentage of the capital outlay of the defence budget has been reserved for procurement from domestic industry.</li>
<li><strong>Defence Industrial Corridors:</strong> The government has also announced 2 dedicated Corridors in the States of TN and UP to act as clusters of defence manufacturing that leverage existing infrastructure, and human capital.</li>
<li><strong>Long-term vision:</strong> The vision of the government is to achieve a turnover of $25 bn including export of $5 bn in Aerospace and Defence goods and services by 2025.</li>
<li><strong>Push for self-reliance:</strong> The govt has identified the Defence and Aerospace sector as a focus area for the ‘Aatmanirbhar Bharat’ or Self-Reliant India initiative.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues retarding defence indigenization</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Excess reliance on Public Sector:</strong> India has four companies (Indian ordnance factories, Hindustan Aeronautics Limited (HAL), Bharat Electronics Limited (BEL) and Bharat Dynamics Limited (BDL)) among the top 100 biggest arms producers of the world.</li>
<li><strong>Policy delays:</strong> In the past few years, the government has approved over 200 defence acquisition worth Rs 4 trillion, but most are still in relatively early stages of processing.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of Critical Technologies:</strong> Poor design capability in critical technologies, inadequate investment in R&amp;D and the inability to manufacture major subsystems and components hamper the indigenous manufacturing.</li>
<li><strong>Long gestation:</strong> The creation of a manufacturing base is capital and technology-intensive and has a long gestation period. By that time newer technologies make products outdated.</li>
<li><strong>‘Unease’ in doing business:</strong> An issue related to stringent labour laws, compliance burden and lack of skills, affects the development of indigenous manufacturing in defence.</li>
<li><strong>Multiple jurisdictions:</strong> Overlapping jurisdiction of the Ministry of Defence and Ministry of Industrial Promotion impair India’s capability of defence manufacturing.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of quality:</strong> The higher indigenization in few cases is largely attributed to the low-end technology.</li>
<li><strong>FDI Policy:</strong> The earlier FDI limit of 49% was not enough to enthuse global manufacturing houses to set up bases in India.</li>
<li><strong>R&amp;D Lacunae:</strong> A lip service to technology funding by making token allocations is an adequate commentary on our lack of seriousness in the area of Research and Development.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of skills:</strong> There is a lack of engineering and research capability in our institutions. It again leads us back to the need for a stronger industry-academia interface.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reducing import dependence:</strong> India was the world’s second-largest arms importer from 2014-18, ceding the long-held tag as the largest importer to Saudi Arabia, says 2019 SIPRI report.</li>
<li><strong>Security Imperative:</strong> Indigenization in defence is critical to national security also. It keeps intact the technological expertise and encourages spin-off technologies and innovation that often stem from it.</li>
<li><strong>Economic boost:</strong> <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indigenisation-in-defence-technologies-manufacturing-will-ensure-indias-strategic-autonomy/">Indigenization in defence</a> can help create a large industry which also includes small manufacturers.</li>
<li><strong>Employment generation:</strong> Defence manufacturing will lead to the generation of satellite industries that in turn will pave the way for a generation of employment opportunities.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/atmanirbhar-in-defence-production/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Stubble burning in Punjab at 3-year low</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/stubble-burning-in-punjab-at-3-year-low/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>GHGs relased by Stubble Burning</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Stubble Burning</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="stubble" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-645413" height="628" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/stubble.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/stubble.jpg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/stubble-300x147.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/stubble-1024x502.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/stubble-768x377.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/stubble-1200x589.jpg 1200w" width="1280"/></strong></p>
<p>Though early days, the number of crop fires reported out of Punjab are at a three-year low, suggest data from the Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) that tracks such fires via satellite.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Stubble Burning?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Stubble (parali) burning is a method of removing paddy crop residues from the field to sow wheat from the last week of September to November.</li>
<li>It is usually required in areas that use the combined harvesting method which leaves crop residue behind.</li>
<li>This practice mostly carried out in Punjab, Haryana and UP contributes solely to the grave winter pollution in the national capital.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Emissions from stubble burning</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The process of burning farm residue is one of the major causes of air pollution in parts of north India, deteriorating the air quality.</li>
<li>Stubble burning is a significant source of carbon dioxide (CO2), volatile organic compounds (VOCs), nitrogen oxides (NOx) and hydrocarbons (HC).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Despite emissions, why do farmers burn stubble?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Crop residue burning is practised by the farmers to <strong><u>prepare the land for the next cultivation</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The major reason behind the stubble burning is the <strong><u>short time available</u></strong> between rice harvesting and sowing of wheat as delay in sowing wheat affects the wheat crop.</li>
<li>Between the harvesting of the paddy crop and the sowing of the next crop, there is only a <strong><u>two to three weeks’ time window</u></strong> is left.</li>
<li>Even though farmers are aware that the burning of straw is harmful to health, they <strong><u>do not have alternatives</u></strong> for utilizing them effectively.</li>
<li>The farmers are ill-equipped to deal with waste because they <strong><u>cannot afford the new technology</u></strong> that is available to handle the waste material.</li>
<li>Therefore, stubble burning is <strong><u>considered one of the cheapest methods</u></strong> to clean the field after the harvesting season.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Impact of stubble burning</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Air Pollution:</strong> Stubble burning emits toxic pollutants in the atmosphere containing harmful gases like Carbon Monoxide (CO), methane (CH4), carcinogenic polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, volatile organic compounds (VOC). These pollutants disperse in the surroundings and eventually affect air quality and people’s health by forming a thick blanket of smog. Along with vehicular emissions, it affects the Air Quality Index (AQI) in the national capital and NCR.</li>
<li><strong>Soil degradation:</strong> Soil becomes less fertile and its nutrients are destroyed when the husk is burned on the ground. Organic content of soil is completely destroyed. Stubble burning generates heat that penetrates into the soil, causing an increase in erosion, loss of useful microbes and moisture.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Alternative solutions </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Power generation:</strong> The available paddy straw can be effectively used for power generation, which will go a long way towards overcoming the problem of disposal of crop residues and power deficit in the region.</li>
<li><strong>In-situ decomposition:</strong> Suitable machinery for collection, chopping and in situ incorporation of straw is required. We can use <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pusa-bio-decomposer/">Pusa Biodecomposer,</a> Biomethanation etc.</li>
<li><strong>Organic manuring:</strong> Convert the removed residues into enriched organic manure through composting.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Unless financial assistance is to be provided by the Centre for boosting farm mechanization, it is difficult to completely stop stubble burning.</li>
<li>States need to make alternative arrangements for the consumption of paddy straw into the soil as per the directions of the NGT.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/stubble-burning-in-punjab-at-3-year-low/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Classifying Merit and Non merit Freebies</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/freebie/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- Freebies issue</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Freebie" class="alignnone wp-image-645400 size-full" height="1025" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.30.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.30.jpeg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.30-300x285.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.30-1024x972.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.30-768x729.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.30-948x900.jpeg 948w" width="1080"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The debate that began with an RBI 2022 report on state finances followed by Prime Minister Narendra Modi’s comment on revdi culture aka freebies, has garnered substantial attention so much so that the Supreme Court is hearing on this issue. Freebies have now assumed more importance than ever.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are freebies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Freebies could be defined as non-merit subsidies. The term Freebies is not new; rather it is a prevalent culture in Indian politics (in the name of socialism).</li>
<li>The political parties are always trying to outdo each other in luring the Indian voters with freebies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Subsidies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Subsidies are money transfers (implicit or explicit) by the government in an attempt to drive prices artificially below market prices.</li>
<li>As a National Institute of Public Finance and Policy (NIPFP) study by Sudipto Mundle and Satadru Sirkar puts it, budget subsidies, in particular, are defined as the unrecovered cost of economic and social services.</li>
<li>However, all subsidies cannot be easily classified into merit or non-merit.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Freebie" class="alignnone wp-image-645402 size-full" height="881" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.43-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.43-1.jpeg 660w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.43-1-225x300.jpeg 225w" width="660"/>What are the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/making-sense-of-the-freebies-issue/">objectives behind providing freebies?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Welfare state</strong>: It could be said that providing freebies empowers the state to, first, deliver welfare as a welfare state should, by providing subsidised merit goods like health and education;</li>
<li><strong>Combating poverty</strong>: To help households combat poverty (especially in economically stressed times characterised by fewer job opportunities, lower incomes, high inflation, etc.) by providing subsidised public goods like food, electricity, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Populist spending</strong>: To appeal to the electorate through outright populist spending.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Question of classification between a merit and a non-merit freebies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Blur Boundary:</strong> The boundaries between the aforementioned objectives begin to blur when it comes to classifying one form of freebie as a merit or a non-merit subsidy.</li>
<li><strong>Few examples</strong>: Are corporate tax cuts non-merit subsidies or a measure to boost investment? 2. Is making bus rides free for women in the national capital a non-merit subsidy or a way to boost women’s mobility and labour-force participation? 3. Are free laptops to students in Tamil Nadu not a way to bridge the digital divide in education?</li>
<li><strong>Varying definition: </strong>The existing arguments develop an understanding that freebies cannot be defined in a finite context, and that the definition varies across space and economic conditions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Freebie" class="alignnone wp-image-645408 size-full" height="600" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.39.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.39.jpeg 800w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.39-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.39-768x576.jpeg 768w" width="800"/>How freebies impact revenue of the state?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Adverse impact on revenues:</strong> Regardless of which one gets classified as good or bad, freebies are simply expenditures or foregone revenues. Any freebie-induced debt burden could have an adverse effect on the state finances if, one, it hasn’t been properly accounted for through transparent budgeting procedures (including off-budget borrowings in debt calculations)</li>
<li><strong>Increase in Fiscal deficit:</strong> Either way, they lead to an increase in fiscal deficit whose financing could necessitate taking on debt. It threatens fiscal sustainability, i e, it limits the state’s ability to service its debt-related commitments without making an unrealistic fiscal adjustment<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Lack of data leading to leakages: </strong>The targeting of beneficiaries to ease the burden on the exchequer is one way to check these expenditures but lack of data has forced a situation wherein leakages and duplication of beneficiaries is commonplace.</li>
<li><strong>Jeopardises long-term growth and development: </strong>In the absence of adequate avenues of revenue mobilisation, any fiscal adjustment achieved by contracting critical expenditures on the social sector and capital formation further jeopardises long-term growth and development. The emanating risk of fiscal sustainability means a “revdi” today would take a toll on tomorrow’s generation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What could be the solution?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Setting up an independent fiscal council: </strong>Setting up an independent fiscal council that has been recommended by the FRBM Review Committee (2017), and recently constituted Finance Commissions too, including the 15th Finance Commission.</li>
<li><strong>Providing information and advisory:</strong> FRBM report says, the council will serve both an ex-ante role providing independent forecasts on key macro variables like real and nominal GDP growth, tax buoyancy, commodity prices as well as an ex-post monitoring role, and also serve as the institution to advise on triggering the escape clause and also specify a path of return.</li>
<li><strong>Monitoring finance: </strong>Such a council should work for the union as well as the states. Monitoring of finances and fiscal rules could also help ensure that states comply with a medium-term fiscal policy framework, which has been long argued for by economists.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Freebie" class="alignnone wp-image-645409 size-full" height="488" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.40.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.40.jpeg 608w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-07.13.40-300x241.jpeg 300w" width="608"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Freebies cannot be defined easily, and constitutionally, any state government should be empowered to spend the way it wants, provided the fiscal policy is sustainable. The message from the freebies debate is to make informed economic decisions whilst attending to key development objectives.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>There is nothing wrong in having social security programme that aims to lift the poor get out of poverty and empower the vulnerable sections of the society. In this context, where do you see the goal of sustainable economic development? Comment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/freebie/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India’s Dark Sky Reserve</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dark-sky-reserve/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Dark Sky Reserve</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Science tourism</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Dark Sky Reserve" class="alignnone wp-image-645423 size-full" height="907" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.35.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.35.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.35-300x213.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.35-1024x726.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.35-768x544.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.35-1200x850.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The union territory of Ladakh will host India’s first Dark Sky Reserve which will be set up in Hanle area in the next three months. The Dark Sky Reserve is being built as part of Ladakh’s high-altitude Changthang Wildlife Sanctuary.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Dark Sky Reserve (DSR)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Definition of Dark Sky Reserve</strong>: The International Dark Sky Association (IDSA) defines an international dark sky reserve (IDSR) as “a public or private land of substantial size (at least 700 km², or about 173,000 acres) possessing an exceptional or distinguished quality of starry nights and nocturnal environment, and that is specifically protected for its scientific, natural, educational, cultural heritage, and/or public enjoyment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Core Area of Dark Sky Reserve?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A dark sky reserve requires a “core” area that has clear sky without any light pollution, which can enable telescopes to see the sky in its natural darkness.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Dark Sky Reserve" class="alignnone wp-image-645426 size-full" height="614" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1170px) 100vw, 1170px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.40.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.40.jpeg 1170w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.40-300x157.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.40-1024x537.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.40-768x403.jpeg 768w" width="1170"/></strong></h4>
<h4>Why Ladakh is chosen as ideal location for DSR?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Ladakh is ideal for long-term observatories and dark-sky sites because of its large arid area, high elevation, and sparse population, extreme cold and minimum temperature drops to minus 40 degree celcius.</li>
<li>The Changthang wildlife Sanctuary, the DSR site is situated around 4,500 metres above sea level, which makes it a perfect host for telescopes.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who is managing India’s DSR?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Department of Science and Technology and Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA) in Bengaluru are providing support for the facility. The IIA already manages the Indian Astronomical Observatory (IAO) complex in Hanle, Ladakh.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the International standards for DSR?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>International Dark Sky Association’s Recognition: </strong>The IDSA recognizes and accredits dark-sky areas worldwide, in three categories. The Mont Mégantic Observatory in Quebec is the first such site to be recognized (in 2007) as an International Dark Sky Reserve.</li>
<li><strong>Categorical Certification: </strong>Individuals or groups can nominate a site for certification to the International Dark Sky Association (IDSA). There are five designated categories, namely International Dark Sky parks, communities, reserves, sanctuaries and Urban Night Sky Places.</li>
<li><strong>Global Recognition</strong>: The certification process is similar to that of a site being awarded the UNESCO World Heritage Site tag or getting recognised as a Biosphere Reserve. Between 2001 and January 2022, there have been 195 sites recognised as International Dark Sky Places globally, the IDSA said.</li>
<li><strong>Dark Sky Park: </strong>IDSA recognized Natural Bridges National Monument in Utah as the world’s first International Dark Sky Park.</li>
<li><strong>Dark Sky Sanctuary</strong>: In 2015, the IDSA introduced the term “Dark Sky Sanctuary” and designated the Elqui Valley of northern Chile as the world’s first International Dark Sky Sanctuary. The Gabriela Mistral Dark Sky Sanctuary is named after a Chilean poet.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Dark Sky Reserve" class="alignnone wp-image-645444 size-full" height="720" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.48.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.48.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.48-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.48-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.48-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.48-1200x675.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>What is <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-first-dark-sky-reserve-in-ladakh/">India’s objective with DSR</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>To promote AstroTourism: </strong>The primary objective of the proposed Dark Sky Reserve is to promote astronomy tourism in a sustainable and environment-friendly manner. Scientific methods will be used here to preserve the night sky from ever-increasing light pollution.</li>
<li><strong>To offer clear skies for observations</strong>: With metros, cities and peripheral areas experiencing light pollution and remaining constantly lit up, there are diminishing areas that offer a view of clear skies on cloudless nights.</li>
<li><strong>For training purpose: </strong>In the pilot phase, the Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA),has procured ten small and easy-to-handle telescopes and light-reflecting shields. IIA’s scientists and outreach experts will identify locals and train them to use these telescopes.</li>
<li><strong>Sky gazing and a boost for village economy:</strong> This will include basic sky gazing, identification of constellations, and locating the pole star, among others. These telescopes will be installed at the homestays, which is a popular option for tourist accommodation in Ladakh.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Dark Sky Reserve" class="alignnone wp-image-645446 size-full" height="452" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 678px) 100vw, 678px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.44.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.44.jpeg 678w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.03.44-300x200.jpeg 300w" width="678"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Dark Sky Reserve is likely to boost Astro tourism in India where there has been no such reserve. Once set up, the reserve will be the highest-located site in the country for infrared, gamma-ray, and optical telescopes<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. </strong><strong>What are the Dark Sky Reserves? How DRS will help in astronomical research and observations in India?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dark-sky-reserve/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Boosting India’s Cotton Production</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-cotton/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Cotton crop,Voluntary Sustainable Standards (VSS)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Textile industry,Voluntary Sustainable Standards (VSS)</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="India" class="alignnone wp-image-645443" height="272" sizes="(max-width: 595px) 100vw, 595px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.04.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.04.jpeg 1196w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.04-300x137.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.04-1024x468.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.04-768x351.jpeg 768w" width="595"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cotton, one of the most important crops, has a strategic role in India’s international agriculture play. India is the world’s third-largest exporter of cotton and the second-largest exporter of textiles, therefore, also contributing significantly to the country’s economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>All you need to know about the Cotton crop</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rainfall and Temperature: </strong>Sensitive to timing of rainfall and rainfall during harvest might lead to crop failure. Temperature required is around 20-30 degree c., while rainfall is about 75-100cm.</li>
<li><strong>Soil: </strong>Black soil ideally suited for cotton cultivation as it is rich in lime.cotton is vulnerable to pest attack.</li>
<li><strong>Humidity: </strong>Cotton cultivation requires more than 200 frost free days. Humidity during harvest is harmful.</li>
<li><strong>Oilcake</strong>: The cotton seeds are crushed for oil and the oilcake is an important animal fodder and also used as farm manure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="India" class="alignnone wp-image-645445 size-full" height="627" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1112px) 100vw, 1112px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.58.52.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.58.52.jpeg 1112w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.58.52-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.58.52-1024x577.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.58.52-768x433.jpeg 768w" width="1112"/></strong></h4>
<h4><strong>What is the Present status of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/challenges-facing-the-south-asian-textile-industry/">cotton in India?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India holds a 4% share of the U.S.$840 billion global textile and apparel market</li>
<li>India has been successful in developing backward links, with the aid of the Technical Upgradation Fund Scheme (TUFS), in the cotton and technical textiles industry.</li>
<li>However, India is yet to move into man-made fibres as factories still operate in a seasonal fashion.</li>
<li>Areas of cotton cultivation are Gujrat, Maharashtra, Telangana, Punjab, etc.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;"><em>Do you</em></strong><em style="font-size: 32px; font-weight: bold; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;"> k</em><em style="font-size: 32px; font-weight: bold; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">now? </em></p>
<p>The latest archaeological discovery in Mehrgarh puts the dating of early cotton cultivation and the use of cotton to 5000 BCE. The Indus Valley civilization started cultivating cotton by 3000 BCE. Cotton was mentioned in Hindu hymns in 1500 BCE.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="India" class="alignnone wp-image-645448 size-large" height="887" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.09-1024x887.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.09-1024x887.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.09-300x260.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.09-768x666.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.09-1038x900.jpeg 1038w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.09.jpeg 1080w" width="1024"/>What are the voluntary sustainable standards (VSS) in cotton?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Voluntary Sustainability Standards (VSS): </strong> Voluntary Sustainability Standards (VSS), which encapsulate certification schemes, labelling programmes, and private standards. The major VSS that are dominant in the sustainable cotton value chain today include Better Cotton Initiative (BCI), Organic Cotton, Fair trade Cotton, and Cotton Made in Africa.</li>
<li><strong>To achieve sustainable Goal: </strong>The global textile supply chain is undergoing a paradigm shift; it is pursuing environmental and social upgradation to meet the sustainability requirements imposed by global textile and home furnishing retailers, so as to mitigate the adverse impacts of climate change on cotton farmers and cotton cultivation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the benefits for India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enhance position in global cotton supply: </strong>Adapting to VSS is clearly beneficial for India. On the one hand, it will help it remain globally competitive in the cotton supply chain and strengthen its position in the export market, while on the other, it will help meet India’s SDG commitments.</li>
<li><strong>Takes India a step closer towards sustainable farming: </strong>India has made considerable progress in its transition towards a more sustainable cotton farming ecosystem. The total cotton area under VSS has reached 1.5 million hectares, contributing to 24 percent of the global VSS cotton area.</li>
<li><strong>Increases organic production of cotton: </strong>With approximately 0.2 million hectares of area for production, it is the largest producer of organic cotton, accounting for 50 percent of global organic cotton production, and the second-largest producer of ‘Better Cotton’, accounting for 16.5 percent of total Better Cotton production covering an area of 1.5 million hectares.</li>
<li><strong>Higher yeild</strong>: According to the BCI’s 2020 Impact Report for India, Better Cotton farmers have 9 percent higher yields and 18 percent higher profit than conventional farmers.</li>
<li><strong>Eco friendly production:</strong>The Thinkstep report 2018 on the Life Cycle Assessment of VSS Cotton conducted in Madhya Pradesh revealed a reduction of 50 percent in climate change impact, 59 percent in blue water consumption, 84 percent in ecotoxicity, and 100 percent eutrophication in organic over conventional cotton.</li>
<li><strong>To achieveSDG Targets</strong>: The VSS cotton growth story in India has already demonstrated its contribution towards the achievement of SDG targets for Zero Hunger (Goal 2), Clean Water and Sanitation (Goal 6), Responsible Consumption and Production (Goal 12), Life on Land (Goal 15), and Climate Action (Goal 16).</li>
<li><strong>NITI Aayog’s Assessment: </strong>VSS cotton delivers real, measurable outcomes according to priority indicators as outlined by NITI Aayog which maps India’s SDG goals. These indicators include changes in the extent of water bodies, improving groundwater withdrawal against availability, and rationalising nitrogen fertiliser.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="India" class="alignnone wp-image-645450 size-full" height="614" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.17.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.17.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.17-300x144.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.17-1024x491.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.17-768x368.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-08-at-10.59.17-1200x576.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India must scale up the VSS while aligning it with its SDG commitments since VSS in cotton ensures a better production system, sourcing methods, and consumption patterns while also influencing the lives of hundreds of millions.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. </strong><strong>What are the Voluntary Sustainable Standards (VSS)? Cotton production can be boosted in India using VSS method. Elaborate</strong>.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-cotton/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>