<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2022 01:52:47 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>In news: Ongole Cattle Breed</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/in-news-ongole-cattle-breed/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ongole Cattle</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Indigenous cattle breedss</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-619914" height="268" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 407px) 100vw, 407px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ongole.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ongole.jpg 407w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ongole-300x198.jpg 300w" width="407"/></strong></p>
<p>Ongole breed of cattle had remained indispensable for all farm operations for centuries in Prakasam district of Andhra Pradesh in view of their draught power.</p>
<h4>Ongole Cattle</h4>
<ul>
<li>Ongole cattle are an indigenous cattle breed that originates from Prakasam District in the state of Andhra Pradesh.</li>
<li>The breed derives its name from the place the breed originates from, Ongole.</li>
<li>The Ongole breed of cattle <strong><u>Bos Indicus</u></strong>, has a great demand as it is said to possess resistance to both foot and mouth disease and mad cow disease.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What’s so special about this breed?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Cattle breeders use the fighting ability of the bulls to choose the right stock for breeding in terms of purity and strength.</li>
<li>Ongole cattle are known for their toughness, rapid growth rate, and natural tolerance to tropical heat and disease resistance.</li>
<li>It was perhaps the first Indian breed of cattle to gain worldwide recognition.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Ongole milk is rich in A2 (allele of Beta Casein).</li>
<li>They fetches a premium price of over ₹150 per litre as it enables consumers build immunity against viral and other diseases.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Global Prominence</h4>
<ul>
<li>Ongole bulls have gone as far as America, the Netherlands, Malaysia, Brazil, Argentina, Colombia, Mexico, Paraguay, Indonesia, West Indies, Australia, Fiji, Mauritius, Indo-China and Philippines.</li>
<li>The Brahmana bull in America is an off-breed of the Ongole.</li>
<li>The population of Ongole off-breed in Brazil is said to number several million.</li>
<li>The famous Santa Gertrudis breed developed in Texas, USA have Ongole blood.</li>
<li>It has gained global prominence, particularly in Brazil which imported barely hundred animals and produced multiple superior breeds like the world famous Zebu.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/in-news-ongole-cattle-breed/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre to file review petition on Eco-Sensitive Zones in SC</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-to-file-review-petition-on-eco-sensitive-zones-in-sc/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Eco-sensitive Zones (ESZs)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>Union Minister of Environment, Forest and Climate Change has said that the Ministry will file a review petition in the Supreme Court urging a relook into its judgment on eco-sensitive zones.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court has earlier directed that every protected forest, national park and wildlife sanctuary across the country should have a mandatory eco-sensitive zone (ESZ) of a minimum one km starting from their demarcated boundaries.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why such move?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The purpose of declaring ESZs around national parks, forests and sanctuaries is to create some kind of a “shock absorber” for the protected areas.</li>
<li>These zones would act as a transition zone from areas of high protection to those involving lesser protection.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the Eco-sensitive Zones (ESZs)?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Eco-Sensitive Zones (ESZs) or Ecologically Fragile Areas (EFAs) are areas notified by the MoEFCC around Protected Areas, National Parks and Wildlife Sanctuaries.</li>
<li>The purpose of declaring ESZs is to create some kind of “shock absorbers” to the protected areas by regulating and managing the activities around such areas.</li>
<li>They also act as a transition zone from areas of high protection to areas involving lesser protection.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How are they demarcated?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 does not mention the word “Eco-Sensitive Zones”.</li>
<li>However, Section 3(2)(v) of the Act, says that Central Government can restrict areas in which any industries, operations or processes or class of industries, operations or processes shall be carried out or shall not, subject to certain safeguards.</li>
<li>Besides Rule 5(1) of the Environment (Protection) Rules, 1986 states that central government can prohibit or restrict the location of industries and carrying on certain operations or processes on the basis of certain considerations.</li>
<li>The same criteria have been used by the government to declare No Development Zones (NDZs).</li>
</ul>
<h4>Defining its boundaries</h4>
<ul>
<li>An ESZ could go up to 10 kilometres around a protected area as provided in the Wildlife Conservation Strategy, 2002.</li>
<li>Moreover, in the case where sensitive corridors, connectivity and ecologically important patches, crucial for landscape linkage, are beyond 10 km width, these should be included in the ESZs.</li>
<li>Further, even in the context of a particular Protected Area, the distribution of an area of ESZ and the extent of regulation may not be uniform all around and it could be of variable width and extent.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-to-file-review-petition-on-eco-sensitive-zones-in-sc/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SMILE-75 scheme to rehabilitate Beggars</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/smile-75-scheme-to-rehabilitate-beggars/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>SMILE Scheme</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The Social Justice and Empowerment Ministry has launched the ‘SMILE-75’ initiative for comprehensive rehabilitation of persons engaged in begging in 75 identified municipalities as a part of the celebrations of 75 years of Independence.</p>
<h4>SMILE Scheme</h4>
<ul>
<li>SMILE is an acronym for Support for Marginalised Individuals for Livelihood and Enterprise.</li>
<li>This scheme is a sub-scheme under the ‘Central Sector Scheme for Comprehensive Rehabilitation of persons engaged in the act of Begging’.</li>
<li>It also focuses on rehabilitation, provision of medical facilities and intervention, counselling, education, skill development, economic linkages to transgender persons.</li>
<li>It covers several comprehensive measures including welfare measures for persons who are engaged in the act of begging.</li>
<li>The focus of the scheme is extensively on rehabilitation, provision of medical facilities, counselling, basic documentation, education, skill development, economic linkages and so on.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Its implementation</h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme would be implemented with the support of State/UT Governments/Local Urban Bodies, Voluntary Organizations, Community Based Organizations (CBOs), institutions and others.</li>
<li>The scheme provides for the use of the existing shelter homes available with the State/UT Governments and Urban local bodies for rehabilitation of the persons engaged in the act of Begging.</li>
<li>In case of the non-availability of existing shelter homes, new dedicated shelter homes are to be set up by the implementing agencies.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/smile-75-scheme-to-rehabilitate-beggars/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Essential Commodities Act?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/essential-commodities-act-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Essential Commodities Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Centre has invoked the Essential Commodities Act of 1955 to ask States to monitor and verify the stocks of Arhar/Tur Dal available with traders.</p>
<h4><strong>Essential Commodities Act</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ECA, 1955 was established to ensure the delivery of certain commodities or products, the supply of which, if obstructed due to hoarding or black marketing, would affect the normal life of the people.</li>
<li>The list of items under the Act includes drugs, fertilizers, pulses, and edible oils, as well as petroleum and petroleum products.</li>
<li>The Centre can include new commodities as and when the need arises, and takes them off the list once the situation improves.</li>
<li>Additionally, the government can also fix the maximum retail price (MRP) of any packaged product that it declares an “essential commodity”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How ECA works?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Centre notifying stock limit holding</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>If the Centre finds that a certain commodity is in short supply and its price is spiking, it can notify stock-holding limits on it for a specified period.</li>
<li>The States act on this notification to specify limits and take steps to ensure that these are adhered to.</li>
<li>Anybody trading or dealing in the commodity, be it wholesalers, retailers or even importers are prevented from stockpiling it beyond a certain quantity.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) States can opt-out</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>A State can, however, choose not to impose any restrictions.</li>
<li>But once it does, traders have to immediately sell into the market any stocks held beyond the mandated quantity.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What happens for non-compliance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As not all shopkeepers and traders comply, State agencies conduct raids to get everyone to toe the line and the errant are punished.</li>
<li>The excess stocks are auctioned or sold through fair price shops.</li>
<li>This improves supplies and brings down prices.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>Ex: The Union Government has brought masks and hand-sanitizers under the ECA to make sure that these products, key for preventing the spread of Covid-19 infection, are available to people at the right price and in the right quality. Later this move was reverted.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>What about Food Items?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Items covered:</strong></p>
<p>Rice, wheat, atta, gram dal, arhar dal, moong dal, urad dal, masoor, dal, tea, sugar, salt, Vanaspati, groundnut oil, mustard oil, milk, soya oil, palm oil, sunflower oil, gur, potato, onion and tomato.</p>
<p><strong>(2) Price Stabilization Fund (PSF):</strong></p>
<p>The government utilizes the buffer of agri-horticultural commodities like pulses, onion, etc. built under Price Stabilization Fund (PSF) to help moderate the volatility in prices.</p>
<h4><strong>Recent amendments to the ECA</strong></h4>
<p>In 2020, the EC Act was amended for the stock limit to be imposed only under exceptional circumstances such as famine or other calamities.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Exceptional circumstances:</strong> It allowed the centre to delist certain commodities as essential, allowing the government to regulate their supply and prices only in cases of war, famine, extraordinary price rises, or natural calamities.</li>
<li><strong>Commodities de-regulated:</strong> The commodities that have been deregulated are food items, including cereals, pulses, potatoes, onion, edible oilseeds, and oils.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Exceptions provided</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The government regulation of stocks will be based on rising prices, and can only be imposed if there is</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>A 100% increase in retail price in the case of horticultural produce and</li>
<li>A 50% increase in retail price in the case of non-perishable agricultural food items</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>These restrictions will not apply to stocks of food held for public distribution in India.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/essential-commodities-act-india/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Explained: Baloch Freedom Movement</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-baloch-freedom-movement/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Balochistan, BLA, Khan of Kelat</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Baloch Freedom Movement</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-619915" height="839" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/baloch.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/baloch.jpg 800w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/baloch-286x300.jpg 286w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/baloch-768x805.jpg 768w" width="800"/></p>
<p>Baloch separatism under the Baloch Liberation Army (BLA) has been an ongoing issue in Pakistan since the birth of the nation in 1947.</p>
<h4><strong>Who are the BLA fighters?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The BLA <strong>announced itself in 2005</strong> with a rocket attack on a paramilitary camp in Balochistan Kohlu during a visit by then President Pervez Musharraf.</li>
<li>It is a nationalist militant group that has been waging an insurgency for <strong><u>Baloch self-determination and a separate homeland</u></strong> for the Baloch people.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Rise of Baloch nationalism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While the BLA’s armed insurgency is about two decades old, demands of Baloch nationalists for political autonomy and <strong><u>threats of secession date back to 1947</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Khan of Kalat (who claimed sovereignty over the four princely states of Kalat, Lasbela, Kharan and Makran) held out for independence, and the Pakistan Army forced his accession in March 1948.</li>
<li>Between 1973 and 1977, the Zulfikar Ali Bhutto-led government sent in the Pakistan Army to crush a leftist guerilla war <strong><u>inspired by the liberation of Bangladesh</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The tribal sardars of Balochistan, who had been at the forefront of Baloch nationalism, and were co-opted by the state in the late 1970s, grew rebellious again.</li>
<li>The insurgency gathered momentum from 2006, after the Pakistan Army killed the Bugti sardar, Nawab Akbar Khan Bugti, who had been also been a chief minister and governor of the province.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why it is gaining momentum now?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Pakistan Army’s operations against Baloch nationalists</u></strong> over the last two decades have seen <strong><u>hundreds of disappearances, and other alleged human rights violations.</u></strong></li>
<li>Baloch nationalists also see the <strong><u>sudden influx of jihadist groups</u></strong> in the province as a move by the Pakistan security establishment to counter their nationalist demands.</li>
<li>In 2012, the <strong><u>US Congress</u></strong> convened a hearing on Balochistan and <strong>supported the demand for a free Baloch land</strong>.</li>
<li>In a significant shift in policy, back then in 2016, <strong><u>PM Modi had made a reference to the Baloch freedom struggle in his Independence Day speech</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why does Balochistan matters?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Balochistan <strong>borders Afghanistan and Iran</strong>.</li>
<li>The people are mostly tribal with secular principles and are <strong><u>admirers of ties with India</u></strong>.</li>
<li>With gas, oil, copper and gold deposits, it is the <strong><u>most resource-rich of Pakistan’s four provinces</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It <strong><u>makes up half of Pakistan’s area</u></strong>, but has only 3.6% of its population.</li>
<li><u>Pakistan alleges that the</u> <u>insurgency is backed by India</u>.</li>
<li>This is the region where a former <strong><u>Indian Navy officer Kulbhushan Jadhav was abducted from Iran and charged for espionage</u></strong> supporting Baloch activism in Pakistan.</li>
<li>Many <strong>Baloch activists had been</strong> <strong><u>seeking asylum and has applied for Indian citizenship</u></strong>. New Delhi neither confirmed nor deny the reports.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why did BLA target the Chinese now?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The BLA claimed it attacks Chinese nationals because Beijing <strong>ignored warnings not to enter deals and agreements regarding Balochistan </strong>before the province had been “liberated”.</li>
<li>Baloch people see China-Pakistan Economic Corridor (<strong>CPEC) as a neo-colonist move against their sovereignty.</strong></li>
<li>Among China’s major projects in Balochistan is the port of Gwadar, strategically located near the Strait of Hormuz – a crucial oil shipping route in the Arabian Sea.</li>
<li>The security of its nationals in Pakistan has become a major issue for Beijing, especially since it launched the CPEC.</li>
<li>Such attacks has literally <strong><u>stalled the work in progress of CPEC projects making it a sheer failure</u></strong><u>.</u></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Significance of recent events</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is rare that the <strong><u>BLA deployed female suicide bombers</u></strong>. Recent attack was done by a highly educated lady and mother of two.</li>
<li>This is also the first time that a <strong><u>non-jihadist ethno-nationalist group</u></strong> has deployed a woman suicide bomber <strong><u>in the manner of Sri Lanka’s LTTE</u></strong>.</li>
<li>According to security experts familiar with the Baloch insurgency, it marks a <strong><u>worsening security situation in Pakistan. </u></strong></li>
<li>As the training camps are alleged by Pakistan to be in Afghanistan, the incident may also be a pointer to <strong><u>Pakistan’s loss of control over the Talibans</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-baloch-freedom-movement/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Govt. to enumerate Sanitation Workers</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/govt-to-enumerate-sanitation-workers/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Rashtriya Garima Abhiyan</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Plight of sanitation workers in India</p></div></div><p>The Ministry of Social Justice and Empowerment (MoSJ&amp;E) is now preparing to undertake a nationwide survey to enumerate all people engaged in the hazardous cleaning of sewers and septic tanks.</p>
<h4>Why such move?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Cleaning of sewers and septic tanks has led to at least 351 deaths since 2017.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Various initiatives for sanitation workers</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ministry now has proper <strong><u>distinction between sanitation work and manual scavenging</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The practice of <strong><u>manual scavenging no longer takes place</u></strong> in the country as all manual scavengers had been accounted for and enrolled into the rehabilitation scheme, said the ministry.</li>
<li>The enumeration of sanitization workers is soon to be conducted across 500 AMRUT (Atal Mission for Rejuvenation and Urban Transformation) cities, as a part of <strong><u>National Action Plan for Mechanised Sanitation Ecosystem (NAMASTE).</u></strong></li>
<li>The NAMASTE scheme aims to eradicate unsafe sewer and septic tank cleaning practices.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Manual Scavenging in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>Manual scavenging is the practice of removing human excreta by hand from sewers or septic tanks.</li>
<li>India <strong><u>banned</u></strong> the practice under the <strong>Prohibition of Employment as Manual Scavengers and their Rehabilitation Act, 2013 (PEMSR). </strong></li>
<li>The Act bans the use of any individual for manually cleaning, carrying, disposing of or otherwise handling in any manner, human excreta till its disposal.</li>
<li>In 2013, the definition of manual scavengers was also broadened to include people employed to clean septic tanks, ditches, or railway tracks.</li>
<li>The Act recognizes manual scavenging as a “<strong><u>dehumanizing practice</u></strong>,” and cites a need to “<strong>correct the historical injustice and indignity suffered by the manual scavengers</strong>.”</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is it still prevalent in India?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low awareness:</strong> Manual scavenging is mostly done by the marginalized section of the society and they are generally not aware about their rights.</li>
<li><strong>Enforcement issues:</strong> The lack of enforcement of the Act and exploitation of unskilled labourers are the reasons why the practice is still prevalent in India.</li>
<li><strong>High cost of automated:</strong> The Mumbai civic body charges anywhere between Rs 20,000 and Rs 30,000 to clean septic tanks.</li>
<li><strong>Cheaper availability:</strong> The unskilled labourers, meanwhile, are much cheaper to hire and contractors illegally employ them at a daily wage of Rs 300-500.</li>
<li><strong>Caste dynamics:</strong> Caste hierarchy still exists and it reinforces the caste’s relation with occupation. Almost all the manual scavengers belong to lower castes.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Various policy initiatives</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Prohibition of Employment as Manual Scavengers and their Rehabilitation (Amendment) Bill, 2020:</strong> It proposes to completely mechanise sewer cleaning, introduce ways for ‘on-site’ protection and provide compensation to manual scavengers in case of sewer deaths.</li>
<li><strong>Prohibition of Employment as Manual Scavengers and their Rehabilitation Act, 2013:</strong> Superseding the 1993 Act, the 2013 Act goes beyond prohibitions on dry latrines, and outlaws all manual excrement cleaning of insanitary latrines, open drains, or pits.</li>
<li><strong>Rashtriya Garima Abhiyan:</strong> It started national wide march “Maila Mukti Yatra” for total eradication of manual scavenging from 30th November 2012 from Bhopal.</li>
<li><strong>Prevention of Atrocities Act:</strong> In 1989, the Prevention of Atrocities Act became an integrated guard for sanitation workers since majority of the manual scavengers belonged to the Scheduled Caste.</li>
<li><strong>Compensation:</strong> As per the Prohibition of Employment of Manual Scavengers and their Rehabilitation (PEMSR) Act, 2013 and the Supreme Court’s decision in the Safai Karamchari Andolan vs Union of India case, a compensation of Rs 10 lakh is awarded to the victims family.</li>
<li><strong>National Commission for Safai Karamcharis (NCSK):</strong> It is currently a temporary non-statutory body that investigates the conditions of Safai Karamcharis (waste collectors) in India and makes recommendations to the Government.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/govt-to-enumerate-sanitation-workers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Reaping our demographic dividend</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/reaping-our-demographic-dividend/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India's demographic dividend</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s <strong>biggest strength is its ‘demographic dividend’</strong> and people need to fully leverage it to fast-track the country’s progress in various sectors</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The 2022 edition of <strong>the World Population Prospects (WPP) of</strong> the United Nations has projected that <strong>India may surpass China as the world’s most populous country next year.</strong></li>
<li>The report estimates that India will have a population of 1.66 billion in 2050, ahead of China’s 1.317 billion around that time<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is demographic dividend?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Demographic dividend, as defined by the <strong>United Nations Population Fund</strong>, is “<strong>the economic growth potential that can result from shifts in a population’s age structure</strong>, mainly when the share of the <strong>working-age population is larger than the non-working-age</strong> share of the population”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Current status for India </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India entered the <strong>demographic dividend opportunity</strong> window in 2005-06 and will remain there till 2055-56.</li>
<li>This is the period when the <strong>working age ratio is equal to or more than 150%</strong> and the <strong>dependency ratio is equal to or lower than 66.7%, </strong>generally taken as the cut-off for the demographic dividend window.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How India can leverage this dividend</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Investment in right direction </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Investments in human and physical infrastructure will need to be scaled up dramatically to promote entrepreneurship and create jobs.</li>
<li>Investment in education is crucial for ensuring that working-age people are prepared for the demands of the economy.</li>
<li>Increase spending on health</li>
<li>Increase investments in Research and Development</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Absorption of labour into productive employment</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Promote entrepreneurship and job creation</li>
<li>Service sector like tourism, logistics should be promoted</li>
<li>Skill development of the working-age population so that they can turn out to be productive for the country’s economy</li>
</ul>
<h4>Challenges in reaping this</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Drastic quality improvement:</strong> India’s challenge is to create conditions for faster growth of productive jobs outside of agriculture, especially in the organized manufacturing and in services.</li>
<li><strong>Severe shortages</strong>: India currently faces a severe shortage of well trained, skilled workers. Large sections of the educated workforce have little or no job skills, making them largely Unemployable.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dismal health sector:</strong> A closer look implies various factors such as poor health which although obvious, play a major role in the poor performance of working population.</li>
<li><strong>Socio economic dimensions:</strong> The status of institutions in India regarding caste discrimination, gender inequalities, widening income gap between the rich and the poor, religious differences, inefficient and slow legal system- all contribute to the poor standard of living of the masses.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Government steps </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>National Skill Development Corporation (NSDC</strong>): incorporated on 31st July, 2008, is a first-of-its-kind Public Private Partnership (PPP) in India set up to facilitate the development and upgrading of the skills of the growing Indian workforce through skill training programs.</li>
<li><strong>National Skill Development Agency</strong>: Currently, skill development efforts are spread across approximately20 separate ministries, 35 State Governments and Union Territories and the private sector.</li>
<li><strong>National Skill Certification and Money Reward Scheme: </strong>encouragement is given for skill development for youth by providing monetary rewards for successful completion of approved training programs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Strategies exist to exploit the demographic window of opportunity that India has today, but they need to be adopted and implemented.</li>
<li>The dreams of huge income flow and resultant economic growth due to demographic dividend could be realized only when we inculcate the required skills in the work force to make it as competent as its counterparts in the developed world.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Important data for mains </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>India’s working-age population has numerically outstripped its non-working age population.</strong></li>
<li><strong>India’s total fertility rate (TFR)</strong> has declined from 2.2 in 2015-16 to 2.0 in 2019-21, indicating the <strong>significant progress of population control measures</strong>, revealed the report of the fifth round of the <strong>National Family Health Survey (NFHS-5).</strong></li>
<li><strong>The</strong> <strong>TFR is the average number of children born to a woman in her lifetime.</strong></li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Mains question </strong></h4>
<p><strong><em>Q. Do you think the right has come that India should adopt moving away policy from population control towards reaping its demographic dividends? Critically examine.</em></strong></p></blockquote>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/reaping-our-demographic-dividend/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Labour welfare necessity</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/labour-welfare-necessity/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Labour welfare initiatives</p></div></div><p><strong>Context </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>One of the biggest economic fallout of the pandemic has been the deteriorating labour market conditions.</li>
<li>In the years ahead when the health crisis subsides and the economy witnesses a rebound, the healing of the labour market may take some more time. This is because the impact of recovery on this market is always felt with a lag.</li>
<li>Given the ebb and flow of the pandemic, the growth recovery is likely to be fragmented and will weigh on the number and types of jobs available.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Definition</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Labour welfare relates to taking care of the well-being of workers by employers, trade unions, governmental and non-governmental institutions and agencies.</li>
<li>Welfare includes anything that is done for the comfort and improvement of employees and is provided over and above the wages.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are labour rights?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Labour rights or workers’ rights are both legal rights and human rights relating to labour relations between workers and employers. These rights are codified in national and international labour and employment law. In general, these rights influence working conditions in relations of employment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why labour law is needed </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Labour law aims to correct the imbalance of power between the worker and the employer; to prevent the employer from dismissing the worker without good cause; to set up and preserve the processes by which workers are recognized as ‘equal’ partners in negotiations about their working conditions etc<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Constitutional mandate </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Article 41</strong> – The state shall within the limits of its economic capacity and development make effective provision for securing the right to work, to education and to public assistance in cases of unemployment, old age, sickness and disablement and in other cases of underserved want.</li>
<li><strong>Article 42</strong> – The state shall make provision for securing just and humane conditions of work and for maternity relief.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Necessity for welfare </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There were only 25 million during the initial period of industrial growth, while the strength of the workers is increasing year after year and hence, need for a mechanism to look into the welfare of the labour.</li>
<li>Workers put in long hours of work in unhealthy surrounding and the drudgery of the factory work continues to have adverse effect. To counter these welfare measures were felt necessary.</li>
<li>As a result of hardwork, they fall prey to alchoholism, gambling and other immoral activities results in absenteeism and other problems in the organisation. Hence the need was felt.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Scope for labour welfare in India </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Contribute to the productivity of labour and efficiency of the enterprise.</li>
<li>Raise the standard of living of workers by indirectly reducing the burden on their purse.</li>
<li>Be in tune and harmony with similar services obtaining in a neighbouring community where an enterprise is situated.</li>
<li>Be based on an intelligent prediction of the future needs of industrial work and be so designed as to offer a cushion to absorb the shock of industrialization and urbanization</li>
<li>Be administratively viable and essentially development in outlook.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Government steps in this direction </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Social Security Measures: </strong>The social security measures would help man to face the contingencies as such it is difficult for him either to work or to get work and support himself and his family. Thus social security measure provides a self balancing social insurance or assistance from public funds.</li>
<li><strong>Social Insurance</strong>: is described as the giving in return for contribution, benefits up to subsistence level, as of right and without a means test, so that an individual may build freely upon it.</li>
<li><strong>Social Assistance</strong>: is provided as an supplement to social insurance for those needy persons who cannot get social insurance payments and is offered after a means test.</li>
<li><strong>Public Service</strong>: is a programme constituting the third main type of social security. They are financed directly by the government from its general revenues in form of cash payments or services to every member of the community falling within a defined category.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Case study of Finland </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Universal basic income pilot project:</strong> For two years Finland’s government gave 2,000 unemployed citizens €560 a month with no strings attached. It was the first nationwide basic income experiment. The concept is slowly becoming difficult for people to ignore.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges in labour welfare in India </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Technical glitches:</strong> Under the Constitution of India, Labour is a subject in the concurrent list where both the Central and State Governments are competent to enact legislation. As a result, a large number of labour laws have been enacted catering to different aspects of labour e.g. occupational health, safety, employment etc.</li>
<li><strong>Loopholes:</strong> Because of the predominantly heavy-handed labour regulations (also called as Inspector Raj) with exploitable gaps, the MNCs and domestic organizations have resorted to alternate ways i.e. employing contract labour at less than half the payroll of a permanent employee.</li>
<li><strong>Gaps in labour laws:</strong> One of the main reasons for labour reforms is the concept of contract labour. Trade Unions suggest that this concept itself should be removed. There is stringent hiring and firing process defined in Industry Disputes Act. It makes it mandatory for the organization to seek Government permission before removing an employee.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Labour Welfare helps labourers improve their working conditions, providing social security and raising their standard of living.</li>
<li>Raise the employee’s morale use the workforce more effectively besides removing dissatisfaction help to develop loyalty in workers towards the organization.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Mains question </strong></h4>
<p><em>Q.What is labour welfare according to you? Why it is needed? Explain the challenges in front of Indian labour reforms<strong>.</strong></em></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/labour-welfare-necessity/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India @75 –Relooking our democracy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-75-relooking-our-democracy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As we celebrate the nation @75 , we must also reflect on the mixed nature of our democracy</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Definition of democracy</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>“Government of the people, by the people and for the people” were the words used by Abraham Lincoln in the year 1863 while talking about democracy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Purpose of democracy </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cornerstones of democracy include freedom of assembly, association, property rights, freedom of religion and speech, inclusiveness and equality, citizenship, consent of the governed, voting rights, freedom from unwarranted governmental deprivation of the right to life and liberty, and minority rights.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India is a parliamentary democratic secular republic in which the president of India is the head of state &amp; first citizen of India and the prime minister of India is the head of government.</li>
<li>It is based on the federal structure of government, although the word is not used in the Constitution itself.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How it has performed </strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1)</strong> <strong>Political front</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India is the world’s the largest democracy proved success in accommodation of group and regional demands in a complex, quasi-federal, polity.</li>
<li>During the first general election in the 1951 India had 54 political parties and now it has grown up to 464 in the 2014 general election as an evident of deepening of the democratic process.</li>
<li>In the first General election 1951, 173 million citizens were given right to vote.</li>
<li>In the 16<sup>th</sup> general election in 2014, the size of the electorate had increased to 814 million.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Social front </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The democratic process has brought about a shift of political power from the middle and higher castes and classes of urban society to backward classes who are now the politically most influential ones in the country.</li>
<li>They have won reservations for themselves in legislatures and government services as were accorded to the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes after independence through Constitutional provisions.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Economic Front</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>These include strategic affairs and security, politico-legal democratic governance as well as society and economy.</li>
<li>India has been able to emerge as a regional power in Asia and super power in south Asia backed by its economic, military and nuclear capabilities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Contradictions in democracy </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Performance of Bureaucracy:</strong> Dishonest officials to protect themselves from the consequences of their wrong-doings have largely exploited constitutional protection for the Services under Article 311.</li>
<li><strong>Administration of Justice:</strong> Judicial system has not been able to meet even the modest expectations of the society. Its delays and costs are frustrating, its processes slow and uncertain. People are pushed to seek recourse to Extra-legal methods for relief. Trial system both on the civil and criminal side has utterly broken down.</li>
<li><strong>Areas of Concern:</strong> There is a fundamental breach of the constitutional faith on the part of the Governments and their method of governance lies in the neglect of the people who are the ultimate source of all political authority.</li>
<li><strong>Regionalism:</strong> Issues of national integrity and security have not received adequate and thoughtful attention. Mechanisms for the assessment of early warning symptoms of social unrest are absent.</li>
<li><strong>Corruption:</strong> The increasing instability of elected governments is attributable to opportunistic politics and unprincipled defections.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Some positive suggestions to government </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Feedback</strong>: The Government should hear criticism rather than rejecting it outrightly. Suggestions on eroding democratic values need a thoughtful, and respectful response.</li>
<li><strong>Freedom of press:</strong> The press and the judiciary which are considered the pillars of India’s Democracy, require to be independent of any executive interference.</li>
<li><strong>Opposition:</strong> strong democracy requires strong opposition. Without an alternative choice, the very objective of election to provide a check on arbitrary power gets defeated.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The institutionalization of constitutional democracy has helped the people of India realize the importance of democracy and inculcate democratic sensibilities among them.</li>
<li>At the same time, it is important that all the government organs work in harmony to uphold the trust people of the country have held in them and ensure the objectives of true democracy.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Mains question </strong></h4>
<p><em>Q.We are celebrating Azadi ka amrit mahotsav India @75, trace the journey of democracy critically by providing some suggestions for robust democracy.</em></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-75-relooking-our-democracy/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>History of the PIN code, which turns 50 this I-Day</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/history-of-the-pin-code-which-turns-50-this-i-day/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PIN code</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The 75th Independence Day coincides with another milestone in the country’s history — it was on August 15, 1972, that the Postal Index Number (PIN) was introduced in India.</p>
<p>As the PIN code turns 50 on Monday, we look at its history and evolution.</p>
<h4>Why was the PIN code introduced?</h4>
<ul>
<li>According to the Department of Posts, there were 23,344 post offices, primarily in urban areas, in India at the time of Independence.</li>
<li>But, the country was growing rapidly and the postal network had to keep pace.</li>
<li>The PIN code was meant to ease the process of mail sorting and delivery in a country where different places, often, have the same or similar names, and letters are written in a wide variety of languages.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How does the PIN code work?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The PIN is made up of six digits.</li>
<li>The first number indicates the postal region — Northern, Eastern, Western, Southern; and number 9, which signifies the Army Postal Service.</li>
<li>The second number denotes a sub-region, and the third represents the sorting district.</li>
<li>The remaining numbers narrow the geography further to the specific post office making the delivery.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who was the person behind the initiative?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The person behind the initiative was <strong><u>Shriram Bhikaji Velankar</u></strong>, additional secretary in the Union Ministry of Communications and a senior member of the Posts and Telegraphs Board.</li>
<li>Velankar was also a Sanskrit poet of eminence who had been conferred the President’s Award for Sanskrit in 1996, three years before he died in Mumbai.</li>
<li>He had set up a cultural group in Mumbai, called the Dev Vani Mandiram, which worked to create awareness about Sanskrit in India and foreign countries.</li>
<li>Velankar was also the chairman of the World Philatelic Exhibition, called Indipex, which was held in New Delhi in 1973 and featured 120 countries.</li>
<li>He retired from his government service on December 31, 1973.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are some parallel systems followed world over?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Globally, in the US, the Zone Improvement Plan (ZIP) code was introduced July 1, 1963, under the aegis of the Postal Service Nationwide Improved Mail Service plan to improve the speed of mail delivery.</li>
<li>Under the old system letters went through about 17 sorting stops – the new system was going to be considerably less time-consuming utilizing newer, more mechanical systems.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Is the PIN code still relevant?</h4>
<ul>
<li>With the spread of the Internet, when people are sending fewer letters, it is easy to question the relevance of the PIN code.</li>
<li>But try to order food delivery or a parcel over online shopping and the importance of Velankar’s work in India will become evident.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/history-of-the-pin-code-which-turns-50-this-i-day/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Women heroes of India’s freedom struggle, mentioned by PM in his I-Day speech</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-heroes-of-indias-freedom-struggle-mentioned-by-pm-in-his-i-day-speech/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Freedom fighters in news</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>In his Independence Day address to the nation the Prime Minister paid tributes to women freedom fighters for showing the world the true meaning of India’s “nari shakti”. A look at the women he named in his speech:</p>
<h4>Rani Laxmibai</h4>
<ul>
<li>The queen of the princely state of Jhansi, Rani Laxmibai is known for her role in the First War of India’s Independence in 1857.</li>
<li>Born Manikarnika Tambe in 1835, she married the king of Jhansi.</li>
<li>The couple adopted a son before the king’s death, which the British East India Company refused to accept as the legal heir and decided to annex Jhansi.</li>
<li>Refusing to cede her territory, the queen decided to rule on behalf of the heir, and later joined the uprising against the British in 1857.</li>
<li>Cornered by the British, she escaped from Jhansi fort. She was wounded in combat near Gwalior’s Phool Bagh, where she later died.</li>
<li>Sir Hugh Rose, who was commanding the British army, is known to have described her as “personable, clever…and one of the most dangerous Indian leaders”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Jhalkari Bai</h4>
<ul>
<li>A soldier in Rani Laxmibai’s women’s army, Durga Dal, she rose to become one of the queen’s most trusted advisers.</li>
<li>She is known for putting her own life at risk to keep the queen out of harm’s way.</li>
<li>Till date, the story of her valour is recalled by the people of Bundelkhand, and she is often presented as a representative of Bundeli identity.</li>
<li>According to Ministry of Culture’s Amrit Mahotsav website, “Many Dalit communities of the region look up to her as an incarnation of God and also celebrate Jhalkaribai Jayanti every year in her honour.”</li>
</ul>
<h4>Durga Bhabhi</h4>
<ul>
<li>Durgawati Devi, who was popularly known as Durga Bhabhi, was a revolutionary who joined the armed struggle against colonial rule.</li>
<li>A member of the Naujawan Bharat Sabha, she helped Bhagat Singh escape in disguise from Lahore after the 1928 killing of British police officer John P Saunders.</li>
<li>During the train journey that followed, Durgawati and Bhagat Singh posed as a couple, and Rajguru as their servant.</li>
<li>Later, as revenge for the hanging of Bhagat Singh, Rajguru, and Sukhdev, she made an unsuccessful attempt to kill the former Punjab Governor, Lord Hailey.</li>
<li>Born in Allahabad in 1907 and married to Hindustan Socialist Republican Association (HSRA) member Bhagwati Charan Vohra, Durgawati, along with other revolutionaries, also ran a bomb factory in Delhi.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Rani Gaidinliu</h4>
<ul>
<li>Born in 1915 in present-day Manipur, Rani Gaidinliu was a Naga spiritual and political leader who fought the British.</li>
<li>She joined the Heraka religious movement which later became a movement to drive out the British. She rebelled against the Empire, and refused to pay taxes, asking people to do the same.</li>
<li>The British launched a manhunt, but she evaded arrest, moving from village to village.</li>
<li>Gaidinliu was finally arrested in 1932 when she was just 16, and later sentenced for life. She was released in 1947.</li>
<li>Then PM Nehru described Gaidinliu as the “daughter of the hills”, and gave her the title of ‘Rani’ for her courage.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Rani Chennamma</h4>
<ul>
<li>The queen of Kittur, Rani Chennamma, was among the first rulers to lead an armed rebellion against British rule.</li>
<li>Kittur was a princely state in present-day Karnataka.</li>
<li>She fought back against the attempt to control her dominion in 1824 after the death of her young son. She had lost her husband, Raja Mallasarja, in 1816.</li>
<li>She is seen among the few rulers of the time who understood the colonial designs of the British.</li>
<li>Rani Chennamma defeated the British in her first revolt, but was captured and imprisoned during the second assault by the East India Company.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Begum Hazrat Mahal</h4>
<ul>
<li>After her husband, Nawab of Awadh Wajid Ali Shah, was exiled after the 1857 revolt, Begum Hazrat Mahal, along with her supporters, took on the British and wrested control of Lucknow.</li>
<li>She was forced into a retreat after the colonial rulers recaptured the area.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Velu Nachiyar</h4>
<ul>
<li>Many years before the revolt of 1857, Velu Nachiyar waged a war against the British and emerged victorious. Born in Ramanathapuram in 1780, she was married to the king of Sivagangai.</li>
<li>After her husband was killed in battle with the East India Company, she entered the conflict, and won with support of neighbouring kings.</li>
<li>She went on to produce the first human bomb as well as establish the first army of trained women soldiers in the late 1700s.</li>
<li>Her army commander Kuyili is believed to have set herself ablaze and walked into a British ammunition dump.</li>
<li>She was succeeded by her daughter in 1790, and died a few years later in 1796.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-heroes-of-indias-freedom-struggle-mentioned-by-pm-in-his-i-day-speech/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Punjab bans use of 10 insecticides</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/punjab-bans-use-of-10-insecticides/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Maximum Residue Limit (MRL)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>Amid reports that several samples of basmati rice contained the residue of certain pesticides above the maximum residue level (MRL), the Punjab government has decided to ban the use of 10 formulations.</p>
<h4>Which are the chemicals banned?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The State government believed that the sale, stock distribution, and use of Acephate, Buprofezin, Chloropyriphos, Methamidophos, Propiconazole, Thiamethoxam, Profenofos, Isoprothiolane, Carbendazim, and Tricyclazole was not in the interest of basmati rice growers.</li>
<li>It is said that there is a risk of breaching the MRL fixed by the competent authority for basmati rice.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the Maximum Residue Limit (MRL)?</h4>
<ul>
<li>MRL is the highest level of pesticide residue that is legally tolerated in or on food or feed when pesticides are applied correctly in accordance with Good Agricultural Practice promulgated by Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO).</li>
<li>The MRL is usually determined by repeated (on the order of 10) field trials at an appropriate pre-harvest interval or withholding period has elapsed.</li>
<li>For many pesticides, this is set at the Limit of determination (LOD) – since only major pesticides have been evaluated and understanding of acceptable daily intake (ADI) is incomplete.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/punjab-bans-use-of-10-insecticides/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was Kakasaheb Gadgil?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-kakasaheb-gadgil/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Kakasaheb Gadgil</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-621721" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 290px) 100vw, 290px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gadgil-290x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gadgil-290x300.jpg 290w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/gadgil.jpg 550w" width="290"/></p>
<p>The Gadgil Wada of Pune was recently lighted into tricolour for the 75th anniversary of Independence.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>Gadgil Wada was where plans for the reconstitution of the socialist Rashtra Seva Dal took place in early 1940s, with socialists like S.M. Joshi, N.G. Gore, Shirubhau Limaye and Kakasaheb in the lead.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4>Kakasaheb Gadgil</h4>
<ul>
<li>Gadgil was an Indian freedom fighter and politician from Maharashtra, India.</li>
<li>He was also a writer. He wrote in both Marathi and English.</li>
<li>Gadgil graduated from Fergusson College in Pune in 1918, and obtained a degree in Law in 1920.</li>
<li>In India’s pre-independence days, freedom fighters Lokmanya Tilak, Mahatma Gandhi, Jawaharlal Nehru, and Vallabhbhai Patel influenced Gadgil.</li>
<li>He joined the Indian National Congress in 1920, immediately after obtaining his law degree and started his active participation in the national freedom movement.</li>
<li>He suffered imprisonment from the ruling British government eight times for the participation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Notable work during freedom struggle</h4>
<ul>
<li>In India’s pre-independence days, Gadgil served as the secretary of Poona District Congress Committee (1921–25), the president of Maharashtra Pradesh Congress Committee (1937–45).</li>
<li>He was elected to the central Legislative Assembly in 1934.</li>
<li>Gadgil was a pioneer in social reform movements in Maharashtra in the 1930s.</li>
<li>During the Civil Disobedience Movement, which began in 1930, Gadgil was listed as a leader for the Maharashtra Civil Disobedience Committee and the Pune War Council.</li>
<li>He was associated with several public associations and institutions, including Sarvajanik Sabha, Pune; Young Men’s Association, Pune; Maharashtra Youth League, Bombay; Pune Central Cooperative Bank; and Pune Municipality.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Service after India’s independence</h4>
<ul>
<li>Between 1947 and 1952 Gadgil served as a minister in the first central cabinet of independent India.</li>
<li>He held the portfolios of Public Works, and Mines and Power.</li>
<li>In his first year in the central Cabinet, he initiated the project of building a military-caliber road from Pathankot to Srinagar via Jammu in Kashmir as a part of India’s activities in the 1947 Indo-Pakistan War.</li>
<li>As a cabinet minister, he also initiated the important development projects pertaining to Bhakra, Koyna, and Hirakund dams.</li>
<li>He was a member of the Congress Working Committee from 1952 to 1955.</li>
<li>His son Vitthalrao Gadgil was a veteran congressman and MP from Pune Lok Sabha constituency, and his grandson Anant Gadgil is currently spokesman for Maharashtra Pradesh Congress Committee.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Authorship</h4>
<ul>
<li>Gadgil wrote several books and articles on politics, economics, law, and history.</li>
<li>The following are some of Gadgil’s books:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Pathik (autobiography)</li>
<li>Rajya Shastra Wichar</li>
<li>Shubha Shastra</li>
<li>Waktrutwa Shastra</li>
<li>Gyanbache Arthashastra</li>
<li>Government from Inside</li>
<li>Shikhancha Itihaas (history of Sikhs)</li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-kakasaheb-gadgil/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Panel moots district-level survey to bring more children into adoption ambit</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/panel-moots-district-level-survey-to-bring-more-children-into-adoption-ambit/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CARA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Child Adoption</p></div></div><p>A report recently tabled on “Review of Guardianship and Adoption Laws” in Parliament has stated that- India despite a country with millions of orphans, there are only 2,430 children available for adoption.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There are many enthusiastic parents who are ready to adopt children.</li>
<li>To address this paradox, a Parliamentary panel has recommended district-level surveys to proactively identify orphaned and abandoned children.</li>
<li>According to the report, there were 27,939 prospective parents registered with the Child Adoption Resource Authority (CARA) as on December 2021, up from nearly 18,000 in 2017.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is CARA?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Central Adoption Resource Authority (CARA) is an autonomous and statutory body of the Ministry of Women and Child Development. It was set up in 1990.</li>
<li>It functions as the nodal body for the adoption of Indian children and is mandated to monitor and regulate in-country and inter-country adoptions.</li>
<li>CARA is designated as the Central Authority to deal with inter-country adoptions in accordance with the provisions of the 1993 Hague Convention on Inter-country Adoption, ratified India in 2003.</li>
<li>It primarily deals with the adoption of orphaned, abandoned and surrendered children through its associated and recognized adoption agencies.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Adoption Process</h4>
<ul>
<li>The eligibility of prospective adoptive parents living in India, duly registered on the <strong>Child Adoption Resource Information and Guidance System (CARINGS)</strong>, irrespective of marital status and religion, is Procedure for adoption adjudged by<strong> specialised adoption agencies</strong> preparing home study reports.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>The specialized adoption agency then secures court orders approving the adoption.</li>
<li>All <strong>non-resident persons</strong> approach authorized adoption agencies in their foreign country of residence for registration under CARINGS.</li>
<li>Their eligibility is adjudged by authorised foreign adoption agencies through home study reports.</li>
<li>CARA then issues a pre-adoption ‘no objection’ certificate for foster care, followed by a court adoption order.</li>
<li>A final <strong>‘no objection’ certificate from CARA</strong> or a conformity certificate under the adoption convention is mandatory for a passport and visa to leave India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What else regulates child adoption?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) Act, 2015</u></strong> permits the <strong><u>adoption of same-sex children</u></strong>, allowing biological or adopted parents to adopt a child of the same gender.</li>
<li>A single or divorced person can adopt under the JJ Act, but a single male cannot adopt a girl child.</li>
<li>According the <strong><u>Hindu Adoption and Maintenance Act, 1956 (HAMA)</u></strong>, a Hindu parent or guardian can place a child for adoption with another Hindu parent under the Act.</li>
<li>A prospective parent can also adopt a male child if he has no other male children or grandchildren, or a female child if he has no other female children or grandchildren.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with child adoption in India</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Parent-centrism:</strong> The current adoption approach is very parent-centred, but parents must make it child-centred.</li>
<li><strong>Age of child:</strong> Most Indian parents also want a child between the ages of zero and two, believing that this is when the parent-child bond is formed.</li>
<li><strong>Institutional issues:</strong> Because the ratio of abandoned children to children in institutionalised care is lopsided, there are not enough children available for adoption.</li>
<li><strong>Lineage discrimination:</strong> Most Indians have a distorted view of adoption because they want their genes, blood, and lineage to be passed down to their children.</li>
<li><strong>Red-tapism:</strong> Child adoption is also not so easy task after the Juvenile Justice Rules of 2016 and the Adoption Regulations of 2017 were launched.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/panel-moots-district-level-survey-to-bring-more-children-into-adoption-ambit/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Have coastal ecosystem norms been violated?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/have-coastal-ecosystem-norms-been-violated/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CAG Audit, CRZ norms</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>This week, the Comptroller and Auditor General (CAG) of India tabled a report in Parliament on whether steps taken by the Union Environment Ministry to conserve India’s coastal ecosystems have been successful.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The CAG frequently undertakes ‘performance audits’ of government programmes and ministries.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Centre’s obligations on conserving the coastline</h4>
<ul>
<li>The government has issued notifications under the <strong><u>Environment Protection Act, 1986</u></strong>, to regulate activities along India’s coasts particularly regarding construction.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Coastal Regulation Zone Notification (CRZ), 2019</u></strong> implemented by the Ministry, <strong><u>classifies the coastal area into different zones</u></strong> to manage infrastructure activities and regulate them.</li>
</ul>
<p>The three institutions responsible for the implementation of the CRZ are:</p>
<ol>
<li>National Coastal Zone Management Authority (NCZMA) at the <strong><u>Centre</u></strong>,</li>
<li>State/Union Territory Coastal Zone Management Authorities (SCZMAs/UTCZMAs) in every <strong><u>coastal State and Union Territory</u></strong></li>
<li>District Level Committees (DLCs) in <strong><u>every district</u></strong> that has a coastal stretch and where the CRZ notification is applicable</li>
</ol>
<h4>Functions under CRZ rules</h4>
<ul>
<li>These bodies examine if CRZ clearances granted by the government are as per procedure, if project developers are once given the go-ahead are complying with conditions and if the project development objectives under the Integrated Coastal Zone Management Programme (ICZMP) are successful.</li>
<li>They also evaluate the measures taken up by the government towards achieving the targets under Sustainable Development Goals.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="1kBr0inoKN"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-crz-norms/">What are CRZ norms?</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="1kBr0inoKN" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-crz-norms/embed/#?secret=2v1N5NP6nJ#?secret=1kBr0inoKN" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“What are CRZ norms?” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<h4>Why did the CAG undertake this audit?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The CAG has a constitutional mandate to investigate and report on publicly funded programmes.</li>
<li>The CAG conducted “pre-audit studies” and found that there were large-scale CRZ violations in the coastal stretches.</li>
<li>Incidences of illegal construction activities (reducing coastal space) and effluent discharges from local bodies, industries and aquaculture farms had been reported by the media and this prompted it to undertake a detailed investigation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What did the recent audit find?</h4>
<p>The audit pointed out <strong><u>various categories of violations</u></strong>.</p>
<ul>
<li>There were instances of the Expert Appraisal Committees —who evaluate the feasibility of an infrastructure project and its environmental consequences — not being present during project deliberations.</li>
<li>There were also instances of the members of the EAC being fewer than half of the total strength during the deliberations.</li>
<li>The SCZMA had <strong><u>not been reconstituted</u></strong> in Karnataka and there was delayed reconstitution in the States of Goa, Odisha and West Bengal.</li>
<li>The DLCs of Tamil Nadu lacked participation from local traditional communities. In Andhra Pradesh, DLCs were not even established.</li>
<li>There were instances of <strong><u>projects being approved despite inadequacies</u></strong> in the Environment Impact Assessment (EIA) reports.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What problems did the CAG find in the States?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of strategy:</strong> Tamil Nadu didn’t have a strategy in place to conserve the Gulf of Mannar Islands.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of monitoring:</strong> In Goa, there was no system for monitoring coral reefs and no management plans to conserve turtle nesting sites.</li>
<li><strong>No scientific oversight:</strong> In Gujarat, instruments procured to study the physiochemical parameters of soil and water of the inertial area of the Gulf of Kutch weren’t used.</li>
<li><strong>Monitoring issues:</strong> Sea patrolling in Gahirmatha Sanctuary, in Kendrapara, Odisha did not happen.</li>
<li><strong>No information in public domain:</strong> There was no website to disseminate the information related to the NCZMA, the CAG found, which is a clear violation of the mandated requirements of the Authority.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What lies ahead?</h4>
<ul>
<li>These reports are placed before the Standing Committees of Parliament, which select those findings and recommendations that they judge to be the most critical to public interest and arrange hearings on them.</li>
<li>In this case, the Environment Ministry is expected to explain omissions pointed out by the CAG and make amends.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Comptroller and Auditor General (CAG) of India</h4>
<ul>
<li>The CAG is the Constitutional Authority, established under Article 148 of the Constitution of India.</li>
<li>They are empowered to Audit all receipts and expenditure of the GoI and the State Governments, including those of autonomous bodies and corporations substantially financed by the Government.</li>
<li>The CAG is also the statutory auditor of Government-owned corporations.</li>
<li>It conducts supplementary audit of government companies in which the Government has an equity share of at least 51 per cent or subsidiary companies of existing government companies.</li>
<li>The reports of the CAG are laid before the Parliament/Legislatures and are being taken up for discussion by the Public Accounts Committees (PACs) and Committees on Public Undertakings (COPUs).</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/have-coastal-ecosystem-norms-been-violated/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Five years after SC verdict, talaq petitioners living as ‘half-divorcees’</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/five-years-after-sc-verdict-talaq-petitioners-living-as-half-divorcees/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>Five years after the Supreme Court’s five-judge Bench under then CJI J.S. Khehar invalidated instant triple talaq in August 2017, the women petitioners continue to live a life of half-divorcees.</p>
<h4>What is triple talaq?</h4>
<ul>
<li>‘Triple Talaq’ is a procedure of divorce under the Sharia Law which is a body of the Islamic law.</li>
<li>Under this, a husband can divorce his wife by pronouncing ‘Talaq’ thrice.</li>
<li>The Supreme Court invalidated instant triple talaq in the Shayara Bano versus the Union of India case while refraining from commenting on the state of their marriages directly.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What was the issue all about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The case dates back to 2016 when the Supreme Court had sought assistance from the then Attorney General Mukul Rohatgi on pleas challenging the <strong><u>constitutional validity of “triple talaq”.</u></strong></li>
<li>The hearing also included cases of <strong>“nikah halala” </strong>and<strong> “polygamy”</strong>, to assess whether Muslim women face gender discrimination in cases of divorce.</li>
<li>The issue gained political momentum on March 2017 when the Personal Law Board (AIMPLB) told the Supreme Court that <strong>the issue of triple talaq falls outside the judiciary’s realm.</strong></li>
<li>However, on August 22, the Supreme Court set aside the decade-old practice of instant triple talaq saying it was<strong> <u>violative of Article 14 and 21 of the Indian Constitution</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why was triple talaq abolished?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In spite of protests by Muslim women and activists world-wide the procedure was <strong><u>most prevalent throughout the country.</u></strong></li>
<li>There are several instances where ‘triple talaq’ has enabled husbands to <strong><u>divorce arbitrarily, devoid of any substantiation.</u></strong></li>
<li>Oral talaq or ‘triple talaq’ <strong><u>delivered through social media platforms</u></strong> like Skype, text messages, email and WhatsApp have become an increasing cause of worry for the community.</li>
<li>The ‘triple talaq’ has been <strong><u>abolished in 21 countries including Pakistan</u></strong>, but is still prevalent in India.</li>
<li>The Centre reasons that these practices are <strong><u>against constitutional principles</u></strong> such as gender equality, secularism, international laws etc.</li>
<li>When these practices are <strong><u>banned in Islamic theocratic countries</u></strong>, the practices could have absolutely no base in religion and are only prevalent to permit the dominance of men over women.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news now?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Half-divorce:</strong> Technically still married, practically divorced, they enjoy no conjugal rights nor receive any regular maintenance from the estranged husbands.</li>
<li><strong>Cannot remarry:</strong> Practically abandoned, the women cannot remarry in the absence of a legally valid divorce.</li>
<li><strong>No legal action:</strong> After the verdict, none of the men were visited by law enforcement bodies and told to take back their wives.</li>
<li><strong>No legal implementation:</strong> Further, no arrests could be made for giving instant triple as the Muslim Women (Protection of Rights on Marriage) Act, 2019 came into force long after the pronouncement of instant talaq.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/five-years-after-sc-verdict-talaq-petitioners-living-as-half-divorcees/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Controversial visit of a Chinese vessel to Hambantota</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/controversial-visit-of-a-chinese-vessel-to-hambantota/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Chinese takeover of Hambantota port</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-621713" height="209" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 371px) 100vw, 371px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/yang-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/yang-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/yang.jpg 600w" width="371"/></p>
<p>Much recently, Sri Lanka approved the arrival of a Chinese satellite-tracking vessel to its southern Chinese-funded Hambantota port.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has raised concerns over the ship’s visit.</li>
<li>Caught in a delicate diplomatic and geopolitical spot, <strong><u>Colombo gave its nod despites India’s requests to deny the permission.</u></strong></li>
<li>It is asserted that <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-the-sri-lankan-default/">bankrupt Sri Lanka</a> succumbed to Chinese pressure after <strong><u>initially refusing</u></strong> the ship to dock.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Yuan Wang 5: The vessel</h4>
<ul>
<li>Yuan Wang 5 was described by the Sri Lankan government as a “scientific research ship”.</li>
<li>The BRISL (Belt &amp; Road Initiative Sri Lanka), a Colombo-based organisation studying China’s ambitious connectivity project, was the first to draw attention to the visit.</li>
<li>It said that the Yuan Wang 5 will conduct “satellite control and research tracking in the northwestern part of the Indian Ocean Region”.</li>
<li>Vessels of the Yuan Wang class are said to be used for tracking and supporting satellite as well as intercontinental ballistic missiles by the People’s Liberation Army Strategic Support Force.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s reaction</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has expressed its concern over the Chinese vessel visit.</li>
<li>It is carefully monitoring any development having a bearing on its security and economic interests.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How have other countries reacted?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The developments showed that Colombo was caught between the U.S. and India on the one hand, and China on the other.</li>
<li>That too at a time when the Sri Lankan government is counting on all their support as the island nation, hit by a devastating economic crisis, embarks on debt restructuring ahead of a promised IMF package.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did China respond?</h4>
<ul>
<li>China reacted strongly at Sri Lanka, following concerns voiced by India.</li>
<li>It clarified that Sri Lanka is a transportation hub in the Indian Ocean.</li>
<li>Scientific research vessels from various countries including China have made port calls in Sri Lanka for replenishment.</li>
<li>Secondly, it invoked Sri Lanka’s sovereignty and the right to develop relations with other countries based on its development interests.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Sri Lanka’s stand?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is reported that the US and Indian envoys were asked to provide concrete reasons for their objections.</li>
<li>Not satisfied with the reasons being sufficient to refuse entry to the Chinese vessel, SL decided to inform the Chinese embassy in Colombo to inform the ship to continue its journey to Hambantota.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/controversial-visit-of-a-chinese-vessel-to-hambantota/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Inclusive growth and social justice</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/inclusive-growth-and-social-justice/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Inclusive growth, Social justice</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Key findings of the World Inequality Report 2022 related to India: National Income: In India, the top 10% and top 1% hold respectively 57% and 22% of total national income.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is inclusive growth?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) defines Inclusive growth as the economic growth that is distributed fairly across society and creates opportunities for all. It refers to ‘broad-based’, ‘shared’, and ‘pro-poor growth’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is social justice?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Social justice is the view that everyone deserves equal economic, political and social rights and opportunities. Social workers aim to open the doors of access and opportunity for everyone, particularly those in greatest need.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Meaning of Inclusiveness</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Inclusiveness is a concept that encompasses equity, equality of opportunity, and protection in market and employment transitions and is, therefore, an essential ingredient of any successful growth strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Need of inclusive growth </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Complete development</strong>: India is the 7th largest by area and 2nd by population and 12th largest economy at market exchange rate. Yet, India is away from the development<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Income inequality</strong>: Low agriculture growth, low quality employment growth, low human development, rural-urban divides, gender and social inequalities, and regional disparities etc. are the problems for the nation.</li>
<li><strong>Human development: </strong>Reducing poverty and inequality and increasing economic growth are the main aim of the country through inclusive growth<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Need of social justice </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Equality</strong>: We should shift from equality of outcomes to equality of opportunities.</li>
<li><strong>Peace and Order</strong>: If the majority disregards smaller sections in the community, it drives them to rebellion.</li>
<li><strong>Dignity</strong>: To ensure life to be meaningful and liveable with human dignity.</li>
<li><strong>Mitigate Sufferings: </strong>It is a dynamic device to mitigate the sufferings of the poor, weak Dalits, tribal and deprived sections of the society.</li>
<li><strong>Human Resources</strong>: It will help in the conservation of human resource by provision of health and education facilities.</li>
<li><strong>Freedom to form political</strong>, economic or religious institutions: It will help to eradicate the challenges of caste system, untouchability and other discrimination in the society.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges before inclusive growth and social justice </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Wage Gap: </strong>When it comes to wages in the workplace, there is a noticeable differentiation between men and women. According to the American Association of University Women (AAUW), in 2018, the gender pay gap from men and women for the same job was 82 percent. Stated simply, women make 82 percent of what men make doing the same work. This can be further broken down into a pay gap for minority men and women.</li>
<li><strong>LGBTQ Oppression: </strong>When it comes to oppression and human rights, individuals of the Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transsexual and Queer (LGBTQ) community face several forms of social injustice and oppression. For example, same sex marriages are outlawed in some states and countries. Additionally, transsexual students often face discrimination and bullying within school settings.</li>
<li><strong>Education System: </strong>Globally, steps are being made to close the education gap between male and female students. However, there are still several areas around the world where girls may never set foot into a classroom at all. UNESCO notes that more than nine million girls never go to school, compared to only six million boys in areas of Africa.</li>
<li><strong>Child Welfare: </strong>Social workers and human rights activists are working tirelessly to combat issues relating to children and their welfare. Despite their efforts, there are still several problems children face that are harmful to their health and mental wellbeing.</li>
<li><strong>Forced Child Labour</strong>: Laws are in place around the world to ensure a safe work environment for children. These laws were drafted from historically harsh and dangerous working conditions for children. While many would like to believe that child labour is a thing of the past, it persists in some areas around the globe.</li>
<li><strong>Child Abuse and Neglect</strong>: Thousands of children globally are being neglected. They’re also being physically, sexually and emotionally abused. The World Health Organization (WHO) reports that as many as a quarter of adults have been abused as children. This abuse has both social and economic impacts that include mental health problems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Government measures to address this challenge </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>SETU(Self Employment and Talent Utilization)</li>
<li>Skill India</li>
<li>Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA)</li>
<li>Pradhan Mantri Jan Dhan Yojana</li>
<li>MUDRA (Micro Units Development and Refinance Agency)Bank</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Equality of opportunity is the core of inclusive growth, and the inclusive growth emphasises to create employment and other development opportunities through rapid and sustained economic growth, and to promote social justice and the equality of sharing of growth results by reducing and eliminating inequality of opportunity.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p>Explain the term inclusive growth in brief. How we can achieve social justice through inclusive growth?</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/inclusive-growth-and-social-justice/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Importance of India EU ties</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/importance-of-india-eu-ties/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Green strategic partnership</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>EU–India Cooperation Agreement, Strategic Partnership</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While India celebrates its 75th year of Independence, it also <strong>celebrates 60 years</strong> of diplomatic relations with the European Union (EU).</li>
<li>A cooperation agreement signed in 1994 took the bilateral relationship beyond trade and economic cooperation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Definition </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Relations between the European Union and the Republic of India are currently defined by <strong>the 1994 EU–India Cooperation Agreement.</strong> The EU is a significant trade partner for India and the two sides have been attempting to negotiate <strong>a free trade</strong> deal since 2007.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Common roadmap and shared vision</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The road map highlights engagement across five domains: foreign policy and security cooperation; trade and economy; sustainable modernisation partnership; global governance; and people-to-people relations.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-621903" height="322" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 644px) 100vw, 644px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/euind-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/euind-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/euind-1024x512.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/euind-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/euind.jpg 1200w" width="644"/></p>
<h4><strong>Brief history </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India-EU relations date to the early 1960s, with India being amongst the first countries to establish diplomatic relations with the European Economic Community.</li>
<li>At the 5th India-EU Summit at The Hague in 2004, the relationship was upgraded to a <strong>‘Strategic Partnership’.</strong></li>
<li>The two sides adopted <strong>a Joint Action Plan</strong> in 2005 (which was reviewed in 2008) that provided for strengthening dialogue and consultation mechanisms in the political and economic spheres, enhancing trade and investment, and bringing peoples and cultures together.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is strategic partnership?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A ‘strategic partnership’, as the term suggests, involves a shared understanding between the two or more states involved on the nature of threats in the environment and the place of their collective power in helping mitigate the threats.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why they are important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As the world’s two largest democracies, the EU and India share a commitment to protecting and promoting human rights, a rules-based global order, effective multilateralism, sustainable development and open trade.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Significance </strong></h4>
<p>[A] <strong>Political Partnership</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Joint Political Statement signed in 1993, opened the way for annual ministerial meetings and a broad political dialogue.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Cooperation Agreement signed in 1994</u></strong> took the bilateral relationship beyond trade and economic cooperation.</li>
<li>A multi-tiered institutional architecture of cooperation has since been created, presided over by the <strong><u>India-EU Summit since 2000</u></strong><strong>.</strong></li>
<li>Today EU stands as a major reference for India’s legislative process in the field of <strong><u>Data security and privacy.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p>[B] <strong>Economic Ties</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Bilateral trade</strong>: The EU is India’s largest trading partner, while India is the EU’s 9<sup>th</sup> largest trading partner. It is the second-largest destination for Indian exports after the United States.</li>
<li><strong>Investment</strong>: The EU’s share in foreign investment inflows to India has more than doubled from 8% to 18% in the last decade. This makes the EU an important foreign investor in India.</li>
<li><strong>Preferential treatment</strong>: India is the benefactor of the unilateral preferential tariffs under the EU Generalised Scheme of Preferences (GSP).</li>
<li><strong>Energy</strong>: Both sides have finalised civil nuclear cooperation agreement after 13 years of negotiations called as the European Atomic Energy Community (EURATOM). It involves collaboration in the civil nuclear energy sector.</li>
<li><strong>Development cooperation:</strong><strong> </strong>Over €150 million worth of projects by EU are currently ongoing in India. European Investment Bank (EIB) is providing loans for Lucknow, Bangalore, and Pune Metro Projects.</li>
</ul>
<p>[C] <strong>Defence &amp; Security</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>EU and India have instituted several mechanisms for greater cooperation on pressing security challenges like <strong><u>counterterrorism, maritime security, and nuclear non-proliferation</u></strong><strong>.</strong></li>
<li>Information Fusion Centre – Indian Ocean Region in New Delhi (IFC-IOR) has recently been linked-up with the Maritime Security Centre – Horn of Africa (MSC-HOA) established by the EU Naval Force (NAVFOR).</li>
</ul>
<p>[D] <strong>Climate Change</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>EU and India also underline their highest political commitment to the<strong> <u>effective implementation of the Paris Agreement</u> </strong>and the UNFCCC despite US withdrawing from the same.</li>
<li><strong><u>India-EU Clean Energy and Climate Partnership</u></strong> was agreed at the 2016 Summit – to promote access to and disseminate clean energy and climate friendly technologies and encourage R&amp;D.</li>
<li><strong><u>Energy cooperation</u></strong> is now ongoing on a broad range of energy issues, like smart grids, energy efficiency, offshore wind and solar infrastructure, and research and innovation.</li>
<li>EU and India also cooperate closely on the <strong><u>Clean Ganga initiative</u></strong> and deal with other water-related challenges in coordinated manner.</li>
</ul>
<p>[E] <strong>Research and Development</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India-EU Science &amp; Technology Steering Committee meets annually to review scientific cooperation.</li>
<li>Both have official mechanisms in fields such as Digital Communications, 5G technology, Biotechnology, artificial intelligence etc.</li>
<li>ISRO has a long-standing cooperation with the European Union, since 1970s. It has contributed towards the <strong><u>EU’s satellite navigation system Galileo</u></strong><strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Future scope </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Trade figures and Investments</strong>: Bilateral trade between the two surpassed $116 billion in 2021-22. The EU is India’s second largest trading partner after the U.S., and the second largest destination for Indian exports.</li>
<li><strong>Job creation</strong>: There are 6,000 European companies in the country that directly and indirectly create 6.7 million jobs.</li>
<li><strong>Green strategic partnership:</strong> between India and Denmark aims to address climate change, biodiversity loss and pollution, and the India-Nordic Summit focused on green technologies and industry transformation that are vital for sustainable and inclusive growth.</li>
<li><strong>Energy security</strong>: Energy serves as an important aspect of the relationship between India and the EU. Given the impacts of climate change, this aspect has become extremely crucial today. Both entities have been pursuing cooperation for the joint development of clean energy.</li>
<li><strong>Political cooperation</strong>: India and the EU may benefit from increasing cooperation in the resolution of issues such as terrorism and radicalization, cyber-security, coordinating on certain key and relevant aspects of foreign policy, and other humanitarian issues.</li>
<li><strong>International support</strong>: It is crucial that Europe recognize India as a partner for peace that is committed to human rights, both regionally and internationally.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges before them </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Deadlock over BTIA</strong>: The negotiations for a Broad-based Bilateral Trade and Investment Agreement (BTIA) were held between 2007 to 2013 but have remained dormant/suspended since then.</li>
<li><strong>Export hurdles</strong>: Indian demands for ‘Data secure’ status (important for India’s IT sector) to ease norms on temporary movement of skilled workers, relaxation of Sanitary and Phytosanitary (SPS), etc. stands largely ignored.</li>
<li><strong>Trade imbalance</strong>: This heavily leans towards China. India accounts for only 1.9% of EU total trade in goods in 2019, well behind China (13.8%).</li>
<li><strong>Brexit altercations</strong>: In the longer term of balancing of global powers, a smaller Europe without the key military and economic force UK, is much weaker in the wake of an ambitious China and an increasingly protectionist US.</li>
<li><strong>EU primarily remains a trade bloc:</strong> This has resulted in a lack of substantive agreements on matters such as regional security and connectivity.</li>
<li><strong>Undue references to sovereign concerns</strong>: The European Parliament was critical of both the Indian government’s decision to scrap Jammu and Kashmir’s special status in 2019 and the Citizenship (Amendment) Act.</li>
<li><strong>China’s influence</strong>: EU’s affinity lies with China. This is because of its high dependence on the Chinese market. It is a major partner in China’s Belt and Road Initiative (BRI).</li>
<li><strong>Ukrainian war</strong>: EAM S. Jaishankar’s witty reply about EU’s oil import from Russia has not been welcomed across the EU. It still expects India to criticize Russia.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Way forward </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>A close bilateral relation between India and the EU has far-reaching economic, political and strategic implications on the crisis-driven international order.</li>
<li>Both sides should realise this potential and must further the growth of the bilateral ties with a strong political will.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p>What do you understand by the term strategic partnership? India and EU are celebrating 60 years of diplomatic relations trace their journey with significance and challenges in their ties.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/importance-of-india-eu-ties/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Nehru’s luminous legacy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nehrus-luminous-legacy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Public sector enterprise</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Challenges of public sector undertakings</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-621908" height="300" sizes="(max-width: 209px) 100vw, 209px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Jnehru-209x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Jnehru-209x300.jpg 209w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Jnehru-712x1024.jpg 712w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Jnehru-768x1104.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Jnehru-1069x1536.jpg 1069w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Jnehru-626x900.jpg 626w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Jnehru-1200x1725.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/Jnehru.jpg 1365w" width="209"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Seventy-five years ago, India’s first Prime Minister Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru made these remarks in his <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g0HvWuCiPZ4" rel="noopener" target="_blank">stirring speech on India attaining freedom at midnight</a>: “The achievement we celebrate today is but a step, an opening of opportunity, to the greater triumphs and achievements that await us. Are we brave enough and wise enough to grasp this opportunity and accept the challenge of the future?”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Nehru’s vision for India </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Nehru’s vision of India was anchored in a set of ideas such as democracy, secularism, inclusive economic growth, free press and non-alignment in international affairs and also in institutions that would lay the foundation for India’s future growth.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Leadership of Nehru after independence </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In 1947, Nehru, as Prime Minister, inherited an India that was politically shattered, socially divided and emotionally devastated. Yet, with restraint and self-confidence, he steered the country through those turbulent times and laid out the vision of a modern, progressive nation that quietly earned the respect of the global community.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Temple of modern India </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Bhakra-Nangal Dam: </strong>The Bhakra-Nangal Dam project is a series of multi-purpose dams that were among the earliest river valley developments schemes undertaken by the government of India after independence. The project, though, had been conceived long before independence.</li>
<li><strong>Bhilai Steel Plant</strong>: Bhilai, located in Chhattisgarh, was home to massive iron-ore deposits at Dalli Rajhara. Taking this into consideration, the government of India and the USSR entered into an agreement which was signed on March 2nd 1955, at New Delhi.</li>
<li><strong>Bhabha Atomic Research Centre</strong>: The Atomic Energy Establishment, Trombay (AEET), was started by the government of India on January 3rd 1954 with the intention of consolidating all research and development activities for nuclear reactors and technology under the Atomic Energy Commission.</li>
<li><strong>Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR)</strong>: to support indigenous scientists like Boshi Sen, who is credited with producing hybrid maize and irradiated wheat mutant.</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-621909" height="168" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/psu.jpeg" width="300"/></p>
<h4><strong>Relevance of these institutions </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Economic Development</strong>:Economic development mainly depends upon industrial development. Heavy &amp; basic industries like iron &amp; steel, shipping, mining, etc. are required for supplying raw materials to small industries.</li>
<li><strong>Regional Development</strong>:Private sector usually neglect backward area. But public sector organizations set up their units in economically backward areas. By this public sector removes regional imbalance &amp; brings regional development.</li>
<li><strong>Employment</strong>:Various public sectors operating in India needs lot of manpower &amp; this provide employment to unlimited individuals according to their education, experience &amp; abilities.</li>
<li><strong>Service Motive</strong>: Public sector organizations are working with the only motive of providing public utility services to society at large irrespective of profit.</li>
<li><strong>Sound Infrastructure</strong>:Rapid industrial growth in a country needs sound infrastructure. Infrastructural industries require huge capital for construction of Roads, Railways, Electricity &amp; many such industries. Private sector is unable to have such huge capital &amp; that also without any high return but public sector can easily afford to provide all infrastructural facilities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Some challenges they face today </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inefficient Management: </strong>It has been found that these enterprises are managed by public savants. They are not professionally qualified nor experts in the management of industrial enterprises.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of Efficiency: </strong>They are not run on commercial principles. Their main motto is social welfare, not profit earning.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of Innovations</strong>: Innovations are essential for economic development. Public enterprise lacks it due to monopoly or lack of competition. The private sector is always busy with innovating new techniques, new production methods, etc. For the purpose of cost reduction and profit maximization.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Some suggestions to address the challenges </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sound business principles</strong>: The enterprise should be run on sound business principles. There should be focus on improving efficiency in all functional areas. Policies, systems and procedures should be modified with the aim of making the enterprise flexible, efficient and profitable.</li>
<li><strong>Autonomy</strong>: Public enterprises should have considerable autonomy in their functioning. Authority should be delegated and they should have the freedom to take decisions. Autonomy would ensure that decisions are taken at the right time and growth opportunities utilized in the best possible manner.</li>
<li><strong>Freedom from political interference</strong>: Many public enterprises are considered to be the kingdoms of politicians. They are run to suit the needs and requirements of the ruling party.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Today, opinions are divided about the iconic leader. While Nehru always had his critiques even back in the day, a significant section of the masses despise the dynasty politics of the Congress that ensued after his passing in 1964.</li>
<li>However, his contributions to India’s freedom, and as a Prime Minister to his country are acknowledged by people both within and outside India. His shortcomings do not take away from the legacy he cemented as a propagator for freedom, and as the free nation’s first Prime Minister.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p>Assess the Nehruvian legacy of public sector. Do you think they are still relevant today? While discussing challenges they face what suggestion will you give to improve their performance.</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nehrus-luminous-legacy/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>