<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 17:19:05 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>What is National List of Essential Medicines (NLEM)?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-national-list-of-essential-medicines-nlem/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Essential Medicines</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-635839" height="216" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 418px) 100vw, 418px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nlem-300x155.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nlem-300x155.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nlem.jpg 613w" width="418"/></p>
<p>The latest National List of Essential Medicines (NLEM) released September 13, 2022 by the Union health ministry added 34 new medicines and dropped 26 old ones from the previous list.</p>
<h4>What is NLEM?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As per the World Health Organisation (WHO), Essential Medicines are those that satisfy the priority health care needs of the population.</li>
<li>Ministry of Health and Family Welfare hence prepared and released the first National List of Essential Medicines of India in 1996 consisting of 279 medicines.</li>
<li>The list is made with consideration to disease prevalence, efficacy, safety and comparative cost-effectiveness of the medicines.</li>
<li>Such medicines are intended to be available in adequate amounts, in appropriate dosage forms and strengths with assured quality.</li>
<li>They should be available in such a way that an individual or community can afford.</li>
</ul>
<h4>NLEM in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>Drugs listed under NLEM — also known as scheduled drugs — will be cheaper because the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-nppas-role-in-fixing-drug-prices/">National Pharmaceutical Pricing Authority (NPPA)</a> caps medicine prices and changes only based on wholesale price index-based inflation.</li>
<li>The list includes anti-infectives medicines to treat diabetes such as insulin — HIV, tuberculosis, cancer, contraceptives, hormonal medicines and anaesthetics.</li>
<li>They account for 17-18 per cent of the estimated Rs 1.6-trillion domestic pharmaceutical market.</li>
<li>Companies selling non-scheduled drugs can hike prices by up to 10 per cent every year.</li>
<li>Typically, once NLEM is released, the department of pharmaceuticals under the ministry of chemicals and fertilisers adds them in the Drug Price Control Order, after which NPPA fixes the price.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of EML</h4>
<ul>
<li>Drawing an essential medicines list (EML) is expected to result in better quality of medical care, better management of medicines and cost-effective use of health care resources.</li>
<li>This is especially important for a resource limited country like India.</li>
<li>The list of essential medicines is intended to have a positive impact on the availability and rational use of medicines.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="8eMB0tPNor"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-nppas-role-in-fixing-drug-prices/">What is the NPPA’s role in fixing drug prices?</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="8eMB0tPNor" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-nppas-role-in-fixing-drug-prices/embed/#?secret=vBnMpFr7Ot#?secret=8eMB0tPNor" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“What is the NPPA’s role in fixing drug prices?” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-national-list-of-essential-medicines-nlem/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-arattupuzha-velayudha-panicker/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="Arattupuzha" class="alignnone wp-image-635838" height="409" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 272px) 100vw, 272px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atrap-200x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atrap-200x300.jpg 200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atrap-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atrap.jpg 720w" width="272"/></p>
<p>A recently-released Malayalam film Pathonpatham Noottandu (‘Nineteenth Century’) is based on the life of Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker, a social reformer from the Ezhava community in Kerala who lived in the 19th century.</p>
<h4>Who was Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Born into a well-off family of merchants in Kerala’s Alappuzha district, Panicker was one of the most influential figures in the reformation movement in the state.</li>
<li>He challenged the domination of upper castes or ‘Savarnas’ and brought about changes in the lives of both men and women.</li>
<li>The social reform movement in Kerala in the 19th century led to the large-scale subversion of the existing caste hierarchy and social order in the state.</li>
<li>Panicker was murdered by a group of upper-caste men in 1874 at the age of 49. This makes him the ‘first martyr’ of the Kerala renaissance.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What was Panicker’s role in initiating social reforms?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Panicker is credited with building two temples dedicated to the Hindu god Shiva, in which members of all castes and religions were allowed entry.</li>
<li>One was built in his own village Arattupuzha in 1852, and one in Thanneermukkom in 1854, another village in the Alappuzha district.</li>
<li>Some of his most significant contributions were in protesting for the rights of women belonging to Kerala’s backward communities.</li>
<li>In 1858, he led the Achippudava Samaram strike at Kayamkulam in Alappuzha.</li>
<li>This strike aimed to earn women belonging to oppressed groups the right to wear a lower garment that extended beyond the knees.</li>
<li>In 1859, this was extended into the Ethappu Samaram, the struggle for the right to wear an upper body cloth by women belonging to backward castes.</li>
<li>In 1860, he led the Mukkuthi Samaram at Pandalam in the Pathanamthitta district, for the rights of lower-caste women to wear ‘mukkuthi’ or nose-ring, and other gold ornaments.</li>
<li>These struggles played an important role in challenging the social order and in raising the dignity of women belonging to the lower strata of society in public life.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Other work</h4>
<ul>
<li>Apart from issues related to women, Panicker also led the first-ever strike by agricultural labourers in Kerala, the Karshaka Thozhilali Samaram, which was successful.</li>
<li>He also established the first Kathakali Yogam for the Ezhava community in 1861, which led to a Kathakali performance by Ezhavas and other backward communities, another first for them.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this PYQ:</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Q. The Shri Narayan Dharma Paripalana Yogam (SNDP) Movement(1902-03) was related to which of the following community?</strong></p>
<p>a) Mopilla Community</p>
<p>b) South Indian Tea Planters</p>
<p>c) Ezhava Community in Kerala</p>
<p>d) North Eastern Tea Planters</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-arattupuzha-velayudha-panicker/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was activist-author Annabhau Sathe?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-activist-author-anna-bhau-sathe/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Annabhau Sathe</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="anna" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-635837" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 224px) 100vw, 224px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/anna-224x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/anna-224x300.jpg 224w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/anna.jpg 237w" width="224"/></p>
<p>Maharashtra’s Deputy Chief Minister and other leaders are in Moscow to unveil the statue of Lok Shahir (balladeer) Annabhau Sathe at the All-Russia State Library for Foreign Literature.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sathe’s work was immensely inspired by the Russian revolution and the Communist ideology.</li>
<li>He was a member of the Communist Party of India (CPI), and featured among the selected authors from India whose work was translated in Russian.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who was Anna bhau Sathe?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Tukaram Bhaurao Sathe, who later came to be known as Annabhau Sathe, was born in a Dalit family on August 1, 1920 in Maharashtra’s Wategaon village in Satara district.</li>
<li>In 1930, his family left the village and came to Mumbai. Here, he worked as a porter, a hawker and even a cotton mill helper.</li>
<li>In 1934, Mumbai witnessed a workers’ strike under the leadership of Lal Bawta Mill Workers Union in which he participated.</li>
<li>During his days at the Matunga Labour Camp, he got to know R B More, an associate of Dr Babasaheb Ambedkar in the famous ‘Chavdar Lake’ satyagraha at Mahad, and joined the labour study circle.</li>
<li>Being a Dalit, he was denied schooling in his village. It was during these study circles that he learned to read and write.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did Anna start writing songs, ballads and books?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sathe wrote his first poem on the menace of mosquitoes in the labour camp.</li>
<li>He formed Dalit Yuvak Sangh, a cultural group and started writing poems on workers’ protests, agitations.</li>
<li>The group used to perform in front of the mill gates.</li>
<li>Progressive Writers Association was formed at the national level at the same time with the likes of Premchand, Faiz Ahmad Faiz, Manto, Ismat Chugtai, Rahul Sankrutyayan, Mulkraj Anand as its members.</li>
<li>The group would translate the Russian work of Maxim Gorky, Anton Chekhov, Leo Tolstoy, Ivan Turgenev into Marathi, which Sathe got hooked on.</li>
<li>It not only had an ideological impact on him, but inspired him to write street plays, stories, novels etc. In 1939, he wrote his first ballad ‘Spanish Povada’.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How popular was his work?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sathe and his group travelled across Mumbai campaigning for workers’ rights.</li>
<li>Out of the 49 years that he lived, Sathe, who began writing only after the age of 20, churned out 32 novels, 13 collections of short stories, four plays, a travelogue and 11 <strong><u>povadas (ballads).</u></strong></li>
<li>Several of his works like ‘<strong><u>Aklechi Goshta</u></strong>,’ ‘<strong><u>Stalingradacha Povada</u></strong>,’ ‘<strong><u>Mazi Maina Gavavar Rahili</u></strong>,’ ‘<strong><u>Jag Badal Ghaluni Ghav’</u></strong> were popular across the state.</li>
<li>Almost six of his novels were turned into films and many translated into other languages, including Russian.</li>
<li>His ‘<strong><u>Bangalchi Hak’ </u></strong>(Bengal’s Call) on the Bengal famine was translated into Bengali and later presented at London’s Royal Theatre.</li>
<li>His literature depicted the caste and class reality of Indian society of that time.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Left leanings</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sathe’s work was influenced by Marxism, but at the same time he brought out the harsh realities of the caste system.</li>
<li>In 1943, he formed the Lal Bawta Kala Pathak.</li>
<li>The group toured across Maharashtra presenting programmes on caste atrocities, class conflict, and workers’ rights.</li>
<li>He dedicated his most famous novel Fakira to Dr Ambedkar.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What was his Russian connection?</h4>
<ul>
<li>He was once called the <strong><u>Maxim Gorky of Maharashtra</u></strong>.</li>
<li>He was immensely inspired by <strong><u>Gorky’s ‘The Mother’</u></strong> and the Russian revolution, which was reflected in his writings.</li>
<li>He travelled to Russia in 1961 along with a group of other Indians.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Is there a reason behind the statue being unveiled now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sathe belonged to the Matang community among Dalits.</li>
<li>With the Left failing to claim his artistic legacy, Sathe is now restricted as a symbol of a particular community.</li>
<li>The right wing is angling to claim the credit for making Sathe a global icon.</li>
<li>Installing Sathe’s oil painting at the Indian consulate at Moscow also shows that the central government is using this occasion to increase cultural dialogue between two countries.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-activist-author-anna-bhau-sathe/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How to make robust patent system for a number 1 knowledge economy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/patent-system/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>KAPILA scheme</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>IPR regime</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="patent system" class="alignnone wp-image-635778" height="410" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 547px) 100vw, 547px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-istock-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-istock-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-istock-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-istock-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-istock.jpg 1200w" width="547"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Increasing the efficiency of processing patent applications and wider academia-industry collaboration are crucial steps for patent system.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is patent system? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A patent system is a type of intellectual property that gives its owner the legal right to exclude others from making, using, or selling an invention for a limited period of time in exchange for publishing an enabling disclosure of the invention.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why are patents important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A patent is important because it can help safeguard our invention. It can protect any product, design or process that meets certain specifications according to its originality, practicality, suitability, and utility. In most cases, a patent can protect an invention for up to 20 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="patent system" class="alignnone wp-image-635779" height="309" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 464px) 100vw, 464px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/patent_0-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/patent_0-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/patent_0-1.jpg 724w" width="464"/>How to get patent? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To get a patent, technical information about the invention must be disclosed to the public in a patent application.</li>
<li>The patent owner may give permission to, or license, other parties to use the invention on mutually agreed terms.</li>
<li>The owner may also sell the right to the invention to someone else, who will then become the new owner of the patent.</li>
<li>Once a patent expires, the protection ends, and an invention enters the public domain; that is, anyone can commercially exploit the invention without infringing the patent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/diluting-of-patent-working-discloser-rule-and-its-implications-for-compulsory-license-regime/"><strong>Terms of Patent</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Patents may be granted for inventions in any field of technology, from an everyday kitchen utensil to a nanotechnology chip.</li>
<li>An invention can be a product – such as a chemical compound, or a process, for example – or a process for producing a specific chemical compound.</li>
<li>Patent protection is granted for a limited period, generally 20 years from the filing date of the application.</li>
<li>Patents are territorial rights. In general, the exclusive rights are only applicable in the country or region in which a patent has been filed and granted, in accordance with the law of that country or region.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="patent system" class="alignnone wp-image-635780" height="295" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-2.jpeg" width="496"/>How patents can support inventors and improve lives</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Recognize and reward</strong>: Patents recognize and reward inventors for their commercially-successful inventions. As such they serve as an incentive for inventors to invent. With a patent, an inventor or small business knows there is a good chance that they will get a return on the time, effort and money they invested in developing a technology. In sum, it means they can earn a living from their work.</li>
<li><strong>Economic opportunity</strong>: When a new technology comes onto the market, society as a whole stands to benefit – both directly, because it may enable us to do something that was previously not possible, and indirectly in terms of the economic opportunities (business development and employment) that can flow from it.</li>
<li><strong>Research and development (R&amp;D): </strong>The revenues generated from commercially successful patent-protected technologies make it possible to finance further technological research and development (R&amp;D), thereby improving the chances of even better technology becoming available in the future.</li>
<li><strong>Opportunities for business growth</strong>: A patent effectively turns an inventor’s know-how into a commercially tradeable asset, opening up opportunities for business growth and job creation through licensing and joint ventures, for example.</li>
<li><strong>Commercialization of a technology</strong>: Holding a patent also makes a small business more attractive to investors who play a key role in enabling the commercialization of a technology.</li>
<li><strong>Spark new ideas</strong>: The technical information and business intelligence generated by the patenting process can spark new ideas and promote new inventions from which we can all benefit and which may, in turn, qualify for patent protection.</li>
<li><strong>No freebies</strong>: A patent can help stop unscrupulous third parties from free riding on the efforts of the inventor.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is KAPILA Initiative?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Full form</strong>: KAPILA is an acronym for Kalam Program for IP (Intellectual Property) Literacy and Awareness.</li>
<li><strong>Guidelines for patent</strong> <strong>Filing: </strong>Under this campaign, students pursuing education in higher educational institutions will get information about the correct system of the application process for patenting their invention and they will be aware of their rights.</li>
<li><strong>Encouragement to students</strong>: The program will facilitate the colleges and institutions to encourage more and more students to file patents.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Thing to remember </strong></p>
<p>Remember one thing, ‘KAPILA’ Program is related to IP awareness. It sounds much like an animal husbandry related initiative.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Way ahead </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As the patent system is a critical aspect of the national innovation ecosystem, investing in the patent ecosystem will help in strengthening the innovation capability of India.</li>
<li>The right interventions should be made for the promotion of the quality of patent applications and collaboration between academia and industry.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>A patent can help stop unscrupulous third parties from free riding on the efforts of the inventor. Discuss this statement in context of protection of innovative ecosystem in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/patent-system/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How to fight anaemia as it is stagnating our productivity</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/anaemia/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>iron fortification</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>women health</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="anaemia" class="alignnone wp-image-635790" height="324" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 486px) 100vw, 486px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.52980700_1586241921_women-health-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.52980700_1586241921_women-health-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.52980700_1586241921_women-health-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.52980700_1586241921_women-health.jpg 1024w" width="486"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The recent National Family Health Survey (NFHS-5) data shows anaemia rates increased from 53 per cent to 57 per cent in women and 58 per cent to 67 per cent in children in 2019-21.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Definition of anaemia </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The WHO defines anaemia as a condition where the number of red blood cells or the haemoglobin concentration within them is lower than normal. This compromises immunity and impedes cognitive development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why anaemia is a concern?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Adverse effects of anaemia affect all age groups lower physical and cognitive growth and alertness among children and adolescents, and lesser capacity to learn and play, directly impacting their future potential as productive citizens.</li>
<li>Anaemia among adolescent girls (59.1 per cent) advances to maternal anaemiaand is a major cause of maternal and infant mortality and general morbidity and ill health in a community.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What causes anaemia?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Imbalanced diet</strong>: Cereal-centric diets, with relatively less consumption of iron-rich food groups like meat, fish, eggs, and dark green leafy vegetables (DGLF), can be associated with higher levels of anaemia.</li>
<li><strong>Underlying factors</strong>: High levels of anaemia are also often associated with underlying factors like poor water quality and sanitation conditions that can adversely impact iron absorption in the body.</li>
<li><strong>Iron deficiency is major cause</strong>: A diet that does not contain enough iron, folic acid, or vitamin B12 is a common cause of anaemia.</li>
<li><strong>Some other conditions</strong>: That may lead to anaemia include pregnancy, heavy periods, blood disorders or cancer, inherited disorders, and infectious diseases.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="anaemia" class="alignnone wp-image-635793" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 100vw, 542px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Indian-women_simon-williams-ekta-parishad_wiki-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Indian-women_simon-williams-ekta-parishad_wiki-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Indian-women_simon-williams-ekta-parishad_wiki.jpg 750w" width="542"/>Why is anaemia so high in the country?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low vitamin intake</strong>: Iron-deficiency and vitamin B12-deficiency anaemia are the two common types of anaemia in India.</li>
<li><strong>High population and nutrition deprivation</strong>: Among women, iron deficiency prevalence is higher than men due to menstrual iron losses and the high iron demands of a growing foetus during pregnancies.</li>
<li><strong>Overemphasis on cereals</strong>: Lack of millets in the diet due to overdependence on rice and wheat, insufficient consumption of green and leafy vegetables could be the reasons behind the high prevalence of anaemia in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is</strong> <strong>Iron fortification?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Iron fortification of food is a methodology utilized worldwide to address iron deficiency. Iron fortification programs usually involve mandatory, centralized mass fortification of staple foods, such as wheat flour.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mandatory-rice-fortification-policy-should-be-re-examined/" class="alignnone wp-image-635795" height="593" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 425px) 100vw, 425px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0da17f852d10621c79c6d4a1935af0fa-215x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0da17f852d10621c79c6d4a1935af0fa-215x300.jpg 215w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0da17f852d10621c79c6d4a1935af0fa.jpg 500w" width="425"/>Why need iron fortification?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Iron deficiency anaemia is due to insufficient iron.</li>
<li>Without enough iron, the body can’t produce enough of a substance in red blood cells that enables them to carry oxygen (haemoglobin).</li>
<li>Severe anaemia during pregnancy increases risk of premature birth, having a low birth weight baby and postpartum depression. Some studies also show an increased risk of infant death immediately before or after birth.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="anaemia" class="alignnone wp-image-635794" height="329" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 494px) 100vw, 494px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-1536x1024.jpeg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-2048x1366.jpeg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-1200x800.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-1980x1320.jpeg 1980w" width="494"/>Success story / value addition</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Nepal’s success story to improve maternal anaemia by national action plan .</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mandatory-rice-fortification-policy-should-be-re-examined/"><strong>Anaemia Mukt Bharat</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme aims to reduce the prevalence of anaemia in India.</li>
<li>It provides bi weekly iron Folic acid supplementation to all under five children through Asha workers.</li>
<li>Also, it provides biannual Deworming for children and adolescents. The scheme also establishes institutional mechanisms for advanced research in anaemia.</li>
<li>It also focuses on non-nutritional causes of anaemia.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>We need to focus on the following interventions</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Prophylactic Iron and Folic Acid supplementation.</li>
<li>Intensified year-round Behaviour Change Communication Campaign (Solid Body, Smart Mind).</li>
<li>Appropriate infant and young child feeding practices.</li>
<li>Increase in intake of iron-rich food through diet diversity/quantity/frequency and/or fortified foods with focus on harnessing locally available resources.</li>
<li>Testing and treatment of anaemia, using digital methods and point of care treatment, with special focus on pregnant women and school-going adolescents</li>
<li>Mandatory provision of Iron and Folic Acid fortified foods in government-funded public health programmes</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s nutrition programmes must undergo a periodic review.</li>
<li>The Integrated Child Development Services (ICDS), which is perceived as the guardian of the nation’s nutritional well-being must reassess itself and address critical intervention gaps, both conceptually and programmatically, and produce rapid outcomes.</li>
<li>The nutritional deficit which ought to be considered an indicator of great concern is generally ignored by policymakers and experts. Unless this is addressed, rapid improvement in nutritional indicators cannot happen.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When a person is anaemic, the capacity of his blood cells to carry oxygen decreases. This reduces the productivity of the person which in turn affects the economy of the country. Therefore, it is highly important to cover Anaemia under National Health Mission.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>“Every second adolescent girl has anaemia. Every second woman of reproductive age is anaemic”. In this context do you think </strong><strong>Women’s empowerment will not have any meaning without tackling anaemia? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/anaemia/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Sustainable port development promises blue economy to bloom</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/port-development/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Sustainable coast management</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is politically hard, but developmentally critical, to run port development projects with coastal management sustainably.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="port" class="alignnone wp-image-632083" height="314" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 419px) 100vw, 419px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler.jpg 1200w" width="419"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-ports-development/">What is a port?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A port is a maritime facility comprising one or more wharves or loading areas, where ships load and discharge cargo and passengers. Although usually situated on a sea coast or estuary, ports can also be found far inland, such as Hamburg, Manchester and Duluth; these access the sea via rivers or canals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is meant by port management?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A port management analysis involves an understanding of the port conditions, including intra-port distribution, and routes and hinterland connections outside the port.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why ports are important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Ports infrastructure is key to the development of any nation. India has a coastline spanning about 7,500 km. around 90 percent of India’s external trade by volume and 70 percent by value are handled by ports.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="port" class="alignnone wp-image-632085" height="303" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 502px) 100vw, 502px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Jawaharlal_Nehru_Trust_Port-300x181.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Jawaharlal_Nehru_Trust_Port-300x181.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Jawaharlal_Nehru_Trust_Port.jpg 640w" width="502"/>What are concerns with port projects?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Displacement: </strong>Some 350 families that have lost homes to coastal erosion last year, and those living in makeshift schools and camps are just a foretaste of things to come if coastal erosion and extreme cyclones continue unabated.</li>
<li><strong>Ecological impact</strong>: A further danger is an irreversibly destroyed ecology, triggering deadlier hazards of nature. Ports without adequate safeguards in a highly delicate ecology unleash destruction on marine life and the livelihoods of the local population.</li>
<li><strong>Coastal erosion</strong>: Visakhapatnam and Chennai show how siltation, coastal erosion and accretion can be exacerbated by deepening of harbour channels in ecologically sensitive areas.</li>
<li><strong>Oil spills:</strong> During the operation of ports, spillage or leakages from the loading and unloading of cargo and pollution from oil spills are common due to poor adherence to environmental laws and standards.</li>
<li><strong>Ecosystem threat</strong>: The water discharged during the cleaning of a ship and the discharge of ballast water is a threat to marine ecosystems</li>
<li><strong>Impact on fisheries: </strong>Dredging cause’s environmental problems (increased sedimentation) affecting local productivity of the local waters and its fisheries</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Value addition example </strong></p>
<p>A just published study shows that during 2006-20, the sea gobbled some 2.62 square kilometres or close to 650 acres from the Thiruvananthapuram coast alone.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="port" class="alignnone wp-image-632086" height="291" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 455px) 100vw, 455px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1953413479_27757193ef_o-800x512-1-300x192.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1953413479_27757193ef_o-800x512-1-300x192.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1953413479_27757193ef_o-800x512-1-768x492.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1953413479_27757193ef_o-800x512-1.jpg 800w" width="455"/>Steps to take</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Compensation:</strong> The first order of business, as in infrastructure projects worldwide, is that the project provides compensation to the displaced people and restores their rights.</li>
<li><strong>Reversing marine damage:</strong> Second, the gross neglect of the damage to invaluable marine biodiversity must be redressed with an acceptable EIA, including inputs from experts in biology, ecology, and oceanography.</li>
<li><strong>Safeguard to place:</strong> Third, there needs to be an independent assessment of safeguards that port authorities must put in place as a precondition for any further construction.</li>
<li><strong>Blue Economy:</strong>Blue Economy as a concept includes all the economic activities related to oceans, seas, and coastal areas and emerges from a need for integrated conservation and sustainability in the management of the maritime domain.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Master plan</strong>: Countries should adopt a National Long-term Mater plan addressing the aspects of smarter, greener, safer sustainable port development and productivity improvement.</li>
<li><strong>Planning:</strong> Port development and investment should be driven by setting specific and realistic goals, such as building a stable infrastructure focused on reducing trade costs and contribute to achieving sustainable transport.</li>
<li><strong>Cooperation of multiple sectors</strong>: In order to establish a comprehensive port development master plan, cooperation with financial, environmental, technical, energy, transportation and urban development authorities is essential and must reflect the needs of users, including shippers and shipping lines.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To address existing challenges, we should provide research, analysis and technical assistance to help ports and the maritime transport sector especially in developing countries to improve operations and become more sustainable and resilient to crises, including climate change.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. What do you understand by sustainable port development and port productivity? Discuss the challenges in achieving the same along with way forward.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/port-development/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is a Windfall Tax?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-windfall-tax/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Windfall taxes</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="windfall" class="alignnone wp-image-635835" height="274" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 391px) 100vw, 391px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/windfall-300x210.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/windfall-300x210.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/windfall-768x536.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/windfall.jpg 945w" width="391"/></strong></p>
<p>Finance Minister has defended the windfall tax imposed by the Centre on domestic crude oil producers, saying that it was not an ad hoc move but was done after full consultation with the industry.</p>
<h4>What is a Windfall Tax?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Windfall taxes are designed to tax the profits a company derives from an external, sometimes unprecedented event — for instance, the energy price-rise as a result of the Russia-Ukraine conflict.</li>
<li>These are profits that cannot be attributed to something the firm actively did, like an investment strategy or an expansion of business.</li>
<li>The US Congressional Research Service (CRS) defines a windfall as an “unearned, unanticipated gain in income through no additional effort or expense”.</li>
<li>One area where such taxes have routinely been discussed is oil markets, where price fluctuation leads to volatile or erratic profits for the industry.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When did India introduce this?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In July this year, India announced a windfall tax on domestic crude oil producers who it believed were reaping the benefits of the high oil prices.</li>
<li>It also imposed an additional excise levy on diesel, petrol and air turbine fuel (ATF) exports.</li>
<li>Also, India’s case was different from other countries, as it was still importing discounted Russian oil.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How is it levied?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Governments typically levy this as a <strong><u>one-off tax retrospectively</u></strong> over and above the normal rates of tax.</li>
<li>The Central government has introduced a windfall profit tax of ₹23,250 per tonne on domestic crude oil production, which was subsequently revised fortnightly four times so far.</li>
<li>The latest revision was on August 31, when it was hiked to ₹13,300 per tonne from ₹13,000.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why govt. introduced windfall tax?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There have been varying rationales for governments worldwide to introduce windfall taxes like:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Redistribution of unexpected gains when high prices benefit producers at the expense of consumers,</li>
<li>Funding social welfare schemes, and</li>
<li>Supplementary revenue stream for the government</li>
</ol>
<h4>Why are countries levying windfall taxes now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Prices of oil, gas, and coal have seen <strong><u>sharp increases</u></strong> since last year and in the first two quarters of the current year, although they have reduced recently.</li>
<li><strong><u>Pandemic recovery</u></strong> and supply issues resulting from the Russia-Ukraine conflict <strong><u>shored up energy demands</u></strong>, which in turn have driven up global prices.</li>
<li>The rising prices meant huge and record profits for energy companies while resulting in <strong><u>hefty gas and electricity bills for households</u></strong> in major and smaller economies.</li>
<li>Since the gains stemmed partly from external change, multiple analysts have called them windfall profits.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with imposing such taxes</h4>
<ul>
<li>Companies are confident in investing in a sector if there is <strong><u>certainty and stability in a tax regime</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Since windfall taxes are imposed retrospectively and are often influenced by unexpected events, they can brew <strong><u>uncertainty in the market about future taxes</u></strong>.</li>
<li>IMF says that taxes in response to price surges <strong><u>may suffer from design problems</u></strong>—given their expedient and <strong><u>political nature</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It added that introducing a temporary windfall profit tax <strong><u>reduces future investment</u></strong> because prospective investors will internalise the likelihood of potential taxes when making investment decisions.</li>
<li>There is another argument about what exactly constitutes true windfall profits; how can it be determined and <strong><u>what level of profit is normal or excessive</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Another issue is<strong> <u>who should be taxed</u></strong> — only the big companies responsible for the bulk of high-priced sales or smaller companies as well— raising the question of whether producers with revenues or profits below a certain threshold should be exempt.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-windfall-tax/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is India’s current policy of multi alignment? Advantages and challenges</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/multi-alignment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>non alignment movement</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>foreign policy</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Multi alignment" class="alignnone wp-image-635811" height="330" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 586px) 100vw, 586px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nonaligned_movement-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nonaligned_movement-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nonaligned_movement-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nonaligned_movement.jpeg 770w" width="586"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Forthcoming Shanghai Cooperation Organization (SCO) summit in Samarkand, Uzbekistan is leading India to multi alignment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s journey of foreign policy from being the founder of non-alignment to the multi-alignment. In his book The India Way, External Affairs Minister S. Jaishankar offers a critique of India’s traditional policy of “non-alignment”, where he distinguishes between the “optimistic  non- alignment ” of the past, which he feels has failed, that must give way to more realistic “multiple engagements of the future”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Shanghai Co-operation Organization (SCO)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>SCO is a Eurasian political, economic and security organization.</li>
<li>It is the world’s largest regional organization,</li>
<li>40% of the world population</li>
<li>More than 30% of global GDP.</li>
<li>Members: 8-China, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Russia and Tajikistan, Uzbekistan, India and Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Multi alignment" class="alignnone wp-image-635812" height="281" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 499px) 100vw, 499px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/RIC-1-1095x616-1-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/RIC-1-1095x616-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/RIC-1-1095x616-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/RIC-1-1095x616-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/RIC-1-1095x616-1.jpg 1095w" width="499"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/shanghai-cooperation-organisation-sco/">SCO SUMIIT, 2022</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Host- Uzbekistan,</li>
<li>Uzbekistan will host a full house: 15 leaders including eight member states from four Central Asian States, China, India, Pakistan and Russia,</li>
<li>The observer states: Belarus, Mongolia and Iran (which will become member this year) —</li>
<li>Afghanistan is not invited</li>
<li>Leaders of guest countries -Armenia, Azerbaijan, Turkey and Turkmenistan</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is non- alignment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It’s a policy, a brainchild of Nehru. Non-alignment movement emerged after second world war.</li>
<li>Non-alignment means not having an alliance with any of superpower, either USSR or USA.  Decolonized nations of Asia and Africa was largely a part of this group.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Multi alignment" class="alignnone wp-image-635813" height="487" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Stevan_Kragujevic_Tito_Naser_Nehru_Dolazak_na_Brione-277x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Stevan_Kragujevic_Tito_Naser_Nehru_Dolazak_na_Brione-277x300.jpg 277w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Stevan_Kragujevic_Tito_Naser_Nehru_Dolazak_na_Brione.jpg 440w" width="450"/>India’s policy of non-alignment </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At bandung conference in 1955 non-alignment movement started with India as one of the founding member.</li>
<li>With policy of non-alignment India refused to gravitate towards USA or USSR.</li>
<li>India was the leader of non-alignment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is India’s current policy of multi- alignment? Advantages and challenges.</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Since the start of his tenure from 2014, Prime Minister Narendra Modi have not attended any conference of non-alignment.</li>
<li>External Affairs Minister Dr. S. Jaishankar in his book, The Indian way have criticized the non-alignment.</li>
<li>In the words of Former Foreign Secretary Vijay Gokhale India is no longer the non-align nation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How it is a Multi alignment policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India to truly multi aligned or all aligned by being a part of every major grouping.</li>
<li>India is a part of BRICS and Prime Minister Modi is attending the SCO SUMMIT in Samarkand.</li>
<li>On parallel to rival groups India is also the part of Quad and Indo pacific economic framework.</li>
<li>India is buying the discounted Russian oil and reusing to buckle under pressure from west and USA.</li>
<li>S-400 purchase is happening and India have dodged the bullet of sanctions from USA.</li>
<li>India is choosing the bilateral Free trade agreement like with Australia and UAE and withdrew from groupings like RCEP and Most recently IPEF. This policy are is said to be in the economic interest of India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Advantages of Multi alignment </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India no longer wants to repeat the mistake of missing out of P5 Security council (“Permanent membership in the Security Council was granted to five states based on their importance in the aftermath of World War II).</li>
<li>If any group work against your interest it is better to be part of group rather than remain outside and do nothing</li>
<li>With retreating USA and its collapsing hegemony world is moving towards multiple polar world order.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Disadvantages </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Major disadvantage of non-alignment is you no longer have influence over adverse policy of friendly country.</li>
<li>For example. Russia sells S-400 to India but it also sold the same weapon to china.</li>
<li>USA and India are strategically getting closer day by day but USA recently approved the sale of $450 million F-16 fighter jets to Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Multi alignment will serve India its best national interest.</li>
<li>So far India has managed the rival parties at world stage to secure its foreign policy objectives but with Russian aggression and Chinese assertion and divided world will pose a significant challenge to India’s multi alignment policy.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you understand by non-alignment and multi-alignment? Analyze the shift In India’s foreign policy from non-alignment to multi-alignment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/multi-alignment/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Urban planning can change the future of cities to happy cities</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-planning/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Urbanization issues</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Urban planning" class="alignnone wp-image-629340" height="285" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 506px) 100vw, 506px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city.jpg 1280w" width="506"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the recent few years, the growth of the economy and urbanization have accelerated. Rapid unplanned urbanization has put extreme pressure on natural resources.</li>
<li>Unplanned urbanization, however, exerts great strain on our cities. In fact, the Covid-19 pandemic has revealed the dire need for the planning and management of our cities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does urban planning mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Urban planning, also known as regional planning, town planning, city planning is a technical and political process that is focused on the development and design of land use and the built environment, including air, water, and the infrastructure passing into and out of urban areas, such as transportation, communications, and distribution networks and their accessibility.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are ‘Happy Cities’?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A term that follows the Green City, Sustainable City, Liveable City, in the lingo of urban planning</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a smart city?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A smart city is one that uses information and communication technologies to enhance citizen engagement. It is a neo-vision which seeks to improve the delivery of services in urban areas. The following story maps out the steps being taken by India to explore this concept in practice.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Smart Cities Mission?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sustainable cities</strong>: The Smart Cities Mission aims at developing 100 cities, which were shortlisted, into self-sustainable urban settlements.</li>
<li><strong>Chronology</strong>: The mission was launched on June 25, 2015 and was projected as one aimed at transforming the process of urban development in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Comprehensive revamp</strong>: Among its strategic components is ‘area-based development’, which includes city improvement (retrofitting), city renewal (redevelopment) and city extension (Greenfield development), plus a pan-city initiative in which ‘smart solutions’ are applied covering larger parts of the city.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Fast Facts – Urbanization in India</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Most Urbanized States: Tamil Nadu 43.9%; Maharashtra 4%; Gujarat  37.4%</li>
<li>3 out of world’s 21 mega cities: Mumbai (19 mill); Delhi (15 mill); Kolkata (14 mill)</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Urban planning" class="alignnone wp-image-629341" height="216" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 514px) 100vw, 514px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84-300x126.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84-300x126.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84.jpg 450w" width="514"/>Urban planning challenges </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Planning</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Many urban governments lack a modern planning framework</li>
<li>The multiplicity of local bodies obstructs efficient planning and land use</li>
<li>Rigid master plans and restrictive zoning regulations limit the land available for building, constricting cities’ abilities to grow in accordance with changing needs<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Housing</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Building regulations that limit urban density – such as floor space indexes – reduce the number of houses available, thereby pushing up property prices</li>
<li>Outdated rent control regulations reduce the number of houses available on rent – a critical option for the poor</li>
<li>Policy, planning, and regulation deficiencies lead to a proliferation of slums</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Service delivery</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is a strong bias towards adding physical infrastructure rather than providing financially and environmentally sustainable services</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Infrastructure</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Most urban bodies do not generate the revenues needed to renew infrastructure, nor do they have the creditworthiness to access capital markets for funds</li>
<li>Urban transport planning needs to be more holistic – there is a focus on moving vehicles rather than meeting the needs of the large numbers of people who walk or ride bicycles in India’s towns and cities.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Environment:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The deteriorating urban environment is taking a toll on people’s health and productivity and diminishing their quality of life.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Urban planning" class="alignnone wp-image-629343" height="301" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 572px) 100vw, 572px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/876209-87578-jxyilybgfi-1524127120.jpg 1200w" width="572"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-reforms-in-urban-planning-capacity-in-india/">Solution offered by NITI ayog committee report on urban planning</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Demystifying Planning and Involving Citizens: </strong>While it is important to maintain the master plans’ technical rigour, it is equally important to demystify them for enabling citizens’ participation at relevant stages. Therefore, the committee strongly recommends a ‘Citizen Outreach Campaign’ for demystifying urban planning.</li>
<li><strong>Steps for Enhancing the Role of Private Sector: </strong>The report recommends that concerted measures must be taken at multiple levels to strengthen the role of the private sector to improve the overall planning capacity in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Revision of Town and Country Planning Acts: </strong>Most States have enacted the Town and Country Planning acts, that enable them to prepare and notify master plans for implementation. However, many need to be reviewed and upgraded.</li>
<li><strong>Revision of Town and Country Planning Acts: </strong>Most States have enacted the Town and Country Planning Acts, that enable them to prepare and notify master plans for implementation. However, many need to be reviewed and upgraded.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Interesting fact </strong></p>
<p>India is home to 11% of the total global urban population.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Government initiatives</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Atal Mission for Rejuvenation and Urban Transformation (AMRUT);</li>
<li>Pradhan Mantri Awas Yojana (PMAY) – Housing for all (Urban),</li>
<li>Smart Cities Mission (SCM),</li>
<li>Swachh Bharat Mission (SBM),</li>
<li>Heritage City Development and Augmentation Yojana (HRIDAY);</li>
<li>Deen Dayal Antyodaya Yojana – National Urban Livelihoods Mission (DAY-NULM).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>What is now increasingly understood, is that urban planning and design can be a powerful contributor to the happiness of citizens. The structure and layout of our streets, the availability of green spaces, the possibility of using urban spaces freely, the inclusion of beauty in public space.</li>
<li>It is safe to assume that when there are avenues for a community to come together in a pleasant environment, which is accessible to everyone, it can only increase well-being.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>Can urban planning and design change Indian cities to be happy cities? Express your views by addressing the roadblocks in the same.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-planning/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What it will take to fulfill India’s Solar Power Dream?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-it-will-take-to-fulfill-indias-solar-power-dream/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Solar energy targets of India</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>From less than 10 MW in 2010, India has added significant PV capacity over the past decade, achieving over 50 GW by 2022.</p>
<h4>Solar energy in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>Solar photovoltaics (PV) has driven India’s push towards the adoption of cleaner energy generation technologies.</li>
<li><strong><u>India is targeting about 500 GW by 2030</u></strong>, of renewable energy deployment, out of which ~280 GW is expected from solar PV.</li>
<li>This necessitates the deployment of nearly 30 GW of solar capacity every year until 2030.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Key components</h4>
<ul>
<li>A typical solar PV value chain consists of first fabricating polysilicon ingots which need to be transformed into thin Silicon wafers that are needed to manufacture the PV mini-modules.</li>
<li>The mini-modules are then assembled into market-ready and field-deployable modules.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Various challenges</h4>
<p>There are challenges that need to be overcome for the sustainability of the PV economy.</p>
<p><strong>(1) PV Modules</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Indian solar deployment or installation companies <strong><u>depend heavily on imports</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It currently <strong><u>imports 100% of silicon wafers and around 80% of cells</u></strong> even at the current deployment levels.</li>
<li>India currently <strong><u>does not have enough module</u></strong> and cell manufacturing capacity.</li>
<li>India’s current solar module <strong><u>manufacturing capacity is limited to ~15 GW per year</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>demand-supply gap widens</u></strong> as we move up the value chain — for example, India only produces ~3.5 GW of cells currently.</li>
<li>India has <strong><u>no manufacturing capacity</u></strong> for solar wafers and polysilicon ingots.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Field deployment</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Also, out of the 15 GW of module manufacturing capacity, <strong><u>only 3-4 GW of modules</u></strong> are <strong><u>technologically competitive and worthy of deployment</u></strong> in grid-based projects.</li>
<li>India remains dependent on the import of solar modules for field deployment.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Size and technology</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Most of the Indian industry is currently tuned to handling M2 wafer size, which is roughly 156 x 156 mm2, while the global industry is already moving towards M10 and M12 sizes, which are 182 x 182 mm2 and 210 x 210 mm2 respectively.</li>
<li>The bigger size has an advantage in terms of silicon cost per wafer, as this effectively means lower loss of silicon during ingot to wafer processing.</li>
<li>In terms of cell technology, most of the manufacturing still uses Al-BSF technology, which can typically give efficiencies of ~18-19% at the cell level and ~16-17% at the module level.</li>
<li>By contrast, cell manufacturing worldwide has moved to PERC (22-23%), HJT(~24%), TOPCON (23-24%) and other newer technologies, yielding module efficiency of &gt;21%.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Land issue</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Producing more solar power for the same module size means more solar power from the same land area.</li>
<li>Land, the most expensive part of solar projects, is scarce in India — and Indian industry has no choice but to move towards newer and superior technologies as part of expansion plans.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Raw materials supply</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is a <strong><u>huge gap on the raw material supply</u></strong> chain side as well.</li>
<li>Silicon wafer, the most expensive raw material, is not manufactured in India.</li>
<li>India will have to work on technology tie-ups to make the right grade of silicon for solar cell manufacturing — and since &gt;90% of the world’s solar wafer manufacturing currently happens in China.</li>
<li>It is not clear how and where India will get the technology.</li>
<li>Other key raw materials such as <strong><u>metallic pastes of silver and aluminium</u></strong> to form the electrical contacts too, <strong><u>are almost 100% imported</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Thus, <strong><u>India is more of an assembly hub than a manufacturing</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Lack of investment</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India has hardly invested in this sector which can help the industry to try and test the technologies in a cost-effective manner.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Current govt policy</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>government has identified this gap</u></strong>, and is rolling out various policy initiatives to push and motivate the industry to <strong><u>work towards self-reliance</u></strong> in solar manufacturing, both for cells and modules.</li>
<li>Key initiatives include:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>40% duty on the import of modules and</li>
<li>25% duty on the import of cells, and</li>
<li>Production Linked Incentive (PLI) scheme to support manufacturing capex</li>
<li>Compulsion to procure modules only from an approved list of manufacturers (ALMM) for projects that are connected to state/ central government grids</li>
<li>Only India-based manufacturers have been approved</li>
</ol>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s path to become a manufacturing hub for the same <strong><u>requires more than just putting some tax barriers and commercial incentives</u></strong> in the form of PLI schemes, etc.</li>
<li>It will warrant <strong><u>strong industry-academia collaboration</u></strong> in an innovative manner to start developing home-grown technologies which could, in the short-term.</li>
<li>It needs to <strong><u>work with the industry</u></strong> to provide them with trained human resource, process learnings, root-cause analysis through right testing and, in the long term, develop India’s own technologies.</li>
<li>High-end technology development requires <strong><u>substantial investment</u></strong> in several clusters which operate in industry-like working and management conditions, appropriate emoluments, and clear deliverables.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-it-will-take-to-fulfill-indias-solar-power-dream/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Alcohol Laws in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/alcohol-laws-in-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Alcohol laws</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The most ambitious Delhi’s Alcohol Policy 2021-22 which brought in big discounts for consumers was scrapped on July 31 amid allegations of corruption and irregularities in the drafting and implementation of the policy.</p>
<p>After scrapping the new policy, the Delhi government decided to bring back the ‘<strong><u>old excise regime</u></strong>’ that was in force before.</p>
<blockquote><p>Definitely! We shall not nit-pick the old vs. new policy. Let us generally understand how alcohol is regulated in India.</p></blockquote>
<h4>Alcohol laws of India: A backgrounder</h4>
<ul>
<li>The legal drinking age in India and the laws which regulate the sale and consumption of alcohol vary significantly from state to state.</li>
<li>In India, consumption of alcohol is prohibited in the states of Bihar, Gujarat, Nagaland and Mizoram.</li>
<li>There is partial ban on alcohol in some districts of Manipur.</li>
<li>All other Indian states permit alcohol consumption but fix a legal drinking age, which ranges at different ages per region.</li>
<li>In some states the legal drinking age can be different for different types of alcoholic beverage.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Regulation</h4>
<ul>
<li>Alcohol is a subject in the <strong><u>State List</u></strong> under the Seventh Schedule of the Constitution of India.</li>
<li>Therefore, the <strong><u>laws governing alcohol vary from state to state</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Liquor in India is generally sold at liquor stores, restaurants, hotels, bars, pubs, clubs and discos but not online.</li>
<li>Some states, like Kerala and Tamil Nadu, prohibit private parties from owning liquor stores making the state government the sole retailer of alcohol in those states.</li>
<li>In some states, liquor may be sold at groceries, departmental stores, banquet halls and/or farm houses.</li>
<li>Some tourist areas have special laws allowing the sale of alcohol on beaches and houseboats.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Drunk driving law</h4>
<ul>
<li>The blood alcohol content (BAC) legal limit is 0.03% or 0.03 mg alcohol in 100 ml blood.</li>
<li>On 1 March 2012, the Union Cabinet approved proposed changes to the Motor Vehicle Act.</li>
<li>Higher penalties were introduced, including fines from ₹2,000 to ₹10,000 and imprisonment from 6 months to 4 years.</li>
<li>Different penalties are assessed depending on the blood alcohol content at the time of the offence.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Dry days</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dry days are specific days when the sale of alcohol is not permitted.</li>
<li>Most of the Indian states observe these days on major national festivals/occasions such as Republic Day (26 January), Independence Day (15 August) and Gandhi Jayanti (2 October).</li>
<li>Dry days are also observed during elections in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Taxation on Alcohol</h4>
<ul>
<li>Most states levy either Value added Tax (VAT) or Excise duty or both.</li>
<li>Excise duty is a tax levied to discourage the consumption of a product.</li>
<li>It is calculated on a per-unit basis. Meaning, if you buy 1 litre of liquor, you pay a fixed excise duty of Rs 15.</li>
<li>Value-added Tax is charged in the proportion of the product. If a bottle costs Rs 100, and the state levies 10 percent VAT, the price rises to Rs 110.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Tax rates in States</h4>
<ul>
<li>The 29 states/UTs in India approach liquor taxation differently.</li>
<li>For instance, Gujarat has banned its citizens from consuming liquor since 1961.</li>
<li>But outsiders with special licenses can still buy.</li>
<li>Puducherry, on the other hand, earns most of its revenue from alcohol trading.</li>
<li>Bihar has prohibited alcohol consumption entirely, meaning the state’s revenue from liquor consumption is nil.</li>
<li>Its neighbour, Uttar Pradesh, earns the most excise duty on liquor.</li>
<li>The state does not levy VAT but a special duty on liquor, collecting funds for particular purposes.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Do you know?</strong></h4>
<p>Andhra Pradesh, Telangana, Kerala, Karnataka, and Tamil Nadu consume as much as 45 percent of the liquor sold in the country.</p>
<p>Nationally, Maharashtra charges the highest rate but draws only a portion of its revenue from its sales.</p></blockquote>
<h4>Why alcohol isn’t banned everywhere?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Taxes from alcohol sales roughly form a quarter of state revenues.</li>
<li>If this stream suddenly stops, states have to compulsorily cut some important spending.</li>
<li>Also, moderate alcohol consumption may provide some health benefits.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/alcohol-laws-in-india/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Europe heading for Recession</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/europe-heading-for-recession/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Recessions, Depression</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-631660" height="272" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 501px) 100vw, 501px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-300x163.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-300x163.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-1024x555.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession-768x416.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/recession.jpg 1026w" width="501"/></p>
<p>The Eurozone is almost certainly entering a recession, with surveys showing a deepening cost-of-living crisis and a gloomy outlook that is keeping consumers wary of spending.</p>
<h4>What is Recession?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/imf-flags-recession-risk/">recession</a> is a significant decline in economic activity that lasts for months or even years.</li>
<li>Experts declare a recession when a nation’s economy experiences negative GDP, rising levels of unemployment, falling retail sales, and contracting measures of income and manufacturing for an extended period of time.</li>
<li>Recessions are considered an unavoidable part of the business cycle—or the regular cadence of expansion and contraction that occurs in a nation’s economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What causes Recessions?</h4>
<p>These phenomena are some of the main drivers of a recession:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>A sudden economic shock:</strong> An economic shock is a surprise problem that creates serious financial damage. The coronavirus outbreak, which shut down economies worldwide, is a more recent example of a sudden economic shock.</li>
<li><strong>Excessive debt:</strong> When individuals or businesses take on too much debt, the cost of servicing the debt can grow to the point where they can’t pay their bills. Growing debt defaults and bankruptcies then capsize the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Asset bubbles:</strong> When investing decisions are driven by emotion, bad economic outcomes aren’t far behind. Investors can become too optimistic during a strong economy.</li>
<li><strong>Too much inflation:</strong> Inflation is the steady, upward trend in prices over time. Inflation isn’t a bad thing per se, but excessive inflation is a dangerous phenomenon. Central banks control inflation by raising interest rates, and higher interest rates depress economic activity.</li>
<li><strong>Too much deflation:</strong> While runaway inflation can create a recession, deflation can be even worse. Deflation is when prices decline over time, which causes wages to contract, which further depresses prices. When a deflationary feedback loop gets out of hand, people and business stop spending, which undermines the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Technological change:</strong> New inventions increase productivity and help the economy over the long term, but there can be short-term periods of adjustment to technological breakthroughs. In the 19th century, there were waves of labour-saving technological improvements.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What’s the difference between <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/imf-flags-recession-risk/">Recession</a> and Depression?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Recessions and depressions have similar causes, but the overall impact of a depression is much, much worse.</li>
<li>There are greater job losses, higher unemployment and steeper declines in GDP.</li>
<li>Most of all, a depression lasts longer—years, not months—and it takes more time for the economy to recover.</li>
<li>Economists do not have a set definition or fixed measurements to show what counts as a depression. Suffice to say, all the impacts of a depression are deeper and last longer.</li>
<li>In the past century, the US has faced just one depression: The Great Depression.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Great Depression</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Great Depression started in 1929 and lasted through 1933, although the economy didn’t really recover until World War II, nearly a decade later.</li>
<li>During the Great Depression, unemployment rose to 25% and the GDP fell by 30%.</li>
<li>It was the most unprecedented economic collapse in modern US history.</li>
<li>By way of comparison, the Great Recession was the worst recession since the Great Depression.</li>
<li>During the Great Recession, unemployment peaked around 10% and the recession officially lasted from December 2007 to June 2009, about a year and a half.</li>
<li>Some economists fear that the coronavirus recession could morph into a depression, depending how long it lasts.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How long do recessions last?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Gulf War Recession (July 1990 to March 1991):</strong> At the start of the 1990s, the U.S. went through a short, eight-month recession, partly caused by spiking oil prices during the First Gulf War.</li>
<li><strong>The Great Recession (2008-2009):</strong> As mentioned, the Great Recession was caused in part by a bubble in the real estate market.</li>
<li><strong>Covid-19 Recession:</strong> The most recent recession began in February 2020 and lasted only two months, making it the shortest US recession in history.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Can we predict a recession?</h4>
<p>Given that economic forecasting is uncertain, predicting future recessions is far from easy. However, the following warning signs can give you more time to figure out how to prepare for a recession before it happens:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>An inverted yield curve:</strong> The yield curve is a graph that plots the market value—or the yield—of a range. When long-term yields are lower than short-term yields, it shows that investors are worried about a recession. This phenomenon is known as a yield curve inversion, and it has predicted past recessions.</li>
<li><strong>Declines in consumer confidence:</strong> Consumer spending is the main driver of the US economy. If surveys show a sustained drop in consumer confidence, it could be a sign of impending trouble for the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Drop in the Leading Economic Index (LEI):</strong> Published monthly by the Conference Board, the LEI strives to predict future economic trends. It looks at factors like applications for unemployment insurance, new orders for manufacturing and stock market performance.</li>
<li><strong>Sudden stock market declines:</strong> A large, sudden decline in stock markets could be a sign of a recession coming on, since investors sell off parts and sometimes all of their holdings in anticipation of an economic slowdown.</li>
<li><strong>Rising unemployment:</strong> It goes without saying that if people are losing their jobs, it’s a bad sign for the economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How does a recession affect individuals?</h4>
<ul>
<li>We may lose your job during a recession, as unemployment levels rise. It becomes much harder to find a job replacement since more people are out of work.</li>
<li>People who keep their jobs may see cuts to pay and benefits, and struggle to negotiate future pay raises.</li>
<li>Investments in stocks, bonds, real estate and other assets can lose money in a recession, reducing your savings and upsetting your plans for retirement.</li>
<li>Business owners make fewer sales during a recession, and may even be forced into bankruptcy.</li>
<li>With more people unable to pay their bills during a recession, lenders tighten standards for mortgages, car loans, and other types of financing.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/europe-heading-for-recession/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Electricity Amendment Bill 2022 – Addressing the transition and equity</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/electricity/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of the bill</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>electricity reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="electricity" class="alignnone wp-image-629013" height="343" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download.jpeg" width="558"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Concerns of states on some provisions of the new Electricity Bill are justified. But the legislation proposes welcome correctives to longstanding problems of the power sector.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Important provisions of the bill</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Payment security</strong>: The Bill provides that electricity will not be scheduled or despatched if adequate payment security is not provided by the discom.   The central government may prescribe rules regarding payment security.</li>
<li><strong>Contract enforcement</strong>: The Bill empowers the CERC and SERCs to adjudicate disputes related to the performance of contracts.  These refer to contracts related to the sale, purchase, or transmission of electricity.  Further, the Commissions will have powers of a Civil Court.</li>
<li><strong>Renewable purchase obligation</strong>: The Act empowers SERCs to specify renewable purchase obligations (RPO) for discoms.  RPO refers to the mandate to procure a certain percentage of electricity from renewable sources.  The Bill adds that RPO should not be below a minimum percentage prescribed by the central government.  Failure to meet RPO will be punishable with a penalty between 25 paise and 50 paise per kilowatt of the shortfall.</li>
<li><strong>Selection committee for SERCs</strong>: Under the Act, the Chairperson of the Central Electricity Authority or the Chairperson of the CERC is one of the members of the selection committee to recommend appointments to the SERCs.  Under the Bill, instead of this person, the central government will nominate a member to the selection committee.  The nominee should not be below the rank of Additional Secretary to the central government.</li>
<li><strong>Composition of Commissions and APTEL</strong>: The Bill increases the number of members (including the chairperson) in SERCs from three to four.  Further, at least one member in both the CERC and SERCs must be from law background.  Under the Act, Appellate Tribunal for Electricity (APTEL) consists of a chairperson and three other members.  The Bill instead provides that the APTEL will have three or more members, as may be prescribed by the central government.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>State apprehensions of the bill </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multi state license: </strong>The clause pertaining to applicants seeking a distribution licence in more than one state. It states that the Central Electricity Regulatory Commission (CERC), and not the SERC, will grant the licence. This is problematic because a SERC is likely to be more aware of the field-level conditions in a state than its central counterpart.</li>
<li><strong>Centre can bypass state: </strong>The Bill has a provision empowering the Centre to give directions directly to the SERCs. Till now, the CERC received instructions from the Centre and the SERCs were under the state. The new Bill enables the Centre to bypass state governments. It’s not surprising that this is a matter of concern for the states.</li>
<li><strong>Direct appointment by centre:</strong> The Bill states that the SERC chairperson will now be a nominee of the central government and will be an additional secretary-level official. This gives the impression that the Centre is trying to control the appointments to the SERCs<strong>. </strong></li>
</ul>
<div class="mceTemp"></div>
<p><img alt="electricity" class="alignnone wp-image-629016" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 481px) 100vw, 481px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy-300x208.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy-300x208.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy.jpg 650w" width="481"/></p>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/power-sector-reforms/"><strong>Why the bill is important? </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Compensation clause: </strong>The Bill states that if power purchase agreement PPAs are renegotiated, the affected party has to be compensated within 90 days from the date of submission of the petition.</li>
<li><strong>Uniformity in tariffs revision:</strong> New tariffs have to be made applicable from the beginning of the financial year. New tariffs often come into force in the middle of the financial year (due to delays in the issuing of orders by SERCs). This means that discoms do not earn their full revenues leading to cash flow problems.</li>
<li><strong>Easy tariff petition processing now:</strong> The Bill has proposed a reduction in the time for processing tariff petitions from 120 days to 90 days.</li>
<li><strong>Suo moto jurisdiction</strong>: Regulatory commissions have been given suo motu jurisdiction if tariff petitions are not filed within 30 days of the stipulated time. This too is a step in the right direction.</li>
<li><strong>More teeth to load dispatcher: </strong>the Bill proposes to give more teeth to the national load dispatcher. We need to strengthen the load dispatcher for the smooth functioning of the grid, especially with a huge renewable capacity where intermittency of generation is a major issue in the offing.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The rollout of the proposed amendments through a consensus-based approach would go a long way in overhauling the weakest link in the nation’s power supply chain.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Electricity Bill 2022 is a remedy worse than the disease afflicting India’s power sector. Critically analyse.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/electricity/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The great Indian thirst: The story of India’s water stress</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/water-stress/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>various water reports</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>water conservation</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="water stress" class="alignnone wp-image-636154" height="315" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 559px) 100vw, 559px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vsemirnyi-den-vody-2017-nrwf-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vsemirnyi-den-vody-2017-nrwf-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vsemirnyi-den-vody-2017-nrwf-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vsemirnyi-den-vody-2017-nrwf.jpeg 770w" width="559"/></strong><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>United Nations World Water Development Report of 2022 has expressed global concern over the sharp rise in freshwater withdrawal from streams, lakes, aquifers and human made reservoirs, significant water stress and also water scarcity being experienced in diﬀerent parts of the world.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who publishes the UNs world water development report?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The United Nations World Water Development Report (WWDR) is published by UNESCO, on behalf of UN-Water and its production is coordinated by the UNESCO World Water Assessment Program (WWAP).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the level of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-water-crisis/#:~:text=Nearly%20600%20million%20Indians%20faced,million%20people%2C%20the%20study%20noted.">water stress</a> in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Global Drought Risk and Water Stress map (2019)</strong>: It shows that major parts of India, particularly west, central and parts of peninsular India are highly water stressed and experience water scarcity.</li>
<li><strong>Composite Water Management Index (2018):</strong> Released by Niti Aayog indicates that more than 600 million people are facing acute water stress.</li>
<li><strong>India is the world’s largest extractor of groundwater</strong>: Accounting for 25 per cent of the total. 70 percent of our water sources are contaminated and our major rivers are dying because of pollution.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="water stress" class="alignnone wp-image-636155" height="304" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 456px) 100vw, 456px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-768x511.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478.jpg 976w" width="456"/>Why is Rural to Urban transfer of water becoming an issue in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rising urban population: </strong>According to Census 2011, the urban population in India accounted for 34% of total population. It is estimated that the urban population component in India will cross the 40% mark by 2030 and the 50% mark by 2050 according to World Urbanization Prospects, 2018.</li>
<li><strong>Water use in the urban areas: </strong>Water use in the urban sector has increased as more and more people shift to urban areas. Per capita use of water in these centers rises, which will continue to grow with improved standards of living.</li>
<li><strong>Shifting of water source in Urban areas: </strong>As the city grows and water management infrastructures develop, dependence shifts to surface water from groundwater. <strong>For example:</strong> In Ahmedabad, more than 80% of water supply used to be met from groundwater sources till the mid-1980s. Due to such overexploitation of groundwater the depth to groundwater level reached 67 meters in confined aquifers. The city now depends on the Narmada canal for the bulk of its water supply.</li>
<li><strong>Dependence of urban areas on rural areas for water source and rural-urban disputes over water: </strong>Cities largely depend on rural areas for raw water supply, which has the potential to ignite the rural-urban dispute. For example: Nagpur and Chennai face the problem of rural-urban water disputes.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong><img alt="water stress" class="alignnone wp-image-636156" height="336" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 596px) 100vw, 596px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Water1-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Water1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Water1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Water1.jpg 800w" width="596"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/kaveri-river-water-dispute/">Reasons for disputes</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Diversion of resource</strong>: Water is transported to urban areas at the expense of rural areas. Due to the high population in urban areas the water requirement for daily use is very high.</li>
<li><strong>High demand of water for industrial purposes: </strong>In urban areas the water is heavily used in industries creating water stress.</li>
<li><strong>High Agriculture dependence:</strong> In the rural areas water is used mainly for irrigation purposes and due to heavy dependence on agriculture the water is very essential in rural areas.</li>
<li><strong>Water pollution</strong>: In cities, most of this water is in the form of grey water with little recovery or reuse, eventually contributing to water pollution.</li>
<li><strong>Bad governance</strong>: Politicization of water for vote bank and skewed distribution of water particular regions For example: Andhra and Telangana.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="water stress " class="alignnone wp-image-636157" height="387" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-1536x1025.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-1980x1321.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo.jpg 2048w" width="581"/>Climate change exacerbate the rural-urban disputes</strong><strong> </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Affecting rainfall pattern: </strong>Climate change affects the amount of rainfall in the region which is the prime source of both surface water and groundwater.</li>
<li><strong>Increase rate of evaporation over surface water:</strong> because of high temperature the surface waters of lakes, rivers, canals etc. face high evaporation water loss.</li>
<li><strong>Melting of glaciers: </strong>glaciers are the sources for perennial rivers of India. Due to global warming, glaciers are melting and hence affecting the perennial nature of rivers.</li>
<li><strong>Frequent droughts:</strong> It affects the groundwater recharge process and drying of surface waters which creates shortage of water. It exacerbate the rural-urban conflict.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A system perspective and catchment scale based approach are necessary to link reallocation of water with wider discussions on development, infrastructure investment, fostering an rural-urban partnership and adopting an integrated approach in water management.</li>
<li>The government cannot manage the water crisis alone. It will take the combined efforts of civil society, the private sector including the public at large to meet the challenge.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Rural and urban areas use water from the same stock, i.e., the water resources of the country. Therefore, it is important to strive for a win- win situation by securing the interests of both urban and rural areas. Good Governance is the key to achieve such a win-win situation.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question Q.</strong></p>
<p><strong>How the rising water stress and growing urbanization in India is fuelling rural-urban conflict over water issues? Also highlight the role of climate change in exacerbating these conflicts. Elaborate.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/water-stress/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Here is how HDI has performed in last 3 decades</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hdi/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of report</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>human development</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="HDI" class="alignnone wp-image-636168" height="345" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 448px) 100vw, 448px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-300x231.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-300x231.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-1024x787.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-768x590.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-1171x900.jpg 1171w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant.jpg 1200w" width="448"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India, belonging to the medium HDI category, shows dimensional inequalities similar to or slightly below the average figures in the category, except in the case of education where it is high and closer to the low HDI countries. The inequalities in health and education are more than twice that of the very high and high HDI categories.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The bad news for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/human-development-report-by-undp/">India is that its global HDI rank has slipped</a> from 129 in 2019 to 131 in 2020 and to 132 in 2021-22.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the meaning of human development?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Human development is defined as the process of enlarging people’s freedoms and opportunities and improving their well-being. Human development is about the real freedom ordinary people have to decide who to be, what to do, and how to live.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is meant by Human Development Index?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The HDI is a summary measure of human development. The HDI is a summary composite measure of a country’s average achievements in three basic aspects of human development: health, knowledge and standard of living.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who publishes HDI?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Human Development Report (HDR) is an annual Human Development Index report published by the Human Development Report Office of the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="HDI" class="alignnone wp-image-636170" height="338" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3.jpg 960w" width="600"/>Dimensions of the Human Development Index</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Long and healthy life: </strong>The long and healthy life dimension is measured by life expectancy at birth. The life expectancy at birth is a statistical measure that an average individual is expected to live based on certain demographic factors such as the year of birth and current age.</li>
<li><strong>Education</strong>: This is a second dimension in the HDI. The indicators of education are the expected years of schooling and the mean years of schooling. According to the UN, the average maximum years of schooling is 18 years, while the mean maximum years of schooling is 15 years.</li>
<li><strong>Standard of living: </strong>The standard of living is usually measured by the gross national income (GNI) per capita. The GNI indicates the total domestic and foreign output created by the residents of a certain country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the 4 indicators of HDI?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Mean years of schooling</li>
<li>Expected years of schooling</li>
<li>Life expectancy at birth</li>
<li>Gross national income (GNI) per capita</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Which Countries Have the Highest HDI?</strong></p>
<p>In the latest HDI ranking, from 2022, Switzerland finished first with an HDI value of 0.962.</p></blockquote>
<p><img alt="HDI" class="wp-image-636173" height="339" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 509px) 100vw, 509px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook.jpg 1536w" width="509"/></p>
<h4><strong>Issues in HDI</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) An incomplete indicator</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Human development is incomplete without human freedom and that while the need for qualities judgement is clear; there is no simple quantitative measure available yet to capture the many aspects of human freedom.</li>
<li>HDI also does not specifically reflect quality of life factors, such as empowerment movements or overall feelings of security or happiness.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Limited idea of development</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The HDI is not reflecting the human development idea accurately.</li>
<li>It is an index restricted to the socio-economic sphere of life; the political and civil spheres are in the most part kept separate.</li>
<li>Hence there is a sub-estimation of inequality among countries, which means that this dimension is not being taken into consideration appropriately.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) A vague concept</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Concerning data quality and the exact construction of the index HDI is conceptually weak and empirically unsound.</li>
<li>This strong critic comes from the idea that both components of HDI are problematic. The GNP in developing countries suffers from incomplete coverage, measurement errors and biases.</li>
<li>The definition and measurement of literacy are different among countries and also, this data has not been available since 1970 in a significant number of countries.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Data quality issues</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The HDI, as a combination of only four relatively simple indicators, doesn’t only raise a questions what other indicators should be included, but also how to ensure quality and comparable input data.</li>
<li>It is logical that the UNDP try to collect their data from international organizations concentrating in collecting data in specific fields.</li>
<li>Quality and trustworthiness of those data is disputable, especially when we get the information from UN non-democratic members, as for example Cuba or China.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) A tool for mere comparison</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The concept of HDI was set up mainly for relative comparison of countries in one particular time.</li>
<li>HDI is much better when distinguishing between countries with low and middle human development, instead of countries at the top of the ranking.</li>
<li>Therefore, the original notion was not to set up an absolute ranking, but let’s quite free hands in comparison of the results.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Development has to be greener</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The human development approach has not adequately incorporated environmental conditions which may threaten long-term achievements on human development. The most pervasive failure was on environmental sustainability.</li>
<li>However, for the first time in 2020, the UNDP introduced a new metric to reflect the impact caused by each country’s per-capita carbon emissions and its material footprint.</li>
<li>This is Planetary Pressures-adjusted HDI or PHDI. It measured the amount of fossil fuels, metals and other resources used to make the goods and services it consumes.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(7) Wealth can never equate welfare</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Higher national wealth does not indicate welfare. GNI may not necessarily increase economic welfare; it depends on how it is spent.</li>
<li>For example, if a country spends more on military spending – this is reflected in higher GNI, but welfare could actually be lower.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Importance of HDI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multidimensionality</strong>: It is one of the few multidimensional indices as it includes indicators such as literacy rate, enrolment ratio, life expectancy rate, infant mortality rate, etc.</li>
<li><strong>True yardstick</strong>: It acts as a true yardstick to measure development in real sense.</li>
<li><strong>Helps in measuring a nation’s well-being:</strong> Unlike per capital income, which only indicates that a rise in per capital income implies economic development; HDI considers many other vital social indicators and helps in measuring a nation’s well-being.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Value addition line</strong></p>
<p><em>People are the real wealth of a nation. The basic objective of development should be to create an enabling environment for people to live long, healthy and creative lives. This may appear to be a simple truth.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To sum up, the introduction of the HDI three decades ago was an early attempt to address the shortcomings in conventional measures of wellbeing.</li>
<li>The HDI has continued to attract widespread attention and motivates the work of activists, scholars and political leaders around the world.</li>
<li>The HDI compels us to ask what matters more, the quantitative expansion of an economy, or the qualitative improvement in the capabilities of society.</li>
<li>Indeed the revival of interest in this subject at the highest levels of government is the need of the hour.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you understand by human development? Critically analyse the human development index given by UNDP.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hdi/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>old age problems that we should address now</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/old-age/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>government schemes</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>social welfare</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="old age" class="alignnone wp-image-636184" height="302" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 671px) 100vw, 671px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/809500-jnxnqsfxdc-1465291749-300x135.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/809500-jnxnqsfxdc-1465291749-300x135.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/809500-jnxnqsfxdc-1465291749-1024x459.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/809500-jnxnqsfxdc-1465291749-768x344.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/809500-jnxnqsfxdc-1465291749.jpg 1200w" width="671"/>Context             </strong></h4>
<p>India will be facing the immediate challenge –The ageing of the population. Challenge to ensure a decent quality of life for the old age people in the near future, planning and providing for it must begin today.</p>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Life expectancy in India has more than doubled since Independence from around 32 years in the late 1940s to 70 years or so today, a historical achievement.</li>
<li>Over the same period, the fertility rate has crashed from about six children per woman to just two, which liberated women from the cycle of continuous child bearing and child care.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is ageing of the population?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Meaning: </strong>Population ageing is a shift in the distribution of a country’s population towards older ages.</li>
<li><strong>Reason behind it</strong>: Decline in the fertility rate and Rise In the life expectancy. An increase in longevity increases the average age of the population by increasing the numbers of surviving older people.</li>
<li><strong>Impact of the ageing population:</strong>, labor supply shortage, change in patterns of saving and investment, deteriorate fiscal balance, lack of adequate welfare system etc.</li>
<li><strong>Challenges they impose: </strong>Social security, elderly Healthcare, Dependence on the family etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the status in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to the National Commission on Population, The share of the elderly (persons aged 60 years and above) close to 9% in 2011.</li>
<li>It is growing fast and may reach 18% by 2036.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="old age" class="alignnone wp-image-636185" height="424" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 645px) 100vw, 645px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/senior-citizens-_-demonetisation-300x197.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/senior-citizens-_-demonetisation-300x197.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/senior-citizens-_-demonetisation.jpg 760w" width="645"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/old-age-poverty/">Problems faced by elderly</a> </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Depression</strong>: According to survey by Abdul Latif Jameel foundation in Tamilnadu, 30-50% of people above age of 60 has a symptoms of depression.The proportion with depression symptoms is much higher for women than men, and rises sharply with age. In most cases, depression remains undiagnosed and untreated.</li>
<li><strong>Loneliness</strong>: Loneliness one the major factor leading to depression. A large majority of elderly persons living alone are women, mainly widows.</li>
<li><strong>Hardship of age</strong>: Monetary assistance can certainly help to cope with many health issues.</li>
<li><strong>Poverty and poor health</strong>: Old age pensions are vital. Cash helps to lead a dignified life.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="old age" class="alignnone wp-image-636186" height="310" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 508px) 100vw, 508px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/old-age-300x183.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/old-age-300x183.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/old-age.jpg 675w" width="508"/>Current government schemes for elderly </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Pradhan Mantri Vaya Vandana Scheme</strong> – This is one of the most popular senior citizen pension schemes in India.</p>
<ul>
<li>Designed for senior citizens above 60 years of age, the policy term of this Prime Minister Senior Citizen Scheme extends to ten years.</li>
<li>The pensioner can choose the frequency of the payment – monthly/quarterly/half- yearly/annually.</li>
<li>You can earn interest of 8% per annum over this scheme.</li>
<li>The minimum and maximum capping of pension are Rs. 3,000 per month and 10,000 per month, respectively</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>National Programme for the Health Care of Elderly (NPHCE)</strong>–</p>
<ul>
<li>Introduced in 2010, this scheme concentrates on preventive as well as promotive, care for the maintenance of overall health.</li>
<li>This program was launched to address the health issues faced by seniors.</li>
<li>The district-level objectives include providing dedicated health facilities in district hospitals, community health centres (CHC), primary health centres (PHC), and sub-centres (SC) levels through State Health Society.</li>
<li>These facilities maybe free or highly subsidized.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Varishta Mediclaim Policy</strong> –</p>
<ul>
<li>This policy aids seniors by covering the cost of medicines, blood, ambulance charges, and other diagnosis related charges.</li>
<li>Designed for senior citizens between the age of 60 and 80 years, this helps meet the health-related expenses of senior citizens.</li>
<li>Income tax benefits are allowed for payment of premium.</li>
<li>Although the policy period is for one year, you can extend the renewal up to the age of 90 years.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Rashtriya Vayoshri Yojana</strong> –</p>
<ul>
<li>This scheme provides physical aids and assisted-living devices to the elderly above 60 years of age that belong to the BPL (below the poverty line) category.</li>
<li>If senior citizens wish to avail this, then they must have a BPL card.</li>
<li>This is a Central Sector Scheme and is entirely funded by the Central Government.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Varishta Pension Bima Yojana</strong> –</p>
<ul>
<li>This pension scheme, launched by the Ministry of Finance, is for senior citizens above 60 years.</li>
<li>The LIC of India has the authority to operate this scheme.</li>
<li>Any Medical check-ups is not necessary to avail this policy.</li>
<li>It offers assured pension with a guaranteed interest rate of 8% per annum for up to 10 years –</li>
<li>You can opt for monthly, quarterly, half-yearly, and yearly pension – depends on how you’d like to receive it.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Vayoshreshtha Samman</strong> –</p>
<p>This scheme focuses on those seniors who have made significant contributions in their disciplines and recognized their efforts.</p>
<p>It was upgraded to the National Award in 2013, and since then, awards have been granted below thirteen categories.</p>
<h4><strong><img alt="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/old-age-poverty/" class="alignnone wp-image-636195" height="340" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 629px) 100vw, 629px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-1-300x162.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-1-300x162.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-1.jpg 746w" width="629"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Social security pensions, of course, are just the first step towards a dignified life for the elderly. They also need other support and facilities such as health care, disability aids and assistance with daily tasks, recreation opportunities and a good social life. They can be the active contributor to the economy having the years of experience and mentorship to the demographic dividend.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question Q.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Discuss the challenges before our elderly today? What steps have been taken by government to address these challenges?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/old-age/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>[pib] Indian Navy participates in Exercise Kakadu hosted by Australia</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/exercise-kakadu/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ex Kakadu</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p>INS Satpura and a P8 I Maritime Patrol Aircraft of the Indian Navy reached Darwin in Australia on for participation in the multinational Exercise Kakadu – 2022, hosted by the Royal Australian Navy.</p>
<h4><strong>Exercise KAKADU</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/prelims-spotlight-important-submarines-and-naval-ships/">Exercise</a> KAKADU, which <strong><u>started in 1993</u></strong>, is the premier multilateral regional maritime engagement exercise hosted by the Royal Australian Navy (RAN) and supported by the Australian Air Force.</li>
<li>The exercise is <strong><u>held biennially in Darwin</u></strong> and the Northern Australian Exercise Areas (NAXA).</li>
<li>It <strong><u>derives its name from Kakadu National Park</u></strong>, which is a protected area in the northern territory of Australia, 171 km south-east of Darwin</li>
<li>During the exercise, professional exchanges in harbour and diverse range of activities at sea, including complex surface, sub-surface and air operations would enable sharing of best practices and honing of operational skills.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>India’s presence at the exercise</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian Navy’s participation in KAKADU provides an excellent opportunity to engage with regional partners and undertake multinational maritime activities ranging from constabulary operations to high-end maritime warfare in a combined environment</li>
<li>It is aimed at enhancing interoperability and developing of common understanding of procedures for maritime operations gaining importance with the Indo-Pacific narrative.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="AgJlNxC8j2"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/prelims-spotlight-important-submarines-and-naval-ships/">[Prelims Spotlight] Important Submarines and Naval Ships</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="AgJlNxC8j2" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/prelims-spotlight-important-submarines-and-naval-ships/embed/#?secret=UigWdCg5kh#?secret=AgJlNxC8j2" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Prelims Spotlight] Important Submarines and Naval Ships” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/exercise-kakadu/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre adds 4 new tribes to Scheduled Tribes (ST) List</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/new-tribes-to-scheduled-tribes-list/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Tribes in news</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Union Cabinet under the chairmanship of PM has approved the addition of four tribes to the list of Scheduled Tribes (ST), including those from Himachal Pradesh, Tamil Nadu and Chhattisgarh.</p>
<h4>Which tribes are we talking about?</h4>
<ol>
<li><strong><u>Hatti </u></strong>tribe in the Trans-Giri area of Sirmour district in Himachal Pradesh</li>
<li><strong><u>Narikoravan</u></strong> and <strong><u>Kurivikkaran</u></strong> hill tribes of Tamil Nadu and</li>
<li><strong><u>Binjhia</u></strong> tribe in Chhattisgarh, which was listed as ST in Jharkhand and Odisha but not in Chhattisgarh</li>
</ol>
<h4>Other tribes in news</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Cabinet also approved ‘<span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Betta-Kuruba</strong></span>’ as a synonym for the Kadu Kuruba tribe In Karnataka.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who are the Scheduled Tribes?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The term ‘<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/what-is-the-reason-for-special-provisions-for-the-scheduled-tribes-in-the-constitution-of-india-are-these-provisions-successful-in-ameliorating-their-conditions-250-words/">Scheduled Tribes’</a> first appeared in the Constitution of India.</li>
<li><strong><u>Article 366 (25)</u></strong> defined scheduled tribes as “such tribes or tribal communities or parts of or groups within such tribes or tribal communities as are deemed under Article 342 to be Scheduled Tribes for the purposes of this constitution”.</li>
<li><strong><u>Article 342</u></strong> prescribes procedure to be followed in the matter of specification of scheduled tribes.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Among the tribal groups, several have adapted to modern life but there are tribal groups who are more vulnerable.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Dhebar Commission (1973)</u></strong> created a separate category “Primitive Tribal Groups (PTGs)” which was renamed in 2006 as “<strong><u>Particularly Vulnerable Tribal Groups (PVTGs</u></strong>)”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How are STs notified?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The first specification of Scheduled Tribes in relation to a particular State/ Union Territory is by a notified order of the President, after consultation with the State governments concerned.</li>
<li>These orders can be modified subsequently only through an Act of Parliament.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Status of STs in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Census 2011 has revealed that there are said to be 705 ethnic groups notified as Scheduled Tribes (STs).</li>
<li>Over 10 crore Indians are notified as STs, of which 1.04 crore live in urban areas.</li>
<li>The STs constitute 8.6% of the population and 11.3% of the rural population.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="uvIVi0e0Qc"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/what-is-the-reason-for-special-provisions-for-the-scheduled-tribes-in-the-constitution-of-india-are-these-provisions-successful-in-ameliorating-their-conditions-250-words/">What is the reason for special provisions for the Scheduled Tribes in the constitution of India? Are these provisions successful in ameliorating their conditions? (250 Words)</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="uvIVi0e0Qc" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/what-is-the-reason-for-special-provisions-for-the-scheduled-tribes-in-the-constitution-of-india-are-these-provisions-successful-in-ameliorating-their-conditions-250-words/embed/#?secret=Y52cNVyCdp#?secret=uvIVi0e0Qc" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“What is the reason for special provisions for the Scheduled Tribes in the constitution of India? Are these provisions successful in ameliorating their conditions? (250 Words)” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/new-tribes-to-scheduled-tribes-list/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How the National Logistics Policy will speed up lumbering freight sector?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/how-the-national-logistics-policy-will-speed-up-lumbering-freight-sector/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NLP</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="logistics" class="alignnone wp-image-636221" height="263" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logistics-300x148.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logistics-300x148.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logistics.jpg 684w" width="533"/></strong></p>
<p>The government will announce the National Logistics Policy (NLP) this week, aiming to bring down logistics costs and address challenges plaguing importers and exporters.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Logistics? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Logistics refers to the overall process of managing <strong><u>how resources are acquired, stored, and transported</u></strong> to their final destination.</li>
<li>It involves identifying prospective distributors and suppliers and determining their effectiveness and accessibility.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need a logistics policy?</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="logistics" class="alignnone wp-image-636220" height="273" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 438px) 100vw, 438px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist-300x187.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist-300x187.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist-768x479.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist.jpg 827w" width="438"/></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Organizing and consolidating the sector:</strong> India’s logistics sector is largely unorganized and fragmented.</li>
<li><strong>Reducing logistics cost:</strong> This is why the country’s logistics costs are as high as 14-15% of the GDP, against 7-8% in developed nations such as the Singapore and the US, who leverage it to boost exports. The NLP aims to bring down India’s logistics cost to 8% in the next five years.</li>
<li><strong>Preventing waste of perishable items:</strong> As per some estimates in India, about 16% of agri-production is wasted at different stages of the supply chain.</li>
<li><strong>Warehousing development:</strong> Moreover, due to factors such as limited capacity and availability of warehouses, the cost of transaction increases.</li>
<li><strong>Multi-modal integration:</strong> The new policy is going about simplification, technology and will have a multimodal approach that will combine rail, water, and air — all modes of transport.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What role will technology play?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Advanced analytics:</strong> The NLP will aim to harness technologies such as AI and blockchain. It aims to create a data analytics centre for driving greater transparency and continuous monitoring of key logistics metrics.</li>
<li><strong>Single window portal:</strong> Under NLP, a portal will be created, where service providers such as warehousing providers, shipping experts, transporters, customs brokers, and various governmental agencies will be unified.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Will it boost cooperation between ministries?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Unifying multiple departments:</strong> Currently, the logistics value chain is managed by several ministries—road transport and highways, shipping, railways, and civil aviation.</li>
<li><strong>Single-point clearances:</strong> Agencies like the Central Drug Standard Control Organization and the Food Safety and Standard Authority of India provide clearances.</li>
<li><strong>Nationwide integration:</strong> The NLP could enhance their integration at the central level.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What about reducing the carbon footprint?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Energy-efficient transportation:</strong> The draft logistics policy lays emphasis on the shift to more energy-efficient means of transportation, as well as the use of greener fuels which could reduce the supply chain’s carbon footprint.</li>
<li><strong>Vehicular emission reduction:</strong> Moreover, the draft policy, released earlier, emphasized creating regulations for controlling vehicular noise, emissions, and wastage.</li>
<li><strong>Green warehousing principles:</strong> The new logistics policy also aims to incorporate green principles in the functioning of warehouses which contribute to nearly 10% of the logistics costs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Will it change India’s commodity transport?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Transport of crucial commodities:</strong> The proposed policy aims to focus on the transport of crucial commodities such as coal, steel, iron ore, food grains, steel, cement, fruits and vegetables.</li>
<li><strong>Creating nationwide clusters:</strong> The current logistical network for transporting them is mainly confined to regional clusters.</li>
<li><strong>Integrating national supply-chains:</strong> The NLP could help establish a link between the place of origin, and destination place and integrate the supply on a national level.</li>
<li><strong>Optimum logistics identification:</strong> The draft also proposes identification of the right mode of transport for each of these commodities to minimise losses during transport.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/how-the-national-logistics-policy-will-speed-up-lumbering-freight-sector/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Hindi not a competitor of regional languages: Home Minister</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hindi-not-a-competitor-regional-languages/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>National language debate</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-636219" height="223" sizes="(max-width: 426px) 100vw, 426px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hindi-300x157.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hindi-300x157.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hindi.jpg 500w" width="426"/></strong></p>
<p>Union Home Minister has appealed to guardians to speak to children in their mother tongue to enable them to learn Hindi without much effort, on the Hindi Divas.</p>
<h4>What did HM say on Hindi?</h4>
<ul>
<li>He said it was time that <strong><u>inferiority complex around Indian languages</u></strong>, instilled by the British, was overthrown from people’s conscience with the help of regional languages and Hindi.</li>
<li>He also said that <strong><u>Hindi was not a competitor but a “friend” of all the other regional languages</u></strong> in the country and they were mutually dependent on each other for their growth.</li>
<li>He said there was a concerted <strong><u>disinformation campaign to pit Hindi against other languages</u></strong> such as Marathi and Tamil, and underlined the need to strengthen local languages with Hindi.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Debate over Hindi</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Between September 12 and 14, 1949, that the Constituent Assembly debated the status of India’s languages.</li>
<li>Among the issues that were discussed were the use of the term ‘<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-national-language-debate/">national language’</a> instead of ‘official’ language.</li>
<li>Hindi author Seth Govind Das, who represented the Central Provinces and Berar, argued for ‘one language and one script’ and suggested that Hindi should replace English at the earliest.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the status of Hindi?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Finally, the Constituent Assembly adopted what was known as “<strong><u>Munshi-Ayyangar Formula</u></strong>.”</li>
<li>According to this, Hindi in the Devnagari script would be the official language of the Union.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Official, not national</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>English would continue to be used for all official purposes for the next 15 years, to enable a smooth transition for non-Hindi speaking states.</li>
<li>The deadline was 26 January 1965.</li>
<li>Under Article 343 of the Constitution, the official language of the Union shall be Hindi in Devanagari script.</li>
<li>The international form of Indian numerals will be used for official purposes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why has language become a sensitive issue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Self-identification:</strong> A strong identification with one’s regional language and an underlying fear of homogenisation is at the heart of the national language question in India. An individual conceptualises and communicates his thoughts in a language, enabling him to be an active part of society.</li>
<li><strong>Language defines primary group:</strong> People identify with one another based on language, thus giving them a primary group. A nation is the largest primary group that once can address.</li>
<li><strong>Learning abilities at stake:</strong> The dangers of imposing a language are manifold. It can affect the learning ability of non-native speakers thereby affecting their self-confidence.</li>
<li><strong>Threats to endangered languages:</strong> It can also endanger other languages and dialects and reduce diversity.</li>
<li><strong>Threats to diversity:</strong> National integration cannot come at the cost of people’s linguistic identities. Language is integral to culture and therefore privileging Hindi over all other languages spoken in India takes away from its diversity.</li>
<li><strong>Promises made by Constituent Assembly:</strong> Then PM Pt. Nehru had promised that Hindi would only serve as a linking language and it would not be imposed on non-Hindi speaking states as long as they were against it.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Benefits of having a national language</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Wide range of speakers:</strong> Hindi is still the most widely spoken language in the country with an estimated 258 million people declaring that Hindi is their native language and millions more comfortable with Hindi.</li>
<li><strong>Language as a unifying language:</strong> A complete usage of Hindi language whilst respecting the various native languages would also ensure better coordination and cooperation among all the states and act as a strong unifying factor and eliminate all regional differences.</li>
<li><strong>Reputation at international fora:</strong> When countries like Germany, Japan, France, Italy etc. use their respective language as a medium of communication even during International forums not only has the reputation of those countries have greatly enhanced but also those languages have gained a huge reputation worldwide.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues with Hindi</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inherent opposition to Hindi:</strong> The Constituent Assembly was bitterly divided on the question, with members from States that did not speak Hindi initially opposing the declaration of Hindi as a national language.</li>
<li><strong>Fear of imposition:</strong> Opponents were against English being done away with, fearing that it may lead to Hindi domination in regions that did not speak the language.</li>
<li><strong>Symbol of identity politics:</strong> The approach towards linguistic policy seems to be driven more by the politics of identity than values of aspiration or accommodation.</li>
<li><strong>Favour for majoritarianism:</strong> The primary argument in favour of Hindi has been reduced to assertions of slim majoritarianism.</li>
<li><strong>Few speakers, still dominant:</strong> Even then, there are concerns about the claim based on mere numerical strength, as only 25 per cent of Indians seem to recognise Hindi as their mother tongue (Census 2011).</li>
<li><strong>Demographic barriers:</strong> Today nearly 35% of people are migrating daily for work. In such a situation, we have to conceptualise a new form of language identity for our states.</li>
<li><strong>Economic barriers:</strong> Any idea of one link language, whether Hindi or English, will be economically disastrous for India. It will slow down migration and reduce the ease of capital flow.</li>
<li><strong>Multiple dialects:</strong> Only five states in India have Hindi as their’ native language’. However, in those states, too, the dialects of Hindi are associated with locals and their communities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why Hindi cannot be the national language?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multiple dialects:</strong> Hindi has largely been influenced by Persian — and then English, among other languages. Also, when the languages were enumerated, Hindi subsumed Bhojpuri, which is spoken by a little over five crore people.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inefficacy of Sanskrit:</strong> There were demands to make Sanskrit the official language, while some argued in favour of ‘Hindustani’.</li>
<li><strong>Issue over Script:</strong> There were differences of opinion over the script too. When opinion veered towards accepting Hindi, proponents of the language wanted the ‘Devanagari’ script to be adopted both for words and numerals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why this issue needs a rational consideration?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Linguistic chauvinism:</strong> Various policies on language have been framed both by the central and state governments that have been termed as forms of linguistic chauvinism.  Ex. Obsession for Marathi in Mumbai</li>
<li><strong>Secular fabric under threat:</strong> The states’ fear of the central government’s ideology of monopolising faith, education, and language will adversely affect the Indian political system, which is based on pluralism and accommodation.</li>
<li><strong>Monolingualism can prove disastrous: </strong>If there is a mechanical and monolithic idea of unity followed by any entity, such an entity generally generates great hostility beyond its immediate borders.  In neighbouring Bangladesh – then East Pakistan – the language movement against the imposition of Urdu on Bengali speakers was a key driver of Pakistan splitting into two nations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Language as a skill:</strong> Language should be looked at as an important skill to operate in a world which is more connected today than at any other point in time.</li>
<li><strong>Language not a cultural burden:</strong> A united nation has to have space for diversity. India is united in its diversity. Diversity is a great philosophical idea and should never be seen as a cultural burden.</li>
<li><strong>Linguistic heritage needs priority:</strong> This is not to contend that our linguistic heritage should be neglected or trivialised. Our metropolises must be recognized as multilingual entities.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hindi-not-a-competitor-regional-languages/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>