<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 18:19:44 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Adani’s global footprint and India’s infrastructure diplomacy   </title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/infrastructure-diplomacy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Infrastructure diplomacy</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="infrastructure diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-639689" height="317" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 598px) 100vw, 598px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1602768183608-300x159.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1602768183608-300x159.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1602768183608.jpg 600w" width="598"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>From mines to ports and logistics, the Adani conglomerate has been expanding across sectors, regions. This has gone hand in hand with India’s diplomatic and strategic outreach towards infrastructure diplomacy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is infrastructure?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Infrastructure is the set of facilities and systems that serve a country, city, or other area, and encompasses the services and facilities necessary for its economy, households and firms to function.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/infrastructure-sector-in-india-definitions-growth-and-infrastructure-linkage/"><strong>What are the features of infrastructure?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Power and the source of its production such as coal and oil;</li>
<li>Roads and road transport;</li>
<li>Railways;</li>
<li>Communication, especially telecommunication;</li>
<li>Ports and airports; and.</li>
<li>For agriculture, irrigation constitutes the important infrastructure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="infrastructure diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-639690" height="488" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 559px) 100vw, 559px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/word-image148-300x262.png" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/word-image148-300x262.png 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/word-image148-1024x895.png 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/word-image148-768x671.png 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/word-image148-1030x900.png 1030w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/word-image148.png 1046w" width="559"/>What is infrastructure diplomacy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Infrastructure diplomacy is to promote infrastructure cooperation and economic ties overseas through political means and to enhance political trust between countries via collaboration in infrastructure development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>“Several foreign governments are now approaching us to work in their geographies and help build their infrastructure. Therefore, in 2022, we also laid the foundation to seek a broader expansion beyond India’s boundaries,” chairman and founder of the Adani group Gautam Adani,<strong><a href="https://indianexpress.com/article/business/gautam-adani-second-most-richest-billionaire-forbes-list-bernard-arnault-jeff-bezos-elon-musk-8154481/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">now the world’s third-richest person</a>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="infrastructure diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-639691" height="364" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Adani-300x168.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Adani-300x168.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Adani-768x430.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Adani.jpeg 770w" width="650"/>Background </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Foreign presence much earlier</strong>: In fact, the Adani group had been scouting abroad much earlier. Since 2010, the Adani group has been in Australia, developing the Carmichael coal mine in Queensland.</li>
<li><strong>A greenfield multi-purpose port:</strong> In 2017, Adani Ports and Special Economic Zones (Ltd) signed an MoU for a greenfield multi-purpose port for handling containers at Carey Island in Selangor state, about 50 km southwest of Kuala Lumpur.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is situation now?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Company pursue international infrastructure projects aggressively</strong>: The last two years, however, have seen the company pursue international infrastructure projects aggressively. In May 2022, APSEZ made a winning bid of $1.18 billion for Israeli state-owned Haifa Port, jointly with Israeli chemicals and logistics firm Gadot.</li>
<li><strong>Strategic joint investments</strong>: In August this year, APSEZ and Abu Dhabi’s AD Ports Group signed MoU for “strategic joint investments” in Tanzania. The new ASEZ-AD MoU will look at a bouquet of infrastructure projects besides Bagamoyo in the East African Indian Ocean nation — rail, maritime services, digital services and industrial zones<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>India’s strategic objectives than has been possible so far</strong>: Is it just a coincidence that Adani’s global expansion closely shadows the Chinese footprint along its Belt and Road Initiative? Or is it that as <a href="https://indianexpress.com/section/cities/delhi/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Delhi</a>competes with China for influence in the neighbourhood and beyond, the Adani group’s size, resources and capacity are seen as a key element in achieving India’s strategic objectives than has been possible so far.</li>
<li><strong>India’s infrastructure diplomacy</strong>: Is now becoming identified the world over with one company.</li>
<li><strong>Public and private investment to bridge gaps</strong>: For the Adani group, described as India’s biggest ports and logistics company, there couldn’t be a better time. As the Quad grouping of Australia, India, Japan, and the US, competes with China in the Indo-Pacific, it has committed “to catalyse infrastructure delivery” by putting more than $50 billion on the table for “assistance and investment” in the Indo-Pacific over the next five years and “drive public and private investment to bridge gaps”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="infrastructure diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-639692" height="484" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 859px) 100vw, 859px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213.jpg 1600w" width="859"/>Implications of infrastructure diplomacy</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Win-Win deal</strong>: Adani’s new “no-hands” model of doing business with neighbours a power plant in Jharkhand, exporting all its output to Bangladesh has been seen as a “win-win” deal.</li>
<li><strong>Economic interests lie at the heart of geopolitics:</strong> The link between diplomacy and commercial interests has generated its share of debate, especially in the US, where its diplomats, intelligence agencies and military interventions abroad have actively pushed the interests of big business first the hunt for cheaper raw materials, then for markets abroad, then to shift industry where manpower was cheaper. As seen in the new age trading blocs the US-led IPEF, and the Chinese dominated RCEP economic interests lie at the heart of geopolitics.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At a time when global rivalries are growing sharper in the shadow of the war in Europe, and as India looks out for its own interests, pushing powerful corporates to the centre-stage of its diplomacy, whether it is to build ports, buy or sell weapons or make chips, is inevitable.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Economic interests lie at the heart of geopolitics. Analyse this statement in context of India’s active push for infrastructure diplomacy by including private conglomerates like Adani in it.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/infrastructure-diplomacy/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Constitutional Breakdown in Nepal</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/constitutional-breakdown-in-nepal/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India-Nepal Relations</p></div></div><p><img alt="nepal" class="alignnone wp-image-639720 size-full" height="379" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 724px) 100vw, 724px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nepal.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nepal.jpg 724w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nepal-300x157.jpg 300w" width="724"/></p>
<p>Nepal is in a constitutional crisis with major organs of the state confronting each other as the Chief Justice is under undeclared house arrest and the PM openly criticizing the President.</p>
<h4>Nepal polity in turmoil</h4>
<ul>
<li>Prime Minister who is backed by the chiefs of four major coalition partners, is at loggerheads with President.</li>
<li>The President might seek to rule as an extra-constitutional authority beyond the sanction and imagination of the Constitution that completed six years last week.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Genesis of the crisis: Row over Citizenship</h4>
<ul>
<li>The current crisis began after President refused to ratify Nepal’s citizenship bill, which was sent to her twice after it was passed by both Houses of Parliament over the span of a month.</li>
<li>The bill seeks to give citizenship by birth and by descent to an estimated 500,000 individuals.</li>
<li>It was also sought to provide non-voting citizenship to non-resident Nepalis living in non-SAARC countries.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Constitutional crisis in Nepal: A backgrounder</h4>
<ul>
<li>Nepal transitioned into a democracy beginning with the fall of the monarchy in 2006 and the subsequent election of the Maoist government in 2008.</li>
<li>The emergence of the multiparty system was followed by the adoption of a constitution on September 20, 2015.</li>
<li>All Nepalese citizens born before this date got naturalised citizenship.</li>
<li>But their children remained without citizenship as that was to be guided by a federal law which has not yet been framed.</li>
<li>This amendment Act was expected to pave the way to citizenship for many such stateless youth as well as their parents.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the issues with the Act?</h4>
<p><strong>Ans. <u>Gender bias</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The main criticism against the Citizenship Amendment Act, 2006 is that it goes against established parameters of gender justice.</li>
<li>According to Article 11(2b), a person born to a father or a mother with Nepalese citizenship can get citizenship by descent.</li>
<li>Another article says a person who is born to a Nepalese mother (who has lived in the country) and an unidentified father will also get citizenship by descent.</li>
<li>But this section appears humiliating for a mother as she has to declare that her husband is unidentified for the child to be eligible for citizenship.</li>
<li>In case of a Nepalese father, such declarations are not required.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why has the President refused to sign the Act?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Bhandari is the first female President of Nepal.</li>
<li>Her refusal to sign the Act has drawn attention to certain sections in the constitution that thrusts greater responsibility on women.</li>
<li>For example, Article 11 (5) says that a person who is born to a Nepalese mother and an unidentified father can be granted citizenship by descent.</li>
<li>Next, it says that in case the unidentified father turns out to be a foreigner, the citizenship by descent would be converted to naturalised citizenship.</li>
<li>Furthermore, it supports punitive action against the mother if the father is found later.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Indian connection to the issue</h4>
<ul>
<li>There is an unarticulated concern in the orthodox sections that Nepalese men, particularly from the Terai region, continue to marry women from northern India.</li>
<li>These people feel that Nepalese identity would be undermined.</li>
<li>Because of this “Beti-Roti” (Nepalese men marrying Indian women) issue, many women could not become citizens of Nepal.</li>
<li>They were subjected to the infamous seven-year cooling off period before they could apply for citizenship in Nepal.</li>
<li>As such women were stateless, children of such families were also often found to be without Nepalese citizenship.</li>
<li>However, the new amendments have done away with the cooling off period for these stateless women.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/constitutional-breakdown-in-nepal/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>On the trail of alarming rabies cases which is having serious apprehensions</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rabies/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of virus</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Human health</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="rabies" class="alignnone wp-image-639695" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 689px) 100vw, 689px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/p032g69z-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/p032g69z-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/p032g69z-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/p032g69z.jpg 976w" width="689"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The death of a 12-year-old girl in Pathanamthitta has sharpened the focus on the rising number of rabies cases and the growing population of stray dogs in Kerala</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is rabies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The rabies virus attacks the central nervous system of the host, and in humans, it can cause a range of debilitating symptoms including states of anxiety and confusion, partial paralysis, agitation, hallucinations, and, in its final phases, a symptom called “hydrophobia,” or a fear of water.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are rabies caused by?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Rabies is a preventable viral disease most often transmitted through the bite of a rabid animal. The rabies virus infects the central nervous system of mammals, ultimately causing disease in the brain and death.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Can rabies person survive?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Once clinical signs of rabies appear, the disease is nearly always fatal, and treatment is typically supportive. Less than 20 cases of human survival from clinical rabies have been documented.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How long can a human live with rabies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Death usually occurs 2 to 10 days after first symptoms. Survival is almost unknown once symptoms have presented, even with intensive care.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="rabies" class="alignnone wp-image-639696" height="574" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 574px) 100vw, 574px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infographic-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infographic-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infographic-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infographic-768x766.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infographic.jpg 876w" width="574"/>Facts on rabies </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>What animal has the most rabies?</strong></li>
<li><strong>Bats</strong></li>
<li><strong>Wild animals accounted for 92.7% of reported cases of rabies in 2018. Bats were the most frequently reported rabid wildlife species (33% of all animal cases during 2018), followed by raccoons (30.3%), skunks (20.3%), and foxes (7.2%).</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="rabies" class="alignnone wp-image-639698" height="417" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 626px) 100vw, 626px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/straydogs-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/straydogs-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/straydogs.jpg 621w" width="626"/>What is the issue?                                   </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>There is a blame game over the rising rabies cases:</strong> With the rabies deaths causing panic and reports of residents killing stray dogs through poisoning and strangulation, there is a blame game over the rising canine population and rabies cases. Some legal experts blame it on conflicts in the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act, 1960 and the Animal Birth Control (Dogs) Rules, 2001; others point to the flawed implementation of birth control measures.</li>
<li><strong>Legal battle over the issue in the Supreme Court:</strong> Canine culling campaigners and advocates of animal rights are also engaged in a protracted legal battle over the issue in the Supreme Court. V.K. Biju, a lawyer of the Supreme Court, who brought the issue of the “stray dog menace” before the apex court, contends that the root cause is the enactment of the Rules, which according to him, were passed in contravention of the parent Act, the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act.</li>
<li><strong>Existence of stray dogs has adversely affected the fundamental rights of citizens</strong>: Biju says that while the Act stands for the “destruction” of stray dogs, the rules are against the “destruction” of stray dogs, including the rabies affected ones, besides providing specific protection of stray dogs. In his submission before the Supreme Court, he argues that the existence of stray dogs has adversely affected the fundamental rights of citizens, i.e. the right to life and free movement.</li>
<li><strong>The quashing of the Rules to make India free of stray dogs</strong>: In his writ petition filed before the apex court, Biju has sought orders for the strict implementation of the Act and the quashing of the Rules to make India free of stray dogs.</li>
<li><strong>Animal rights campaigners are apprehensive</strong>: In the light of this, animal rights campaigners are apprehensive over the campaign to cull dogs to check rabies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="rabies" class="alignnone wp-image-639697" height="505" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infection-from-dog-to-human-300x261.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infection-from-dog-to-human-300x261.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infection-from-dog-to-human.jpg 500w" width="580"/>How can we prevent rabies in animals?</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li>First, visit your veterinarian with your pet on a regular basis and keep rabies vaccinations up-to-date for all cats, ferrets, and dogs.</li>
<li>Second, maintain control of your pets by keeping cats and ferrets indoors and keeping dogs under direct supervision.</li>
<li>Third, spay or neuter your pets to help reduce the number of unwanted pets that may not be properly cared for or vaccinated regularly.</li>
<li>Finally, call animal control to remove all stray animals from your neighbourhood since these animals may be unvaccinated or ill.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>How can we prevent rabies in humans?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Leave all wildlife alone.</li>
<li>Know the risk: contact with infected bats is the leading cause of rabies deaths in people followed by exposure to rabid dogs while traveling internationally.</li>
<li>Wash animal bites or scratches immediately with soap and water.</li>
<li>If you are bitten, scratched, or unsure, talk to a healthcare provider about whether you need postexposure prophylaxis. Rabies in people is 100% preventable through prompt appropriate medical care.</li>
<li>Vaccinate your pets to protect them and your family.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/a-one-health-approach-that-targets-people-animals/"><strong>Initiatives by Government to curb Neglected Tropical Diseases</strong></a></h4>
<p><a href="https://ncdc.gov.in/index1.php?lang=1&amp;level=1&amp;sublinkid=146&amp;lid=150" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>National Rabies Control Programme</strong></a>: This programme is being restructured as Integrated National Rabies Control Programme under ‘One Health Approach’, with a aim to provide vaccination to stray dogs and free vaccines through Government hospitals.</p>
<p><strong>Way forward</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Think globally, act locally. Study and adopt global ‘best-practices’ after customising them to local needs.</li>
<li>Apply integrated approach. Follow a holistic strategy.</li>
<li>Ensure efficient and effective collaboration across various government departments.</li>
<li>Partner with Civil Society Organisations (especially with WASH – Water, Sanitation and Hygiene – sector) for ground-level implementation and monitoring.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What is rabies? What ethical challenges are involved in culling of stray dogs? Explain the control measures for the same.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rabies/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why our urban centres need to be better planned</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-centres/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>smart city mission</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>urban planning</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="urban centres " class="alignnone wp-image-639704" height="677" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 875px) 100vw, 875px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-300x232.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-300x232.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1024x793.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-768x595.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1536x1190.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1162x900.jpg 1162w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1200x929.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1980x1534.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities..jpg 2000w" width="875"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian urban centres need to plan for migration, climate change. Healthcare, affordable housing, sustainability and inclusion hold the key reimagining them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does urban planning mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Urban planning encompasses the preparation of plans for and the regulation and management of towns, cities, and metropolitan regions. It attempts to organize socio-spatial relations across different scales of government and governance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are ‘Happy Cities’?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A term that follows the Green City, Sustainable City, Liveable City, in the lingo of urban planning</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="urban centres " class="alignnone wp-image-639706" height="451" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Kampung_Admiralty_by_Ramboll_Studio_Dreiseitl__WOHA_and_Storm._Image__Patrick_Bingham-Hall_1-300x209.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Kampung_Admiralty_by_Ramboll_Studio_Dreiseitl__WOHA_and_Storm._Image__Patrick_Bingham-Hall_1-300x209.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Kampung_Admiralty_by_Ramboll_Studio_Dreiseitl__WOHA_and_Storm._Image__Patrick_Bingham-Hall_1.jpg 750w" width="647"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/smart-cities-mission-and-the-public-health/">What is a smart city?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A smart city is one that uses information and communication technologies to enhance citizen engagement. It is a neo-vision which seeks to improve the delivery of services in urban areas. The following story maps out the steps being taken by India to explore this concept in practice.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Fast Facts -Urbanization in India</strong></h4>
<p>Most Urbanized States: Tamil Nadu 43.9%; Maharashtra 4%; Gujarat  37.4%.</p>
<p>3 out of world’s 21 mega cities: Mumbai (19 mill); Delhi (15 mill); Kolkata (14 mill)</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Global best practices in urban planning </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garden_city_movement" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>The Garden City movement:</strong> </a>In the West, the Garden City movement (initiated by Ebenezer Howard in 1898) sought to decentralise the working environment in the city centre with a push for providing healthier living spaces for factory workers. The ideal garden city was planned on a concentric pattern with open spaces, public parks and boulevards, housing 32,000 people on 6,000 acres, linked to a central city with over 50,000 people. Once a garden city reached maximum capacity, another city would be developed nearby.</li>
<li><strong>Neighbourhood concept</strong>: In the US, the garden city movement evolved into the neighbourhood concept, where residential houses and streets were organised around a local school or community centre, with a push for lowering traffic and providing safe roads. London has a metropolitan green belt around the city, covering 5,13,860 hectares of land, to offset pollution and congestion and maintain biodiversity. Why can’t Indian cities have something similar, instead of ring roads and urban sprawls?</li>
<li><strong>La ville du quart d’heure: </strong>Paris has taken this forward with the “15-minute city” (‘la ville du quart d’heure’). The idea is rather simple, every Parisian should be able to do their shopping, work, and recreational activities and fulfil their cultural needs within a 15-minute walk or bike ride this means that the number of vehicular trips gets reduced significantly.</li>
<li><strong>Investment in pedestrian infrastructure and non-motorised transport zones</strong>: A city would then be planned for pedestrians, instead of cars and motors. This requires an extensive usage of mixed-use developments, along with investment in pedestrian infrastructure and non-motorised transport zones. Instead of widening highways, this approach would push for widening pedestrian walkways.</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="urban centres " class="alignnone wp-image-639707" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-300x208.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-300x208.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-1024x711.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-768x533.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-1200x833.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000.jpg 1440w" width="560"/></p>
<h4><strong>What should be adopted for India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Every Indian city should ideally have a Master Plan</strong>: A strategic urban planning document which would be updated every decade or two. The document would entail how a city is supposed to grow, vertically and horizontally, across zones, while offering a high quality of life in a sustainable manner. Such plans would also consider poverty mitigation, affordable housing and liveability for urban migrants.</li>
<li><strong>Urban land use needs to be better</strong>: One look at satellite map imagery will show that India’s urban growth is increasingly haphazard, with informal, unplanned and sprawling neighbourhoods developing in paddy fields and along linear infrastructure (arterial roads, open spaces). India’s hidden urbanisation, driven partly by our stringent definition of the word, along with weak enforcement of building codes, has meant that the local government is often playing catch-up, unable to provide urban services and infrastructure to keep up with growth.</li>
<li><strong>Public land availability</strong>: Meanwhile, in places where there are formally recognised towns and urban neighbourhoods, outdated planning practices have meant that land utilisation is poor. Consider the case of Mumbai, where almost 1/4th of the land is open public space while over half of it is the underutilised space around buildings, which is enclosed by walls and hived off from public access. Such open spaces, if available, would help cities like Mumbai achieve similar ratios as globally benchmarked cities (Amsterdam, Barcelona) in public land availability (typically above 40 per cent).</li>
<li><strong>India’s urban density will also need to be thought through</strong>: Dense construction on the peripheries of our major cities (for instance, dense construction in Delhi’s suburbs, like Noida and Gurugram) will inevitably mean that public services are stretched and emissions (due to transportation to the main city) remain high. Such urbanisation will unavoidably lock India into a high emissions future while making our cities prone to extreme heat and flooding.</li>
<li><strong>Then there is climate change: </strong>According to the World Bank, climate change may reduce India’s GDP by 3 per cent, while depressing the living standards of its citizens by 2050. Many urban experts cite technological solutions that may save our cities a chain of sea walls, river embankments and reclamations, for instance from such potential calamities. However, structural engineering simply may not be an economically and environmentally feasible option everywhere instead, our focus must be on conservation.</li>
<li><strong>Climate resilience perspective</strong> Bengaluru, with its network of interconnected lakes, could have considered Bangkok-style ferries instead of draining out its lakes. All ongoing and upcoming urban infrastructure projects must be reconsidered from a future climate resilience perspective does the ongoing sea reclamation for the upcoming coastal road in Mumbai make sense if sea levels are rising?</li>
<li><strong>Establishing a sense of cityhood</strong>: By making a push for a city as a co-created space will also require building up institutional capacity.</li>
<li><strong>Addressing lack of town planning education: </strong>India would ideally require 3,00,000 town and country planners by 2031 (there are just 5,000 town planners currently). Much of this problem is fundamentally due to a lack of town planning education in the country there are just 26 institutes that provide this course, producing 700 town planners each year. We already have a shortage of 1.1 million planners. More schools are needed, with a push for local IITs and NITs to have a standalone planning department. With over 8,000 towns and cities, there is a clear unmet need.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="urban centres" class="alignnone wp-image-639709" height="347" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 616px) 100vw, 616px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432-1-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432-1.jpg 768w" width="616"/>Conclusion </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Our policymakers also need to be cognisant of the historical context of our urban development a push for glass buildings or utilising granite may not always be suitable for our cities. Why can’t our cities look distinctly Indian, inspired by our historical architecture? Renewing our cities will require us to rethink various urban topics, including urban design, urban healthcare, affordable housing, sustainability and inclusion among others. Our urban future depends on getting this right.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Renewing our cities will require us to rethink various urban topics, including urban design, urban healthcare, affordable housing, sustainability and inclusion among others. Elaborate.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-centres/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Nationwide Crackdown on PFI</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pfi-nationwide-crackdown-on-pfi/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PFI</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Terrorism and radicalization in India</p></div></div><p><img alt="pfi" class="alignnone wp-image-639719 size-full" height="415" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 712px) 100vw, 712px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nia.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nia.jpg 712w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nia-300x175.jpg 300w" width="712"/></p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/functioning-of-the-national-investigation-agency-nia/">National Investigation Agency (NIA)</a> has launched a massive nationwide search operation in connection with anti-terror activities linked to the Popular Front of India-PFI.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the Popular Front of India (PFI)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PFI was created in 2007 through the merger of three radicalists organisations in southern India, the National Democratic Front in Kerala, the Karnataka Forum for Dignity, and the Manitha Neethi Pasarai in Tamil Nadu.</li>
<li>A decision to bring the three outfits together was taken in November 2006 at a meeting in Kozhikode in Kerala.</li>
<li>The formation of the PFI was formally announced at a rally in Bengaluru during what was called the “Empower India Conference” on February 16, 2007.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Agenda of the PFI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PFI has projected itself as an organisation that fights for the rights of minorities, Dalits, and marginalised communities.</li>
<li>It has frequently targeted the alleged anti-people policies of the State even as these mainstream parties have accused one another of being in cahoots with the PFI to gather the support of Muslims at the time of elections.</li>
<li>The PFI has itself never contested elections.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Parallel organizations to PFI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2009, a political outfit named Social Democratic Party of India (SDPI) evolved out of the PFI, with the aim of taking up the political issues of Muslims, Dalits, and other marginalised communities.</li>
<li>The SDPI’s stated goal is advancement and uniform development of all the citizenry including Muslims, Dalits, Backward Classes and Adivasis and to share power fairly among all the citizens.</li>
<li>The PFI is a key provider of ground workers for the SDPI’s political activities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is PFI under crackdown?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Links to terror outfits</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Many volunteers of PFI are allegedly involved in terror funding, organising training camps, and radicalising people to join proscribed organisations.</li>
<li>It has been involved in carrying out social and Islamic religious work among Muslims on the lines of the work done by right-wing groups.</li>
<li>The PFI does not maintain records of its members, and it has been difficult for law enforcement agencies to pin crimes on the organisation after making arrests.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Promoting Radicalization</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The outfit is hostile to the consolidation across the country and the rise of a single non-secular party as the nation’s pre-eminent political and ideological force.</li>
<li>The post-2014 political landscape and the self-alienation of minorities has further pushed sections of the community towards groups like the PFI.</li>
<li>The outfit is also said to have a large number of supporters in Gulf countries who contribute handsomely to its kitty, something which is under the scanner of investigating agencies.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Hostility against state mechanism</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Starting out as an organisation primarily rooted in Kerala, Karnataka and Tamil Nadu, the PFI has spread its wings far and wide, with a presence in at least 18 states.</li>
<li>It has found particularly fertile ground in parts of Uttar Pradesh and Assam.</li>
<li>Authorities have accused the outfit of instigating and funding protests against the CAA and the National Register of Citizens.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Barbarism in the name of religion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The PFI has had the most visible presence in Kerala, where it has been repeatedly accused of murder, rioting, intimidation, and having links with terrorist organisations.</li>
<li>The Kerala government affidavit said PFI activists were involved in 27 cases of MURDER, mostly of CPM and RSS cadres, and that the motives were highly communal.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pfi-nationwide-crackdown-on-pfi/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>In news: Sittanavasal Rock Cave Temple</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/in-news-sittanavasal-rock-cave-temple/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Sittanavasal</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="Sittanavasal" class="alignnone wp-image-640535 size-full" height="569" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sittanavasal-1.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sittanavasal-1.jpg 800w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sittanavasal-1-300x213.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sittanavasal-1-768x546.jpg 768w" width="800"/></p>
<p>The Sittanavasal Rock Cave Temple, a major centre of Jain influence for 1,000 years just before the Christian era, is in need of better upkeep.</p>
<h4><strong>Sittanavasal</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sittanavasal is a small hamlet in Pudukkottai district of Tamil Nadu, India.</li>
<li>It is known for the Sittanavasal Cave, a 2nd-century Jain cave complex. From the 7th to the 9th century A.D., the village flourished as a Jain centre.</li>
<li>Sittanavasal is the name used synonymously for the hamlet and the hillock that houses the:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Arivar Kovil</strong> (temple of Arihants — Jains who conquered their senses)</li>
<li><strong>Ezhadipattam</strong> (a cavern with 17 polished rock beds), megalithic burial sites and the</li>
<li><strong>Navachunai</strong> tarn (small mountain lake) with a submerged shrine</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What makes it special?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The artwork on the ceiling of the sanctum and the ardha mandapam of Arivar Kovil is an early example of post-Ajanta cave paintings of the fourth to sixth centuries.</li>
<li>It was also done using the fresco-secco technique (a process that dispenses with preparation of the wall with wet plaster).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Features of the cave paintings</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ceiling paintings show ‘<strong><u>bhavyas’</u></strong> (exalted souls who work to achieve moksha or spiritual liberation) enjoying themselves in a pool, full of lotuses; today much of it is obscured by patchy plastering.</li>
<li>Faint outlines linger of dancing girls on the ‘<strong><u>ardha mandapam</u></strong>’ pillars.</li>
<li>The colours are a mixture of plant dyes and mineral elements such as <strong><u>lime, lamp black, and clay pigments</u></strong> such as ochre for yellow and terre verte for the greyish-green tints.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news now?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Unrestricted public access and general exposure to the elements have led to a gradual fading away of these paintings.</li>
<li>At the Ezhadipattam, inscriptions have been vandalised beyond recognition.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Also try this PYQ:</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Q.There are only two known examples of cave paintings of the Gupta period in ancient India. One of these is paintings of Ajanta caves. Where is the other surviving example of Gupta paintings?</strong></p>
<p>(a) Bagh caves</p>
<p>(b) Ellora caves</p>
<p>(c) Lomas Rishi cave</p>
<p>(d) Nasik caves</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>Post your answers here.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/in-news-sittanavasal-rock-cave-temple/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Odisha offering cash incentive for PVTGs Marriages</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/odisha-offering-cash-incentive-for-pvtgs-marriages-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PVTGS</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>Keeping the rampant child marriages among the Particularly Vulnerable Tribal Groups (PVTGs) of Odisha in mind, the State government is providing an incentive of ₹20,000 to the couples marrying after the age of 18 years.</p>
<h4><strong>Particularly Vulnerable Tribal Groups (PVTGs)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There are certain tribal communities who have declining or stagnant population, low level of literacy, pre-agricultural level of technology and are economically backward.</li>
<li>They generally inhabit remote localities having poor infrastructure and administrative support.</li>
<li>These groups are among the most vulnerable section of our society as they are few in numbers, have not attained any significant level of social and economic development.</li>
<li>75 such groups have been identified and categorized as Particularly Vulnerable Tribal Groups (PVTGs).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Origin of the concept</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Dhebar Commission (1960-1961)</u></strong> stated that within Scheduled Tribes there existed an inequality in the rate of development.</li>
<li>During the fourth Five Year Plan a sub-category was created within Scheduled Tribes to identify groups that considered to be at a lower level of development.</li>
<li>This was created based on the Dhebar Commission report and other studies.</li>
<li>This sub-category was named “Primitive tribal group”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Features of PVTGs</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The features of such a group include a:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Pre-agricultural system of existence</li>
<li>Practice of hunting and gathering</li>
<li>Zero or negative population growth</li>
<li>Extremely low level of literacy in comparison with other tribal groups</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Groups that satisfied any one of the criterion were considered as PTG.</li>
<li>In 2006 the government of India proposed to rename “Primitive tribal group” as Particularly vulnerable tribal group”.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this PYQ:</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Q.Consider the following statements about Particularly Vulnerable Tribal Groups (PVTGs) in India:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>PVTGs reside in 18 States and one Union Territory.</li>
<li>A stagnant or declining population is one of the criteria for determining PVTG status.</li>
<li>There are 95 PVTGs officially notified in the country so far.</li>
<li>Irular and Konda Reddi tribes are included in the list of PVTGs.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Which of the statements given above are correct? (CSP 2019)</strong></p>
<p>(a) 1, 2 and 3</p>
<p>(b) 2, 3 and 4</p>
<p><strong>(c) 1, 2 and 4</strong></p>
<p>(d) 1, 3 and 4</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/odisha-offering-cash-incentive-for-pvtgs-marriages-2/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Rohini RH-200: ISRO eyeing 200th successful launch of Rohini RH-200</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rohini-rh-200-isro-eyeing-200th-successful-launch-of-rohini-rh-200/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Rohini</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="rohini" class="alignnone wp-image-640536 size-full" height="437" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 591px) 100vw, 591px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rohini-1.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rohini-1.jpg 591w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rohini-1-300x222.jpg 300w" width="591"/></p>
<p>In a few weeks’ time, the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO) hopes to achieve a remarkable feat — the 200th successful launch of the Rohini RH-200 sounding rocket in a row.</p>
<h4>Rohini RH-200</h4>
<ul>
<li>RH-200 is a two-stage rocket capable of climbing to a height of 70 km bearing scientific payloads.</li>
<li>The first and second stages of RH-200 are powered by solid motors. The ‘200’ in the name denotes the diameter of the rocket in mm.</li>
<li>Other operational Rohini variants are RH-300 Mk-II and RH-560 Mk-III.</li>
<li>For years, the RH-200 rocket had used a polyvinyl chloride (PVC)-based propellant.</li>
<li>The first RH-200 to use a new propellant based on hydroxyl-terminated Polybutadiene (HTPB) was successfully flown from the TERLS in September 2020.</li>
<li>The first and second stages of RH200 rocket are powered by solid motors.</li>
<li>Since inception of RH200 rocket, both solid stages are processed using polyvinyl chloride (PVC) based propellant.</li>
<li>As compared to PVC based propellants, HTPB based propellant is more energetic, higher mechanical &amp; interface properties and has less defects due to lower processing temperature.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What basically is a Sounding Rocket?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A sounding rocket is an instrument-carrying rocket designed to take measurements and perform scientific experiments during its sub-orbital flight.</li>
<li>The rockets are used to launch instruments from 48 to 145 km above the surface of the Earth, the altitude generally between weather balloons and satellites.</li>
<li>The maximum altitude for balloons is about 40 km and the minimum for satellites is approximately 121 km.</li>
</ul>
<h4>History of sounding rockets in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sounding rockets have an important place in the ISRO story.</li>
<li>The first sounding rocket to be launched from Thumba was the American Nike-Apache — on November 21, 1963.</li>
<li>After that, two-stage rockets imported from Russia (M-100) and France (Centaure) were flown. The ISRO launched its own version — Rohini RH-75 — in 1967.</li>
<li>The ISRO has launched more than 1,600 RH-200 rockets so far.</li>
<li>Currently, the RH200, RH300 MkII and RH560 Mk-III rockets are operational which were developed during the early phase of our journey in rocketry.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rohini-rh-200-isro-eyeing-200th-successful-launch-of-rohini-rh-200/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>In news: Attorney-General (A-G) of India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/attorney-general-a-g-of-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Attorney General</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>A senior and renowned advocate has declined the offer from the Union government to be the next Attorney-General (A-G) of India as the incumbent AGI is set to retire this week.</p>
<h4><strong>Attorney General of India (AGI)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AGI is the Indian government’s chief legal advisor and is a primary lawyer in the Supreme Court of India.</li>
<li>They can be said to be the advocate from the government’s side.</li>
<li>They are appointed by the President of India on the advice of Union Cabinet under Article 76(1) of the Constitution and holds office during the pleasure of the President.</li>
<li>They must be a person qualified to be appointed as a Judge of the Supreme Court ( i.e. a judge of some high court for five years or an advocate of some high court for ten years or an eminent jurist, in the opinion of the President and must be a citizen of India.).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Functions and duties</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AGI is necessary for advising the Government of India on legal matters referred to them.</li>
<li>They also perform other legal duties assigned to them by the President.</li>
<li>The AGI has the right of audience in all Courts in India as well as the right to participate in the proceedings of the Parliament, though not to vote.</li>
<li>The AGI appears on behalf of the Government of India in all cases (including suits, appeals and other proceedings) in the Supreme Court in which GoI is concerned.</li>
<li>They also represent the Government of India in any reference made by the President to the Supreme Court under Article 143 of the Constitution.</li>
<li>The AG is assisted by a Solicitor General and four Additional Solicitors General.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Powers of AG<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AG can accept briefs but cannot appear against the Government.</li>
<li>They cannot defend an accused in criminal proceedings and accept the directorship of a company without the permission of the Government.</li>
<li>The AG is to be consulted only in legal matters of real importance and only after the Ministry of Law has been consulted.</li>
<li>All references to the AG are made by the Law Ministry.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Limitations to his powers<br/>
</strong></h4>
<p>The AG:</p>
<ul>
<li>should not advise or hold a brief against the Government of India</li>
<li>should not defend accused persons in criminal cases without the permission of the government of India</li>
<li>should not accept appointment as a director in any company without the permission of the government</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Office of AG across the world<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Unlike the Attorney General of the United States, the AGI does not have any executive authority.</li>
<li>Those functions are performed by the Law Minister of India.</li>
<li>Also, the AG is not a government servant and is not debarred from private legal practice.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/attorney-general-a-g-of-india/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Asian Palm Oil Alliance (APOA) formed by 5 South Asian Countries</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/asian-palm-oil-alliance-apoa-formed-by-5-south-asian-countries/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Palm Oil, APOA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>Edible oil trade associations from five palm oil importing countries in South Asia – India, Pakistan, Sri Lanka, Bangladesh and Nepal – on Thursday announced the setting up of Asian Palm Oil Alliance (APOA).</p>
<h4><strong>What is Oil Palm?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Palm oil is an edible vegetable oil derived from the mesocarp of the fruit of the oil palms.</li>
<li>The oil is used in food manufacturing, in beauty products, and as biofuel.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is APOA?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Through APOA, the countries aim at safeguarding the economic and business interests of the palm oil consuming countries and will work towards increasing the consumption of palm oil in member countries.</li>
<li>The idea is to gain collecting bargaining power and make imports sustainable.</li>
<li>APOA held its first general body meeting on the side-lines of the Globoil Summit.</li>
<li>The industry associations of Asian palm oil importing countries, unlike their counterparts in Europe, are not involved in shaping the global discourse on sustainable palm oil in a collective way.</li>
<li>The alliance would work towards ensuring that palm oil is recognised as a high-quality, economical, and healthy vegetable oil and to change the negative image of palm oil.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why such move?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s annual imports of edible oil is around 13-14 million tonne (MT).</li>
<li>Around 8 MT of palm oil is imported from Indonesia and Malaysia, while other oils, such as soya and sunflower, come from Argentina, Brazil, Ukraine and Russia.</li>
<li>Asia accounts for around 40% of the global palm oil consumption while Europe accounts for 12% of palm oil trade.</li>
<li>Indonesia and Malaysia are the biggest palm oil exporters in the world.</li>
<li>India is the largest importer of palm oil in Asia, accounting for 15% of global imports, followed by China (9%), Pakistan (4%) and Bangladesh (2%).</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ:</h4>
<p><strong>Q.Among the agricultural commodities imported by India, which one of the following accounts for the highest imports in terms of value in the last five years?</strong></p>
<p>(a) Spices</p>
<p>(b) Fresh fruits</p>
<p>(c) Pulses</p>
<p>(d) Vegetable oils</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/asian-palm-oil-alliance-apoa-formed-by-5-south-asian-countries/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why India Inc. needs a neurodiverse workplace ?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/neurodiverse/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>human right of neuro-diverse people</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="neurodiverse" class="alignnone wp-image-640541" height="562" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 423px) 100vw, 423px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/neurodiversity-226x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/neurodiversity-226x300.jpg 226w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/neurodiversity.jpg 386w" width="423"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Discrimination in employment is a worldwide phenomenon. Gender, ethnic, racist discrimination are well known but discrimination towards neurodiverse persons are hardly debated in public forums. Despite having special abilities companies are not using their potentials.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/what-is-neurodiversity-202111232645#:~:text=The%20word%20neurodiversity%20refers%20to,as%20ADHD%20or%20learning%20disabilities." rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>What is </strong><strong>neurodiversity?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Harvard Health Publishing defines, neurodiversity as a notion that every person interacts and experiences their surroundings differently; there is no right way of thinking, learning, or/and behaving. These differences should not be construed as defects or disorders.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a neuro-diverse workplace?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Neurodiversity in the workplace refers to including people with neuro-divergent conditions such as attention-deﬁcit/hyperactivity disorder, autism spectrum disorders, dyslexia, dyspraxia, dyscalculia and Asperger’s Syndrome.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are those Conditions that make them different from normal humans?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Autism:</strong> A mental condition in which a person finds it difficult to communicate or form relationships with other people. Signs of autism include not responding to their name, avoiding eye contact, not smiling when you smile at them.</li>
<li><strong>Dyslexia:</strong> a difficulty that some people have with reading and spelling signs include confusion over letters that look similar and putting letters the wrong way round , confusing the order of letters in words, reading slowly or making errors when reading aloud</li>
<li><strong>Asperger’s syndrome:</strong> A developmental disorder related to autism and characterized by awkwardness in social interaction, pedantry in speech, and preoccupation with very narrow interests. Less severe symptoms than Autism syndrome.</li>
<li><strong>Dyscalculia:</strong> A brain disorder in which a wide range of difficulties with math, including weaknesses in understanding the meaning of numbers, and difficulty applying mathematical principles to solve problems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="neurodiverse" class="alignnone wp-image-640542" height="373" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 622px) 100vw, 622px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2869adc7-4764-4e36-8262-2e9c6a04820a-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2869adc7-4764-4e36-8262-2e9c6a04820a-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2869adc7-4764-4e36-8262-2e9c6a04820a.jpg 600w" width="622"/>How they can be naturally efficient and creative?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>More efficient: </strong>Studies have shown that teams with both neurodivergent and neurotypical members are far more efficient than teams that comprise neurotypical employees alone.</li>
<li><strong>Ability to focus: </strong>Neurodivergent individuals possess excellent attention to detail and an uncanny ability to focus on complex and repetitive tasks over a more extended period than their neurotypical peers.</li>
<li><strong>Ability to work at faster speed: </strong>A study by the University of Montreal found that in a test involving completing a visual pattern, people on the autism spectrum could finish their task 40% faster than those who were not on the spectrum.</li>
<li><strong>Robust spatial reasoning</strong>: People with dyslexia can think about objects in three dimensions and analyses such objects even with limited information.</li>
<li><strong>Out of box thinking</strong>: They have problem-solving capabilities which allow them to see multiple solutions to a problem. They are often out-of-the-box thinkers with average or above-average intelligence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Current Status of people living with neurodivergent conditions</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>People suffer with the Condition: </strong>According to a recent report, nearly 2 million people in India suffer from this neurological and developmental disorder and are therefore identified as autistic. Another study by Deloitte estimates that nearly 20% of the world is neurodiverse. In the U.S., it is estimated that 85% of people on the autism spectrum are unemployed compared with 4.2% of the overall population</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-discrimination-report/"><strong>Discrimination at employment</strong>:</a> Even with all the necessary skill sets and degrees, these persons are denied a job because they may react to situations differently from non-neurodiverse persons.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of awareness: </strong>Lack of awareness about neurodivergent conditions, and how the people with condition may react and lack of and accommodating environment. Hence, there is an urgency to create a work environment that welcomes neurodiverse individuals<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="neurodiverse" class="alignnone wp-image-640543" height="371" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 589px) 100vw, 589px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-300x189.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-300x189.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-1024x646.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-768x484.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-1536x969.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-1200x757.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic.jpg 1903w" width="589"/>Current work profile of companies and workplaces</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A 2019 McKinsey study revealed that companies with gender diversity were 25% more likely to have above-average profitability while those with ethnic diversity out-rival their competitors by 36%.</li>
<li>Another report titled ‘India’s Best Workplaces in Diversity, Equity &amp; Inclusion 2021’ states that diverse teams perform better, boost leadership integrity, heighten trust in the organization’s management and multiply revenue growth.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="neurodiverse" class="alignnone wp-image-640544" height="392" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960x0-300x201.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960x0-300x201.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960x0-768x514.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960x0.jpg 959w" width="585"/>Few Examples show that things are changing</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Competitive environment</strong>: Organisations embracing neurodiversity enjoy a competitive edge in several areas such as efficiency, creativity, and culture.</li>
<li><strong>Various MNC’s hiring program</strong>: Companies such as Deloitte, Microsoft, SAP, JPMorgan Chase, and E&amp;Y have introduced neurodiversity hiring programs.</li>
<li><strong>Indian company: </strong>Indian-origin companies Hatti Kaapi and Lemon Tree Hotels have also included a neurodiverse workforce.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to create more inclusive workplaces?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Creating neurodivergent friendly offices</strong>: .Many employees with neurodiversity may find the hustle and bustle of a traditional office disturbing. Therefore, neurodivergent friendly offices catering to the employees’ diverse sensory responses can help ensure that these employees are comfortable in office spaces.</li>
<li><strong>Openness:</strong> Creating the right environment is an ever-evolving exercise that requires openness and a will to change on the employer’s part. This flexibility can result in exceptional benefit with minimal or no additional costs.</li>
<li><strong>Wider Inclusivity</strong>: To ensure higher profitability and be respected as a responsible employer globally, companies need to widen their definition of inclusivity by providing higher participation of a neurodiverse workforce.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Organizations must not only remove barriers that obstruct the progress of such individuals but also create conducive conditions for them to achieve their true potential and providing proper infrastructure so that they can perform at their optimal levels.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. People with neurodiversity are discriminated not only socially but also economically, Comment. What measures could be taken to bridge this gap within the society?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/neurodiverse/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Soft power, the new race every country wants to win</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/soft-power/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>na</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Soft power</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="soft power" class="alignnone wp-image-640548" height="224" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/quote-the-image-of-a-country-is-not-just-about-economic-and-military-strength-the-soft-face-narendra-modi-130-43-87-300x126.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/quote-the-image-of-a-country-is-not-just-about-economic-and-military-strength-the-soft-face-narendra-modi-130-43-87-300x126.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/quote-the-image-of-a-country-is-not-just-about-economic-and-military-strength-the-soft-face-narendra-modi-130-43-87-768x323.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/quote-the-image-of-a-country-is-not-just-about-economic-and-military-strength-the-soft-face-narendra-modi-130-43-87.jpg 843w" width="533"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Increased interest, especially by smaller nations in the world, in investing more and doing well in elite sports in international sporting events boosts a nation’s chances of attaining soft power.</li>
<li>India’s medal tally at recent International sports events demonstrate the country’s soft power on the global stage and encourage working towards the status of a great “geopolitical actor”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.bridgeindia.org.uk/the-rise-of-india-as-a-global-soft-power/" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>What is soft power?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Origin:</strong>
<ul>
<li>As far back as the 4<sup>th</sup> century BC, Kautilya (chankyaniti) had propounded the concept of Saam(advice or cajole),daam(pay or bribe),dand(punish),bhed(exploit secrets) which acquired western touch and can be understood by Soft power, smart power, hard power, and sharp power respectively.</li>
<li>Joseph Nye introduced the concept of “soft power” in the late 1980s. For Nye, power is the ability to influence the behavior of others to get the outcomes you want.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Meaning:</strong></li>
<li>Soft power is the ability of a country to persuade others to do what it wants without force or coercion.</li>
<li>Soft power is the ability to influence the behavior of others to get the outcomes you want.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="soft power" class="alignnone wp-image-640547" height="327" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 491px) 100vw, 491px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749.jpg 1200w" width="491"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-yoga-indias-soft-power/">Why Soft power is so significant?</a></strong></h4>
<p>Use of ‘Soft Power’ includes the number of cultural missions such as language schools, Olympic Medals and the quality of a country’s overall growth. Soft power produces following things:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Familiarity</strong>: If people know more about your country, culture, sports, and its talents, businesses, and resources, then soft power is enhanced.</li>
<li><strong>Reputation</strong>: For a nation to be attractive and a role model for others, its overall reputation must be strong and positive.</li>
<li><strong>Influence</strong>: A direct measure of the perceived presence and impact that your country has in other countries</li>
<li><strong>Business/Innovation/Sports</strong>: The attractiveness of a country’s economic model, its digital engagement with the world, performance in sports etc.</li>
<li><strong>Government</strong>: Showcases the ability of country’s political leadership and what it delivers to its people in different arenas.</li>
<li><strong>Multi-Alignment:</strong> As a country rises up the ‘Soft Power’ list, more and more outside parties align themselves with the common goals of that country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why the Sports being used as a tool of soft power in modern international relations?</strong></h4>
<p>Sport can be used as tool of soft power both internationally and domestically.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>International platform</strong>: Sports provide a platform for countries to showcase their culture, values and tradition.</li>
<li><strong>Puts a Better image of a country</strong>: Sports as a tool to achieve social, political, and financial goals, and improve the image of the country<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>International exposure: </strong>The focus on culture and peaceful values in sports make it a useful tool for countries to use soft power to achieve international goals and improve their public diplomacy.</li>
<li><strong>Reducing differences</strong>: Sports provides a platform for trust-building; and reconciliation, integration and anti-racism.</li>
<li><strong>Learning from China’s Case</strong>:</li>
<li>Dongfeng Liu (International Professor of Sport Management) in his survey on China’s performance in the Olympics he found that a country’s Olympic achievement has a positive effect on its national soft power.</li>
<li>As china is a communist country and reputation about human rights is not good, so China uses its superiority in elite sports to build “people-to-people” relations with other countries. For example, athletes from African countries such as Madagascar are trained in swimming, badminton, table tennis, etc. in China, which helps Beijing create a positive impact on a wider population and result in better formal relations as well.</li>
<li>There is also China’s memorandum of understanding with countries such as Kenya so that Chinese runners can train with Kenyan athletes, as they are among the best in the world when it comes to long-distance running.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="soft power" class="alignnone wp-image-640550" height="512" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/80906-yutjpg-1554537206-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/80906-yutjpg-1554537206-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/80906-yutjpg-1554537206.jpg 640w" width="683"/>Introspection on India’s performance at recent International Sports events</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is being said that the golden period of Indian sports may have begun as at the Tokyo Olympics and then the Birmingham 2022 Commonwealth Games (CWG) are examples of a good performance.</li>
<li>India’s medal tally in the Tokyo Olympics Games — seven — was its most decorated Olympic Games in Indian history.</li>
<li>At the Commonwealth games (CWG) 2022, Indian athletes won 61 medals, including 22 gold.</li>
<li>India has one of the world’s poorest population-to-medal ratios when it comes to the Olympics.</li>
<li>Ensuring competent coaches, and having adequate funding and more sports academics still remain major issues even decades later</li>
<li>India spends only three paise per day per capita on sports. In contrast China spends 1 per day per capita.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to increase the country’s sporting performance and soft power</strong><strong>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Train Indian players overseas:</strong></li>
<li>India should concentrate on forging MoUs with nations that excel in specific sports and train Indian players overseas.</li>
<li>For example, Australia and the United Kingdom can assist us in swimming given their standing here.</li>
<li>When it comes to running, negotiating collaborative training agreements with African countries such as Kenya would be ideal.</li>
<li><strong>No Politics over assistance: </strong></li>
<li>There should be no politics in seeking or even offering assistance.</li>
<li>For example China has requested Indian assistance in improving cricket development in China (Chongqing city).</li>
<li><strong>Private Investment</strong>:</li>
<li>Private investment needs to be harnessed to develop infrastructure. The better a country performs in sporting events the greater a sports person’s interest in their sports atmosphere. This also creates a huge market for private players to invest in.</li>
<li>For example, leading corporate houses in India have already shown how their active participation and investment can improve sporting performance as a result of unique corporate sports programmes.</li>
<li><strong>Public –private partnership at grass root :</strong></li>
<li>The Government should also work on a public-private partnership (PPP) model to create basic sporting infrastructure.</li>
<li>As recommended by NITI Aayog, at the district level too so that talent can be captured at an early stage.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sports as a tool of soft power had always been a key element of leadership from the ancient times. Sports provide an international platform to develop an attitude of unity in a divided multi-polar modern world.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Sports provide an international platform to develop an attitude of unity and influence others in a divided multi-polar modern world. Discuss in this context that soft power is not an end but a means to an end.</strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/soft-power/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The future of India is linked to police reforms</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/police-reforms/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Police reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The future of India is linked to police reforms. If the country is to progress and emerge as a great power, there is no alternative to radical reforms in the police.</li>
<li>September 22, is observed as <a href="https://bprd.nic.in/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Police Reforms day</a> since the Supreme Court gave a landmark judgment on police reforms in 2006 on the same.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a term Police stands for?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Police is a constituted body of uniformed persons empowered by a state who are responsible for keeping law and order intact.</li>
<li>Their lawful powers include arrest and the use of force.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Role of Police?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Law enforcement</strong><strong>: </strong>The basic role of the police is to function as a law enforcement agency and render impartial service to law, without any heed to wishes, indications or desires expressed by the government which either come in conflict with or do not conform to the provisions contained in the constitution or laws.</li>
<li><strong>Service delivery</strong><strong>:</strong> The police should have duly recognised service-oriented role in providing relief to people in distress situations. They should be trained and equipped to perform the service oriented functions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Issues with police institution in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Colonial practice</strong>: The Police Act of 1861, which governs substantially the functioning of police even today, is a symbol of colonial rule.</li>
<li><strong>Cost of internal security on economic growth</strong>: Economic development depends on sound law and order and we can have good law and order only if we have professional police. According to the Institute for Economics and Peace, violence cost the country 7 per cent of its GDP in 2020.</li>
<li><strong>Infiltration of persons of questionable background at power:</strong> According to the Association of Democratic Reforms, the percentage of such people in Parliament has been showing a steady upward trend. It was 24 per cent in 2004, 30 per cent in 2009, 34 per cent in 2014 and 43 per cent in the last election held in 2019.This poses a challenge for police to take action against this segment of people and their supporters who have a shady background and who may one day devour the very system that has placed them in power.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of Internal security doctrine:</strong> Problems are tackled as per the perception of the ruling dispensation at any given point time and therefore police are not able to deal with the internal security challenges as effectively as they should.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of confidence of public in police:</strong> Most people believe police to be abusive and also believe that police personnel misuse their power in order to bring order to society. This is particularly true of the lower strata of society, who feel that there is one law for the poor and another for the rich and powerful as police under influence of political and financial clout.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing complexity of organized crimes</strong>: Organised crime has acquired international dimensions. Arms trafficking and drug trafficking do not observe any borders and Cybercrimes are increasing in geometrical progression.<strong> </strong></li>
<li><strong> Poor infrastructure and human resource: </strong>The police are not able to deliver partly because of poor infrastructure moreover there is a vacancy of more than 5,00,000 personnel.</li>
<li><strong>Poor housing conditions and long working hours:</strong> poor housing conditions and long working hours have an adverse impact on police performance.  According to the Status of Policing in India Report, 2019, an average policeman works for 14 hours a day and does not get any weekly off. This takes a heavy toll on his mental and physical health.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is meant by police reforms?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The aim of Police reforms is to enhance efficiency, capability, and adoptability according to the time and transforming culture, values and existing practice of police system.</li>
<li>As per the Indian Constitution Police comes under state list.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to improve <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/reforms-police-in-india-need/">efficiency of police in India</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Police sensitisation about their role in society: </strong>The sensitisation module should aim at bringing about attitudinal change in police — especially pertaining to gender and power relations and police behavior. It is necessary to increase public confidence in the police by upgrading levels of police service delivery as well as by investigating and acting in cases of police misconduct<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Increasing accountability</strong><strong>: </strong>Making them answerable to law and law alone and not to work under pressure of the political and financial clout.</li>
<li><strong>Develop infrastructure and fill vacancies:</strong> Overall, there is a vacancy of more than 5,00,000 personnel. These must be filled. There is huge scope for improvement in transport, communications and forensics as well</li>
<li><strong>Improving hosing conditions:</strong> The National Police Commission had recommended 100 per cent family accommodation for all non gazetted police personnel. The satisfaction level today is hardly 31.24 per cent.</li>
<li><strong> Reducing working hours:</strong> Long working hours have an adverse impact on police performance. We should have 12-hour shifts straightaway and gradually aim to achieve eight-hour shifts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A new role and new philosophy have to be defined for the police to not only make it a capable and effective body but also one accountable to the law of the land and to the people whom they serve.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. </strong><strong>If the country is to progress and emerge as a great power, there is no alternative to radical reforms in the police. Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/police-reforms/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>In news: Rotterdam Convention</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rotterdam-convention-chemicals-pic/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Rotterdam convention, PIC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>International trade of two new hazardous pesticides — Iprodione and Terbufos — has been recommended for “prior informed consent” (PIC) procedure under the Rotterdam convention.</p>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In India, the use of these chemicals was permitted by the 2015 Anupam Verma committee report. The country is among the largest exporters of Terbufos.</li>
<li>The chemicals are dangerous for humans and aquatic animals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Rotterdam Convention</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Rotterdam Convention is formally known as the Convention on the Prior Informed Consent Procedure for Certain Hazardous Chemicals and Pesticides in International Trade.</li>
<li>It is a multilateral treaty to promote shared responsibilities in relation to importation of hazardous chemicals.</li>
<li>The convention promotes open exchange of information and calls on exporters of hazardous chemicals to use proper labelling, include directions on safe handling, and inform purchasers of any known restrictions or bans.</li>
<li>Signatory nations can decide whether to allow or ban the importation of chemicals listed in the treaty, and exporting countries are obliged to make sure that producers within their jurisdiction comply.</li>
<li>India is a party to the convention, with 161 other parties.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Prior Informed Consent (PIC) procedure?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PIC procedure is a mechanism for formally obtaining and disseminating the decisions of importing parties on their willingness to receive future shipments of hazardous chemicals.</li>
<li>The PIC procedure is a mechanism for formally obtaining and disseminating the decisions of importing Parties as to whether they wish to receive future shipments of those chemicals listed in the Convention.</li>
<li>For each of the chemicals listed in Annex III and subject to the PIC procedure a decision guidance document (DGD) is prepared and sent to all Parties.</li>
<li>All Parties are required to take a decision as to whether or not they will allow future import of each of the chemicals in Annex III of the Convention.</li>
<li>These decisions are known as import responses.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Which are the new chemicals listed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Iprodione, a fungicide used on vines, fruits, trees and vegetables, has been classified as carcinogenic and toxic for reproduction.</li>
<li>Terbufos is a soil insecticide used commonly on sorghum, maize, beet and potatoes. It has also been found to pose risk to aquatic organisms due to its toxicity.</li>
<li>Both pesticides, which are used in agriculture, are known for their harmful impacts on human health and the environment.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rotterdam-convention-chemicals-pic/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre defers new Foreign Trade Policy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-defers-new-foreign-trade-policy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Foreign Trade Policy</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The government has extended the launch of new Foreign Trade Policy (FTP) (2022-27) by six more months and would continue with the existing one.</p>
<h4><strong>Why such delay in Foreign Trade Policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Geopolitical uncertainty:</strong> The geo-political situation is not suitable for long-term foreign trade policy, said Union Commerce Minister.</li>
<li><strong>Global recession:</strong> Currently, fears of a recession in major economies like the US and Europe have escalated a panic among investors.</li>
<li><strong>Decline in USD inflows:</strong> Foreign investors have begun to pull back their money from equities.</li>
<li><strong>Rupee depreciation:</strong> The US Dollar is at a 22-year high, while the Rupee hit a new all-time low of $81.6.</li>
<li><strong>Huge trade deficit:</strong> The trade deficit widened by more than 2-folds to $125.22 billion (April – August 2022) compared to $53.78 billion in the same period last year.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Foreign Trade Policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s Foreign Trade Policy (FTP) is a set of guidelines for goods and services imported and exported.</li>
<li>These are developed by the Directorate General of Foreign Trade (DGFT), the Ministry of Commerce and Industry’s regulating body for the promotion and facilitation of exports and imports.</li>
<li>FTPs are enforceable under the Foreign Trade Development and Regulation Act 1992.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is India’s Foreign Trade Policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In line with the ‘Make in India,’ ‘Digital India,’ ‘Skill India,’ ‘Startup India,’ and ‘Ease of Doing Business initiatives, the Foreign Trade Policy (2015-20) was launched on April 1, 2015.</li>
<li>It provides a framework for increasing exports of goods and services, creating jobs, and increasing value addition in the country.</li>
<li>The FTP statement outlines the market and product strategy as well as the steps needed to promote trade, expand infrastructure, and improve the entire trade ecosystem.</li>
<li>It aims to help India respond to external problems while staying on top of fast-changing international trading infrastructure and to make trade a major contributor to the country’s economic growth and development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues with FTP (2015-2020)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Acting on Washington’s protest, a WTO dispute settlement panel ruled in 2019 that India’s export <strong><u>subsidy measures are in violation of WTO norms</u></strong> and must be repealed.</li>
<li><strong><u>Tax incentives</u></strong> under the popular <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-rodtep-scheme/">Merchandise Exports from India Scheme (MEIS)</a> (now renamed as RODTEP Scheme)and Service Exports from India Scheme (SEIS) programmes were among them.</li>
<li>The panel found that because India’s per capita gross national product exceeds $1,000 per year, it may no longer grant subsidies based on export performance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>WTO-compliance:</strong> With incentives under MEIS and SEIS in the cloud, WTO-compliant tax benefits are a must.</li>
<li><strong>Access to credit:</strong> Credit availability has long been a need of exporters, particularly MSMEs.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure upgrade:</strong> China’s network of ports, motorways, and high-speed trains, which are among the greatest in the world, is one of the reasons it is a manufacturing and export powerhouse.</li>
<li><strong>Digitization and e-commerce boost:</strong> India requires innovative trading procedures as a result of Covid-19 breaking old supply channels.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-defers-new-foreign-trade-policy/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre’s push for NavIC System  </title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centres-push-for-navic-system/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NAVIC, IRNSS, GPS</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="navic" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-352595" height="595" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 641px) 100vw, 641px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/irnss.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/irnss.jpg 641w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/irnss-300x278.jpg 300w" width="641"/></p>
<p>The Union government is pushing tech giants to make smartphones compatible with its home-grown navigation system ‘NavIC’.</p>
<h4>What is NavIC?</h4>
<ul>
<li>NavIC, or Navigation with Indian Constellation, is an independent stand-alone navigation satellite system developed by the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO).</li>
<li>NavIC was originally approved in 2006 at a cost of $174 million.</li>
<li>It was expected to be completed by late 2011, but only became operational in 2018.</li>
<li>NavIC consists of <strong><u>eight satellites</u></strong> and <strong><u>covers the whole of India’s landmass and up to 1,500 km</u></strong> (930 miles) from its boundaries.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Note:</strong> The numbers of satellites in this constellation is disputed. It is given as 7 and 8 on different sources. Total Nine satellites were launched out of which the very first (IRNSS-1A) is partially failed because of some issue in its <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-entangled-atomic-clocks/">Atomic Clock</a>. Another and the last satellite had a launch failure. Hence the number 7/8.</p></blockquote>
<h4>Why is the Centre pushing for NavIC?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Currently, NavIC’s use is limited.</li>
<li>It is being used in public vehicle tracking in India.</li>
<li>It helps providing emergency warning alerts to fishermen venturing into the deep sea where there is no terrestrial network connectivity, and for tracking and providing information related to natural disasters.</li>
<li>Enabling it in smartphones is the next step India is pushing for.</li>
<li>India’s 2021 satellite navigation draft policy stated the government will work towards expanding the coverage from regional to global to ensure availability of NavIC signal in any part of the world.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How does NavIC compare?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The main difference is the serviceable area covered by these systems.</li>
<li>GPS caters to users across the globe and its satellites circle the earth twice a day, while NavIC is currently for use in India and adjacent areas.</li>
<li>Like GPS, there are three more navigation systems that have global coverage – Galileo from the European Union, Russia-owned GLONASS and China’s Beidou.</li>
<li>QZSS, operated by Japan, is another regional navigation system covering Asia-Oceania region, with a focus on Japan.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Strategic significance of NavIC</h4>
<ul>
<li>India says NavIC is conceived with the aim of <strong><u>removing dependence</u></strong> on foreign satellite systems for navigation service requirements, particularly for “strategic sectors.”</li>
<li>Relying on systems like GPS and GLONASS <strong><u>may not always be reliable</u></strong>, India says, as those are operated by the defence agencies of respective nations.</li>
<li>It is possible that <strong><u>civilian services can be degraded or denied</u></strong>.</li>
<li>NavIC is an indigenous positioning system that is under <strong><u>Indian control</u></strong>.</li>
<li>There is <strong><u>no risk of the service being withdrawn</u></strong> or denied in a given situation.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ:</h4>
<p><strong>Q. With reference to the Indian Regional Navigation Satellite System (IRNSS), consider the following statements:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li><strong>IRNSS has three Satellites in geostationary and four satellites the geosynchronous orbits.</strong></li>
<li><strong>IRNSS covers entire India and about 5500 sq. km beyond its borders.</strong></li>
<li><strong>India will have its own satellite navigation system with full global coverage by the middle of 2019.</strong></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Which of the statements given above is/are correct?</strong></p>
<p>(a) 1 only</p>
<p>(b) 1 and 2 only</p>
<p>(c) 2 and 3 only</p>
<p>(d) None</p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Answer:</strong> (Post it here.)</p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centres-push-for-navic-system/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Karnataka brings law giving Quota for Locals</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/karnataka-brings-law-giving-quota-for-locals/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Quota for Locals</p></div></div><p>The Karnataka government recently tabled The Kannada Language Comprehensive Development Bill which gives preference to Kannadigas in government jobs and also provides for a reservation to locals in private jobs generated in the state.</p>
<h4><strong>What does the Karnataka legislation envisage?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Apart from ensuring job guarantee to Kannada speakers, the Bill pushes for the use of Kannada in institutes of higher learning and for sops to industries that employ locals.</li>
<li>Features highlighted in the Bill include reservation in higher, technical and professional education to those who studied in Kannada medium schools.</li>
<li>It seeks introduction of Kannada as essential language for seeking employment in the state government.</li>
<li>Also, industries will be entitled to concessions, tax rebates and deferment of taxes if they provide reservation for Kannadigas, as per the state’s industrial policy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Quota for Locals?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Ans.</strong> Constitutional provision for Equal Treatment</p>
<ul>
<li>Article 16 of the Constitution guarantees equal treatment under the law in matters of public employment. It prohibits the state from discriminating on grounds of place of birth or residence.</li>
<li>Article 16(2) states that “no citizen shall, on grounds only of religion, race, caste, sex, descent, place of birth, residence or any of them, be ineligible for, or discriminated against in respect of, any employment or office under the State”.</li>
<li>The provision is supplemented by the other clauses in the Constitution that guarantee equality.</li>
<li>However, Article 16(3) of the Constitution provides an exception by saying that Parliament may make a law “prescribing” a requirement of residence for jobs in a particular state.</li>
<li>This power vests solely in the Parliament, not state legislatures.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why does the Constitution prohibit reservation based on domicile?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When the Constitution came into force, India turned itself into one nation from a geographical unit of individual principalities and the idea of the universality of Indian citizenship took root.</li>
<li>India has single citizenship, and it gives citizens the liberty to move around freely in any part of the country.</li>
<li>Hence the requirement of a place of birth or residence cannot be qualification for granting public employment in any state.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>But are reservations not granted on other grounds such as caste?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Equality enshrined in the Constitution is not mathematical equality and does not mean all citizens will be treated alike without any distinction.</li>
<li>To this effect, the Constitution underlines two distinct aspects which together form the essence of equality law:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Non-discrimination among equals, and</li>
<li>Affirmative action to equalize the unequal</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Supreme Court rulings on quota for locals</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court has ruled against reservation based on place of birth or residence.</li>
<li>In 1984, ruling in Dr Pradeep Jain v Union of India, the issue of legislation for “sons of the soil” was discussed.</li>
<li>The court expressed an opinion that such policies would be unconstitutional but did not expressly rule on it as the case was on different aspects of the right to equality.</li>
<li>In a subsequent ruling in Sunanda Reddy v State of Andhra Pradesh (1995), the Supreme Court affirmed the observation in 1984 ruling to strike down a state government policy that gave 5% extra weightage to candidates.</li>
<li>In 2002, the Supreme Court invalidated appointment of government teachers in Rajasthan in which the state selection board gave preference to “applicants belonging to the district or the rural areas of the district concerned”.</li>
<li>In 2019, the Allahabad HC struck down a recruitment notification by the UP PSC which prescribed preference for women who are “original residents” of the UP alone.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why it is a bad idea?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Against Equality as well as meritocracy</strong>: It goes against the Constitution of India. In fact, it violates several fundamental rights, such as freedom to move anywhere, the right not to be discriminated on the basis of place of birth, the right to be treated equally before laws and the right to pursue one’s livelihood.</li>
<li><strong>Migration criteria not justified</strong>: The actual data on inter-State migration shows that inter-State migration is relatively low in India. Migration often bring skills, motivation, energy which may be in short supply or lacking locally.</li>
<li><strong>Free movement of labour</strong>: A more analytical aspect to highlight is that free movement of labour partly compensates for the uneven economic progress of different States. The idea also goes against the established fact that migration of labour is good for the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Un-ease of doing business</strong>: Local reservation in the private sector may not be the ideal solution to tackle the unemployment crisis. In fact, it can deter the corporate sector from investing in states that come up with such a rule.</li>
<li><strong>Scapegoating the private sector: </strong>What distinguishes the private sector from the public sector is the inherent competition and a hunger for improvement. In such a scenario, chief ministers should do well to engage with the private sector in a much more holistic manner, and not burden it with unfeasible rules.</li>
<li><strong>MSMEs to be hit harder: </strong>MSMEs could be the hardest hit. They do not have the necessary capital to relocate and many studies have shown that more than 50 per cent of employees are not residents of the state.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Arguments in favour of quota in private</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Avoiding encroachments:</strong> Often the privileged castes (or groups) use nefarious arguments to protect their interests.</li>
<li><strong>Foul argument of merit:</strong> Reservations once accepted in the constitutional framework are not a charity that is to be kept away from the ‘meritocracy’ of ‘private’ operations.</li>
<li><strong>Ensuring equal opportunity:</strong> Like all other constitutional guarantees, one may feel the necessity to get ensured of equal opportunity in all spaces.</li>
<li><strong>Preventing exclusion:</strong> Giving preference and quotas for socially and educationally deprived sections in the private space is, therefore, in keeping with this fundamental tenet.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The politics of identity and polarization on region/religious lines seems inadequate for the elections.</li>
<li>The philosophy and pragmatism of universal excellence through equality of opportunity for education and advancement across the nation is part of our founding faith and constitutional creed.</li>
<li>Clearly, this is not the appropriate domain of being “vocal for local”.</li>
<li>Although some reservations may still be necessary for the socio-political condition in India, reservation on the basis of domicile or residence within a State would be highly discriminatory.</li>
<li>It is more likely that such politically motivated steps would be overturned by the judiciary as has been done several times in the past.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/karnataka-brings-law-giving-quota-for-locals/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Process of sustainable tourism should be holistic and inclusive</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tourism-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Incredible India</p></div></div><p>“<em>To other Country, I may go as a tourist. But to India I come as a pilgrim</em>”, the words of Martin Luther King says a lot about India’s wisdom and tourism potential.</p>
<h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The three-day National Conference of State Tourism Minister was held at Dharamshala , a first of its kind meeting aimed  to discuss, debate and deliberate on modes and mechanisms to develop tourism in India .</li>
<li>The three-day National Conference concluded with the adoption of “Dharamshala Declaration” which affirms commitment toward developing “sustainable and responsible tourism” and positions India as a “global leader in the tourism sector by 2047”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism is travel for pleasure or business; also the theory and practice of touring, the business of attracting, accommodating, and entertaining tourists, and the business of operating tours.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Types of tourism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Domestic tourism</strong>: Refers to activities of a visitor within their country of residence and outside of their home (e.g. a Indian visiting other parts of India)</li>
<li><strong>Inbound tourism</strong>: Refers to the activities of a visitor from outside of country of residence (e.g. a Spaniard visiting Britain).</li>
<li><strong>Outbound tourism</strong>: Refers to the activities of a resident visitor outside of their country of residence (e.g. an Indian visiting an overseas country).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640662" height="327" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341.jpg 550w" width="580"/>What does sustainable tourism mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sustainable tourism is defined by the UN Environment Program and UN World Tourism Organization as “tourism that takes full account of its current and future economic, social and environmental impacts, addressing the needs of visitors, the industry, the environment and host communities.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the main importance of tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism boosts the revenue of the economy, creates thousands of jobs, develops the infrastructures of a country, and plants a sense of cultural exchange between foreigners and citizens.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640663" height="379" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 605px) 100vw, 605px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan.jpg 1024w" width="605"/>Why tourism is needed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism is not a fad. It is a compulsion driven by the urge to discover new places. Because we have this compulsion to venture into the unknown, we need each other. When humans travel, meet and exchange ideas, civilization flourishes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is “The Dharamshala Declaration” is all about?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Aim of the declaration: </strong>The Dharamshala Declaration aims to recognise India’s role in contributing towards global tourism as well as focusing on recovery by also promoting domestic tourism.</li>
<li><strong>Action plan:</strong> In the declaration, the Tourism Ministry has come up with a with a action plan to encourage more Indians to travel domestically and explore India’s natural, cultural, and spiritual beauty while simultaneously reaching the goal of an ‘Ek Bharat Shrestha Bharat’ (interaction and mutual understanding).</li>
<li><strong>Strategy: </strong>The Tourism Ministry has also been working with the Ministry of External Affairs to identify 20 Indian missions abroad with the highest tourist footfalls to India and build country-specific strategies to attract foreign tourists.</li>
<li><strong>Plan according to G-20: </strong>The Dharamshala Declaration affirms the plan to position India as a major tourism destination during its presidency of G-20 next year. India’s age-old dictum of ‘Atithi Devo Bhava’ will come to the fore as it welcomes delegates from the 20 countries/European Union.</li>
<li><strong>Necessary steps:</strong> The Ministry of Tourism also plans to work with other Ministries to bring in necessary interventions such as visa reforms, ease of travel, travel-friendly and improved immigration facilities at airports.</li>
<li><strong>National Tourism policy</strong><strong>:</strong> Drafted with a holistic vision and strategy to revive India’s tourism and targets to contribute USD 1 trillion to the GDP by 2047.<strong><br/>
</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640666" height="519" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 692px) 100vw, 692px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1200x900.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1980x1485.jpg 1980w" width="692"/>A draft on National <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gujarats-mice-tourism-policy/">Tourism Policy 2022</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Framework:</strong></li>
<li>Draft on National Tourism Policy 2022 aims at improving the framework conditions for tourism development in the country.</li>
<li>Supporting tourism industries, strengthening tourism support functions and developing tourism sub-sectors.</li>
<li>Impetus to digitalisation, innovation and technology through the National Digital Tourism Mission and skilling through the Tourism and Hospitality Sector Skill Mission.</li>
<li>The policy also gives a special impetus to private sector participation through public-private-partnerships (PPP)</li>
<li><strong>Guiding Principles</strong> :</li>
<li>Promoting sustainable, responsible and inclusive tourism in line with our civilisational ethos From Gautama to Gandhi, India has always spoken about the inherent need to live harmoniously with nature and within our means.</li>
<li>The National Green Tourism Mission aims at institutionalising green approach.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.incredibleindia.org/content/incredible-india-v2/en.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640665" height="375" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 666px) 100vw, 666px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-768x433.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism.jpg 1170w" width="666"/>Tourism Potential in India</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Employement generation:</strong> India has huge tourism potential. If capitalised properly it can emerge as one of the leading sectors to contribute to GDP and also has the potential to augment employment.</li>
<li><strong>The Pandemic cost and recovery: </strong>The pandemic has caused conspicuous losses for this sector but over the past few months, all the major tourism indices such as domestic air passenger traffic, hotel occupancy and tourist footfalls have shown signs of recovery and are going back to pre-pandemic levels.</li>
<li><strong>Short term estimate:</strong> By 2024, in short term the country is estimated to contribute USD 150 billion to the GDP from tourism, USD 30 billion in Foreign Exchange earnings and can get 15 million foreign tourist arrivals..</li>
<li><strong>Medium term by 2030:</strong> It is estimated to grow at seven to nine per cent Compound Annual Growth Rate in the coming decade. In the medium term, that is 2030, the tourism-related goals are USD 250 billion GDP contribution; 137 million jobs, 56 million foreign tourist arrivals and USD 56 billion in foreign exchange earnings.</li>
<li><strong>Visionary schemes</strong>: The visionary schemes like Swadesh Darshan or Dekho Apna Desh have the potential to increase tourism value while maintaining cultural integrity and ecological sustainability of the places.</li>
<li><strong>Dekho Apna Desh</strong>: Dekho apna desh rolled out in 2020 envisages encouraging domestic tourism, urging people to visit places in India. India is a land of rich cultural heritage.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>If the goal of positioning of India as one of the world’s best tourism destinations by 2047, there is need to integrate various schemes of different ministries. Need to involve various stakeholders, and local communities; necessary interventions at urban and rural level should be a priority.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Since the positive and negative outcomes of tourism depend on human factors, including the attitude and behavior of both tourists and hosts, in this context discuss India’s potential to become a global leader in tourism sector.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tourism-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>“Government of the people, by the people and for the people” for vibrant democracy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/democracy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Democratic credentials</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="democracy" class="alignnone wp-image-640675" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-300x199.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-300x199.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-1024x678.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-768x508.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-1536x1017.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-1200x794.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy-1980x1311.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Crespo-Democracy.jpg 2000w" width="585"/>Context</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.g7germany.de/g7-en" rel="noopener" target="_blank">G7 nations and partner countries</a> including India recently signed “2022 Resilient democracies statement”-We, the Leaders of Germany, Argentina, Canada, France, India, Indonesia, Italy, Japan, Senegal, South Africa, the United Kingdom, the United States of America, and the European Union, affirm our commitment to strengthening the resilience of our democracies and to working towards equitable, inclusive and sustainable solutions to global challenges, including climate change and the COVID-19 pandemic, and reaffirm our commitment to the rules-based international order.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>How we define Democracy?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>“Government of the people, by the people and for the people” the words used by Abraham Lincoln in the year 1863 while talking about democracy<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Purpose of democracy</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Cornerstones of democracy include freedom of assembly, association, property rights, freedom of religion and speech, inclusiveness and equality, citizenship, consent of the governed, voting rights, freedom from unwarranted governmental deprivation of the right to life and liberty, and minority rights.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/highlights-of-the-democracy-report-2022/"><strong>Democracy Report 2022</strong></a></p>
<ul>
<li>The study, titled ‘Democracy Report 2022: Autocratisation Changing Nature?’ states that more than twice as many countries are undergoing Autocratisation as are witnessing democratization.</li>
<li>The conceptual scheme takes into account not only the electoral dimension (free and fair elections) but also the liberal principle that democracy must protect “individual and minority rights”</li>
<li>The V-Dem report classifies countries into four regime types based on their score in the Liberal Democratic Index (LDI): a)Liberal Democracy b)Electoral Democracy c)Electoral Autocracy and d)Closed Autocracy</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="democracy" class="alignnone wp-image-640676" height="383" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 676px) 100vw, 676px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/democracy-voting-1-300x170.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/democracy-voting-1-300x170.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/democracy-voting-1-768x435.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/democracy-voting-1.jpg 1000w" width="676"/>Where do the Reports and Indices put India?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Sweden based Sweden-based V-Dem Institute was harsher in its latest report on democracy. It said India had become an “electoral autocracy”</li>
<li>US-based non-profit Freedom House downgraded India from a free democracy to a “partially free democracy”.</li>
<li>India, described as a “flawed democracy”, slipped two places to 53rd position in the latest Democracy Index published by The Economist Intelligence Unit<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Status of Supporters of Democracy</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Decolonised African Countries: </strong></li>
<li>The number of African countries that have adopted democratic systems of government has grown since decolonisation, the collapse of communism and the ending of a number of civil wars.</li>
<li>Some countries, such as Ghana, are seen as resilient democracies, while for others the democratic transition is more fragile, after months of pro-democracy protests in 2019 in Sudan, a civilian-led transitional government is now paving the way for democracy after decades of military rule.</li>
<li><strong>India as example: </strong></li>
<li>India is the world’s largest democracy. India is staying as one unit despite having vast no of cultures, languages and religions. This is possible because of the democracy in India.</li>
<li>Minorities and disadvantaged sections are represented in parliament which enabled inclusive growth.</li>
<li>When India got independence, its economy was in shambles. Extreme poverty, unemployment, food insecurity were the major problems before Indian government. But India’s democratic constitution successfully balanced development and welfare of the country.</li>
<li>Now, India is one of the fastest growing economies in the world.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What critics arguing?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Democracy in crisis</strong>: Democracy is more in crisis than ever before, with the onset of centralisation of power, with a foreign policy defying public opinion, with the media centralised, and with corporate control of the economy tighter than ever.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing polarity: </strong>Threatening world order is emerging, which seeks to abrogate all individual rights and divide us along the extremist polarities that we thought had been neutralised.</li>
<li><strong>Global Crisis: </strong>We move into this new stage of conﬂict carrying the risk of a nuclear tragedy, further exacerbated by the collective buttressing of a global crisis of the novel coronavirus pandemic, uncontrollable ecological disasters, and food and water deﬁciency.</li>
<li><strong>Populism: </strong>Blatant fascist leanings of the so-called “democracies”, and escalating hunger and disease in Africa and other parts of the under-developed world give enough evidence that democracy faces serious issues of populism.</li>
<li><strong>Other global problems: </strong>Growing economic discrimination, overpopulation and environmental degradation, Misgivings about moral progress, about mutual understanding, exacerbate the dismal situation that faces humanity.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="democracy" class="alignnone wp-image-640677" height="301" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 602px) 100vw, 602px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-1024x512.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-1536x768.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-2048x1024.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-1200x600.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Elections-and-Indian-Democracy-scaled-1-1980x990.jpg 1980w" width="602"/>What can be done to strengthen the democracies further?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Strengthening public support:</strong> To protect freedom domestically and build support for a foreign policy that protects democratic rights and values abroad, it is essential to foster a stronger public understanding of democratic principles, especially among young people<strong>. </strong>civic education is necessary.</li>
<li><strong>Rule of law: </strong>In order to maintain trust in public institutions, the principles of legality, legal certainty and prohibition of arbitrariness of the executive powers, judicial independence, impartiality, and equality before the law need to be respected.</li>
<li><strong>Individual rights</strong><strong>: </strong>Democracy entails the right of individuals to participate in and influence the development of society, with free and fair elections at its core. Without an active turnout in elections and proper mechanisms for participation, the essence of democracy can be lost.</li>
<li><strong>Free speech: </strong>Free speech guard the freedom of expression and opinion, and affirmation of commitment to the very idea of democracy and a move towards opposing oppression and violence</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Democracy is always a work in progress. The key ingredients of democracy are effective and accountable institutions, and leadership. Institutions build resilience by embedding norms and standards and bridging periods of weak leadership.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Do you think Democracy is the best solution to tackle the growing fault lines between the communities? What makes India as the best example of Democracy to the world? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/democracy/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Death Penalty : Deciding the rarest of rare</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/death-penalty/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>HUMAN RIGHTS</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Death penalty" class="alignnone wp-image-640696" height="254" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-1.jpg" width="452"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In a momentous ruling last week, the Supreme Court has said that fundamental aspects of death penalty sentencing need re-examination. A three-judge bench acknowledged that there are serious problems in India’s death penalty regime, indicating that the current state of death penalty sentencing is untenable.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In Jagmohan Singh vs State of UP’ (1973), then in ‘Rajendra Prasad vs State of UP’ (1979), and finally in ‘Bachan Singh vs State of Punjab’ (1980<strong>)</strong>the Supreme Court affirmed the constitutional validity of the death penalty.</li>
<li>It said that if capital punishment is provided in the law and the procedure is a fair, just and reasonable one, the death sentence can be awarded to a convict.</li>
<li>This will, however, only be in the “rarest of rare” cases, and the courts should render “special reasons” while sending a person to the gallows.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Death penalty" class="alignnone wp-image-640698" height="261" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download.jpg" width="449"/>What is Death Penalty?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The death penalty, also known as capital punishment, is the harshest form of punishment available under any criminal law in existence anywhere in the world.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>It should be distinguished from extrajudicial executions carried out without due process of law.</li>
<li>The term death penalty is sometimes used interchangeably with capital punishment, though imposition of the penalty is not always followed by execution, because of the possibility of commutation to life imprisonment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>When is it awarded?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The term “Capital Punishment” stands for most severe form of punishment.</li>
<li>It is the punishment which is to be awarded for the most heinous, grievous and detestable crimes against humanity.</li>
<li>While the definition and extent of such crimes vary, the implication of capital punishment has always been the death sentence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the status of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/procedural-gaps-in-death-penalty-sentencing/">Awarding death-penalty in India?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Unprincipled sentencing:</strong></li>
<li>There has long been a judicial crisis in death penalty sentencing on account of unprincipled sentencing, arbitrariness and worrying levels of subjectivity.</li>
<li>The crisis has been acknowledged by the Supreme Court, the Law Commission of India, research scholars and civil society groups.</li>
<li><strong>Crime-centric nature:</strong></li>
<li>Death penalty sentencing has been, by and large, crime-centric.</li>
<li>This approach goes against the requirements imposed on sentencing judges by the Supreme Court in Bachan Singh (1980).</li>
<li><strong>Confusion over the framework: </strong>There is utter confusion across all levels of the judiciary on the requirements of the framework laid down in the Bachan Singh case and its implementation.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Nature of crime a dominant consideration:</strong> An important reason for the breakdown is that factors relating to the crime, the nature of the crime and its brutality are often dominant considerations, and there is barely any consideration of mitigating factors.</li>
<li><strong>Little discussion on mitigating factors:</strong> There has been very little discussion on bringing the socioeconomic profile of death row prisoners as a mitigating factor into the courtroom.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Death penalty" class="alignnone wp-image-640700" height="269" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-2.jpg" width="480"/>What is the Legality framework in India in case of capital punishment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Capital punishment: </strong>The legal method through which the state exercises its power to take an individual’s life is known as capital punishment.</li>
<li><strong>Constitutional safeguard: </strong>“No individual shall be deprived of his life or personal liberty except pursuant to the procedure established by law,” says Article 21 of the Indian Constitution, which guarantees every citizen the fundamental right to life. This means that your right to life will never be taken away from you until you follow the legal system, which means that the state can take away your life if it sees fit through the legal process.</li>
<li><strong>Not all crimes are punished by death: </strong>Not all crimes are punishable by death; in fact, most agencies do not seek capital punishment; rather, it is reserved for the most egregious of offences.</li>
<li><strong>Indian penal code applied to :</strong> Eleven offences mentioned there if performed inside the territory of India are punishable by death, according to the Indian Penal Code and other Acts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Death penalty" class="alignnone wp-image-640699" height="263" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-1.jpg" width="469"/>How is the International framework?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>ICCPR:</strong></li>
<li>Despite the fact that the death penalty was still in practice in the majority of countries in the early 1960s, the drafters of the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights (ICCPR) have already begun efforts to have it abolished in international law.</li>
<li>Although Article 6 of the ICCPR allows for the use of the death penalty in restricted circumstances, it also states that nothing in this Article shall be invoked to delay or hinder any State Party to the present Covenant from abolishing capital punishment.</li>
<li>The ICCPR’s Second Optional Protocol aims to abolish the death penalty.</li>
<li><strong>UN ECOSOC:</strong></li>
<li>The UN Economic and Social Council enacted Safeguards in 1984, ensuring that persons facing the death penalty have their rights protected.</li>
<li>The UN General Assembly ratified the Second Optional Protocol to the ICCPR in 1989, 33 years after the adoption of the Covenant itself, giving abolition a powerful fresh boost. Members of the Protocol’s signatories pledged not to execute anyone within their domains.</li>
<li><strong>Resolutions of the United Nations General Assembly</strong>:</li>
<li>The General Assembly urged states to observe international standards that protect the rights of persons facing the death sentence in a series of resolutions enacted in 2007, 2008, 2010, 2012, 2014, 2016, and 2018, and to gradually reduce the number of offences punishable by death.</li>
<li>The UN General Assembly ratified the Second Optional Protocol to the ICCPR in 1989, giving abolition a powerful fresh boost.</li>
<li>Members of Protocol’s signatories pledged not to execute anyone within their domains.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why death penalty should be abolished?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Innocent execution: </strong>Innocent individuals have been executed in the past and will continue to be executed in the future. Between 2000 and 2014, the Supreme Court and high courts acquitted a fifth of individuals sentenced to death by trial courts<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Arbitrariness</strong>: The possibility of the death penalty being applied arbitrarily cannot be ruled out. According to the National Law University Delhi’s Death Penalty India Report 2016 (DPIR), approximately 75% of all convicts sentenced to death in India are from socio-economically underprivileged categories, such as Dalits, OBCs, and religious minorities.</li>
<li><strong>Eye for an eye:</strong>Reformative justice is more productive, that innocent people are often killed in the search for retribution, and that “an eye for an eye makes the whole world blind.</li>
<li><strong>Deterrence is a myth:</strong>Death penalty is not a deterrent to capital crimes state that there is no evidence to support the claim that the penalty is a deterrent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The death penalty is one of the most controversial issues in the world, and it is a topic that is constantly being debated. Over 70% of the world’s countries have abolished capital punishment in law or practice. New appropriate regulations should be created to ensure the successful execution of alternatives to capital punishment, as well as advice from professionals.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p>Q.<strong>Capital punishment not always serve the purpose of deterrence against heinous crimes in India. Comment</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/death-penalty/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>