<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 06:49:56 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Why we need to build a framework for best global digital governance affirmation</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/digital-governance/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<h4><strong><img alt="digital governance" class="alignnone wp-image-637976" height="444" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/CRN_Services_Portfolio_Technology_696-300x200.jpg" width="667"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In an interview earlier this month, Telecom Minister Ashwini Vaishnaw spoke about a comprehensive policy roadmap for India’s digital economy and digital governance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is digital governance ?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Electronic governance or e-governance can be defined as the usage of Information and Communication Technology (ICT) by the government to provide and facilitate government services, exchange of information, communication transactions and integration of various standalone systems and services.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is “global digital governance”?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Global digital governance encompasses the norms, institutions, and standards that shape the regulation around the development and use of these technologies. Digital governance has long-term commercial and political implications.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is it important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The main objective of e-governance is to provide a friendly, affordable, and efficient interface between a government and its people. It is about ensuring greater transparency, accountability and objectivity, resulting in cost-effective and high-quality public service.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the three domains of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/interactions-between-main-groups-in-e-governance-action-plan-for-india/">e-governance</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>E-administration</strong>: improving government processes</li>
<li><strong>E-services</strong>: connecting individual citizens with their government</li>
<li><strong>E-society</strong>: building interactions with and within civil society.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="digital governance" class="alignnone wp-image-637977" height="422" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 546px) 100vw, 546px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital-India-and-E-governance-300x232.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital-India-and-E-governance-300x232.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital-India-and-E-governance.jpg 529w" width="546"/>Is there a historical parallel to governing key economic sectors globally?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Digital economy is not unprecedented:</strong> Sectors critical to the global economy are subject to international cooperation frameworks and pacts. Therefore, the idea of setting up a single multilateral organization with a mandate to govern the digital economy is not unprecedented.</li>
<li><strong>The International Commission for Air Navigation (ICAN): </strong>Global aviation has been regulated since 1903 when the International Commission for Air Navigation (ICAN) first met, subsequently replaced by the International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO) in 1947.</li>
<li><strong>Bank for International Settlements (BIS): </strong>Similarly, the modern international banking system is governed by the Bank for International Settlements (BIS), an institution initially set up in the interwar period in 1930 to oversee Germany’s reparations to the Allies under the Treaty of Versailles. The BIS acquired a more global mandate beginning in the 1950s and is now partially responsible for global financial stability.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who are the key players in the global contest for digital governance</strong>?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>China seeks to champion the concept of cyber sovereignty: </strong>An authoritarian vision drives the first model. Most notably, China is emerging as the standard-bearer for this model with its desire to “reinvent the internet.” China seeks to champion the concept of “cyber sovereignty,” allowing countries to control access to the internet, censor content, and institute data localization requirements, as a pretext to protecting individual national interests.</li>
<li><strong>European Union’s General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR): </strong>Which provides a more democratic concept for digital governance. This model primarily seeks to protect the privacy and rights of internet users and online content consumers. Adopted with the overwhelming support of the European Parliament in 2014, the GDPR came into effect in May 2018, giving firms that rely on digital technologies the opportunity to modify their data usage and privacy policies. The adoption of the GDPR has been a turning point for global internet governance as consumers gained unprecedented control over their data in a manner that preserved freedom and openness online.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="digital governance" class="alignnone wp-image-637978" height="434" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 591px) 100vw, 591px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Syn-19-1-300x220.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Syn-19-1-300x220.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Syn-19-1.jpg 662w" width="591"/>Why global digital governance is important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Minimum rights and protections for platform workers</strong>: Under the G20, the International Labour Organisation has already placed a proposal in the employment working group for digital labour platforms to develop an international governance system determining minimum rights and protections for platform workers.</li>
<li><strong>Implementation of central bank digital currency projects: </strong>Similarly, on digital money, a reincarnated Bretton Woods is being advocated to address the distrust in private currencies and to coordinate the implementation of central bank digital currency projects.</li>
<li><strong>Digital taxation:</strong> Finally, in the deeply contested area of digital taxation, the OECD facilitated Base Erosion and Profit Shifting (BEPS) negotiations and helped arrive at a global solution.</li>
<li><strong>Digital sovereignty:</strong> The internet is splintering and digital sovereignty is now commonplace; yet, there is no better time for countries to come together and build a framework for global digital governance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="digital governance" class="alignnone wp-image-637981" height="357" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/E-Governance-Kya-Hai-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/E-Governance-Kya-Hai-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/E-Governance-Kya-Hai-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/E-Governance-Kya-Hai.jpg 1000w" width="570"/>What are the big 5 tech companies called?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Big Five tech giants—Apple, Amazon, Google (Alphabet), Meta, and Microsoft.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The rapid digitalisation of the world along with a new focus on trust in the global supply chains for digital products and services presents tremendous opportunities for India and its youth.  It is now up to all of us to engage in a collective “sabka prayas” to realise New India’s economic potential.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. The rapid digitalisation of the world along with a new focus on trust in the global supply chains for digital products and services presents tremendous opportunities for India. Comment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/digital-governance/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is National Automated Fingerprint Identification System (NAFIS)?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nafis/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NAFIS</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-624524" height="292" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nafis-300x292.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nafis-300x292.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nafis.jpg 358w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The Union Home Minister has inaugurated the National Automated Fingerprint Identification System (NAFIS).</p>
<h4>What is NAFIS?</h4>
<ul>
<li>NAFIS is developed by the National Crime Records Bureau (NCRB) at the Central Fingerprint Bureau (CFPB) in New Delhi.</li>
<li>The project is a country-wide searchable database of crime- and criminal-related fingerprints.</li>
<li>The web-based application functions as a central information repository by consolidating fingerprint data from all states and Union Territories.</li>
<li>In April this year, Madhya Pradesh became the first state in the country to identify a deceased person through NAFIS.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Utility of NAFIS</h4>
<ul>
<li>It enables law enforcement agencies to upload, trace, and retrieve data from the database in real time on a 24×7 basis.</li>
<li>It would help in the quick and easy disposal of cases with the help of a centralised fingerprint database.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How does it work?</h4>
<ul>
<li>NAFIS assigns a unique 10-digit National Fingerprint Number (NFN) to each person arrested for a crime.</li>
<li>This unique ID will be used for the person’s lifetime, and different crimes registered under different FIRs will be linked to the same NFN.</li>
<li>The 2020 report states that the ID’s first two digits will be that of the state code in which the person arrested for a crime is registered, followed by a sequence number.</li>
<li>By automating the collection, storage, and matching of fingerprints, along with digitizing the records of fingerprint data, NAFIS will provide the much-needed unique identifier for every arrested person.</li>
<li>It will be included in the CCTNS (Crime and Criminal Tracking Network &amp; Systems) database as both are connected at the backend.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Is this the first time that such an automation project is being attempted?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Upon the recommendations of the <strong><u>National Police Commission in 1986</u></strong>, the Central Fingerprint Bureau first began to automate the fingerprint database.</li>
<li>It began with digitizing the existing manual records through India’s first Automated Fingerprint Identification System (AFI) in 1992, called <strong><u>Fingerprint Analysis &amp; Criminal Tracing System (FACTS 1.0).</u></strong></li>
<li>The latest iteration, FACTS 5.0, which was upgraded in 2007, was considered to have “outlived its shelf life”, according to a 2018 report by the NCRB and thus needed to be replaced by NAFIS.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Since when has India relied on fingerprinting as a crime-fighting tool?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A system of fingerprinting identification first emerged in colonial India, where it was tested before it spread to Europe and beyond.</li>
<li>At first, it was used by British colonial officials for administrative rather than criminal purposes.</li>
<li>William Herschel, the chief administrator of the Hooghly district of Bengal, from the late-middle 1800s onwards, used fingerprinting to reduce fraud and forgeries.</li>
<li>It then aimed to ensure that the correct person was receiving government pensions, signing land transfer deeds, and mortgage bonds.</li>
<li>Anthropometry, the measurement of physical features of the body, was used by officials in India but was soon replaced with a system of fingerprints.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/nafis/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>James Webb telescope : The most powerful space telescope</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/james-webb-telescope/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>JSWT</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>JSWT, Big bang</p></div></div><h4><strong style="letter-spacing: -0.0415625em;"><img alt="James Webb telescope" class="alignnone wp-image-627363" height="289" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/nasa_jwst.jpg 1500w" width="512"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Much of the universe remains unknown. The James Webb telescope will hopefully provide a powerful window to help resolve some of the cosmos’s many mysteries.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/in-news-james-webb-space-telescope/"><strong>What is James Webb Space Telescope (JWST)? </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is a space telescope being jointly developed by NASA, the European Space Agency (ESA), and the Canadian Space Agency (CSA).</li>
<li>It has taken 30 years and $10bn to develop, and is being described as one of the grand scientific endeavors of the 21st Century.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Where it is placed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The James Webb Space Telescope will not be in orbit around the Earth, like the Hubble Space Telescope is – it will actually orbit the Sun, 1.5 million kilometres (1 million miles) away from the Earth at what is called the second Lagrange point or L2.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Mission</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It will be “a giant leap forward in quest to understand the Universe and our origins”, as it will examine every phase of cosmic history: from the Big Bang to the formation of galaxies, stars, and planets to the evolution of our own Solar System.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="james webb telescope " class="alignnone wp-image-627356" height="446" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 446px) 100vw, 446px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-768x770.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1-897x900.jpg 897w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/james-webb-telescope-1.jpg 1021w" width="446"/>Special features of JWST</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Time machine in space: </strong>Powerful space telescopes, like JWST or the Hubble Telescope, are often called time machines because of their ability to view very faraway objects. The light coming from those objects, stars or galaxies, which is captured by these telescopes, began its journey millions of years earlier. Essentially, what these telescopes see are images of these stars or galaxies as they were millions of years ago. The more distant the planet or star, the farther back in time are the telescopes able to see.</li>
<li><strong>Farthest from Earth: </strong>James Webb telescope will also be positioned much deeper into space, about a million miles from Earth, at a spot known as L2. It is one of the five points, known as Lagrange’s points, in any revolving two-body system like Earth and Sun, where the gravitational forces of the two large bodies cancel each other out.</li>
<li><strong>Engineering marvel: </strong>JWST has one large mirror, with a diameter of 21 feet (the height of a typical two-storey building), that will capture the infra-red light coming in from the deep universe while facing away from the Sun.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the goal of this telescope?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The telescope will be able to see just about anything in the sky.</li>
<li>However, it has one overriding objective – to see the light coming from the very first stars to shine in the Universe.</li>
<li>These pioneer stars are thought to have switched on about 100-200 million years after the Big Bang, or a little over 13.5 billion years ago.</li>
<li>James Webb telescope will be picking out groupings of these stars.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="james webb telescope " class="alignnone wp-image-627357" height="291" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 516px) 100vw, 516px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/STScI-01FH8W3VQA6DCG0V9KMQZE4DJC.jpg 1280w" width="516"/>Its significance</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is widely expected to unveil many secrets of the universe, particularly those related to the Formation of stars and galaxies in the early period the first few hundred million years after the Big Bang.</li>
<li>Some have called James Webb telescope  the “telescope that ate astronomy”.</li>
<li>It is said to look back in time to the Dark Ages of the universe.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The universe is vast and most of it is unknown. We hope that the James Webb telescope, over its lifetime would provide us with a powerful window to help resolve some of the many mysteries of the cosmos and make it a little bit more comprehensible.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What is James Webb telescope experiment? Do you think it shades light on dark matter? Explain.  </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/james-webb-telescope/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>5G revolution and challenges</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/5g-revolution/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of 5G</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>scientific achievements and issues with it</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="5G revolution " class="alignnone wp-image-625615" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-in-india-will-only-be-successful.jpeg 1200w" width="581"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Prime Minister Narendra Modi recently announced that 5G revolution deployment in India will commence sooner than expected.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is 5G technology?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>5G or fifth generation revolution  is the latest upgrade in the long-term evolution (LTE) mobile broadband networks.</li>
<li>5G enables a new kind of network that is designed to connect virtually everyone and everything together including machines, objects, and devices.</li>
<li>It’s a unified platform which is much more capable than previous mobile services with more capacity, lower latency, faster data delivery rate and better utilisation of spectrum.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How it evolved from 1G to 5G?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>1G: </strong>Launched in the 1980s. Analog radio signals and supported only voice calls.</li>
<li><strong>2G:</strong> Launched in the 1990s. Uses digital radio signals and supported both voice and data transmission with a Bandwidth (BW) of 64 Kbps.</li>
<li><strong>3G:</strong> Launched in the 2000s. With a speed of 1 Mbps to 2 Mbps it has the ability to transmit telephone signal including digitized voice, video calls and conferencing.</li>
<li><strong>4G</strong>: With a peak speed of 100 Mbps-1 Gbps it also enables 3D virtual reality.</li>
<li><strong>5G:</strong> with a speed of more than 1Gbps, it is capable of connecting entire world without limits.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="5G revolution" class="alignnone wp-image-625641" height="291" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 552px) 100vw, 552px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g1-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g1-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g1.jpg 392w" width="552"/>Salient features</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Capability:</strong> 5G will provide much faster mobile broadband service as compared to the previous versions and will provide support to previous services like mission critical communication and the massive Internet Of Things (IoT).</li>
<li><strong>Upgraded LTE</strong>: 5G is the latest upgrade in the long-term evolution (LTE) mobile broadband networks.</li>
<li><strong>Speed:</strong> With peak delivering rate of up to 20 Gbps and an average of 100Mbps, it will be much faster as compared to its predecessors. The speed increment is partly achieved partly by using higher-frequency radio waves than previous networks.</li>
<li><strong>Capacity</strong>: There will be up to 100 x increase in traffic capacity and network efficiency.</li>
<li><strong>Spectrum usage</strong>: Will provide better usage for every bit of spectrum, from low bands below 1 GHz to high bands.</li>
<li><strong>Latency</strong>: It’s expected to have lower latency with better instantaneous, real-time access of the data. The 5G, like 4G LTE, also uses Orthogonal Frequency Division Multiplexing (OFDM) but the new 5G NR (New Radio) air interface will enhance OFDM and provide better flexibility in data delivery.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><br/>
<img alt="5G revolution" class="alignnone wp-image-625634" height="176" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-300x81.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g-300x81.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/5g.jpg 718w" width="650"/>Applications of 5G technology</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>High-Speed mobile network</strong>: 5G will revolutionize the mobile experience with supercharged wireless network. Compared to conventional mobile transmission technologies, voice and high-speed data can be simultaneously transferred efficiently in 5G.</li>
<li><strong>Entertainment and multimedia</strong>: 5G can provide 120 frames per second, high resolution and higher dynamic range video streaming without interruption. Audiovisual experience will be rewritten after the implementation of the latest technologies powered by 5G wireless. Augmented Reality and virtual Reality services will be better experienced over 5G.</li>
<li><strong>Internet of Things</strong>: IoT applications collects huge amount of data from millions of devices and sensors and thus requires an efficient network for data collection, processing, transmission, control and real-time analytics which 5G network is a better candidate.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Interesting facts about 5G</strong></h4>
<p><strong>According to researchers, about 1.5 billion people will have access to 5G by 2024. </strong></p>
<p><strong>It may not seem like it at present, however, 5G will cover about 40% of the world.</strong></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>The security risks introduced BY 5G</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increased attack surface</strong>: With millions and even billions more connected devices, 5G makes it possible for larger and more dangerous attacks. Current and future vulnerabilities of the existing internet infrastructure are only exacerbated. The risk of more sophisticated botnets, privacy violations, and faster data extraction can escalate with 5G.</li>
<li><strong>More IoT, more problems</strong>: IoT devices are inherently insecure; security is often not built-in by design. Each insecure IoT device on an organization’s networks represents another potential hole that an attacker can expose.</li>
<li><strong>Decreased network visibility</strong>: With 5G, our networks will only expand and become more usable by mobile users and devices. This means much more network traffic to manage. But without a robust wide area network (WAN) security solution like Secure Access Service Edge (SASE) in place, companies may not be able to gain the network traffic visibility required to identify abnormalities or attacks.</li>
<li><strong>Increased supply chain and software vulnerabilities</strong>: Currently and for the foreseeable future, 5G supply chains are limited. Vulnerabilities exist — particularly as devices are rushed to market — increasing the potential for faulty and insecure components. Compared to traditional mobile networks, 5G is also more reliant on software, which elevates the risk of exploitation of the network infrastructure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges in rolling out 5G</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enabling critical infrastructures</strong>: 5G will require a fundamental change to the core architecture of the communication system. The major flaw of data transfer using 5G is that it can’t carry data over longer distances. Hence, even 5G technology needs to be augmented to enable infrastructure.</li>
<li><strong>Financial liability on consumers</strong>: For transition from 4G to 5G technology, one has to upgrade to the latest cellular technology, thereby creating financial liability on consumers.</li>
<li><strong>Capital Inadequacy</strong>: Lack of flow of cash and adequate capital with the suitable telecom companies (like Bharti Airtel and Vodafone Idea) is delaying the 5G spectrum allocation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India should not miss the opportunity and should proactively work to deploy 5G technology. We should focus on strengthening our cyber infrastructure.</li>
<li>5G start-ups that enable this design and manufacturing capabilities should be promoted. This will spur leaps in the coverage, capacity and density of wireless networks.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">Conclusion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The recent recommendation of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India to the government to develop a national road map for India to implement 5G in the best possible manner should include cyber security concerns.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. 5G is already transforming and enhancing connectivity. In this context Discuss India’s preparedness and cybersecurity challenges that needs to be taken care of for earlier roll out of 5G.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/5g-revolution/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Supreme Court’s basic structure doctrine in a new context</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/basic-structure/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Various judgements on basic structure</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Features of constitution</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="basic structure" class="alignnone wp-image-637988" height="285" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 506px) 100vw, 506px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BASIC-STRUCURE-DOCTRINE-IN-INDIAN-CONSTITUTION-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BASIC-STRUCURE-DOCTRINE-IN-INDIAN-CONSTITUTION-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BASIC-STRUCURE-DOCTRINE-IN-INDIAN-CONSTITUTION.jpg 560w" width="506"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The basic structure doctrine constitutes a high watermark in the assertion of the Supreme Court’s judicial power in the teeth of a determined majoritarian regime.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is basic structure of Constitution?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The basic structure doctrine is one of the fundamental judicial principles connected with the Indian Constitution. The doctrine of the basic structure holds that there is a basic structure to the Indian Constitution, and the Parliament of India cannot amend the basic features.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the significance of the basic structure in the Constitution of India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The doctrine of basic structure is nothing but a judicial innovation to ensure that the power of amendment is not misused by Parliament. The idea is that the basic features of the Constitution of India should not be altered to an extent that the identity of the Constitution is lost in the process.08-Dec-2021</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Courts are empowered under our Constitution to invalidate not only executive orders, but also legislative enactments that violate any part of the Fundamental Rights guaranteed in Part III of the Constitution (Bill of Rights).</li>
<li>But as to whether they are also empowered to adjudicate on the validity of constitutional amendments passed with the requisite special majority and following the procedure prescribed in Article 368 the Constitution is silent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="basic structure" class="alignnone wp-image-637989" height="412" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 731px) 100vw, 731px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r.jpeg 770w" width="731"/>Historical developments on evolution of basic structure doctrine </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Constitution provided a mechanism for parliament to amend the constitution in the form of article 368 but the nature and scope of this amending power was questioned in Supreme Court on multiple occasions. Supreme Court gave a series of judgement which ultimately culminated in probably the most landmark judgement Basic structure doctrine judgement.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Shankari Prasad Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Sajjan Singh Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Golakh Nath Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Kesvananda Bharati Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Minerva Mills case</strong></li>
<li><strong>I.R. Koelhi</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Constitutional Provisions</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>1st amendment and 9th schedule</strong></li>
<li><strong>24th amendment</strong></li>
<li><strong>42nd amendment</strong></li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<p>His holiness, Kesavananda bharati, challenged before the supreme court, the validity of 29th CAA which inserted some laws in 9th schedule and affected property of his Hindu Mutt.</p>
<h4><strong>What else was at stake?</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li>Supreme Court (R. C. Cooper case) had struck down bank nationalization act of 1969 which had nationalized 14 major banks for illusory compensation though it conceded parliament’s right to nationalise banks in national interest.</li>
<li>Supreme Court had struck down abolition of privy purses which was a betrayal of solemn promise to erstwhile kings by Sardar Patel.</li>
</ol>
<p>Supreme Court could do all this as it had held in 1967 in Golaknath case that fundamental rights could not be abridged.</p>
<p>Before returning back to Kesavananda, Let’s take a look at the relevant provisions of the constitution and Supreme Court interpretation of the same.</p>
<ul>
<li>Art 13(2) – Any LAW abridging fundamental rights mentioned in part 3 shall be null and void to the extent of contravention</li>
<li>Art 368 -Procedure to amend the constitution.</li>
<li>Art 19(f) – freedom to acquire hold on and dispose off property.</li>
<li>Art 31 – right to property</li>
</ul>
<p>Both the rights were subject to reasonable restriction in public interest and restriction were subject to judicial review.</p>
<p>Soon after the coming into force of the constitution, states enacted land reform acts #Zamindars challenged them. #Patna high court declared Bihar act as unconstitutional for violating right to property #interim parliament passed 1st CAA.</p>
<ol>
<li>ART 31B created 9th schedule. Laws inserted under it by constitutional amendment were immune to judicial review.</li>
</ol>
<p>Other provisions not imp for this article but imp for exams –</p>
<ol>
<li>Reasonable restrictions against freedom of expression under art 19.</li>
<li>To nullify judgment in State of Madras v. Champakam Dorairajan and giving effect to art 46 (promoting educational and economic interests of weaker sections) amplified article 15 (3)</li>
</ol>
<p>Zamindars didn’t like it, not one bit. And here comes the 1st salvo</p>
<h4><strong>Shankari Prasad v Union of India</strong></h4>
<p>Challenged 1st CAA. What was the court’s judgment?</p>
<ol>
<li>Difference b/w constituent power and ordinary legislative power i.e. amendment not law for the purpose of article 13</li>
<li>art 13 and 368 in conflict # apply DOCTRINE OF HARMONIOUS CONSTRUCTION # ART 13 not applicable to art 368</li>
</ol>
<p>Govt 1-0 Zamindars</p>
<p>Govt passed 17th amendment and inserted more laws under 9th schedule ‘</p>
<p>Zamindars fired another salvo-</p>
<h4><strong>Sajjan Singh vs state of rajasthan</strong></h4>
<p>Supreme Court sang Shankari prasad song again</p>
<p>Govt 2-0 jamindars</p>
<p>But Justice Mudholkar was of the view that the every Constitution has certain features which are basic in nature and those features cannot be changed.</p>
<p>2 minority judgements…. utter confusion. And you can see seeds of basic structure were sown here.</p>
<p>Zamindars fired 3rd salvo</p>
<h4><strong>Golaknath v. State of Punjab</strong></h4>
<p>11 judge bench overturned earlier 2 verdicts by a slender majority of 6-5</p>
<p>Really? What was the logic given here?</p>
<ol>
<li>Nothing to suggest constituent power to be separate from legislative power and even if distinct, amending power not same as constituent power which is given only to constituent assembly i.e. amendment is law and subject to article 13</li>
<li>Fundamental rights so sacrosanct and transcendental that they cannot be abridged even if whole parliament unanimously decided to abridge them.</li>
</ol>
<p>But it validated all previous land reform acts as nullifying them would create utter confusion</p>
<p>Govt angry – Zamindars angry</p>
<p>New landlords happy.</p>
<p>Loss – loss to defendants as well as petitioner.</p>
<p>Madam Indira was in power and she did not like this. Not one bit.</p>
<p>Along came 24th amendment to neutralize GOLAKNATH JUDGEMENT</p>
<ol>
<li>Art 13 inapplicable to art 368</li>
<li>Art 368 provided powers as well as procedure to amend the constitution</li>
<li>Parliament by way of addition, variation or repeal can amend any provision of constitution</li>
<li>President shall give assent to CA bills ( VERY VERY IMP FOR PRELIMS )</li>
</ol>
<p>But madam Indira wouldn’t just stop here as Cooper judgment (Bank nationalization ) also had to be neutralized.</p>
<p>Smarting from this setback, Madam Indira (the parliament, herself) passed 24th CAA to neutralise GOLAKNATH judgement. But there was also a small matter of reversing Copper judgment in bank nationalisation case so parliament passed 25th CAA.</p>
<ol>
<li>Art 19f delinked from 31, in effect parliament deciding compensation amount payable instead of courts.</li>
<li>Art 31c  -inserted under which – art 39b and c, most socialist of DPSPs (equitable distribution and prevention of concentration of wealth respectively) precede over 7 freedoms (art 19 ), equality (14), property (31)</li>
<li>Parliament’s power to determine if policy is to give effect to 39b and c not subject to judicial review.</li>
</ol>
<p>29th CAA had put Kerala land reform act under 9th schedule and his holiness challenged the provisions and all hell broke loose.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Now the 4th salvo</p>
<h4><strong><img alt="basic structure" class="alignnone wp-image-637990" height="345" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 616px) 100vw, 616px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1-300x168.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1-300x168.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1-768x431.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1.jpg 896w" width="616"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/kesavananda-bharati-case-1973-the-judgment-that-upheld-basic-structure-of-indias-constitution/">Kesvanada Bharati Case</a></strong></h4>
<p>A 13 judge bench is constituted and what does it do!</p>
<ol>
<li>Overturned Golaknath i.e. amendment not law, fundamental rights amendable, no implied limit under art 368 i.e. CAA 24 constitutional</li>
<li>Art 25 invalid to the extent it takes away judicial review i.e. 39 b and c above 14, 19 and 31 but subject to judicial review</li>
</ol>
<p>Most imp decision of all by slimmest of all 7-6 majority stated Parliament can amend any provision of the Constitution but the basic structure should not be destroyed, damaged or abrogated.</p>
<p>What’s the logic?</p>
<ol>
<li>Expression amendment did not encompass defacing the constitution such that it lost its identity.</li>
<li>In the garb of amendment parliament can not rewrite the constitution.</li>
</ol>
<p>Court gave relief to govt but reserved for itself power to review all amendment not just those that violate fundamental rights.</p>
<p>Aftermath</p>
<p>Indira Gandhi didn’t like the judgement one  bit. She (via the president) superseded 3 judges to appoint justice A.N. Ray as CJI.</p>
<p>Knives had been drawn and the battle was gonna be very bloody –</p>
<ul>
<li>Navnirman movement of JP (Jayprakash<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jayaprakash_Narayan" rel="noopener" target="_blank">)</a> had gathered steam, Indira was on the back foot and along came the judgement of Allahabad High Court convicting Indira of corrupt electoral practices. Election was declared null and void and  6 years ban to contest election was imposed on her.</li>
<li>Supreme Court stayed it and allowed her to remain PM but not to draw salary or speak or vote in parliament.</li>
<li>Darkest chapter in democracy’ 21 month emergency was declared on 25th June 1975 without even consulting cabinet (44th amendment made it mandatory for the president to have written advice of cabinet to declare emergency)</li>
</ul>
<p>Indira Gandhi wasn’t to sit quiet.</p>
<p>CAA 39th – election of president, VP, PM and speaker beyond judicial review</p>
<p>Clownish Rajnarayan challenged the CAA 39.</p>
<h4><strong>Indira Gandhi v/s Raj Narain Case</strong></h4>
<p>For the 1st time Supreme Court applied basic structure doctrine and considered free and fair election and rule of law to be part of basic structure. #amending act invalidated.</p>
<p>Note here that 4 of the 5 judges on the bench had given dissenting judgment in Bharati case but still applied the same doctrine for Supreme Court judgment becomes law until overruled by bigger bench (art 141).</p>
<p>Then how did Indira continue to be prime minister and contest election again and not get banned for 6 years?</p>
<p>Supreme court accepted retrospective amendment to electoral law i.e. electoral malpractice of Indira was no longer a corrupt practice.</p>
<p>Find out for fun the charges against Mrs. Gandhi for which she was convicted and what a popular British magazine had to say about the judgement.</p>
<p>Along came the mini constitution i.e 42nd amendment act TO ELIMINATE IMPEDIMENTS TO THE GROWTH OF THE CONSTITUTION –</p>
<ol>
<li>PART 4a fundamental duties</li>
<li>Socialist,secular and integrity word to preamble</li>
<li>New <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/indepth-understanding-of-the-directive-principles-of-state-policy/">DPSP</a>s were added</li>
</ol>
<p>And for the purpose of this article amendment to article 368 nullifying basic structure doctrine by adding amendments can’t be challenged in courts and parliament possessing unlimited power of amendment</p>
<ol start="4">
<li>All DPSPs to take precedence over all fundamental rights not just 39b and 39c.</li>
</ol>
<p>And Minerva Textile mills of Karnataka fired the 5th and the last salvo</p>
<h4><strong>Minerva Mills v Union of India</strong></h4>
<p>SC unanimously struck down amendment to article 368 holding limited amending power and judicial review to be part of basic structure.</p>
<p>Court held that constitution is founded on the bedrock of balance b/w FRs and DPSPs. Goals set out by DPSPs have to be achieved without abrogation of means provided by FRs.</p>
<p>What’s the logic?</p>
<p>If a donee was vested with limited power, it could not be exercised to control that very power power and convert into unlimited one.</p>
<p>Or</p>
<p>If a genie grants u 3 wishes, it is understood u can not, as one of the wish, ask for unlimited number of wishes!</p>
<p>Janta govt comes to power and 44th CAA deletes art 31 (b) right to property and 19 (f) freedom to acquire, hold and dispose of property as they were not considered part of basic structure</p>
<p>Right to property now a constitutional right under art 300A.</p>
<p>9th schedule and judicial review</p>
<h4><strong>I.R.Coelho vs state of TN</strong></h4>
<p>Supreme Court held that acts placed under 9th schedule after basic structure subject would be subject to judicial review to the extent of those acts violating basic structure of constitution.</p>
<p>Impact of basic structure doctrine.</p>
<p>It certainly saved Indian democracy from degenerating into authoritarian regime during those testing times but it has also given immense untold unbridled power to Supreme Court and made it the most powerful court in the world.</p>
<p>As we would later see in the NJAC Verdict (let’s call it 4th judges case), Supreme Court applied this doctrine, many would say for wrong reasons to strike down the act and kept for itself the power to appoint brother judges. In the original constitution only fetters on the power of parliament was art 13.</p>
<p>Relevance –  It was delivered at the time of single party rule both at the centre and most of the states. In the era of coalition politics no govt is going to wield so much power to destroy the constitution and then there is ever present danger of tyranny of unelected.</p>
<p>But only legitimate way to overturn the verdict would be a 15 judge bench so don’t hold your breath for that.</p>
<p>Now is the time for some thought questions</p>
<p>#1. Consider these 2 statements –</p>
<ol>
<li>Any LAW that is ordinary law violating provisions of constitution would be declared null and void to the extent of contravention.</li>
<li>Any LAW violating art 13 would be declared null and void</li>
</ol>
<p>Both statements are true…..If amendments were not law, what was the purpose of art 13 (2) other laws would anyway be declared unconstitutional!</p>
<p>#2. Is basic structure doctrine relevant in the present political scenario where no single party is unlikely to enjoy majority in both the houses?</p>
<p>#3. What should be the limits to amending power of parliament? Do u think for very substantial amendments instead of courts, people by way of referendum should determine whether amendment should go through or not?</p>
<p>#4. Whatever happens to original intent theory that constitutional courts have to interpret constitution in accordance with the implied intentions of founding fathers and there is enough evidence to suggest founding fathers thoughtfully kept FRs sacrosanct to prevent their abrogation or as we would see in a later article how supreme court by creative interpretation virtually changed procedure established by law in art 21 to due process of law while founding fathers deliberately kept expression as procedure established by law.</p>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>By restraining the amending powers of legislative organ of State, it provided basic Rights to Citizens which no organ of State can overrule. Being dynamic in nature, it is more progressive and open to changes in time unlike the rigid nature of earlier judgements.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. What do you understand by basic structure of constitution? Trace evolution of basic structure in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/basic-structure/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SC takes up pleas against Places of Worship Act</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-takes-up-pleas-against-places-of-worship-act/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Places of Worship Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with the Act</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has set the ball rolling on a series of petitions challenging the validity of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-places-of-worship-act/">Places of Worship Act of 1991</a>, a parliamentary law that protects the identity and character of religious places as on August 15, 1947.</p>
<h4>What are the petitions about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A slew of petitions has been filed against the Act.</li>
<li>The Act has fixed a retrospective cut-off date illegally barring Hindus, Jains, Buddhists and Sikhs from approaching courts to re-claim their places of worship which were invaded and encroached.</li>
<li>The main objective of these petitions is to set right a historical wrong committed by barbaric invaders.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Places of Worship Act, 1991</h4>
<ul>
<li>It was passed in 1991 by the P V Narasimha Rao-led government.</li>
<li>The law seeks to maintain the “religious character” of places of worship as it was in 1947 — except in the case of the Ram Janmabhoomi-Babri Masjid dispute, which was already in court.</li>
<li>The law was brought in at the peak of the Ram Mandir movement, exactly a year before the demolition of the Babri Masjid.</li>
<li>Introducing the law, then Home Minister S B Chavan said in Parliament that it was adopted to curb communal tension.</li>
</ul>
<p>What are its provisions?</p>
<h4>What are its provisions?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Anti-conversion:</strong> Section 3 of the Act bars the conversion, in full or part, of a place of worship of any religious denomination into a place of worship of a different religious denomination — or even a different segment of the same religious denomination.</li>
<li><strong>Holiness of a place:</strong> Section 4(1) declares that the religious character of a place of worship “shall continue to be the same as it existed” on August 15, 1947.</li>
<li><strong>Litigation:</strong> Section 4(2) says any suit or legal proceeding with respect to the conversion of the religious character of any place existing on August 15, 1947, pending before any court, shall abate — and no fresh suit or legal proceedings shall be instituted.</li>
<li><strong>Exception for Ayodhya:</strong> Section 5 stipulates that the Act shall not apply to the Ramjanmabhoomi-Babri Masjid case, and to any suit, appeal or proceeding relating to it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the law under challenge?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>cut-off date of August 15, 1947, is “arbitrary, irrational and retrospective</u></strong>” and prohibits Hindus, Jains, Buddhists, and Sikhs from approaching courts to “reclaim” their places of worship.</li>
<li>Such places, he argued, were “<strong><u>invaded” and “encroached” upon by “fundamentalist barbaric invaders</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The right-wing politicians have opposed the law even when it was introduced, arguing that the Centre has no power to legislate on “pilgrimages” or “burial grounds” which is under the state list.</li>
<li>Another criticism against the law is that the cut-off is the date of Independence, which means that the status quo determined by a colonial power is considered final.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-takes-up-pleas-against-places-of-worship-act/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Species in news: Tasmanian Tiger</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/species-in-news-tasmanian-tiger/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Tasmanian Tiger</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-623646" height="220" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tas-300x220.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tas-300x220.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/tas.jpg 607w" width="300"/></p>
<p>Scientists in the US and Australia have embarked on a $15-million project to resurrect the thylacine or Tasmanian Tiger, a marsupial that went extinct in the 1930s, using gene-editing technology.</p>
<h4>Tasmanian Tiger</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Tasmanian tiger or thylacine (a dog-headed pouched dog) was an exclusively carnivorous marsupial that is considered to be extinct.</li>
<li>It has a resemblance to a dog, with its distinguishing features being the dark stripes beginning at the rear of its body and extending into its tail, its stiff tail and abdominal pouch.</li>
<li>The last known thylacine died in captivity over 80 years ago, in Tasmania’s Hobart Zoo in 1936.</li>
<li>It may also be the only mammal to have become extinct in Tasmania since the European settlement.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did they become extinct?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It was confined to Tasmania in recent times and disappeared from mainland Australia over 2000 years ago, mainly because of over-hunting by humans, diseases and competition from the Dingo (Canis lupus), a wild dog native to Australia.</li>
<li>The Thylacine was also persecuted because it was believed to be a threat to sheep and in its latter years it was hunted for the purposes of collection by museums and zoos.</li>
<li>As per some accounts, the introduction of sheep in 1824 led to a conflict between the settlers and thylacine.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ambitious project aims to reintroduce the animal to its native place Tasmania to revive the region’s lost ecological balance.</li>
<li>Interestingly, this is not the first attempt to revive thylacines.</li>
<li>In 1999, an Australian scientist, Dr Michael Archer, embarked on an unsuccessful journey to resurrect the animal using cloning technology from a perfectly preserved specimen in a museum.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The resurrection process</h4>
<ul>
<li>Even though the last living thylacine died over 86 years ago, many embryos and young specimens of the species have been preserved.</li>
<li>Scientists will be using a genome sequenced from a DNA extracted from a 108-year-old specimen held at Australia’s Victoria Museum.</li>
<li>This genome will be compared with the closest living animal of the species– the fat tailed dunnart — to identify all the differences.</li>
<li>Once all the differences are identified, scientists will engineer the living cell’s DNA where it is different, essentially engineering the extinct species back.</li>
<li>The fat-tailed dunnart is a mouse-like species in the Dasyuridae family in Australia. With an average body length of 2.4–3.5 inches, they are one of the smallest carnivorous marsupials.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Criticisms of the move</h4>
<ul>
<li>Researchers have raised concerns about the practicality of the technology.</li>
<li>De-extinction is a fairytale science a/c to them and is more about media attention for the scientists and less about doing serious science.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: De-extinction technology</h4>
<ul>
<li>De-extinction, or resurrection biology, is the method of creating a species that went extinct or is endangered, in order to revitalise ecological diversity and balance shattered due to reasons ranging from biodiversity loss to climate change.</li>
<li>While cloning is the most widely used method of de-extinction, genome editing and selective breeding are also considered effective ways.</li>
<li>The Pyrenean ibex, a subspecies of Spanish ibex, was one of the first extinct animals that have been resurrected using somatic cell nuclear transfer (SCNT).</li>
<li>However, the baby Ibex died minutes after its birth from lung defect.</li>
<li>One of the challenges of de-extinction is that reintroducing the species to its former habitat may make it an invasive species, which will also impact the balance of the current ecological system.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/species-in-news-tasmanian-tiger/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The hijab case and the doctrine of essentiality</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/doctrine-of-essentiality-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of doctrine of essentiality</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>judicial reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="doctrine of essentiality" class="alignnone wp-image-638019" height="496" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 755px) 100vw, 755px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/19hijab-1140302-1661758240-300x197.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/19hijab-1140302-1661758240-300x197.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/19hijab-1140302-1661758240-1024x671.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/19hijab-1140302-1661758240.jpg 1200w" width="755"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A two-judge Bench of the Supreme Court of India is presently hearing arguments on the correctness of a Karnataka High Court judgment that upheld the ban on the use of the hijab by students in Karnataka which raises question on doctrine of essentiality.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> </strong><strong>What is ‘doctrine of essentiality’? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A seven-judge Bench of the Supreme Court invented the doctrine of “essentiality” in the Shirur Mutt case in 1954. The court held that the term “religion” will cover all rituals and practices “integral” to a religion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Importance doctrine of essentiality</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the legal framework, the doctrine of essentiality is a doctrine that has evolved to protect the religious practices that are essential or integral and does not violate any fundamental right. India being a secular country has discrete religious beliefs and to deny any is to violate the freedom of religion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why hijab is not an essential practice?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Wearing of hijab (head scarf) by Muslim women does not form a part of essential religious practices in Islamic faith and it is not protected under the right to freedom of religion guaranteed under Article 25 of the Constitution of India, the High Court of Karnataka declared on March 15 2022.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="doctrine of essentiality" class="alignnone wp-image-638020" height="366" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 594px) 100vw, 594px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/r04jg7b8_hijab-row-protest_650x400_15_February_22-300x185.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/r04jg7b8_hijab-row-protest_650x400_15_February_22-300x185.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/r04jg7b8_hijab-row-protest_650x400_15_February_22.jpg 650w" width="594"/>Is hijab essential part of Islam?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Qur’an instructs Muslim women and men to dress modestly, and for some, the hijab is worn by Muslim girls and women to maintain modesty and privacy from unrelated males. According to the Encyclopedia of Islam and Muslim World, modesty concerns both men’s and women’s “gaze, gait, garments, and genitalia”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How do you identify essential religion practice?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Court observed that in order to determine whether or not a particular practice is an essential part of religion, the test must be whether the absence of the practice itself</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/op-ed-snap-the-warp-and-weft-of-religious-liberty/"><strong>Meaning of Article 26</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Freedom to manage religious affairs Subject to public order, morality and health, every religious denomination or any section thereof shall have the right.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="doctrine of essentiality" class="alignnone wp-image-638021" height="417" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 626px) 100vw, 626px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1.jpg 1200w" width="626"/>Examples of the essential religious practices test</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While these issues are largely understood to be community-based, there are instances in which the court has applied the test to individual freedoms as well.</li>
<li>In a 2004 ruling, the Supreme Court held that the Ananda Marga sect had no fundamental right <strong>to <u>perform the Tandava dance in public</u></strong> streets since it did not constitute an essential religious practice of the sect.</li>
<li>For example, in 2016, the Supreme Court upheld the discharge of an airman from the Indian Air Force <strong>for <u>keeping a beard</u>.</strong></li>
<li>It distinguished the case of a Muslim airman from that of Sikhs who are allowed to keep a beard.</li>
<li>In 2015, the Supreme Court restored <strong>the<u> Jain religious practice of Santhara/Sallekhan</u>a</strong> (a ritualistic fast unto death) by staying an order of the Rajasthan HC.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="doctrine of essentiality" class="alignnone wp-image-637989" height="336" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 596px) 100vw, 596px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r.jpeg 770w" width="596"/>What is the Supreme Court’s judgement on Doctrine of Essentiality?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The doctrine of “essentiality” was invented by a seven-judge Bench of the Supreme Court in the ‘Shirur Mutt’ case in 1954.</li>
<li>It is a contentious doctrine evolved by the court to protect only such religious practices which were essential and integral to the religion.</li>
<li>The court held that the term “religion” will cover all rituals and practices “integral” to a religion, and took upon itself the responsibility of determining the essential and non-essential practices of a religion.</li>
<li>Referring to the Ayodhya case, the Constitution Bench had ruled in 1994 that A mosque is not an essential part of the practice of the religion of Islam and namaz (prayer) by Muslims can be offered anywhere, even in open.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How has the doctrine been used in subsequent years?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ‘essentiality doctrine’ of the Supreme Court has been criticised by several constitutional experts.</li>
<li>Scholars of constitutional law have argued that the essentiality/integrality doctrine has tended to lead the court into an area that is beyond its competence, and given judges the power to decide purely religious questions.</li>
<li>As a result, over the years, courts have been inconsistent on this question — in some cases they have relied on religious texts to determine essentiality.</li>
<li>In others it relied on the empirical behaviour of followers, and in yet others, based on whether the practice existed at the time the religion originated.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues over the doctrine</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the beginning, the court engaged with the question of whether untouchability, manifested in restrictions on entry into temples, was an “essential part of the Hindu religion”.</li>
<li>After examining selected Hindu texts, it came to the conclusion that untouchability was not an essential Hindu practice.</li>
<li>The idea of providing constitutional protection only to those elements of religion which the court considers “essential” is problematic as it assumes that one element or practice of religion is independent of other elements or practices.</li>
<li>So, while the essentiality test privileges certain practices over others, it is, in fact, all practices taken together that constitute a religion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does essentiality square up against religious freedom?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Freedom of religion was meant to guarantee freedom to practice one’s beliefs based on the concept of “inward association” of man with God.</li>
<li>The apex court in ‘Ratilal Panachand Gandhi vs The State of Bombay and Ors’ (March 18, 1954) acknowledged that “every person has a fundamental right to entertain such religious beliefs as may be approved by his judgment or conscience”.</li>
<li>The framers of the Constitution wanted to give this autonomy to each individual. Scholars have argued that the essentiality test impinges on this autonomy.</li>
<li>The apex court has itself emphasised autonomy and choice in its Privacy (2017), 377 (2018), and Adultery (2018) judgments.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Its effect on society</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Narrowing of safeguards to religious customs:</strong> It has allowed the Court to narrow the extent of safeguards available to religious customs by directly impinging on the autonomy of groups to decide for themselves what they deem valuable, violating, in the process, their right to ethical independence.</li>
<li><strong>Negated legislation that might otherwise enhance the cause of social</strong> <strong>justice</strong>: It has also negated legislation that might otherwise enhance the cause of social justice by holding that such laws cannot under any circumstances encroach on matters integral to the practice of a religion. For example, in 1962, the Court struck down a Bombay law that prohibited excommunications made by the Dai of the Dawoodi Bohra community when it held that the power to excommunicate is an essential facet of faith and that any measure aimed at social welfare cannot reform a religion out of its existence.</li>
<li><strong>A principle of anti-exclusion:</strong> Its application would require the Court to presume that a practice asserted by a religious group is, in fact, essential to the proponents of its faith. But regardless of such grounding, the Constitution will not offer protection to the practice if it excludes people on grounds of caste, gender, or other discriminatory criteria.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>For now, any Court hearing a matter touching upon a matter of faith has the unenviable task of acting not merely as an expert on law but also as an expert on religion.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Every person has a fundamental right to entertain such religious beliefs as may be approved by his judgment or conscience. Critically examine in context of doctrine of essentiality.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/doctrine-of-essentiality-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Backsliding on climate action</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/backsliding-on-climate-action/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Paris agreement</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Climate change</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>Europe is staring at a recession and its appetite for climate action is waning.</p>
<h4>Developed countries moving away from commitment</h4>
<ul>
<li>Countries in Europe led by Germany, Austria and the Netherlands are cranking up their coal plants again.</li>
<li>Fossil fuels are making a comeback and countries are rejecting the European Union (EU)’s plan to reduce natural gas consumption by 15%. Dutch, Polish and other European farmers are protesting against emission cuts from agriculture.</li>
<li>In the U.S. too, the Senate and the Supreme Court have struck blows to climate action.</li>
<li>And in the U.S. too, prices of fuel started increasing last year, not just this year.</li>
<li>Fossil fuels are making a quiet comeback, since the strength of the U.S. is its oil and gas industry.</li>
<li>That is why we have just witnessed a ‘re-calibration’ of U.S. policy towards the Gulf.</li>
<li>Coal, oil and gas are not going anywhere in the developed world; they are, in fact, making a comeback.</li>
<li>The West had rushed to draw down on fossil fuels even before technology for renewables were in place.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Global peaking issue</h4>
<ul>
<li>Article 4 of the Paris Agreement defines ‘Global Peaking’ thus: “In order to achieve the long-term temperature goal set out in Article 2, Parties aim <strong>to reach global peaking</strong> of greenhouse gas emissions as soon as possible, recognizing that peaking will take longer for developing country Parties.”</li>
<li>The developed countries, given their historical emissions, will have to peak first.</li>
<li>That’s why the reference is to<strong> ‘global peaking’</strong> and not ‘individual peaking’.</li>
<li>From this, it logically follows that when developing country parties peak later than developed countries, they will also achieve net zero later than developed countries.</li>
<li>Consequently, it is the logical conclusion of the Article 4 of the Paris Agreement that when we consider net zero, we should only consider ‘global net zero’ and not ‘individual net zero’ for 2050.</li>
<li>The statement calls on developed countries to do a net negative on mitigation by 2050 rather than just “net zero”, if they are serious about fighting climate change.</li>
<li>In effect, the West needs to do a net minus and not just net zero.</li>
<li>Thanks to the efforts of India, the phrase used in the 2021 summit-level declarations at both G-20 and Quad is ‘global net zero’. We need to build on this understanding.</li>
<li>India stands as beacon of hope in renewables.</li>
<li>It is time for all developing countries, especially the small island developing states, to make sure that the developed world doesn’t backslide on its commitments on mitigation yet again.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward for developing countries</h4>
<ul>
<li>With countries of the developed world almost sure to renege on their 2030 Paris Agreement commitments, countries of the developing world must do everything to hold the countries of the developed world to their commitments.</li>
<li>The Western nations have already started reinterpreting the Paris Agreement and look to downgrade their commitments.</li>
<li>The concept of net zero is being cleverly misinterpreted.</li>
<li> To bring this to the attention of the Global South, India, China and eight other countries from Africa, Asia and Latin America made a cross-regional statement on ‘global net zero’ on June 7 at the UN on World Environment Day.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>COP 27 in Egypt gives us that opportunity to hold their feet to the fire. It is time for the developed world to make net minus pledges. If we don’t collectively push for it, we will be collectively pushed back.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/backsliding-on-climate-action/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Fruit Fly: Novel method to study Nuclear Matrix</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nuclear Matrix</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627770" height="489" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 566px) 100vw, 566px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly.jpg 665w" width="566"/></p>
<p>Now, using a novel method, Indian researchers have established a way of studying the nuclear matrix of the fruit fly (Drosophila melanogaster) without removing the nucleus from the embryo.</p>
<h4>Nuclear Matrix of fruit flies</h4>
<ul>
<li>Every cell that makes up an organism contains a copy of its genome.</li>
<li>This genome is packaged in special ways with the help of a structure known as the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>The nuclear matrix gives an organisation and architecture to the nucleus.</li>
<li>A familiar figure, the nuclear matrix of fruit flies, for instance, has been studied for many years, mainly by isolating it in nuclei that have been taken out from fruit fly embryos.</li>
<li>This allows comparative study of nuclear matrix in different cells within the embryo, giving a boost for fruit fly genetics.</li>
<li>Two of the most recent papers on this work have been published in the journals Nucleus and Molecular and Cell Proteomics.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What exactly is Nuclear Matrix?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The nuclear matrix is like a scaffolding.</li>
<li>Using biochemical means, if the nucleus is taken out and treated with an enzyme that digests all the DNA.</li>
<li>It is then washed with a solution of high salt concentration so that viable DNA proteins or protein-protein interactions are removed.</li>
<li>What is then left is a fibrous meshwork of proteins called the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>This is like a building from which all movables have been sucked out, leaving only the beams, ceiling, and walls, plug points, etc.</li>
<li>Analogous to the building, the nuclear matrix creates the architecture in which the genome is packaged.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why study them?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Studying the nuclear matrix is, therefore, very important to get a better picture of how precisely development progresses every time a new individual is born.</li>
<li>We have 220 different types of cells in the body, but all contain identical genomes.</li>
<li>The same genome sequence is present in neurons, where it works for thinking; in the liver, the same sequence enacts metabolism; and in the intestine, it works to digest.</li>
<li>So, this information is packaged differently in different cell types.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was Ramon Magsaysay of Philippines?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-ramon-magsaysay-of-philippines/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ramon Magsaysay</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-631406" height="237" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 350px) 100vw, 350px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay-300x203.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay-300x203.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay.jpg 637w" width="350"/></p>
<p>A leftist leader and former Kerala health minister has declined to receive the Ramon Magsaysay Award as the late President of the Philippines was known for his alleged brutality against the Communists.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lunched in 1958, the Ramon Magsaysay Award, widely considered to be Asia’s equivalent to the Nobel Prize, recognises outstanding leadership and communitarian contributions in Asia.</li>
<li>This year’s annual list of awardees was announced last week.</li>
<li>Shailaja was considered for the award for her performance as state health minister from 2016 to 2021, a period which saw Kerala fight against the Nipah virus and Covid-19.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who was Ramon Magsaysay?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Born on August 31, 1907 to a father who worked as a blacksmith and a mother who was a teacher, Ramon Del Fierro Magsaysay Senior was the seventh president of the Philippines, from 1953 until his death in an air crash in 1957.</li>
<li>Magsaysay started out as an automobile mechanic before being drafted into the Pacific War (1941-1945), during World War II.</li>
<li>The Pacific War would see the Japanese occupation of the Philippines — then a colony of the US — for nearly four years.</li>
<li>The US formally recognised the Philippines as an independent nation in 1946.</li>
</ul>
<h4>His legacy</h4>
<ul>
<li>As a guerrilla leader resisting the Japanese occupation, Magsaysay’s bravery and leadership saw his appointment as a military governor.</li>
<li>In 1946, he would be elected under the Liberal Party to the Philippine House of Representatives, where he would serve two terms as a Congressman before being appointed secretary of National Defence in 1950.</li>
<li>On December 30, 1953, he would be elected president from the Nationalist Party, the oldest political party in the Philippines.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Communism and Magsaysay</h4>
<ul>
<li>Founded in 1902, the Unión Obrera Democrática is considered the first modern trade federation in the Philippines.</li>
<li>The Communist Party of the Philippines or the Partido Komunista ng Pilipinas (PKP) was formed in 1930.</li>
<li>The Hukbong Bayan Laban sa Hapon or the People’s Army Against the Japanese, popularly known as the Hukbalahap (Huk), was a prominent guerrilla outfit that fought the Japanese.</li>
<li>As the country plunged into post-war chaos after 1946, the fortunes of the Hukbalahaps, too, changed dramatically.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How he rose to his fame?</h4>
<ul>
<li>With the expansion of capitalism, the gap between the rich and poor widened and the farmers continued to languish.</li>
<li>Huk leaders were viewed with suspicion over their declaration of commitment to communism and the demand for peasant rights.</li>
<li>With the US as its close ally, the Philippine government cracked down on the Huks, who formed an alliance with the PKP to take their struggle to a parliamentary platform.</li>
<li>The severe crackdown against the Huks continued until Magsaysay became the National Defence Secretary under President Elpidio Quirino.</li>
<li>Magsaysay drew upon his own experience of guerrilla warfare to initiate a two-pronged system of reforms and military campaigns.</li>
<li>It was under his administrative and military policies that the Huk threat was considered to be neutralised.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Ramon Magsaysay Award</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 1957, the Ramon Magsaysay award was set up by trustees of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund and the Philippine government to carry forward Magsaysay’s legacy of service to the people, good governance, and pragmatic idealism.</li>
<li>In the six decades since 1958 — the first year the Award was given out — over 300 organisations and individuals have been recognised for their developmental endeavours crucial to Asia, and, consequently, to the world.</li>
<li>The award is given out every year on August 31, on Magsaysay’s birth anniversary.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Indian winners on the list</h4>
<ul>
<li>Prominent Indians who have won the award include Vinoba Bhave in 1958, Mother Teresa in 1962, Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay in 1966, Satyajit Ray in 1967, Mahasweta Devi in 1997.</li>
<li>In recent years, Arvind Kejriwal (2006), Anshu Gupta of Goonj (2015), human rights activist Bezwada Wilson (2016), and journalist Ravish Kumar (2019) have won the award.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-ramon-magsaysay-of-philippines/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is a Triple-Dip La Nina?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-triple-dip-la-nina/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Triple Dip La-Nina</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="nina" class="alignnone wp-image-356942" height="197" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 444px) 100vw, 444px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/enso-300x133.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/enso-300x133.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/11/enso.jpg 708w" width="444"/></p>
<p>Parts of the world are expected to experience severe weather for the rest of the year and into 2023, as part of a rare “triple dip La Nina” event, according to the World Meteorological Organization (WMO).</p>
<h4><strong>El Nino and La Nina</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While El Niño (Spanish for ‘little boy’), the more common expression, is the abnormal surface warming observed along the eastern and central regions of the Pacific Ocean (the region between Peru and Papua New Guinea).</li>
<li>The La Niña (Spanish for ‘little girl’) is an abnormal cooling of these surface waters.</li>
<li>Together, the El Niño (Warm Phase) and La Niña (Cool Phase) phenomena are termed as El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO).</li>
<li>These are large-scale ocean phenomena which influence the global weather — winds, temperature and rainfall. They have the ability to trigger extreme weather events like droughts, floods, hot and cold conditions, globally.</li>
<li>Each cycle can last anywhere between 9 to 12 months, at times extendable to 18 months — and re-occur after every three to five years.</li>
<li>Meteorologists record the sea surface temperatures for four different regions, known as Niño regions, along this equatorial belt.</li>
<li>Depending on the temperatures, they forecast either as an El Niño, an ENSO neutral phase, or a La Niña.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> What is the “Triple-Dip” La Nina? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A “triple-dip” La Nina is a <strong><u>multiyear cooling of the surface temperature of the equatorial Pacific Ocean</u></strong>, which can cause droughts, fierce winds and heavy rainfall.</li>
<li>According to WMO, the current La Nina is projected to span three consecutive northern hemisphere winters. It began in September 2020.</li>
<li>If it continues for the next six months, it will be the first “triple-dip” La Nina event of the 21st century, WMO says.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How rare is this triple-dip?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is exceptional to have three consecutive years with a la Nina event.</li>
<li>Its cooling influence is temporarily slowing the rise in global temperatures – but it will not halt or reverse the long-term warming trend.</li>
<li>La Nina’s are usually preceded by El Nino, a weather pattern that warms the surface of the eastern tropical Pacific Ocean.</li>
<li>However, an El Nino event did not occur before the current La Nina.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Has it happened before? Will it happen again?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>La Nina’s occurred several times between 1903 to 2010 and 2010 to 2012.</li>
<li>This would be the first “triple-dip” La Nina this century.</li>
<li>However, it is not unprecedented for the weather pattern to last more than nine months to a year, which is typical for a La Nina.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Evaluating the likely impact</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the Indian context, La Nina is associated with good rainfall during the monsoon season.</li>
<li>This is the opposite of El Nino which is known to suppress monsoon rainfall.</li>
<li>Thus, a continued spell of La Nina could lead to expectation of another year of good, or normal, rainfall during the monsoon.</li>
<li>Until now, the monsoon season this year has produced 7% more rain compared to normal. Last year, the seasonal rainfall was almost 100%.</li>
<li>But, even though powerful, ENSO condition is only one of the several factors affecting monsoon rainfall in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Impact on rainfall</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is no one-on-one correlation between the ENSO condition and the amount of rainfall.</li>
<li>Also, the influence of ENSO is at a macro level.</li>
<li>There are wide variations in rainfall at the local level, which are getting exacerbated by climate change.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Differential impacts of this triple-dip event</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The continuance of La Nina further into 2023 is not bad news from the Indian standpoint. But it is not the same for many other regions where La Nina has very different impacts.</li>
<li>In most parts of the <strong><u>United States</u></strong>, for example, La Nina is associated with <strong><u>very dry winters</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In <strong><u>Australia and Indonesia</u></strong>, and generally in the tropical region, La Nina is expected to bring <strong><u>more rainfall.</u></strong></li>
<li>The <strong><u>excessive rainfall in Pakistan</u></strong>, which is experiencing its worst flooding disaster, can also be blamed in part on La Nina.</li>
<li>It said that the persistence of La Nina was most likely to result in a worsening of the <strong><u>drought in Africa</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is its climate change link?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Every</u></strong><u> <strong>unusual weather event these days is attributed to climate change</strong></u>, but science is not conclusive right now.</li>
<li>The occurrences of El Nino or La Nina are not very regular.</li>
<li>Sometimes they emerge every two years, at other times there has been a gap of even seven years.</li>
<li>Historical records do not go very far in the past.</li>
<li>As a result, the natural variability of ENSO is not understood very clearly.</li>
<li>And when the natural variability itself is not clear, the influence of global warming is difficult to quantify.</li>
<li>But there is clearer evidence of another kind of linkage with global warming.</li>
<li>During La Nina years, the colder surfaces allow the oceans to absorb more heat from the atmosphere.</li>
<li>Consequently, the air temperatures tend to go down, producing a cooling effect.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-triple-dip-la-nina/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Southwest Monsoon begins early Withdrawal/Retreat</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/monsoon-begins-early-withdrawal-retreat/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Retreat of Monsoon</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The southwest monsoon rainfall, 7% more than normal, has started to withdraw.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Monsoon Withdrawal/Retreat?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In India, retreating <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/various-terms-related-to-indian-monsoon/">monsoon</a> is the withdrawal of south-west monsoon winds from North India.</li>
<li>The withdrawal is gradual and takes about three months.</li>
<li>With the retreat of the monsoons, the clouds disappear and the sky becomes clear. The day temperature starts falling steeply.</li>
<li>Monsoon rains weaken all over India except few southeastern states.</li>
<li>It is helpful in Rabi crop cultivation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Factors affecting the retreat</strong></h4>
<p>Two predominant factors cause the phenomenon:</p>
<p><strong>(1) Land topography</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>First, the low mountain range in each region runs from north to south, shielding it from west-bound winds that trigger summer monsoon.</li>
<li>After summer, the range aids in the ‘orographic lift’ or rising of east-bound air mass from a lower to higher elevation, forming clouds and resulting in rain.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Atmospheric convection</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The second factor is atmospheric convection or vertical movement of air.</li>
<li>As the earth is heated by the sun, different surfaces absorb different amounts of energy and convection may occur where the surface heats up very rapidly.</li>
<li>As the surface warms, it heats the overlying air, which gradually becomes less dense than the surrounding air and begins to rise.</li>
<li>This condition is more favorable from September to February because of the role played by sea surface temperature or water temperature.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Immediate factors influencing withdrawal</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The withdrawal of the monsoon is based on meteorological conditions such as-</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Anti-cyclonic circulation (dry air that is the opposite of a cyclone)</li>
<li>Absence of rain in the past five days and</li>
<li>Dry weather conditions over the region</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>When does it occur?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The monsoon withdrawal is a long-drawn process and extends into mid-October, though the <strong><u>IMD considers September 30 to be the final day</u></strong> of the season over India.</li>
<li>The rain after that is categorised as “<strong><u>post-monsoon</u></strong>” rainfall.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ:</h4>
<p><strong>Q.The seasonal reversal of winds is the typical characteristic of:</strong></p>
<p>(a) Equatorial climate</p>
<p>(b) Mediterranean climate</p>
<p>(c) Monsoon climate</p>
<p>(d) All of the above climates</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="I4EHflyfgs"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/various-terms-related-to-indian-monsoon/">Various terms related to Indian Monsoon</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="I4EHflyfgs" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/various-terms-related-to-indian-monsoon/embed/#?secret=U6HYHuUCWH#?secret=I4EHflyfgs" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“Various terms related to Indian Monsoon” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/monsoon-begins-early-withdrawal-retreat/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Explained: Lumpy Skin Disease in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-lumpy-skin-disease-in-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Lumpy Skin Disease</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="lumpy" class="alignnone wp-image-638582 size-medium" height="251" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lumpy-300x251.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lumpy-300x251.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lumpy.jpg 523w" width="300"/></strong></p>
<p>The Mumbai Police have ordered the prohibition of cattle transportation in the city to prevent the spread of the lumpy skin disease (LSD).</p>
<h4><strong>What is the Lumpy Skin Disease?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Lumpy skin disease is caused by the lumpy skin disease <strong><u>virus</u></strong> (LSDV), which belongs to the genus capripoxvirus, a part of the poxviridae family.</li>
<li>Smallpox and monkeypox viruses are also a part of the same family.</li>
<li>The LSDV shares antigenic similarities with the sheeppox virus (SPPV) and the goatpox virus (GTPV) or is similar in the immune response to those viruses.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does it spread?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is <strong><u>not a zoonotic virus</u></strong>, meaning the disease <strong><u>cannot spread to humans</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It is a <strong><u>contagious vector-borne disease</u></strong> spread by vectors like mosquitoes, some biting flies, and ticks and usually affects host animals like cows and water buffaloes.</li>
<li>Infected animals shed the virus through oral and nasal secretions which may contaminate common feeding and water troughs.</li>
<li>Thus, the disease <strong><u>can either spread through direct contact</u></strong> with the vectors or through contaminated fodder and water.</li>
<li>Studies have also shown that it can spread through animal semen during artificial insemination.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does it affect the animal?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>LSD affects the lymph nodes of the infected animal, causing the nodes to enlarge and appear like lumps on the skin, which is where it derives its name from.</li>
<li>The cutaneous nodules, 2–5 cm in diameter, appear on the infected cattle’s head, neck, limbs, udder, genitalia, and perineum.</li>
<li>The nodules may later turn into ulcers and eventually develop scabs over the skin.</li>
<li>The other symptoms include high fever, sharp drop in milk yield, discharge from the eyes and nose, salivation, loss of appetite, depression, damaged hides, wasting of animals, infertility and abortions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Do it kills the animal?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The incubation period or the time between infection and symptoms is about 28 days according to the FAO, and 4 to 14 days according to some other estimates.</li>
<li>The morbidity of the disease varies between two to 45% and mortality or rate of date is less than 10%.</li>
<li>However, the reported mortality of the current outbreak in India is up to 15%, particularly in cases being reported in the western part (Rajasthan) of the country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the geographical distribution and how did it spread to India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The disease was <strong><u>first observed in Zambia</u></strong> in 1929.</li>
<li>Subsequently it got spread to most African countries, followed by West Asia, Southeastern Europe, and Central Asia, and more recently spreading to South Asia and China in 2019.</li>
<li>As per the FAO, the LSD disease is currently endemic in several countries across Africa, parts of the West Asia (Iraq, Saudi Arabia, Syrian Arab Republic), and Turkey.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Lumpy in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The spread in South Asia first affected Bangladesh in July 2019 and then reached India in August that year, with initial cases being detected in Odisha and West Bengal.</li>
<li>The long porous borders between India, Nepal and Bangladesh allow for a significant amount of bilateral and informal animal trade, including cattle and buffaloes.</li>
<li>This may have contributed to the spread of LSD in July-August 2019 between Bangladesh and India.</li>
<li>While the 2019 outbreak later subsided, the recent spread in India began in June this year.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Is it safe to consume the milk of affected cattle?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Studies say that it has <strong><u>not been possible to ascertain</u></strong> the presence of viable and infectious LSDV virus in milk derived from the infected animal.</li>
<li>However, that a large portion of the milk in Asia is <strong><u>processed</u></strong> after collection and is either <strong><u>pasteurised</u></strong> or boiled or dried in order to make milk powder.</li>
<li>This process ensures that the <strong><u>virus is inactivated</u></strong> or destroyed.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Economic implications of Lumpy on Dairy Sector</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Milk reduction:</strong> Lumpy leads to reduced milk production as the animal becomes weak and also loses appetite due to mouth ulceration.</li>
<li><strong>Animal wasting:</strong> The income losses can also be due to poor growth, reduced draught power capacity and reproductive problems associated with abortions, infertility and lack of semen for artificial insemination.</li>
<li><strong>Impact of trade ban:</strong> Movement and trade bans after infection also put an economic strain on the whole value chain.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why India is at higher risk?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India is the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/making-india-a-major-milk-exporting-nation/"><strong>world’s largest milk producer</strong></a> at about 210 million tonnes annually.</li>
<li>India also has the <strong><u>largest headcount of bovines</u></strong></li>
<li>In Rajasthan, which is witnessing the worst impact of LSD, it has led to reduced milk production, which lessened by about three to six lakh litres a day.</li>
<li>Reports indicate that milk production has also gone down in Punjab owing to the spread of the disease.</li>
<li>According to FAO, the disease threatens the livelihoods of smaller poultry farmers significantly.</li>
<li>Notably, farmers in Uttar Pradesh and Punjab have incurred losses due to cattle deaths and are seeking compensation from their State governments.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How bad is the current spread in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Lumpy has <strong><u>infected over 16 lakh cattle</u></strong> in 197 districts as of September 11.</li>
<li>Of the nearly 75,000 cattle that the disease has killed, more than 50,000 deaths, mostly cows, have been reported from Rajasthan.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Remedies available in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Union Ministry of Fisheries, Animal Husbandry and Dairying informed that the ‘<strong><u>Goat Pox Vaccine</u></strong>’ is very effective against LSD.</li>
<li>It is being used across affected States to contain the spread.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<p>The FAO has suggested a set of spread-control measures for LSD, which involves:</p>
<ul>
<li>Vaccination of susceptible populations with more than 80% coverage</li>
<li>Movement control of bovine animals and quarantining</li>
<li>Implementing biosecurity through vector control by sanitising sheds and spraying insecticides</li>
<li>Strengthening active and passive surveillance</li>
<li>Spreading awareness on risk mitigation among all stakeholders involved, and</li>
<li>Creating large protection and surveillance zones and vaccination zones</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-lumpy-skin-disease-in-india/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why only 2 firms chose Pre-Pack IBC resolution in a year?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pre-pack-ibc-resolution/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Pre-Packs, IBC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="pre-pack" class="alignnone wp-image-638581" height="335" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 574px) 100vw, 574px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pre-pack-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pre-pack-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pre-pack.jpg 652w" width="574"/></strong></p>
<p>India introduced the pre-packaged insolvency resolution process (PPIRP) in April 2021, as an alternative resolution process for micro, small and medium enterprises (MSMEs). However, it has only two cases admitted under it so far.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code (IBC)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The IBC was enacted in 2016 to simplify insolvency and bankruptcy proceedings, safeguard interests of all stakeholders (the firm, employees, debtors and especially creditors), and resolve non-performing assets.</li>
<li>From a ‘debtor in possession’ regime, it was a shift to a ‘creditor in control’ one.</li>
<li>IBC provides for a time-bound process for resolving insolvencies.</li>
<li>The Insolvency and Bankruptcy Board of India (IBBI) is the regulator implementing the code and overseeing the functioning of stakeholders.</li>
<li>The IBBI last week allowed payment of performance-linked incentives to resolution professionals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Pre-packs?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A pre-pack is the resolution of the debt of a distressed company through an agreement between secured creditors and investors instead of a public bidding process.</li>
<li>This system of insolvency proceedings has become an increasingly popular mechanism for insolvency resolution in the UK and Europe over the past decade.</li>
<li>Under the pre-pack system, financial creditors will agree to terms with a potential investor and seek approval of the resolution plan from the National Company Law Tribunal (NCLT).</li>
<li>The approval of a minimum of 66 percent of financial creditors that are unrelated to the corporate debtor would be required before a resolution plan is submitted to the NCLT.</li>
<li>Further NCLTs are also required to either accept or reject any application for a pre-pack insolvency proceeding before considering a petition for a corporate insolvency resolution process (CIRP).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does it work?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Unlike the CIRP, an informal understanding is reached with creditors before the application is filed.</li>
<li>PPIRP begins only after 66% of financial creditors approve the proposal and the name of resolution professional.</li>
<li>Debt resolution agreement between financial creditor and a potential investor is arrived at in consultation with the corporate debtor for which subsequent approval of the resolution plan is sought from the NCLT.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What were the objectives behind introducing PPIRP?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>MSMEs greatly contribute to the economy, and employ a wide section of the population.</li>
<li>The pandemic severely impacted their operations.</li>
<li>This alternative insolvency resolution process was designed to ensure quicker, cost-effective and value-maximizing outcomes for all.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the progress in PPIRP so far?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Only two insolvency cases have been initiated under PPIRP since it was introduced.</li>
<li>The poor response has been attributed to the hesitancy on the part of financial institutions.</li>
<li>In the case of CIRP, the haircut involved is a last resort, against a voluntary one in case of PPIRP.</li>
<li>Data shows that between December 2016 and June 2022, a total of 5,636 CIRPs commenced, of which 3,637 have been closed.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Does PPIRP defeat the purpose of IBC?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The IBC’s objective is to facilitate exit from failed units so that capital can be reallocated to better ones.</li>
<li>However, banks are not comfortable initiating PPIRP due to voluntary haircuts.</li>
<li>There is a fear that such a decision might be scrutinized later.</li>
<li>This means capital will remain locked up in failed units, defeating the purpose of IBC.</li>
<li>Voluntary haircuts mean fewer resources from the winding-up process and greater scope for corrupt practices.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pre-pack-ibc-resolution/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>More teeth and bigger muscles: ED’s lengthening arm</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/more-teeth-and-bigger-muscles-ed-lengthening-arm/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Enforcement Directorate (ED)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>Since the advent of the Modi government, the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-enforcement-directorate-ed-dreaded-nightmare-of-indian-politicians-businessmen/">ED – Enforcement Directorate</a> has gone after politicians/celebrities suspected of corruption with far greater prowess than other central law enforcement agencies.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Enforcement Directorate (ED)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It goes back to May 1, 1956, when an ‘<strong><u>Enforcement Unit</u>’</strong> was formed in the Department of Economic Affairs.</li>
<li>It then aimed for handling Exchange Control Laws violations under the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act (FERA).</li>
<li>The ED today is a <strong><u>multi-dimensional organisation</u></strong> investigating economic offences under the Prevention of Money Laundering Act (PMLA), Fugitive Economic Offenders Act, Foreign Exchange Management Act and FERA.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>From where does the ED get its powers?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When proceeds of crime (property/money) are generated, the best way to save that money is by parking it somewhere, so one is not answerable to anyone in the country.</li>
<li>Therefore, there was a need to control and prevent the laundering of money.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>PMLA</u></strong> was brought in for this exact reason in 2002, but was enacted only in 2005.</li>
<li>The objective was to prevent parking of the money outside India and to trace out the layering and the trail of money.</li>
<li>So as per the Act, the ED got its power to investigate under Sections 48 (authorities under act) and 49 (appointment and powers of authorities and other officers).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Roles and functions of the ED</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Summon, Search and seizure:</strong> The ED carries out search (property) and seizure (money/documents) after it has decided that the money has been laundered, under Section 16 (power of survey) and Section 17 (search and seizure) of the PMLA.</li>
<li><strong>Arrest and detentions:</strong> On the basis of that, the authorities will decide if an arrest is needed as per Section 19 (power of arrest).</li>
<li><strong>Attachment of property:</strong> Under Section 50, the ED can also directly carry out search and seizure without calling the person for questioning. It is not necessary to summon the person first and then start with the search and seizure.</li>
<li><strong>Filing of chargesheet:</strong> If the person is arrested, the ED gets 60 days to file the prosecution complaint (chargesheet) as the punishment under PMLA doesn’t go beyond seven years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>At what stage does the ED step in when a crime is committed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Whenever any offence is registered by a local police station, which has generated proceeds of crime <strong><u>over and above ₹1 crore</u></strong>, the investigating police officer forwards the details to the ED.</li>
<li>Alternately, <strong><u>if the offence comes under the knowledge of the Central agency</u></strong>, they can then call for the First Information Report (FIR) or the chargesheet if it has been filed directly by police officials.</li>
<li>This will be done to find out if any laundering has taken place.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>PMLA, the ED’s sword arm</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ED’s aggression has been largely on leveraging the massive powers bestowed on the agency by the Prevention of Money Laundering Act (PMLA), 2002.</li>
<li>PMLA, 2002 is an Act of the Parliament of India enacted by the NDA government to prevent money laundering and to provide for the confiscation of property derived from money laundering.</li>
<li>It was enacted in response to India’s global commitment (including the Vienna Convention) to combat the menace of money laundering.</li>
<li>PMLA and the Rules notified there under came into force with effect from July 1, 2005.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How is PMLA going increasingly stringent?</strong></h4>
<p>The PMLA’s ambit was widened through amendments in 2009, 2013, 2015, and 2019, giving the ED the teeth it now has.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Broader jurisdiction for investigation:</strong> In 2009, ‘criminal conspiracy’ under Section 120B of the Indian Penal Code was added to the PMLA’s schedule among various other offences. This has, over the years, allowed the ED to enter any case where a conspiracy is alleged — even if the principal offence is not part of the PMLA schedule. In 2009, the ED also got international jurisdiction as far as tracking laundered money was concerned.</li>
<li><strong>Immediate attachment of property:</strong> Following amendments in 2015 and 2018, the ED was allowed to attach properties in India equivalent to properties acquired abroad through laundered money. Through certain “explanations” inserted into the PMLA in 2019, the government allowed the ED to attach properties earned directly or indirectly through alleged criminal activity that was even “relatable” to a scheduled offence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why ED mostly grips Politicians?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Exposing rampant corruption:</strong> It is not always ironic to say that most politicians are never corrupt. We have a very inglorious past of political corruption.</li>
<li><strong>Selective witch-hunt:</strong> The ED has often been attacked for initiating investigations, raiding and questioning leaders of opposition parties, be it under the current regime or under past governments.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues with PMLA</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Misuse of central agencies:</strong> PMLA is being pulled into the investigation of even ordinary crimes by the Enforcement Directorate.</li>
<li><strong>Seizing of assets:</strong> Assets of genuine victims have been attached. The ED could just walk into anybody’s house.</li>
<li><strong>Politically motivated raids:</strong> In all this, the fundamental purpose of PMLA to investigate the conversion of “illegitimate money into legitimate money” was lost.</li>
<li><strong>Opacity of charges:</strong> Petitioners pointed out that even the Enforcement Case Information Report (ECIR) – an equivalent of the FIR – is considered an “internal document” and not given to the accused.</li>
<li><strong>Vagueness over evidence:</strong> The accused is called upon to make statements that are treated as admissible in evidence.</li>
<li><strong>Harassment:</strong> The ED begins to summon accused persons and seeks details of all their financial transactions and of their family members.</li>
<li><strong>Against individual liberty:</strong> The initiation of an investigation by the ED has consequences that have the potential of curtailing the liberty of an individual.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Allegations against ED</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Huge discretions:</strong> The ED is the only Central agency in the country that does not require permission from the government to summon or prosecute politicians or government functionaries for committing economic offences like money laundering.</li>
<li><strong>Used for petty crimes:</strong> PMLA is pulled into the investigation of even “ordinary” crimes and assets of genuine victims have been attached.</li>
<li><strong>Actual purpose denigrated: </strong>PMLA was a comprehensive penal statute to counter the threat of money laundering, specifically stemming from the trade in narcotics.</li>
<li><strong>Violations of Rights:</strong> PMLA was enacted in response to India’s global commitment to combat the menace of money laundering. Instead, rights have been “cribbed, cabined and confined”.</li>
<li><strong>Functional opacity:</strong> There is also a lack of clarity about ED’s selection of cases to investigate. We often see ED raiding houses of opposition parties suddenly.</li>
<li><strong>Poor rate of conviction:</strong> We have hardly read the conclusion of cases by ED. Meantime media-trial tears off the accused person’s credibility which is the most desired intent.</li>
<li><strong>Under-trials and slower prosecution</strong>: ED has been focusing on keeping the accused in custody rather than actually proving the charges against them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges to ED</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>ED being dragged to court:</strong> The petitions against the ED had the effect of slowing down the investigations, as officers have to defend themselves in court.</li>
<li><strong>Foul crying politicians:</strong> There are attempts to cover up unexplained, high-value transactions that fall within the PMLA’s ambit</li>
<li><strong>Investigation of foreign transactions:</strong> Getting information on accounts and money stashed abroad to establish a trail is the biggest challenge they face.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The fight against corruption is intimately linked with the reform of the investigations.</li>
<li>Therefore the adjudicating authorities must work in cooperation and ensure the highest standards of transparency and fairness.</li>
<li>ED has been walking a tightrope to safeguard its integrity by speeding up investigations and court procedures.</li>
<li>The need of the hour could be systemic fixes—and not shrill calls to throw the baby out with the bathwater.</li>
<li>It is unlikely that corruption can be substantially reduced without modifying the way government agencies operate.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/more-teeth-and-bigger-muscles-ed-lengthening-arm/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Donations to recognised Political Parties come under EC lens</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/donations-recognised-political-parties-come-under-ec-lens/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with Political Funding</p></div></div><p>The Election Commission’s ongoing drive to clean up the electoral space has now gone beyond RUPPs (<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vacant-offices-unaware-office-bearers-curious-case-of-delisted-parties/">registered unrecognised political parties</a>) to cover recognised national and State parties.</p>
<h4>What is Political Funding?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Political Funding implies the methods that political parties use to raise funds to finance their campaign and routine activities.</li>
<li>A political party needs money to pitch itself, its objectives, and its intended actions to get votes for itself. (<a href="http://www.drbrambedkarcollege.ac.in/sites/default/files/UNIT-2_PART-5_CORPORATE%20FUNDING%20OF%20POLITICAL%20PARTIES.pdf" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Reference</a>)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why need political funding?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Across the world, political parties need access to money in order to reach out to the electorate, explain their policies and receive inputs from people.</li>
<li>And in order to do the same, parties resort to political party funding.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Generally who makes these funding?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Individuals:</strong> One of the primary sources of this funding is voluntary contributions made by individuals.</li>
<li><strong>Corporates:</strong> Besides this, corporates pay hefty donations to parties in different forms.</li>
<li><strong>Foreign aid:</strong> This is yet another source but highly controversial.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Statutory Provisions</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Section 29B of the Representation of the People Act (RPA)</u></strong> entitles parties to accept voluntary contributions by any person or company, except a Government Company.</li>
<li><strong><u>Section 29C of the RPA mandates political parties to declare donations</u></strong> that exceed 20,000 rupees. Such a declaration is made by making a report and submitting the same to the EC. Failure to do so on time disentitles a party from tax relief under the Income Tax Act, 1961.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Methods used by Indian Political Parties</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li><strong>Individual Persons:</strong> Section 29B of RPA allows political parties to receive donations from individual persons.</li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<ol start="2">
<li><strong>State/Public Funding:</strong> Here, the government provides funds to parties for election related purposes. State Funding is of two types:</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>Direct Funding:</strong> The government provides funds directly to the political parties. Direct funding by tax is prohibited in India.</li>
<li><strong>Indirect Funding:</strong> It includes other methods except direct funding, like free access to media, free access to public places for rallies, free or subsidized transport facilities. It is allowed in India in a regulated manner.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<ol start="3">
<li><strong>Corporate Funding:</strong> In India, donations by corporate bodies are governed under the Companies Act, 2013. Section 182 of the Act provides that:</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>A company needs to be at least three years old to be able to donate to a political party.</li>
<li>Companies can donate up to 7.5% of average net profits made during three simultaneous preceding financial years. (Now removed after Finance Act, 2017)</li>
<li>Such contributions must be disclosed in the company’s profit and loss account. (Removed)</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<ol start="4">
<li><strong>Electoral Trusts:</strong> A non-profit company created in India for orderly receipt of voluntary contributions from any person like an individual or a domestic company.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>According to the Election Commission Guidelines, all electoral trusts formed after January 2013 are required to declare details of the money received and disbursed.</li>
<li>The Central Government rules mandate these firms to donate 95% of their total income to registered political parties in a financial year.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with Political Funding</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Money laundering:</strong> One of the biggest disadvantages of the corporate funding is the use of fake companies to route black money.</li>
<li><strong>Influence of contributor:</strong> Influence of people and companies over political parties to which they provide funds.</li>
<li><strong>Election malpractices:</strong> There are various gaps in Indian rules, the benefit of which political parties take to avoid any kind of reporting.</li>
<li><strong>Money politics:</strong> Hidden sources of funding lead to more spending of funds in election campaigns, thus impacting the economy of the country.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Recent steps taken</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>FCRA Reforms:</strong> In March, 2018, the government passed a key amendment to the Foreign Contribution Regulation Act, 2010 allowing foreign companies to fund political parties in India.</li>
<li><strong>Electoral Bonds Schemes:</strong> The government notified the Electoral Bond Scheme on 2nd January, 2018 to establish and cleanse the system of political funding in the country.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Electoral Bond Scheme?</h4>
<ul>
<li>An electoral bond is a bearer instrument like a Promissory Note.</li>
<li>It can be purchased by any citizen of India or a body incorporated in India to donate to the political party of their choice.</li>
<li>Donor’s name is not there on the bond.</li>
<li>These bonds can be used for making donations to the political parties registered under Section 29A of the RP Act, 1951.</li>
<li>The party should have secured not less than one per cent of the votes polled in the last general election to the Lok Sabha or a Legislative Assembly.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with the scheme</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Opaque funding:</strong> While the identity of the donor is captured, it is not revealed to the party or public. So transparency is not enhanced for the voter.</li>
<li><strong>No IT break:</strong> Also income tax breaks may not be available for donations through electoral bonds. This pushes the donor to choose between remaining anonymous and saving on taxes.</li>
<li><strong>No anonymity for donors:</strong> The privacy of the donor is compromised as the bank will know their identity.</li>
<li><strong>Differential benefits:</strong> These bonds will help any party that is in power because the government can know who donated what money and to whom.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<p>Former Chief Election Commissioner SY Quraishi has suggested an alternative worth exploring:</p>
<ul>
<li>A National Electoral Fund to which all donors can contribute.</li>
<li>The funds would be allocated to political parties in proportion to the votes they get.</li>
<li>Not only would this protect the identity of donors, it would also weed out black money from political funding.</li>
<li>There can be a tax benefit for those who donate to the fund.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4>Try this question from our AWE Initiative</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="ihyxvccakT"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/q-2-examine-the-issues-with-political-funding-in-india-how-far-has-the-introduction-of-electoral-bonds-succeeded-in-dealing-with-the-issues-with-political-funding-10-marks/">Q.2) Examine the issues with political funding in India. How far has the introduction of electoral bonds succeeded in dealing with the issues with political funding? (10 marks)</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="ihyxvccakT" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/q-2-examine-the-issues-with-political-funding-in-india-how-far-has-the-introduction-of-electoral-bonds-succeeded-in-dealing-with-the-issues-with-political-funding-10-marks/embed/#?secret=Wm8HVXEafF#?secret=ihyxvccakT" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“Q.2) Examine the issues with political funding in India. How far has the introduction of electoral bonds succeeded in dealing with the issues with political funding? (10 marks)” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/donations-recognised-political-parties-come-under-ec-lens/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The heavy rainfall and the crazy Banglore flood: A case to study</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/flood/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>urban floods mitigation</p></div></div><h4><img alt="flood" class="alignnone wp-image-638490" height="321" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/54388ec2-4968-11ec-854b-e26f413988f6_1637348831734.jpg 1600w" width="570"/>Context</h4>
<ul>
<li>The recent events of heavy downpours in short period of time and the recent example of Banglore flood, highlights how cities in India and elsewhere need to adapt to climate change as it brings more extreme rainfall in the future.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is heavy downpour?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A downpour or cloudburst is a sudden and unexpected heavy fall of rain.</li>
<li>It is usually local in nature and of brief duration. Most so-called cloudbursts occur in connection with thunderstorms.</li>
<li>Heavy downpour in short period causes flood, damage to buildings and infrastructure can disrupt transport, communications and connectivity, loss of crops and livestock.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The heavy rainfall and the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/floods/">Banglore flood</a> causes </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rise in built up area: </strong>Lakes and natural depressions may not always fill up during many monsoons so the people who are unaware of hydrology tempts to build and buy in the catchment areas of water-bodies, which will be disastrous when it rains heavily as there is rise in the quantity.</li>
<li><strong>Water-logging: </strong>rainwater and sewage water are forced to build up, which results in water-logging. The highway acts as a dam for the water ,Garbage frequently clogs drains, which limits the flow of sewage, and they are too small to support the weight of the expanding population.</li>
<li><strong>Physical shrinkage of water-bodies</strong>: Destruction of lakes is a major issue .lakes can store the excess water and regulate the flow of water however the pollution of natural water bodies and converting them for development purposes has increased the risks of floods<strong>. </strong>Unplanned growth, Rise in population<strong>, </strong>rise in the built up areas along streams, canals, around the lakes, leaving no storage capacity.</li>
<li><strong>Compromised runoff potential and health hazards</strong>: Choked and encroached drains and lakes, ill designed infrastructure and missing pipes compromising run off potential. Not only the physical quantity of the runoff that poses a hazard. When polluted drains and lakes overflow, the flood can pose a health hazard especially to vulnerable and exposed marginal communities living in informal settlements.</li>
<li><strong>Zero or limited ability to allow infiltration of water: </strong>Encroachments in and around wetlands and green lands harming the natural way of water infiltration and ground water recharge.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of vision in rain water harvesting: </strong>Ignorance towards the tradition rain water harvesting techniques and no or limited vision for creating new systems of rain water harvesting. Exceptionally heavy monsoon rains have been exacerbated by poor urban planning in the Indian tech hub, showing the need for improved water systems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="flood" class="alignnone wp-image-638492" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 641px) 100vw, 641px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/deccan-Herald-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/deccan-Herald-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/deccan-Herald.jpg 708w" width="641"/>What are the reasons behind the frequent floods in urban areas?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Meteorological factors</strong>: change in the weather patterns, increase in the temperature leading to heavy rainfall, sudden downpour, cloudburst, thunderstorms, hailstorms etc.</li>
<li><strong>Hydrological factors</strong>: Natural surface infiltration rate, soil moisture level, presence or absence of Overbank flows, Presence of impervious cover, the occurrence of high tides impeding the drainage in coastal cities.</li>
<li><strong>Man-Made factors: </strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Unplanned urbanization: </strong>Unplanned settlement is one of the main cause of urban flooding. Blocking of natural drainage pathways through construction activity and encroachment on catchment areas, streams, rivers, lakebeds. Reduced infiltration and ground water recharge of water, destruction of lakes, Land-use changes (e.g. surface sealing due to urbanization, deforestation) increase runoff and sedimentation. Inefficiency or non-maintenance of infrastructure etc.</li>
<li><strong>Outdated Drainage systems</strong>: The old and ill-maintained drainage system is one of the main factor making cities in India vulnerable to flooding</li>
<li><strong>Encroachments on and around water-bodies: </strong>Illegal Habitations started growing into towns and cities alongside rivers and watercourses. As a result of this, the capacity of the natural drains has decreased, resulting in flooding.</li>
<li><strong>Climate Change: </strong>Climate change due to various anthropogenic events has led to extreme weather events, increasing temperature which resulting in heavy rainfall in one part while drought and dry spells in other.</li>
<li><strong>Poor Solid Waste Management System:</strong> Indiscriminate disposal of solid waste, poor waste management system, clogging drains because of accumulation of non-biodegradable wastes are major concerns. Domestic, commercial and industrial waste and dumping of it into the drains also contribute significantly to reducing their capacities.</li>
<li><strong>Reduced Seepage:</strong> use of hard and non-porous construction material making the soil impervious, reducing the seepage capability in no of cities in India.</li>
<li><strong>Weak Implementation and lack of awareness:</strong>Even with provisions of rainwater harvesting, sustainable urban drainage systems, etc, in regulatory mechanisms like the Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA), adoption at user end as well as enforcement agencies remains weak.</li>
<li><strong>No Community Participation:</strong>Flood control measures planned without participation of the affected community are unsustainable as they do not meet the needs of relevant stakeholders.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to prevent the urban floods and prevent losses?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Developing climate Resilient Infrastructure:</strong> using permeable material for roads and pavement, green roofs and harvesting systems in buildings. To reduce the burden of road infrastructure in cities Outer Ring Road should be explored. Innovative approaches like Sponge Cities wetland restoration, flushing systems using collected rooftop water, public spaces as flexible water retention facilities can be applied to Indian urban areas.</li>
<li><strong>Use of technology in Early Warning Systems and Communication: </strong>Early-warning systems using sensors across waterbodies and drains, and a network of communication for hotspots of emerging flood risk in the wet-season should be put in place. Providing real-time data where traditional systems fail. Tools such as predictive precipitation modelingcan help do that and are also able to link it with the adaptive capacity of urban land use.</li>
<li><strong>Proper management and regular upgrade of Urban Drainage System:</strong> drains need to be cleaned on a regular basis to permit the free flow of water .Proper management of the drainage system is necessary to ensure that the water does not get stored in one place. Watershed management and emergency drainage plan should be clearly enunciated in policy.</li>
<li><strong>Rainwater Harvesting</strong>: It will serve the twin purposes of lowering the peak runoff and raising the groundwater table. Many municipal corporations in India have already made rainwater harvesting compulsory<strong>. </strong></li>
<li><strong>Conservation of Water Bodies: </strong>Urban water bodies like lakes, tanks, and ponds also play a very important role in the management of urban flooding by reducing the flood water run-off by capturing it.</li>
<li><strong>Holistic approach: </strong>Improved monitoring, forecasting, and decision-support systems. Find out the different method for improving the preparedness for urban flooding.</li>
<li><strong>Responsibility on every stakeholder: </strong>Locally, citizens, local ward officials and staff will need to work together to minimize dumping of solid waste and garbage in storm-water drains. As this is a socio –political problem, public participation awareness and responsibility of citizen is the need of the hour. To develop a long-lasting solution, all parties must acknowledge the issues and adopt a thorough strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What we as citizens can do on a personal level to prevent the urban environment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Raising voice at all available forums and platforms</li>
<li>Making politicians and bureaucrats accountable</li>
<li>Refuse to buy a house in the encroached lands.</li>
<li>Applying methods of rain water harvesting on individual level.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Exceptionally heavy monsoon rains have been exacerbated by poor urban planning in the Indian tech hub, showing the need for improved water systems.</li>
<li>Urbanization is a global and inevitable process, and with cities as engines of the economy, built-up areas will continue to grow. But we need to draw upon these experiences and the growing perils of climate change and extreme rain events and change course.</li>
<li>According to UN projections, by 2050 more than 68% of the world’s population could be concentrated in urban areas.</li>
<li>In this context, resilience-based strategies should be adopted to improve the capacity to handle the crisis arising out of climate change.</li>
<li>Wetlands are the kidneys of the earth, let’s keep it healthy.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What are the factors causing flood in the urban cities? What are the measures to prevent the urban flooding keeping in mind the sustainable development? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/flood/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Multilateralism will open pandora of opportunities for India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/multilateralism/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>SCO and QUAD</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>multilateralism</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="multilateralism" class="alignnone wp-image-638494" height="399" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 599px) 100vw, 599px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/brics-621x414-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/brics-621x414-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/brics-621x414-1.jpg 621w" width="599"/>Context</strong></h4>
<p>India may give up its strategic balancing of China and West if the Ukraine war weakens Russia. Because for major defence supplies India is dependent on Russia.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/growing-salience-of-multilateralism/"><strong>What is the concept of multilateralism?</strong></a></p>
<ul>
<li>Process of organizing relations between groups of three or more states. Beyond that basic quantitative aspect, multilateralism is generally considered to comprise certain qualitative elements or principles that shape the character of the arrangement or institution.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is SCO?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Shanghai Cooperation Organization (SCO) is a Eurasian political, economic and security organization.</li>
<li><strong>Global share:</strong> In terms of geographic scope and population, it is the world’s largest regional organization, covering approximately 60% of the area of Eurasia, 40% of the world population, and more than 30% of global GDP.</li>
<li><strong>Members</strong>: The SCO currently comprises eight Member States. They are- China, India, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Russia, Pakistan, Tajikistan and Uzbekistan.</li>
<li><strong>Headquarters</strong>: Beijing, China.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is QUAD?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (QSD), commonly known as the Quad.</li>
<li>It is a strategic security dialogue.</li>
<li><strong>Members</strong>: Australia, India, Japan, and the United States.</li>
<li><strong>Origin</strong>: The dialogue was initiated in 2007.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="multilateralism" class="alignnone wp-image-638498" height="562" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 538px) 100vw, 538px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-287x300.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-287x300.jpeg 287w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-978x1024.jpeg 978w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-768x804.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2-860x900.jpeg 860w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/18THiStock-538770881-2.jpeg 1200w" width="538"/>Which factors forced India to have more engagements with QUAD?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Chinese threat has been largely responsible in shaping New Delhi’s Indo Pacific Policy.</li>
<li>The China’s Belt and Road initiative and the growing China’s presence in India’s neighborhood- as evident from China’s investment not only in Pakistan and Myanmar, but also in Nepal and Sri Lanka. Because of such activities India felt encircled.</li>
<li>The very launch of the QUAD initiative was the reaction to China’s assertiveness in the Indo Pacific region.</li>
<li>India agreed to upgrade the quad meeting at the ministerial level only after the gunmen attack of 2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How India is maintaining balance between the West and China-Russia Alliance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Plurilateralism</strong>: India continued to believe in <strong>plurilateralism</strong>, a doctrine elucidated by external affairs Minister S Jaishankar in his book <strong>‘The Indian Way</strong>’.</li>
<li><strong>Member of both QUAD and SCO</strong>: Along with QUAD, India also took membership of SCO. It means India dealing with the USA and Japan on one side and Russia and China on the other.</li>
<li><strong>Simultaneously dealing with many powers: </strong>India is engaging with competing powers like the USA, China, the EU or Russia at the same time.</li>
<li><strong>Multipolar world: </strong>India stands in favor of a <strong>multipolar world</strong> where the plurality of power centers would allow her to play one pole against the other. In this context, New Delhi wants Russia to remain an important player.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="multilateralism" class="alignnone wp-image-638500" height="353" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 602px) 100vw, 602px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-300x176.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-300x176.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1.jpg 637w" width="602"/><br/>
What are India’s concerns regarding the West created world order?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The stand on Multilateralism goes together with India’s reservations (not being completely satisfied) against the West’s past hegemony and the international orders that were established after 1945.</li>
<li>MEA S Jaishankar emphasises that the West has imposed norms on the world that need to be dismantled. He says, “The key of western durability till now is the set of institutions and practices that it progressively but firmly established in the period of its dominance”.</li>
<li>The world order and the institutions are created and supported by the West by narratives that serve the West well, while diminishing its competitors.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the steps taken by India to deal with the West created world order and institutions ?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s engagement with the other regional organizations like BRICS, SCO, etc.</li>
<li><strong>Doctrine of Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam: </strong>India’s foreign policy has been based on the philosophy of Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam.</li>
<li><strong>UN Reforms:</strong> Efforts towards bringing reforms in the UNs.</li>
<li><strong>Shift from Non-Alignment to Multi-Alignment:</strong> Multi-alignment is the very essence of India’s foreign policy and the economic policy of India today. Promotion of multilateralism by engaging with many poles simultaneously.</li>
<li><strong>Various Multilateral initiatives: </strong>India has taken the lead in promoting various multilateral initiatives like International Solar Alliance, proposing CCIT for combating terrorism, Asia-Africa Growth corridor.</li>
<li><strong>Collaborating with Like-minded Countries: </strong>India could work closely with the <strong>Alliance for Multilateralism </strong>(an initiative launched by Germany and France) to shape both the alliance itself and the reform agenda at large.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is Russia important for India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Military supplies</strong>: India is heavily dependent on Russia for its military supplies with more than two-third of its weapons coming from Russia. For example: S-400 is the recent supply to India by Russia.</li>
<li><strong>Balancing China:</strong> Russia is important for India to balance China. More isolation of Russia may push Russia closer to China.</li>
<li><strong>To promote multilateralism</strong>: To maintain multilateral world order Russia is a major player or partner for India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A multilateral world order with power decentralized between all the regions and all the economic strata is critical for any sustainable model of peace and prosperity to be gained. The UN and similar bodies must recognize the need of the hour and must reform or else they will perish in yet another set of protectionism, distrust, and possible large-scale military conflicts like Russia- Ukraine.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What are the concerns of India regarding the present world order created by the West? </strong><strong>How can India promote multilateralism by playing a balancing role between the QUAD and the SCO?  What is the importance of Russia for India in the present global situation? Explain.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/multilateralism/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>On reservations for disempowered Dalit Christians and Muslims, a question of government’s intent</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dalit/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>social justice</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="dalit" class="alignnone wp-image-638560" height="367" sizes="(max-width: 551px) 100vw, 551px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1457603210-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1457603210-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1457603210.jpeg 555w" width="551"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Union government intends to appoint a national commission to study the status of Dalits (ex “untouchable” castes) belonging to the Muslim and Christian communities. Aim of study to check the socio-economic condition of Muslims and Christian Dalits on par with Hindu, Sikh, Buddhist Dalits.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Current reservation policy</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At present, scheduled caste reservation is applicable only to schedule caste (Dalit) belongs to Hindu, Sikh, Buddhist. Currently it is unavailable for schedule caste belongs to Muslims and Christians.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why Muslim and Christian Dalit needs reservation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2008 review-study commissioned by the National Commission of Minorities (NCM) and housed in the Sociology Department of <a href="https://indianexpress.com/section/cities/delhi/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Delhi</a> The remit of the study was to conduct a comprehensive review of already existing social-scientific evidence that might offer answers to three questions.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>What is the contemporary status of Dalit Muslims (DMs) and Dalit Christians (DCs) in terms of their material well-being and social status?</li>
<li>How does their situation compare with that of: a) non-Dalits of their own communities, and b) Dalits of other communities?</li>
<li>Do the caste disabilities suffered by these groups justify state intervention?</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong><img alt="dalit" class="alignnone wp-image-638564" height="308" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 547px) 100vw, 547px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/IMG_20220204_204537.jpg 777w" width="547"/>What were the findings of study?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The study reviewed two main kinds of available evidence, ethnographic-descriptive and macro-statistical, in addition to semi-academic NGO reports and publications.</li>
<li>The survey of ethnographic materials began with the finding that the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-caste-system/">existence of caste divisions</a> – including the presence of ex-untouchable castes recognised as such – among both Muslims and Christians – was beyond dispute.</li>
<li>DMs and DCs were identified and segregated much like their counterparts in the Hindu or Sikh communities.</li>
<li>Evidence was tabulated on five forms of caste-based social discrimination – the practice untouchability; enforced ban on inter-marriage; occupational segregation; social and cultural segregation and finally, economic discrimination.</li>
<li>The most common instances were separate mosques or churches (or hierarchically segregated seating); separate burial grounds; strict prohibition on inter-marriage with very severe punishments (sometimes extending to murder) for breaking this taboo; and general avoidance of social interaction and cooperation.</li>
<li>The main findings were that DMs are clearly the worst off among all Dalits, while DCs are somewhat better off than other Dalits except Sikh Dalits (who are by far the best off, especially in the rural sector).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why DMs and DCs doesn’t have reservation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The courts accept that “caste survives conversion” but complain about the lack of reliable data. No recognition, no data; no data, no recognition.</li>
<li>Informal guesstimates (based on the 2001 Census and the 2004-05 NSSO survey) place the proportion of DMs at 1 per cent or less of the Muslim population, and DCs as anything between 40-50 per cent of the Christian population of India.</li>
<li>As per the 2011 Census, Muslims are 14.2 per cent and Christians 2.3 per cent of our population. Taken together, DMs and DCs are likely to form less than 2 per cent of the total Dalit population of India, more than 90 per cent of which is Hindu.</li>
<li>According to experts Adding DMs and DCs will not rock the boat of reservation, since the increment will be roughly one-fifth of the 10 per cent reservation readily granted to the upper castes as the Economically Weaker Sections.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What efforts have been made to include Muslims and Christians of Dalit origin among SCs?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>After 1990, a number of Private Member’s Bills were brought in Parliament for this purpose.</li>
<li>In 1996, a government Bill called The Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Orders (Amendment) Bill was drafted, but in view of a divergence of opinions, the Bill was not introduced in Parliament.</li>
<li>Then government headed by PM Manmohan Singh set up two important panels:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Ranganath Misra Commission:</strong> The National Commission for Religious and Linguistic Minorities, popularly known as the Ranganath Misra Commission, in October 2004 and</li>
<li><strong>Sachar Committee:</strong> A seven-member high-level committee headed by former Chief Justice of Delhi High Court Rajinder Sachar to study the social, economic, and educational condition of Muslims in March 2005.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What did they recommend?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Sachar Committee Report</u></strong> observed that the social and economic situation of Dalit Muslims and Dalit Christians did not improve after conversion.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Ranganath Misra Commission</u></strong>, which submitted its report in May 2007, recommended that SC status should be completely de-linked from religion and Scheduled Castes should be made fully religion-neutral like Scheduled Tribes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="dalit" class="alignnone wp-image-638566" height="321" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 609px) 100vw, 609px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/155105-qfzjwkkklx-1613663244.jpg 1200w" width="609"/>Reception to these recommendations</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The report was tabled in Parliament in 2009, but its recommendation was <strong><u>not accepted</u></strong> in view of inadequate field data and corroboration with the actual situation on the ground.</li>
<li>Few studies, commissioned by the National Commission for Minorities, was also <strong><u>not considered reliable due to insufficient data.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Schedule caste community from all religion India suffers from same fate of untouchability. Change of religion unfortunately, have change their social status. If 70+ year of reservation of Dalit in Hindu haven’t substantially change their social destiny, we have to think beyond reservation for social dignity and economic empowerment of schedule castes in India.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Reservation policy in India is religion based and not based on overall social discrimination. Comment in the context of demand for Dalit reservation extension to Christians and Muslims Dalits.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dalit/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>