<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 15:11:34 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Revisiting the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-627767" height="188" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-768x481.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji.jpg 885w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has referred to a three-judge Bench a series of petitions seeking a judicial direction that political parties who make wild promises should also reveal in their poll manifestos where they will get the money to pay for them.</p>
<p>The reference is a shift from the court’s own stand in the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs Tamil Nadu judgment of 2013.</p>
<h4>Hefty promises: A no lesser corrupt practice</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the <strong><u>Balaji case judgment</u></strong>, a Division Bench of the Supreme Court had held that making promises in election manifestos <strong><u>do not amount to a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> under Section 123 of the Representation of People Act (RP).</li>
<li>However, the Supreme Court is now worried that <strong><u>freebies promised</u></strong> by political parties to win elections could <strong><u>bleed the public exchequer dry</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Court said that parties who form the government riding the wave created by their pre-poll promises of free gifts are bleeding the State finances dry.</li>
<li>Parties actually try to <strong><u>fulfil their outlandish promises using public money</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Supreme Court has therefore decided to revisit the Balaji verdict.</p>
<h4>What triggered the Balaji case?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The course of events started in 2006, during the run-up to the Tamil Nadu Assembly elections.</li>
<li>A party released its election manifesto announcing a scheme of free distribution of colour television sets (CTVs) to each and every household if voted to power.</li>
<li>The party swept to power in the polls and decided to implement its scheme and portioned off ₹750 crore from the budget for the project.</li>
<li>The government finally distributed 30,000 TV sets across the State.</li>
<li>In 2011, the rival party also announced its election manifesto with free gifts to “equalise” the gifts offered.</li>
<li>It promised grinders, mixies, electric fans, laptop computers, four gram gold thalis, a cheque of ₹50,000 for women’s marriage, green houses, 20 kg of rice to ration card holders and free cattle and sheep.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Balaji case</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji, a resident of Tamil Nadu, challenged the schemes introduced by the parties in the Madras High Court.</li>
<li>He said that the <strong><u>expenditure was incurred by the State from the exchequer</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This was “<strong><u>unauthorised, impermissible and ultra vires the constitutional mandates</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>High Court dismissed his case</u></strong>, following which he had moved the apex court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did the case play out?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji argued that <strong><u>the State cannot act</u></strong> in furtherance of “<strong><u>eccentric principles of socialistic philanthropy</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>He argued that the promises of <strong><u>free distribution of non-essential commodities</u></strong> in an election manifesto amounts to electoral bribe under Section 123 of the RP Act.</li>
<li>Money can be taken out of the Consolidated Fund of the State <strong><u>only for “public purposes”</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>distribution of goods to certain sections</u></strong> of people was <strong><u>violative of Article 14 of the Constitution</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Argument provided against the Balaji Case</h4>
<ul>
<li>In response, the State of Tamil Nadu countered that <strong><u>promises do not constitute corrupt practice. </u></strong></li>
<li>Political parties are not the State and ‘<strong><u>freebies’ is a nebulous term which has no legal status</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises implemented by the party after forming the government is an <strong><u>obligation under the Directives Principles of State Policy</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The State is only doing its duty to promote the <strong><u>welfare of its people</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises are <strong><u>implemented by framing various schemes/guidelines/eligibility</u></strong> criteria etc. as well as <strong><u>with the approval of the legislature. </u></strong></li>
<li>Thus, it <strong><u>cannot be construed as a waste of public money</u></strong> or be prohibited by any statute or scheme.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Outcome of the Judgement</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court’s judgment held that <strong><u>promises by a political party cannot constitute a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> on its part.</li>
<li>It would be <strong><u>“misleading” to generalize</u></strong> that all promises in the election manifesto would amount to corrupt practice.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>manifesto is a statement of the policy</u></strong> for a political party.</li>
<li>The question of implementing the manifesto arises only if the political party forms a government.</li>
<li>It is the promise of a future government and not of an individual candidate.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Scope for revisiting the judgment</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court agreed that <strong><u>freebies create an “uneven playing field”.</u></strong></li>
<li>It had asked the Election Commission of India to <strong><u>consult political parties</u></strong> and issue guidelines on the election manifesto and make it a <strong><u>part of the Model Code of Conduct</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the Court’s move to review the Balaji judgment significant?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In its order, the court foresees that “freebies may create a situation wherein the <strong><u>State governments cannot provide basic amenities due to lack of funds</u></strong> and the State is pushed towards imminent bankruptcy”.</li>
<li>The court said it wants a <strong><u>transparent debate</u></strong> before the three-judge Bench on whether an “enforceable” judicial order can stop political parties from promising and distributing ‘irrational freebies’.</li>
<li>The case is unique as the Supreme Court is exploring <strong><u>whether judicial parameters can be set on a purely political act of promising freebies.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>LGBTQ leap forward for positive future growth of human rights</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/lgbtq/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>various judgments</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>human rights</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="LGBTQ" class="alignnone wp-image-631871" height="248" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 372px) 100vw, 372px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gp-kZ7E-621x414%40LiveMint-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gp-kZ7E-621x414%40LiveMint-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gp-kZ7E-621x414%40LiveMint.jpg 621w" width="372"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Four years after landmark LGBTQ verdict: The march to full citizenship.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>On September 6, 2018, exactly four years ago, in Navtej Singh Johar and Ors v Union of India, a five-judge constitution bench of the Supreme Court, in a beautifully elaborate decision, liberated LGBTQI Indians from the darkness of Section 377 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/lgbt-rights/"><strong>What is LGBTQ?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>LGBTQ is an initialism that stands for lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender. In use since the 1990s, the initialism, as well as some of its common variants, functions as an umbrella term for sexuality and gender identity.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Section 377 of the IPC?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It reads – Unnatural offences: Whoever voluntarily has <strong>carnal intercourse against the order of nature </strong>with any man, woman or animal shall be punished with imprisonment for life, or with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to ten years, and shall also be liable to fine.</li>
<li>The terms “carnal intercourse” and “against the order of nature” are not defined precisely anywhere in the code.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="LGBTQ" class="alignnone wp-image-631872" height="254" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 451px) 100vw, 451px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/48561589_101-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/48561589_101-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/48561589_101-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/48561589_101.jpg 1024w" width="451"/>Role played by the judiciary hitherto</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Delhi High Court’s verdict in Naz Foundation vs Government of NCT of Delhi (2009) was a landmark in the law of sexuality and equality jurisprudence in India.</li>
<li>The court held that Section 377 offended the guarantee of equality enshrined in Article 14 of the Constitution, because it creates an unreasonable classification and targets homosexuals as a class.</li>
<li>In a retrograde step, the Supreme Court, in Suresh Kumar Koushal vs Naz Foundation (2013), reinstated Section 377 to the IPC.</li>
<li>However, the Supreme Court in Navtej Singh Johar &amp; Ors. vs Union of India (2018) declared that the application of Section 377 IPC to consensual homosexual behaviour was “unconstitutional”.</li>
<li>This Supreme Court judgment has been a great victory to the Indian individual in his quest for identity and dignity.</li>
<li>It also underscored the doctrine of progressive realisation of rights.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="LGBTQ" class="alignnone wp-image-631876" height="325" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 488px) 100vw, 488px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Section377-621x414-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Section377-621x414-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Section377-621x414-1.jpg 621w" width="488"/>What’s next?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Overarching legislation is needed to guarantee equality to all persons on the basis of sexual orientation, gender identity and expression, sex, caste, religion, age, disability, marital status, pregnancy, nationality, and other grounds.</li>
<li>The law should impose obligations of equality and non-discrimination on all persons, public and private, and in the areas of education, employment, healthcare, land and housing and access to public places.</li>
<li>It should provide for civil remedies to stop discriminatory behaviour, costs and damages, and positive action to make reparations.</li>
<li>We need an equality law to define what equality would encompass.</li>
<li>Supreme Court comes held in its privacy judgment in K.S. Puttuswamy v. Union of India (2017) that equality and liberty cannot be separated, and equality encompasses the inclusion of dignity and basic freedoms.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Schools and colleges must effect changes in curricula for a better understanding of the community.</li>
<li>People of a different sexual orientation or gender identity often narrate harrowing tales of bullying, discrimination, stigma and ostracization.</li>
<li>Gender-neutral restrooms should be compulsory in educational institutes and other places.</li>
<li>Parents too need to be sensitised, because the first point of misunderstanding and abuse often begins at home, with teenagers being forced to opt for “conversion” therapies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Justice Chandrachud, speaking on the fourth anniversary of Johar and the journey ahead, while quoting the Beatles classic “All you need is love”, notes that “simply love is not enough”. Rights are necessary. Which will enhance dignity of the community.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. “Silent segregation” on the grounds of gender, sexual orientation preferences are followed in several houses. Elucidate in context of LGBTQ issues. What Legal remedies are needed for its victims?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/lgbtq/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Scientists remain sceptical about how Liquid Nano Urea benefits crops</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/scientists-sceptical-liquid-nano-urea/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Liquid Nano Urea (LNU)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-631401" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lnu-253x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lnu-253x300.jpg 253w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lnu-865x1024.jpg 865w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lnu-768x909.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lnu-760x900.jpg 760w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lnu.jpg 1081w" width="253"/></strong></p>
<p>Liquid Nano Urea, a fertilizer patented and sold by the Indian Farmers Fertiliser Cooperative Ltd. (IFFCO), has been approved by the government for commercial use because of its potential to substantially reduce the import bill, but several experts have questioned the science underlying its efficacy.</p>
<h4>What is Liquid Nano Urea (LNU)?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Urea is chemical nitrogen fertiliser, white in colour, which artificially provides nitrogen, a major nutrient required by plants.</li>
<li>LNU is essentially urea in the form of a nanoparticle.</li>
<li>It is sprayed directly on the leaves and gets absorbed by the plant.</li>
<li>Fertilisers in nano form provide a targeted supply of nutrients to crops, as they are absorbed by the stomata, pores found on the epidermis of leaves.</li>
<li>According to IFFCO, liquid nano urea contains 4 per cent total nitrogen (w/v) evenly dispersed in water.</li>
<li>The size of a nano nitrogen particle varies from 20-50 nm. (A nanometre is equal to a billionth of a metre.)</li>
</ul>
<h4>Using <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-liquid-nano-urea/">LNU</a></h4>
<ul>
<li>The liquid nano urea produced by IFFCO Limited comes in a half-litre bottle priced at Rs 240, and carries no burden of subsidy currently.</li>
<li>By contrast, a farmer pays around Rs 300 for a 50-kg bag of heavily subsidised urea.</li>
<li>According to IFFCO, a bottle of the nano urea can effectively replace at least one bag of urea.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How efficient is LNU?</h4>
<ul>
<li>While conventional urea has an efficiency of about 25 per cent, the efficiency of liquid nano urea can be as high as 85-90 per cent.</li>
<li>Conventional urea fails to have the desired impact on crops as it is often applied incorrectly, and the nitrogen in it is vaporized or lost as a gas.</li>
<li>A lot of nitrogen is also washed away during irrigation.</li>
<li>Liquid nano urea has a shelf life of a year, and farmers need not be worried about “caking” when it comes in contact with moisture.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of LNU</h4>
<ul>
<li>This patented product is expected to not only <strong><u>substitute imported urea</u></strong>, but to also <strong><u>produce better results in farms.</u></strong></li>
<li>Apart from <strong><u>reducing the country’s subsidy bill</u></strong>, it is aimed at <strong><u>reducing the unbalanced and indiscriminate use of conventional urea</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It will help <strong><u>increase crop productivity</u></strong>, and reduce soil, water, and air pollution.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Plants need nitrogen to make protein and they source almost all of it from soil bacteria which live in a plant’s roots and have the ability to break down atmospheric nitrogen, or that from chemicals such as urea into a form usable by plants.</li>
<li>Chemically packaged urea is 46% nitrogen, which means a 45-kg sack contains about 20 kg of nitrogen.</li>
<li>Contrastingly, nano urea sold in 500-ml bottles has only 4% nitrogen (or around 20 g).</li>
<li>How this can compensate for the kilograms of nitrogen normally required puzzles scientists.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/scientists-sceptical-liquid-nano-urea/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Explained: Bail for Women</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-bail-for-women/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Bails</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Different bail provisions</p></div></div><p>An activist recently walked out of a prison, a day after the Supreme Court granted her <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mudda-aapka-supreme-court-suggests-bail-act/">interim bail</a> in a case of allegedly fabricating evidence related to the 2002 Gujarat riots.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>Here we get to know that bail laws in India are not gender neutral. They somewhat favor women due to certain disprivileged social backgrounds.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>What is Bail?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bail is the conditional release of a defendant with the promise to appear in court when required.</li>
<li>The term also means the security that is deposited in order to secure the release of the accused.</li>
<li>In India’s legal world, the term offense has been categorized as bailable offenses and non-bailable under the Code of Criminal Procedure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need Bail?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bail is a <strong><u>fundamental aspect</u></strong> of any criminal justice system.</li>
<li>The practice of bail grew out of the need <strong><u>to safeguard the fundamental right to liberty</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Liberty is the right of one whose <strong><u>guilt has not yet been proven</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Types of Bail in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Depending upon the sage of the criminal matter, there are commonly three types of bail in India:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Regular bail:</strong> Regular bail is generally granted to a person who has been arrested or is in police custody. A bail application can be filed for regular bail under sections 437 and 439 of CrPC.</li>
<li><strong>Interim bail:</strong> This type of bail is granted for a short period of time and it is granted before the hearing for the grant of regular bail or anticipatory bail.</li>
<li><strong>Anticipatory bail:</strong> Anticipatory bail is granted under section 438 of CrPC either by session court or High Court. An application for the grant of anticipatory bail can be filed by the person who discerns that he may be arrested by the police for a non-bailable offense.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<p>Ans. <strong><u>Favorable treatment for Women</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>During the hearing, the Supreme Court of India has made an oral observation that under Section 437 of the Code of Criminal Procedure (CrPC), a woman is entitled to favourable treatment.</li>
<li>The provision says that, being a woman is a possible ground for granting bail, even when otherwise it cannot be considered.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does the bail provision say in favor of Women? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Section 437</u></strong> of the CrPC deals with bail in case of non-bailable offences.</li>
<li>It says a person shall not be released on bail if there is reasonable ground to believe that he has committed an offence punishable with <strong><u>death or life imprisonment</u></strong>.</li>
<li>However, it also contains exceptions in a provision that says the court may grant bail even in these cases, “<strong><u>if such person is under the age of 16 or is a woman or is sick or infirm</u></strong>”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Are there other provisions favourable to women accused? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There are several provisions in criminal law that give special consideration to women, of any age, when they are victims of offences, including sexual offences, in the way they are treated as witnesses and victims of crimes.</li>
<li>There are also some provisions relating to women when they are made an accused, and arrested.</li>
<li>For instance, when a police officer requires the attendance of any person who he believes is acquainted with a case under investigation, the person has to appear before the officer (Section 160).</li>
<li>However, no woman shall be required to do so at any place other than the place in which she resides.</li>
<li>This is understood to mean that the officer has to visit the place of residence to make enquiries.</li>
<li>This benefit is also available to boys under 15, men above 65 and any mentally or physically disabled person.</li>
<li>In its 84th and 135th Report in 1980 and 1989, the Law Commission suggested that the word ‘place’ is ambiguous, and it would be better to amend it to ‘dwelling place’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does the CrPC say on the arrest of a woman? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A police officer <strong><u>may arrest a person who has committed a cognisable offence without a judicial order</u></strong> or a warrant (Section 41).</li>
<li>If the person does not submit to custody based on the word or action of the police, Section 46 enables the police officer to confine the person physically to effect the arrest.</li>
<li>A proviso was introduced in the CrPC in 2009 to the effect that where a woman is to be arrested, <strong><u>only a female police officer may touch the woman’s person</u></strong>, unless circumstances otherwise require.</li>
<li>Earlier, through a 2005 amendment, a subsection was added to Section 46 to <strong><u>prohibit the arrest of a woman after sunset or before sunrise. </u></strong></li>
<li>However, in exceptional circumstances, a woman police officer can obtain the prior permission of a judicial magistrate to make the arrest.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does it say on women who don’t appear in public? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The police <strong><u>may seek entry into any premises</u></strong> where they suspect that a person who is required to be arrested is present.</li>
<li>In a situation where any such place is an apartment in the occupancy of a female (who is not the person to be arrested) and if the woman is one who, by custom, does not appear in public, <strong><u>the police have to give notice to her</u></strong> so that she may withdraw before they enter it (Proviso to Section 47).</li>
<li>It adds that they shall afford her every reasonable facility for withdrawing before they break open and enter the place.</li>
<li>In yet another exception, a woman who intends to file a defamation case, but is one who does not appear in public according to custom, can ask someone else to file the complaint on her behalf.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="pkyNEbQHOe"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mudda-aapka-supreme-court-suggests-bail-act/">[Sansad TV] Mudda AapKa: Supreme Court Suggests “Bail Act”</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="pkyNEbQHOe" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mudda-aapka-supreme-court-suggests-bail-act/embed/#?secret=3Ss7U6i4RC#?secret=pkyNEbQHOe" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Sansad TV] Mudda AapKa: Supreme Court Suggests “Bail Act”” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-bail-for-women/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was Ramon Magsaysay of Philippines?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-ramon-magsaysay-of-philippines/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ramon Magsaysay</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-631406" height="237" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 350px) 100vw, 350px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay-300x203.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay-300x203.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/magsaysay.jpg 637w" width="350"/></p>
<p>A leftist leader and former Kerala health minister has declined to receive the Ramon Magsaysay Award as the late President of the Philippines was known for his alleged brutality against the Communists.</p>
<h4>What is the news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lunched in 1958, the Ramon Magsaysay Award, widely considered to be Asia’s equivalent to the Nobel Prize, recognises outstanding leadership and communitarian contributions in Asia.</li>
<li>This year’s annual list of awardees was announced last week.</li>
<li>Shailaja was considered for the award for her performance as state health minister from 2016 to 2021, a period which saw Kerala fight against the Nipah virus and Covid-19.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who was Ramon Magsaysay?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Born on August 31, 1907 to a father who worked as a blacksmith and a mother who was a teacher, Ramon Del Fierro Magsaysay Senior was the seventh president of the Philippines, from 1953 until his death in an air crash in 1957.</li>
<li>Magsaysay started out as an automobile mechanic before being drafted into the Pacific War (1941-1945), during World War II.</li>
<li>The Pacific War would see the Japanese occupation of the Philippines — then a colony of the US — for nearly four years.</li>
<li>The US formally recognised the Philippines as an independent nation in 1946.</li>
</ul>
<h4>His legacy</h4>
<ul>
<li>As a guerrilla leader resisting the Japanese occupation, Magsaysay’s bravery and leadership saw his appointment as a military governor.</li>
<li>In 1946, he would be elected under the Liberal Party to the Philippine House of Representatives, where he would serve two terms as a Congressman before being appointed secretary of National Defence in 1950.</li>
<li>On December 30, 1953, he would be elected president from the Nationalist Party, the oldest political party in the Philippines.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Communism and Magsaysay</h4>
<ul>
<li>Founded in 1902, the Unión Obrera Democrática is considered the first modern trade federation in the Philippines.</li>
<li>The Communist Party of the Philippines or the Partido Komunista ng Pilipinas (PKP) was formed in 1930.</li>
<li>The Hukbong Bayan Laban sa Hapon or the People’s Army Against the Japanese, popularly known as the Hukbalahap (Huk), was a prominent guerrilla outfit that fought the Japanese.</li>
<li>As the country plunged into post-war chaos after 1946, the fortunes of the Hukbalahaps, too, changed dramatically.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How he rose to his fame?</h4>
<ul>
<li>With the expansion of capitalism, the gap between the rich and poor widened and the farmers continued to languish.</li>
<li>Huk leaders were viewed with suspicion over their declaration of commitment to communism and the demand for peasant rights.</li>
<li>With the US as its close ally, the Philippine government cracked down on the Huks, who formed an alliance with the PKP to take their struggle to a parliamentary platform.</li>
<li>The severe crackdown against the Huks continued until Magsaysay became the National Defence Secretary under President Elpidio Quirino.</li>
<li>Magsaysay drew upon his own experience of guerrilla warfare to initiate a two-pronged system of reforms and military campaigns.</li>
<li>It was under his administrative and military policies that the Huk threat was considered to be neutralised.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Ramon Magsaysay Award</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 1957, the Ramon Magsaysay award was set up by trustees of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund and the Philippine government to carry forward Magsaysay’s legacy of service to the people, good governance, and pragmatic idealism.</li>
<li>In the six decades since 1958 — the first year the Award was given out — over 300 organisations and individuals have been recognised for their developmental endeavours crucial to Asia, and, consequently, to the world.</li>
<li>The award is given out every year on August 31, on Magsaysay’s birth anniversary.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Indian winners on the list</h4>
<ul>
<li>Prominent Indians who have won the award include Vinoba Bhave in 1958, Mother Teresa in 1962, Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay in 1966, Satyajit Ray in 1967, Mahasweta Devi in 1997.</li>
<li>In recent years, Arvind Kejriwal (2006), Anshu Gupta of Goonj (2015), human rights activist Bezwada Wilson (2016), and journalist Ravish Kumar (2019) have won the award.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-ramon-magsaysay-of-philippines/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>GST Council is a fledgling but vibrant institution: FM</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gst-council-is-a-fledgling-but-vibrant-institution-fm/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>GST Council</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Union Finance Minister has heaped praises on Goods and Services Tax (GST) Council.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>FM was reacting to a case made by <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fifteenth-finance-commission/">Fifteenth Finance Commission</a> chief N.K. Singh to set up a Fiscal Council with the Centre and States.</li>
<li>This is another such recommended body to act as a bridge between the GST Council and the Finance Commission.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the GST Council?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The GST regime came into force after the 101<sup>st</sup> Constitutional Amendment was passed by both Houses of Parliament in 2016.</li>
<li>The GST Council – a joint forum of the Centre and the states — was set up by the President as per Article 279A (1) of the amended Constitution.</li>
<li>The members of the Council include the Union Finance Minister (chairperson), the Union Minister of State (Finance) from the Centre.</li>
<li>Each state can nominate a minister in-charge of finance or taxation or any other minister as a member.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why was the Council set up?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Council, according to Article 279, is meant to “make recommendations to the Union and the states on important issues related to GST, like the goods and services that may be subjected or exempted from GST, model GST Laws”.</li>
<li>It also decides on various rate slabs of GST.</li>
<li>For instance, an interim report by a panel of ministers has suggested imposing 28 per cent GST on casinos, online gaming and horse racing.</li>
<li>A decision on this will be taken at the Council meeting.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Recent reforms</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ongoing meeting is the first since a decision of the Supreme Court in May this year, which stated <strong><u>recommendations of the GST Council are not binding</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The court said Article 246A of the Constitution gives both <strong><u>Parliament and state legislatures “simultaneous” power to legislate on GST</u></strong> .</li>
<li>Recommendations of the Council are the product of a collaborative dialogue involving the Union and States.</li>
<li><strong><u>This was hailed by some states</u></strong>, such as Kerala and Tamil Nadu, who believe states can be more flexible in accepting the recommendations as suited to them.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gst-council-is-a-fledgling-but-vibrant-institution-fm/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is National List of Essential Medicines (NLEM)?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-national-list-of-essential-medicines-nlem/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Essential Medicines</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-635839" height="216" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 418px) 100vw, 418px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nlem-300x155.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nlem-300x155.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nlem.jpg 613w" width="418"/></p>
<p>The latest National List of Essential Medicines (NLEM) released September 13, 2022 by the Union health ministry added 34 new medicines and dropped 26 old ones from the previous list.</p>
<h4>What is NLEM?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As per the World Health Organisation (WHO), Essential Medicines are those that satisfy the priority health care needs of the population.</li>
<li>Ministry of Health and Family Welfare hence prepared and released the first National List of Essential Medicines of India in 1996 consisting of 279 medicines.</li>
<li>The list is made with consideration to disease prevalence, efficacy, safety and comparative cost-effectiveness of the medicines.</li>
<li>Such medicines are intended to be available in adequate amounts, in appropriate dosage forms and strengths with assured quality.</li>
<li>They should be available in such a way that an individual or community can afford.</li>
</ul>
<h4>NLEM in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>Drugs listed under NLEM — also known as scheduled drugs — will be cheaper because the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-nppas-role-in-fixing-drug-prices/">National Pharmaceutical Pricing Authority (NPPA)</a> caps medicine prices and changes only based on wholesale price index-based inflation.</li>
<li>The list includes anti-infectives medicines to treat diabetes such as insulin — HIV, tuberculosis, cancer, contraceptives, hormonal medicines and anaesthetics.</li>
<li>They account for 17-18 per cent of the estimated Rs 1.6-trillion domestic pharmaceutical market.</li>
<li>Companies selling non-scheduled drugs can hike prices by up to 10 per cent every year.</li>
<li>Typically, once NLEM is released, the department of pharmaceuticals under the ministry of chemicals and fertilisers adds them in the Drug Price Control Order, after which NPPA fixes the price.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of EML</h4>
<ul>
<li>Drawing an essential medicines list (EML) is expected to result in better quality of medical care, better management of medicines and cost-effective use of health care resources.</li>
<li>This is especially important for a resource limited country like India.</li>
<li>The list of essential medicines is intended to have a positive impact on the availability and rational use of medicines.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="8eMB0tPNor"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-nppas-role-in-fixing-drug-prices/">What is the NPPA’s role in fixing drug prices?</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="8eMB0tPNor" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-nppas-role-in-fixing-drug-prices/embed/#?secret=vBnMpFr7Ot#?secret=8eMB0tPNor" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“What is the NPPA’s role in fixing drug prices?” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-national-list-of-essential-medicines-nlem/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-arattupuzha-velayudha-panicker/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="Arattupuzha" class="alignnone wp-image-635838" height="409" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 272px) 100vw, 272px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atrap-200x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atrap-200x300.jpg 200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atrap-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atrap.jpg 720w" width="272"/></p>
<p>A recently-released Malayalam film Pathonpatham Noottandu (‘Nineteenth Century’) is based on the life of Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker, a social reformer from the Ezhava community in Kerala who lived in the 19th century.</p>
<h4>Who was Arattupuzha Velayudha Panicker?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Born into a well-off family of merchants in Kerala’s Alappuzha district, Panicker was one of the most influential figures in the reformation movement in the state.</li>
<li>He challenged the domination of upper castes or ‘Savarnas’ and brought about changes in the lives of both men and women.</li>
<li>The social reform movement in Kerala in the 19th century led to the large-scale subversion of the existing caste hierarchy and social order in the state.</li>
<li>Panicker was murdered by a group of upper-caste men in 1874 at the age of 49. This makes him the ‘first martyr’ of the Kerala renaissance.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What was Panicker’s role in initiating social reforms?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Panicker is credited with building two temples dedicated to the Hindu god Shiva, in which members of all castes and religions were allowed entry.</li>
<li>One was built in his own village Arattupuzha in 1852, and one in Thanneermukkom in 1854, another village in the Alappuzha district.</li>
<li>Some of his most significant contributions were in protesting for the rights of women belonging to Kerala’s backward communities.</li>
<li>In 1858, he led the Achippudava Samaram strike at Kayamkulam in Alappuzha.</li>
<li>This strike aimed to earn women belonging to oppressed groups the right to wear a lower garment that extended beyond the knees.</li>
<li>In 1859, this was extended into the Ethappu Samaram, the struggle for the right to wear an upper body cloth by women belonging to backward castes.</li>
<li>In 1860, he led the Mukkuthi Samaram at Pandalam in the Pathanamthitta district, for the rights of lower-caste women to wear ‘mukkuthi’ or nose-ring, and other gold ornaments.</li>
<li>These struggles played an important role in challenging the social order and in raising the dignity of women belonging to the lower strata of society in public life.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Other work</h4>
<ul>
<li>Apart from issues related to women, Panicker also led the first-ever strike by agricultural labourers in Kerala, the Karshaka Thozhilali Samaram, which was successful.</li>
<li>He also established the first Kathakali Yogam for the Ezhava community in 1861, which led to a Kathakali performance by Ezhavas and other backward communities, another first for them.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this PYQ:</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Q. The Shri Narayan Dharma Paripalana Yogam (SNDP) Movement(1902-03) was related to which of the following community?</strong></p>
<p>a) Mopilla Community</p>
<p>b) South Indian Tea Planters</p>
<p>c) Ezhava Community in Kerala</p>
<p>d) North Eastern Tea Planters</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-arattupuzha-velayudha-panicker/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Who was activist-author Annabhau Sathe?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-activist-author-anna-bhau-sathe/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Annabhau Sathe</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="anna" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-635837" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 224px) 100vw, 224px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/anna-224x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/anna-224x300.jpg 224w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/anna.jpg 237w" width="224"/></p>
<p>Maharashtra’s Deputy Chief Minister and other leaders are in Moscow to unveil the statue of Lok Shahir (balladeer) Annabhau Sathe at the All-Russia State Library for Foreign Literature.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sathe’s work was immensely inspired by the Russian revolution and the Communist ideology.</li>
<li>He was a member of the Communist Party of India (CPI), and featured among the selected authors from India whose work was translated in Russian.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who was Anna bhau Sathe?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Tukaram Bhaurao Sathe, who later came to be known as Annabhau Sathe, was born in a Dalit family on August 1, 1920 in Maharashtra’s Wategaon village in Satara district.</li>
<li>In 1930, his family left the village and came to Mumbai. Here, he worked as a porter, a hawker and even a cotton mill helper.</li>
<li>In 1934, Mumbai witnessed a workers’ strike under the leadership of Lal Bawta Mill Workers Union in which he participated.</li>
<li>During his days at the Matunga Labour Camp, he got to know R B More, an associate of Dr Babasaheb Ambedkar in the famous ‘Chavdar Lake’ satyagraha at Mahad, and joined the labour study circle.</li>
<li>Being a Dalit, he was denied schooling in his village. It was during these study circles that he learned to read and write.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did Anna start writing songs, ballads and books?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sathe wrote his first poem on the menace of mosquitoes in the labour camp.</li>
<li>He formed Dalit Yuvak Sangh, a cultural group and started writing poems on workers’ protests, agitations.</li>
<li>The group used to perform in front of the mill gates.</li>
<li>Progressive Writers Association was formed at the national level at the same time with the likes of Premchand, Faiz Ahmad Faiz, Manto, Ismat Chugtai, Rahul Sankrutyayan, Mulkraj Anand as its members.</li>
<li>The group would translate the Russian work of Maxim Gorky, Anton Chekhov, Leo Tolstoy, Ivan Turgenev into Marathi, which Sathe got hooked on.</li>
<li>It not only had an ideological impact on him, but inspired him to write street plays, stories, novels etc. In 1939, he wrote his first ballad ‘Spanish Povada’.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How popular was his work?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sathe and his group travelled across Mumbai campaigning for workers’ rights.</li>
<li>Out of the 49 years that he lived, Sathe, who began writing only after the age of 20, churned out 32 novels, 13 collections of short stories, four plays, a travelogue and 11 <strong><u>povadas (ballads).</u></strong></li>
<li>Several of his works like ‘<strong><u>Aklechi Goshta</u></strong>,’ ‘<strong><u>Stalingradacha Povada</u></strong>,’ ‘<strong><u>Mazi Maina Gavavar Rahili</u></strong>,’ ‘<strong><u>Jag Badal Ghaluni Ghav’</u></strong> were popular across the state.</li>
<li>Almost six of his novels were turned into films and many translated into other languages, including Russian.</li>
<li>His ‘<strong><u>Bangalchi Hak’ </u></strong>(Bengal’s Call) on the Bengal famine was translated into Bengali and later presented at London’s Royal Theatre.</li>
<li>His literature depicted the caste and class reality of Indian society of that time.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Left leanings</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sathe’s work was influenced by Marxism, but at the same time he brought out the harsh realities of the caste system.</li>
<li>In 1943, he formed the Lal Bawta Kala Pathak.</li>
<li>The group toured across Maharashtra presenting programmes on caste atrocities, class conflict, and workers’ rights.</li>
<li>He dedicated his most famous novel Fakira to Dr Ambedkar.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What was his Russian connection?</h4>
<ul>
<li>He was once called the <strong><u>Maxim Gorky of Maharashtra</u></strong>.</li>
<li>He was immensely inspired by <strong><u>Gorky’s ‘The Mother’</u></strong> and the Russian revolution, which was reflected in his writings.</li>
<li>He travelled to Russia in 1961 along with a group of other Indians.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Is there a reason behind the statue being unveiled now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Sathe belonged to the Matang community among Dalits.</li>
<li>With the Left failing to claim his artistic legacy, Sathe is now restricted as a symbol of a particular community.</li>
<li>The right wing is angling to claim the credit for making Sathe a global icon.</li>
<li>Installing Sathe’s oil painting at the Indian consulate at Moscow also shows that the central government is using this occasion to increase cultural dialogue between two countries.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/who-was-activist-author-anna-bhau-sathe/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How to make robust patent system for a number 1 knowledge economy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/patent-system/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>KAPILA scheme</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>IPR regime</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="patent system" class="alignnone wp-image-635778" height="410" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 547px) 100vw, 547px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-istock-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-istock-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-istock-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-istock-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-istock.jpg 1200w" width="547"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Increasing the efficiency of processing patent applications and wider academia-industry collaboration are crucial steps for patent system.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is patent system? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A patent system is a type of intellectual property that gives its owner the legal right to exclude others from making, using, or selling an invention for a limited period of time in exchange for publishing an enabling disclosure of the invention.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why are patents important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A patent is important because it can help safeguard our invention. It can protect any product, design or process that meets certain specifications according to its originality, practicality, suitability, and utility. In most cases, a patent can protect an invention for up to 20 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="patent system" class="alignnone wp-image-635779" height="309" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 464px) 100vw, 464px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/patent_0-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/patent_0-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/patent_0-1.jpg 724w" width="464"/>How to get patent? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To get a patent, technical information about the invention must be disclosed to the public in a patent application.</li>
<li>The patent owner may give permission to, or license, other parties to use the invention on mutually agreed terms.</li>
<li>The owner may also sell the right to the invention to someone else, who will then become the new owner of the patent.</li>
<li>Once a patent expires, the protection ends, and an invention enters the public domain; that is, anyone can commercially exploit the invention without infringing the patent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/diluting-of-patent-working-discloser-rule-and-its-implications-for-compulsory-license-regime/"><strong>Terms of Patent</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Patents may be granted for inventions in any field of technology, from an everyday kitchen utensil to a nanotechnology chip.</li>
<li>An invention can be a product – such as a chemical compound, or a process, for example – or a process for producing a specific chemical compound.</li>
<li>Patent protection is granted for a limited period, generally 20 years from the filing date of the application.</li>
<li>Patents are territorial rights. In general, the exclusive rights are only applicable in the country or region in which a patent has been filed and granted, in accordance with the law of that country or region.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="patent system" class="alignnone wp-image-635780" height="295" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-2.jpeg" width="496"/>How patents can support inventors and improve lives</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Recognize and reward</strong>: Patents recognize and reward inventors for their commercially-successful inventions. As such they serve as an incentive for inventors to invent. With a patent, an inventor or small business knows there is a good chance that they will get a return on the time, effort and money they invested in developing a technology. In sum, it means they can earn a living from their work.</li>
<li><strong>Economic opportunity</strong>: When a new technology comes onto the market, society as a whole stands to benefit – both directly, because it may enable us to do something that was previously not possible, and indirectly in terms of the economic opportunities (business development and employment) that can flow from it.</li>
<li><strong>Research and development (R&amp;D): </strong>The revenues generated from commercially successful patent-protected technologies make it possible to finance further technological research and development (R&amp;D), thereby improving the chances of even better technology becoming available in the future.</li>
<li><strong>Opportunities for business growth</strong>: A patent effectively turns an inventor’s know-how into a commercially tradeable asset, opening up opportunities for business growth and job creation through licensing and joint ventures, for example.</li>
<li><strong>Commercialization of a technology</strong>: Holding a patent also makes a small business more attractive to investors who play a key role in enabling the commercialization of a technology.</li>
<li><strong>Spark new ideas</strong>: The technical information and business intelligence generated by the patenting process can spark new ideas and promote new inventions from which we can all benefit and which may, in turn, qualify for patent protection.</li>
<li><strong>No freebies</strong>: A patent can help stop unscrupulous third parties from free riding on the efforts of the inventor.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is KAPILA Initiative?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Full form</strong>: KAPILA is an acronym for Kalam Program for IP (Intellectual Property) Literacy and Awareness.</li>
<li><strong>Guidelines for patent</strong> <strong>Filing: </strong>Under this campaign, students pursuing education in higher educational institutions will get information about the correct system of the application process for patenting their invention and they will be aware of their rights.</li>
<li><strong>Encouragement to students</strong>: The program will facilitate the colleges and institutions to encourage more and more students to file patents.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Thing to remember </strong></p>
<p>Remember one thing, ‘KAPILA’ Program is related to IP awareness. It sounds much like an animal husbandry related initiative.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Way ahead </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As the patent system is a critical aspect of the national innovation ecosystem, investing in the patent ecosystem will help in strengthening the innovation capability of India.</li>
<li>The right interventions should be made for the promotion of the quality of patent applications and collaboration between academia and industry.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>A patent can help stop unscrupulous third parties from free riding on the efforts of the inventor. Discuss this statement in context of protection of innovative ecosystem in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/patent-system/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How to fight anaemia as it is stagnating our productivity</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/anaemia/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>iron fortification</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>women health</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="anaemia" class="alignnone wp-image-635790" height="324" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 486px) 100vw, 486px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.52980700_1586241921_women-health-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.52980700_1586241921_women-health-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.52980700_1586241921_women-health-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.52980700_1586241921_women-health.jpg 1024w" width="486"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The recent National Family Health Survey (NFHS-5) data shows anaemia rates increased from 53 per cent to 57 per cent in women and 58 per cent to 67 per cent in children in 2019-21.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Definition of anaemia </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The WHO defines anaemia as a condition where the number of red blood cells or the haemoglobin concentration within them is lower than normal. This compromises immunity and impedes cognitive development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why anaemia is a concern?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Adverse effects of anaemia affect all age groups lower physical and cognitive growth and alertness among children and adolescents, and lesser capacity to learn and play, directly impacting their future potential as productive citizens.</li>
<li>Anaemia among adolescent girls (59.1 per cent) advances to maternal anaemiaand is a major cause of maternal and infant mortality and general morbidity and ill health in a community.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What causes anaemia?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Imbalanced diet</strong>: Cereal-centric diets, with relatively less consumption of iron-rich food groups like meat, fish, eggs, and dark green leafy vegetables (DGLF), can be associated with higher levels of anaemia.</li>
<li><strong>Underlying factors</strong>: High levels of anaemia are also often associated with underlying factors like poor water quality and sanitation conditions that can adversely impact iron absorption in the body.</li>
<li><strong>Iron deficiency is major cause</strong>: A diet that does not contain enough iron, folic acid, or vitamin B12 is a common cause of anaemia.</li>
<li><strong>Some other conditions</strong>: That may lead to anaemia include pregnancy, heavy periods, blood disorders or cancer, inherited disorders, and infectious diseases.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="anaemia" class="alignnone wp-image-635793" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 100vw, 542px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Indian-women_simon-williams-ekta-parishad_wiki-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Indian-women_simon-williams-ekta-parishad_wiki-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Indian-women_simon-williams-ekta-parishad_wiki.jpg 750w" width="542"/>Why is anaemia so high in the country?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low vitamin intake</strong>: Iron-deficiency and vitamin B12-deficiency anaemia are the two common types of anaemia in India.</li>
<li><strong>High population and nutrition deprivation</strong>: Among women, iron deficiency prevalence is higher than men due to menstrual iron losses and the high iron demands of a growing foetus during pregnancies.</li>
<li><strong>Overemphasis on cereals</strong>: Lack of millets in the diet due to overdependence on rice and wheat, insufficient consumption of green and leafy vegetables could be the reasons behind the high prevalence of anaemia in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is</strong> <strong>Iron fortification?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Iron fortification of food is a methodology utilized worldwide to address iron deficiency. Iron fortification programs usually involve mandatory, centralized mass fortification of staple foods, such as wheat flour.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mandatory-rice-fortification-policy-should-be-re-examined/" class="alignnone wp-image-635795" height="593" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 425px) 100vw, 425px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0da17f852d10621c79c6d4a1935af0fa-215x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0da17f852d10621c79c6d4a1935af0fa-215x300.jpg 215w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0da17f852d10621c79c6d4a1935af0fa.jpg 500w" width="425"/>Why need iron fortification?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Iron deficiency anaemia is due to insufficient iron.</li>
<li>Without enough iron, the body can’t produce enough of a substance in red blood cells that enables them to carry oxygen (haemoglobin).</li>
<li>Severe anaemia during pregnancy increases risk of premature birth, having a low birth weight baby and postpartum depression. Some studies also show an increased risk of infant death immediately before or after birth.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="anaemia" class="alignnone wp-image-635794" height="329" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 494px) 100vw, 494px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-1536x1024.jpeg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-2048x1366.jpeg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-1200x800.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/338650-gaon-connection-women-empowerment-jharkhand-scaled-1-1980x1320.jpeg 1980w" width="494"/>Success story / value addition</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Nepal’s success story to improve maternal anaemia by national action plan .</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mandatory-rice-fortification-policy-should-be-re-examined/"><strong>Anaemia Mukt Bharat</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme aims to reduce the prevalence of anaemia in India.</li>
<li>It provides bi weekly iron Folic acid supplementation to all under five children through Asha workers.</li>
<li>Also, it provides biannual Deworming for children and adolescents. The scheme also establishes institutional mechanisms for advanced research in anaemia.</li>
<li>It also focuses on non-nutritional causes of anaemia.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>We need to focus on the following interventions</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Prophylactic Iron and Folic Acid supplementation.</li>
<li>Intensified year-round Behaviour Change Communication Campaign (Solid Body, Smart Mind).</li>
<li>Appropriate infant and young child feeding practices.</li>
<li>Increase in intake of iron-rich food through diet diversity/quantity/frequency and/or fortified foods with focus on harnessing locally available resources.</li>
<li>Testing and treatment of anaemia, using digital methods and point of care treatment, with special focus on pregnant women and school-going adolescents</li>
<li>Mandatory provision of Iron and Folic Acid fortified foods in government-funded public health programmes</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s nutrition programmes must undergo a periodic review.</li>
<li>The Integrated Child Development Services (ICDS), which is perceived as the guardian of the nation’s nutritional well-being must reassess itself and address critical intervention gaps, both conceptually and programmatically, and produce rapid outcomes.</li>
<li>The nutritional deficit which ought to be considered an indicator of great concern is generally ignored by policymakers and experts. Unless this is addressed, rapid improvement in nutritional indicators cannot happen.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When a person is anaemic, the capacity of his blood cells to carry oxygen decreases. This reduces the productivity of the person which in turn affects the economy of the country. Therefore, it is highly important to cover Anaemia under National Health Mission.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong> <strong>“Every second adolescent girl has anaemia. Every second woman of reproductive age is anaemic”. In this context do you think </strong><strong>Women’s empowerment will not have any meaning without tackling anaemia? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/anaemia/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is a Windfall Tax?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-windfall-tax/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Windfall taxes</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="windfall" class="alignnone wp-image-635835" height="274" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 391px) 100vw, 391px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/windfall-300x210.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/windfall-300x210.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/windfall-768x536.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/windfall.jpg 945w" width="391"/></strong></p>
<p>Finance Minister has defended the windfall tax imposed by the Centre on domestic crude oil producers, saying that it was not an ad hoc move but was done after full consultation with the industry.</p>
<h4>What is a Windfall Tax?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Windfall taxes are designed to tax the profits a company derives from an external, sometimes unprecedented event — for instance, the energy price-rise as a result of the Russia-Ukraine conflict.</li>
<li>These are profits that cannot be attributed to something the firm actively did, like an investment strategy or an expansion of business.</li>
<li>The US Congressional Research Service (CRS) defines a windfall as an “unearned, unanticipated gain in income through no additional effort or expense”.</li>
<li>One area where such taxes have routinely been discussed is oil markets, where price fluctuation leads to volatile or erratic profits for the industry.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When did India introduce this?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In July this year, India announced a windfall tax on domestic crude oil producers who it believed were reaping the benefits of the high oil prices.</li>
<li>It also imposed an additional excise levy on diesel, petrol and air turbine fuel (ATF) exports.</li>
<li>Also, India’s case was different from other countries, as it was still importing discounted Russian oil.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How is it levied?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Governments typically levy this as a <strong><u>one-off tax retrospectively</u></strong> over and above the normal rates of tax.</li>
<li>The Central government has introduced a windfall profit tax of ₹23,250 per tonne on domestic crude oil production, which was subsequently revised fortnightly four times so far.</li>
<li>The latest revision was on August 31, when it was hiked to ₹13,300 per tonne from ₹13,000.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why govt. introduced windfall tax?</h4>
<ul>
<li>There have been varying rationales for governments worldwide to introduce windfall taxes like:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Redistribution of unexpected gains when high prices benefit producers at the expense of consumers,</li>
<li>Funding social welfare schemes, and</li>
<li>Supplementary revenue stream for the government</li>
</ol>
<h4>Why are countries levying windfall taxes now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Prices of oil, gas, and coal have seen <strong><u>sharp increases</u></strong> since last year and in the first two quarters of the current year, although they have reduced recently.</li>
<li><strong><u>Pandemic recovery</u></strong> and supply issues resulting from the Russia-Ukraine conflict <strong><u>shored up energy demands</u></strong>, which in turn have driven up global prices.</li>
<li>The rising prices meant huge and record profits for energy companies while resulting in <strong><u>hefty gas and electricity bills for households</u></strong> in major and smaller economies.</li>
<li>Since the gains stemmed partly from external change, multiple analysts have called them windfall profits.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with imposing such taxes</h4>
<ul>
<li>Companies are confident in investing in a sector if there is <strong><u>certainty and stability in a tax regime</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Since windfall taxes are imposed retrospectively and are often influenced by unexpected events, they can brew <strong><u>uncertainty in the market about future taxes</u></strong>.</li>
<li>IMF says that taxes in response to price surges <strong><u>may suffer from design problems</u></strong>—given their expedient and <strong><u>political nature</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It added that introducing a temporary windfall profit tax <strong><u>reduces future investment</u></strong> because prospective investors will internalise the likelihood of potential taxes when making investment decisions.</li>
<li>There is another argument about what exactly constitutes true windfall profits; how can it be determined and <strong><u>what level of profit is normal or excessive</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Another issue is<strong> <u>who should be taxed</u></strong> — only the big companies responsible for the bulk of high-priced sales or smaller companies as well— raising the question of whether producers with revenues or profits below a certain threshold should be exempt.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-a-windfall-tax/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is India’s current policy of multi alignment? Advantages and challenges</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/multi-alignment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>non alignment movement</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>foreign policy</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Multi alignment" class="alignnone wp-image-635811" height="330" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 586px) 100vw, 586px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nonaligned_movement-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nonaligned_movement-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nonaligned_movement-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nonaligned_movement.jpeg 770w" width="586"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Forthcoming Shanghai Cooperation Organization (SCO) summit in Samarkand, Uzbekistan is leading India to multi alignment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s journey of foreign policy from being the founder of non-alignment to the multi-alignment. In his book The India Way, External Affairs Minister S. Jaishankar offers a critique of India’s traditional policy of “non-alignment”, where he distinguishes between the “optimistic  non- alignment ” of the past, which he feels has failed, that must give way to more realistic “multiple engagements of the future”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Shanghai Co-operation Organization (SCO)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>SCO is a Eurasian political, economic and security organization.</li>
<li>It is the world’s largest regional organization,</li>
<li>40% of the world population</li>
<li>More than 30% of global GDP.</li>
<li>Members: 8-China, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Russia and Tajikistan, Uzbekistan, India and Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Multi alignment" class="alignnone wp-image-635812" height="281" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 499px) 100vw, 499px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/RIC-1-1095x616-1-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/RIC-1-1095x616-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/RIC-1-1095x616-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/RIC-1-1095x616-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/RIC-1-1095x616-1.jpg 1095w" width="499"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/shanghai-cooperation-organisation-sco/">SCO SUMIIT, 2022</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Host- Uzbekistan,</li>
<li>Uzbekistan will host a full house: 15 leaders including eight member states from four Central Asian States, China, India, Pakistan and Russia,</li>
<li>The observer states: Belarus, Mongolia and Iran (which will become member this year) —</li>
<li>Afghanistan is not invited</li>
<li>Leaders of guest countries -Armenia, Azerbaijan, Turkey and Turkmenistan</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is non- alignment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It’s a policy, a brainchild of Nehru. Non-alignment movement emerged after second world war.</li>
<li>Non-alignment means not having an alliance with any of superpower, either USSR or USA.  Decolonized nations of Asia and Africa was largely a part of this group.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Multi alignment" class="alignnone wp-image-635813" height="487" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Stevan_Kragujevic_Tito_Naser_Nehru_Dolazak_na_Brione-277x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Stevan_Kragujevic_Tito_Naser_Nehru_Dolazak_na_Brione-277x300.jpg 277w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Stevan_Kragujevic_Tito_Naser_Nehru_Dolazak_na_Brione.jpg 440w" width="450"/>India’s policy of non-alignment </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At bandung conference in 1955 non-alignment movement started with India as one of the founding member.</li>
<li>With policy of non-alignment India refused to gravitate towards USA or USSR.</li>
<li>India was the leader of non-alignment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is India’s current policy of multi- alignment? Advantages and challenges.</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Since the start of his tenure from 2014, Prime Minister Narendra Modi have not attended any conference of non-alignment.</li>
<li>External Affairs Minister Dr. S. Jaishankar in his book, The Indian way have criticized the non-alignment.</li>
<li>In the words of Former Foreign Secretary Vijay Gokhale India is no longer the non-align nation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How it is a Multi alignment policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India to truly multi aligned or all aligned by being a part of every major grouping.</li>
<li>India is a part of BRICS and Prime Minister Modi is attending the SCO SUMMIT in Samarkand.</li>
<li>On parallel to rival groups India is also the part of Quad and Indo pacific economic framework.</li>
<li>India is buying the discounted Russian oil and reusing to buckle under pressure from west and USA.</li>
<li>S-400 purchase is happening and India have dodged the bullet of sanctions from USA.</li>
<li>India is choosing the bilateral Free trade agreement like with Australia and UAE and withdrew from groupings like RCEP and Most recently IPEF. This policy are is said to be in the economic interest of India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Advantages of Multi alignment </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India no longer wants to repeat the mistake of missing out of P5 Security council (“Permanent membership in the Security Council was granted to five states based on their importance in the aftermath of World War II).</li>
<li>If any group work against your interest it is better to be part of group rather than remain outside and do nothing</li>
<li>With retreating USA and its collapsing hegemony world is moving towards multiple polar world order.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Disadvantages </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Major disadvantage of non-alignment is you no longer have influence over adverse policy of friendly country.</li>
<li>For example. Russia sells S-400 to India but it also sold the same weapon to china.</li>
<li>USA and India are strategically getting closer day by day but USA recently approved the sale of $450 million F-16 fighter jets to Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Multi alignment will serve India its best national interest.</li>
<li>So far India has managed the rival parties at world stage to secure its foreign policy objectives but with Russian aggression and Chinese assertion and divided world will pose a significant challenge to India’s multi alignment policy.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you understand by non-alignment and multi-alignment? Analyze the shift In India’s foreign policy from non-alignment to multi-alignment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/multi-alignment/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The great Indian thirst: The story of India’s water stress</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/water-stress/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>various water reports</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>water conservation</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="water stress" class="alignnone wp-image-636154" height="315" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 559px) 100vw, 559px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vsemirnyi-den-vody-2017-nrwf-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vsemirnyi-den-vody-2017-nrwf-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vsemirnyi-den-vody-2017-nrwf-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vsemirnyi-den-vody-2017-nrwf.jpeg 770w" width="559"/></strong><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>United Nations World Water Development Report of 2022 has expressed global concern over the sharp rise in freshwater withdrawal from streams, lakes, aquifers and human made reservoirs, significant water stress and also water scarcity being experienced in diﬀerent parts of the world.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who publishes the UNs world water development report?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The United Nations World Water Development Report (WWDR) is published by UNESCO, on behalf of UN-Water and its production is coordinated by the UNESCO World Water Assessment Program (WWAP).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the level of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-water-crisis/#:~:text=Nearly%20600%20million%20Indians%20faced,million%20people%2C%20the%20study%20noted.">water stress</a> in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Global Drought Risk and Water Stress map (2019)</strong>: It shows that major parts of India, particularly west, central and parts of peninsular India are highly water stressed and experience water scarcity.</li>
<li><strong>Composite Water Management Index (2018):</strong> Released by Niti Aayog indicates that more than 600 million people are facing acute water stress.</li>
<li><strong>India is the world’s largest extractor of groundwater</strong>: Accounting for 25 per cent of the total. 70 percent of our water sources are contaminated and our major rivers are dying because of pollution.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="water stress" class="alignnone wp-image-636155" height="304" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 456px) 100vw, 456px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-768x511.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478.jpg 976w" width="456"/>Why is Rural to Urban transfer of water becoming an issue in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rising urban population: </strong>According to Census 2011, the urban population in India accounted for 34% of total population. It is estimated that the urban population component in India will cross the 40% mark by 2030 and the 50% mark by 2050 according to World Urbanization Prospects, 2018.</li>
<li><strong>Water use in the urban areas: </strong>Water use in the urban sector has increased as more and more people shift to urban areas. Per capita use of water in these centers rises, which will continue to grow with improved standards of living.</li>
<li><strong>Shifting of water source in Urban areas: </strong>As the city grows and water management infrastructures develop, dependence shifts to surface water from groundwater. <strong>For example:</strong> In Ahmedabad, more than 80% of water supply used to be met from groundwater sources till the mid-1980s. Due to such overexploitation of groundwater the depth to groundwater level reached 67 meters in confined aquifers. The city now depends on the Narmada canal for the bulk of its water supply.</li>
<li><strong>Dependence of urban areas on rural areas for water source and rural-urban disputes over water: </strong>Cities largely depend on rural areas for raw water supply, which has the potential to ignite the rural-urban dispute. For example: Nagpur and Chennai face the problem of rural-urban water disputes.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong><img alt="water stress" class="alignnone wp-image-636156" height="336" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 596px) 100vw, 596px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Water1-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Water1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Water1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Water1.jpg 800w" width="596"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/kaveri-river-water-dispute/">Reasons for disputes</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Diversion of resource</strong>: Water is transported to urban areas at the expense of rural areas. Due to the high population in urban areas the water requirement for daily use is very high.</li>
<li><strong>High demand of water for industrial purposes: </strong>In urban areas the water is heavily used in industries creating water stress.</li>
<li><strong>High Agriculture dependence:</strong> In the rural areas water is used mainly for irrigation purposes and due to heavy dependence on agriculture the water is very essential in rural areas.</li>
<li><strong>Water pollution</strong>: In cities, most of this water is in the form of grey water with little recovery or reuse, eventually contributing to water pollution.</li>
<li><strong>Bad governance</strong>: Politicization of water for vote bank and skewed distribution of water particular regions For example: Andhra and Telangana.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="water stress " class="alignnone wp-image-636157" height="387" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-1536x1025.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo-1980x1321.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merlin_157734477_4e2f9958-db5d-42ed-b01d-7f08dd764ab6-superJumbo.jpg 2048w" width="581"/>Climate change exacerbate the rural-urban disputes</strong><strong> </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Affecting rainfall pattern: </strong>Climate change affects the amount of rainfall in the region which is the prime source of both surface water and groundwater.</li>
<li><strong>Increase rate of evaporation over surface water:</strong> because of high temperature the surface waters of lakes, rivers, canals etc. face high evaporation water loss.</li>
<li><strong>Melting of glaciers: </strong>glaciers are the sources for perennial rivers of India. Due to global warming, glaciers are melting and hence affecting the perennial nature of rivers.</li>
<li><strong>Frequent droughts:</strong> It affects the groundwater recharge process and drying of surface waters which creates shortage of water. It exacerbate the rural-urban conflict.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A system perspective and catchment scale based approach are necessary to link reallocation of water with wider discussions on development, infrastructure investment, fostering an rural-urban partnership and adopting an integrated approach in water management.</li>
<li>The government cannot manage the water crisis alone. It will take the combined efforts of civil society, the private sector including the public at large to meet the challenge.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Rural and urban areas use water from the same stock, i.e., the water resources of the country. Therefore, it is important to strive for a win- win situation by securing the interests of both urban and rural areas. Good Governance is the key to achieve such a win-win situation.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question Q.</strong></p>
<p><strong>How the rising water stress and growing urbanization in India is fuelling rural-urban conflict over water issues? Also highlight the role of climate change in exacerbating these conflicts. Elaborate.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/water-stress/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Here is how HDI has performed in last 3 decades</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hdi/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of report</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>human development</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="HDI" class="alignnone wp-image-636168" height="345" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 448px) 100vw, 448px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-300x231.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-300x231.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-1024x787.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-768x590.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant-1171x900.jpg 1171w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/15migrant.jpg 1200w" width="448"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India, belonging to the medium HDI category, shows dimensional inequalities similar to or slightly below the average figures in the category, except in the case of education where it is high and closer to the low HDI countries. The inequalities in health and education are more than twice that of the very high and high HDI categories.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The bad news for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/human-development-report-by-undp/">India is that its global HDI rank has slipped</a> from 129 in 2019 to 131 in 2020 and to 132 in 2021-22.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the meaning of human development?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Human development is defined as the process of enlarging people’s freedoms and opportunities and improving their well-being. Human development is about the real freedom ordinary people have to decide who to be, what to do, and how to live.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is meant by Human Development Index?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The HDI is a summary measure of human development. The HDI is a summary composite measure of a country’s average achievements in three basic aspects of human development: health, knowledge and standard of living.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who publishes HDI?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Human Development Report (HDR) is an annual Human Development Index report published by the Human Development Report Office of the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="HDI" class="alignnone wp-image-636170" height="338" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ht-metro-ht-navi-mumbai_f11feabc-b82c-11e8-bbaf-ff4d73ce44e3.jpg 960w" width="600"/>Dimensions of the Human Development Index</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Long and healthy life: </strong>The long and healthy life dimension is measured by life expectancy at birth. The life expectancy at birth is a statistical measure that an average individual is expected to live based on certain demographic factors such as the year of birth and current age.</li>
<li><strong>Education</strong>: This is a second dimension in the HDI. The indicators of education are the expected years of schooling and the mean years of schooling. According to the UN, the average maximum years of schooling is 18 years, while the mean maximum years of schooling is 15 years.</li>
<li><strong>Standard of living: </strong>The standard of living is usually measured by the gross national income (GNI) per capita. The GNI indicates the total domestic and foreign output created by the residents of a certain country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the 4 indicators of HDI?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Mean years of schooling</li>
<li>Expected years of schooling</li>
<li>Life expectancy at birth</li>
<li>Gross national income (GNI) per capita</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Which Countries Have the Highest HDI?</strong></p>
<p>In the latest HDI ranking, from 2022, Switzerland finished first with an HDI value of 0.962.</p></blockquote>
<p><img alt="HDI" class="wp-image-636173" height="339" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 509px) 100vw, 509px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook-1200x800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/o-poor-india-slum-water-facebook.jpg 1536w" width="509"/></p>
<h4><strong>Issues in HDI</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) An incomplete indicator</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Human development is incomplete without human freedom and that while the need for qualities judgement is clear; there is no simple quantitative measure available yet to capture the many aspects of human freedom.</li>
<li>HDI also does not specifically reflect quality of life factors, such as empowerment movements or overall feelings of security or happiness.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Limited idea of development</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The HDI is not reflecting the human development idea accurately.</li>
<li>It is an index restricted to the socio-economic sphere of life; the political and civil spheres are in the most part kept separate.</li>
<li>Hence there is a sub-estimation of inequality among countries, which means that this dimension is not being taken into consideration appropriately.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) A vague concept</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Concerning data quality and the exact construction of the index HDI is conceptually weak and empirically unsound.</li>
<li>This strong critic comes from the idea that both components of HDI are problematic. The GNP in developing countries suffers from incomplete coverage, measurement errors and biases.</li>
<li>The definition and measurement of literacy are different among countries and also, this data has not been available since 1970 in a significant number of countries.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Data quality issues</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The HDI, as a combination of only four relatively simple indicators, doesn’t only raise a questions what other indicators should be included, but also how to ensure quality and comparable input data.</li>
<li>It is logical that the UNDP try to collect their data from international organizations concentrating in collecting data in specific fields.</li>
<li>Quality and trustworthiness of those data is disputable, especially when we get the information from UN non-democratic members, as for example Cuba or China.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) A tool for mere comparison</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The concept of HDI was set up mainly for relative comparison of countries in one particular time.</li>
<li>HDI is much better when distinguishing between countries with low and middle human development, instead of countries at the top of the ranking.</li>
<li>Therefore, the original notion was not to set up an absolute ranking, but let’s quite free hands in comparison of the results.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Development has to be greener</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The human development approach has not adequately incorporated environmental conditions which may threaten long-term achievements on human development. The most pervasive failure was on environmental sustainability.</li>
<li>However, for the first time in 2020, the UNDP introduced a new metric to reflect the impact caused by each country’s per-capita carbon emissions and its material footprint.</li>
<li>This is Planetary Pressures-adjusted HDI or PHDI. It measured the amount of fossil fuels, metals and other resources used to make the goods and services it consumes.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(7) Wealth can never equate welfare</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Higher national wealth does not indicate welfare. GNI may not necessarily increase economic welfare; it depends on how it is spent.</li>
<li>For example, if a country spends more on military spending – this is reflected in higher GNI, but welfare could actually be lower.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Importance of HDI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multidimensionality</strong>: It is one of the few multidimensional indices as it includes indicators such as literacy rate, enrolment ratio, life expectancy rate, infant mortality rate, etc.</li>
<li><strong>True yardstick</strong>: It acts as a true yardstick to measure development in real sense.</li>
<li><strong>Helps in measuring a nation’s well-being:</strong> Unlike per capital income, which only indicates that a rise in per capital income implies economic development; HDI considers many other vital social indicators and helps in measuring a nation’s well-being.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Value addition line</strong></p>
<p><em>People are the real wealth of a nation. The basic objective of development should be to create an enabling environment for people to live long, healthy and creative lives. This may appear to be a simple truth.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To sum up, the introduction of the HDI three decades ago was an early attempt to address the shortcomings in conventional measures of wellbeing.</li>
<li>The HDI has continued to attract widespread attention and motivates the work of activists, scholars and political leaders around the world.</li>
<li>The HDI compels us to ask what matters more, the quantitative expansion of an economy, or the qualitative improvement in the capabilities of society.</li>
<li>Indeed the revival of interest in this subject at the highest levels of government is the need of the hour.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you understand by human development? Critically analyse the human development index given by UNDP.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hdi/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>old age problems that we should address now</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/old-age/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>government schemes</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>social welfare</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="old age" class="alignnone wp-image-636184" height="302" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 671px) 100vw, 671px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/809500-jnxnqsfxdc-1465291749-300x135.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/809500-jnxnqsfxdc-1465291749-300x135.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/809500-jnxnqsfxdc-1465291749-1024x459.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/809500-jnxnqsfxdc-1465291749-768x344.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/809500-jnxnqsfxdc-1465291749.jpg 1200w" width="671"/>Context             </strong></h4>
<p>India will be facing the immediate challenge –The ageing of the population. Challenge to ensure a decent quality of life for the old age people in the near future, planning and providing for it must begin today.</p>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Life expectancy in India has more than doubled since Independence from around 32 years in the late 1940s to 70 years or so today, a historical achievement.</li>
<li>Over the same period, the fertility rate has crashed from about six children per woman to just two, which liberated women from the cycle of continuous child bearing and child care.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is ageing of the population?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Meaning: </strong>Population ageing is a shift in the distribution of a country’s population towards older ages.</li>
<li><strong>Reason behind it</strong>: Decline in the fertility rate and Rise In the life expectancy. An increase in longevity increases the average age of the population by increasing the numbers of surviving older people.</li>
<li><strong>Impact of the ageing population:</strong>, labor supply shortage, change in patterns of saving and investment, deteriorate fiscal balance, lack of adequate welfare system etc.</li>
<li><strong>Challenges they impose: </strong>Social security, elderly Healthcare, Dependence on the family etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the status in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to the National Commission on Population, The share of the elderly (persons aged 60 years and above) close to 9% in 2011.</li>
<li>It is growing fast and may reach 18% by 2036.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="old age" class="alignnone wp-image-636185" height="424" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 645px) 100vw, 645px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/senior-citizens-_-demonetisation-300x197.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/senior-citizens-_-demonetisation-300x197.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/senior-citizens-_-demonetisation.jpg 760w" width="645"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/old-age-poverty/">Problems faced by elderly</a> </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Depression</strong>: According to survey by Abdul Latif Jameel foundation in Tamilnadu, 30-50% of people above age of 60 has a symptoms of depression.The proportion with depression symptoms is much higher for women than men, and rises sharply with age. In most cases, depression remains undiagnosed and untreated.</li>
<li><strong>Loneliness</strong>: Loneliness one the major factor leading to depression. A large majority of elderly persons living alone are women, mainly widows.</li>
<li><strong>Hardship of age</strong>: Monetary assistance can certainly help to cope with many health issues.</li>
<li><strong>Poverty and poor health</strong>: Old age pensions are vital. Cash helps to lead a dignified life.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="old age" class="alignnone wp-image-636186" height="310" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 508px) 100vw, 508px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/old-age-300x183.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/old-age-300x183.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/old-age.jpg 675w" width="508"/>Current government schemes for elderly </strong></h4>
<p><strong>Pradhan Mantri Vaya Vandana Scheme</strong> – This is one of the most popular senior citizen pension schemes in India.</p>
<ul>
<li>Designed for senior citizens above 60 years of age, the policy term of this Prime Minister Senior Citizen Scheme extends to ten years.</li>
<li>The pensioner can choose the frequency of the payment – monthly/quarterly/half- yearly/annually.</li>
<li>You can earn interest of 8% per annum over this scheme.</li>
<li>The minimum and maximum capping of pension are Rs. 3,000 per month and 10,000 per month, respectively</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>National Programme for the Health Care of Elderly (NPHCE)</strong>–</p>
<ul>
<li>Introduced in 2010, this scheme concentrates on preventive as well as promotive, care for the maintenance of overall health.</li>
<li>This program was launched to address the health issues faced by seniors.</li>
<li>The district-level objectives include providing dedicated health facilities in district hospitals, community health centres (CHC), primary health centres (PHC), and sub-centres (SC) levels through State Health Society.</li>
<li>These facilities maybe free or highly subsidized.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Varishta Mediclaim Policy</strong> –</p>
<ul>
<li>This policy aids seniors by covering the cost of medicines, blood, ambulance charges, and other diagnosis related charges.</li>
<li>Designed for senior citizens between the age of 60 and 80 years, this helps meet the health-related expenses of senior citizens.</li>
<li>Income tax benefits are allowed for payment of premium.</li>
<li>Although the policy period is for one year, you can extend the renewal up to the age of 90 years.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Rashtriya Vayoshri Yojana</strong> –</p>
<ul>
<li>This scheme provides physical aids and assisted-living devices to the elderly above 60 years of age that belong to the BPL (below the poverty line) category.</li>
<li>If senior citizens wish to avail this, then they must have a BPL card.</li>
<li>This is a Central Sector Scheme and is entirely funded by the Central Government.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Varishta Pension Bima Yojana</strong> –</p>
<ul>
<li>This pension scheme, launched by the Ministry of Finance, is for senior citizens above 60 years.</li>
<li>The LIC of India has the authority to operate this scheme.</li>
<li>Any Medical check-ups is not necessary to avail this policy.</li>
<li>It offers assured pension with a guaranteed interest rate of 8% per annum for up to 10 years –</li>
<li>You can opt for monthly, quarterly, half-yearly, and yearly pension – depends on how you’d like to receive it.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Vayoshreshtha Samman</strong> –</p>
<p>This scheme focuses on those seniors who have made significant contributions in their disciplines and recognized their efforts.</p>
<p>It was upgraded to the National Award in 2013, and since then, awards have been granted below thirteen categories.</p>
<h4><strong><img alt="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/old-age-poverty/" class="alignnone wp-image-636195" height="340" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 629px) 100vw, 629px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-1-300x162.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-1-300x162.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/108205197_gettyimages-1152798478-1.jpg 746w" width="629"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Social security pensions, of course, are just the first step towards a dignified life for the elderly. They also need other support and facilities such as health care, disability aids and assistance with daily tasks, recreation opportunities and a good social life. They can be the active contributor to the economy having the years of experience and mentorship to the demographic dividend.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question Q.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Discuss the challenges before our elderly today? What steps have been taken by government to address these challenges?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/old-age/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>[pib] Indian Navy participates in Exercise Kakadu hosted by Australia</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/exercise-kakadu/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ex Kakadu</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p>INS Satpura and a P8 I Maritime Patrol Aircraft of the Indian Navy reached Darwin in Australia on for participation in the multinational Exercise Kakadu – 2022, hosted by the Royal Australian Navy.</p>
<h4><strong>Exercise KAKADU</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/prelims-spotlight-important-submarines-and-naval-ships/">Exercise</a> KAKADU, which <strong><u>started in 1993</u></strong>, is the premier multilateral regional maritime engagement exercise hosted by the Royal Australian Navy (RAN) and supported by the Australian Air Force.</li>
<li>The exercise is <strong><u>held biennially in Darwin</u></strong> and the Northern Australian Exercise Areas (NAXA).</li>
<li>It <strong><u>derives its name from Kakadu National Park</u></strong>, which is a protected area in the northern territory of Australia, 171 km south-east of Darwin</li>
<li>During the exercise, professional exchanges in harbour and diverse range of activities at sea, including complex surface, sub-surface and air operations would enable sharing of best practices and honing of operational skills.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>India’s presence at the exercise</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian Navy’s participation in KAKADU provides an excellent opportunity to engage with regional partners and undertake multinational maritime activities ranging from constabulary operations to high-end maritime warfare in a combined environment</li>
<li>It is aimed at enhancing interoperability and developing of common understanding of procedures for maritime operations gaining importance with the Indo-Pacific narrative.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="AgJlNxC8j2"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/prelims-spotlight-important-submarines-and-naval-ships/">[Prelims Spotlight] Important Submarines and Naval Ships</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="AgJlNxC8j2" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/prelims-spotlight-important-submarines-and-naval-ships/embed/#?secret=UigWdCg5kh#?secret=AgJlNxC8j2" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Prelims Spotlight] Important Submarines and Naval Ships” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/exercise-kakadu/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre adds 4 new tribes to Scheduled Tribes (ST) List</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/new-tribes-to-scheduled-tribes-list/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Tribes in news</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Union Cabinet under the chairmanship of PM has approved the addition of four tribes to the list of Scheduled Tribes (ST), including those from Himachal Pradesh, Tamil Nadu and Chhattisgarh.</p>
<h4>Which tribes are we talking about?</h4>
<ol>
<li><strong><u>Hatti </u></strong>tribe in the Trans-Giri area of Sirmour district in Himachal Pradesh</li>
<li><strong><u>Narikoravan</u></strong> and <strong><u>Kurivikkaran</u></strong> hill tribes of Tamil Nadu and</li>
<li><strong><u>Binjhia</u></strong> tribe in Chhattisgarh, which was listed as ST in Jharkhand and Odisha but not in Chhattisgarh</li>
</ol>
<h4>Other tribes in news</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Cabinet also approved ‘<span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Betta-Kuruba</strong></span>’ as a synonym for the Kadu Kuruba tribe In Karnataka.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who are the Scheduled Tribes?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The term ‘<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/what-is-the-reason-for-special-provisions-for-the-scheduled-tribes-in-the-constitution-of-india-are-these-provisions-successful-in-ameliorating-their-conditions-250-words/">Scheduled Tribes’</a> first appeared in the Constitution of India.</li>
<li><strong><u>Article 366 (25)</u></strong> defined scheduled tribes as “such tribes or tribal communities or parts of or groups within such tribes or tribal communities as are deemed under Article 342 to be Scheduled Tribes for the purposes of this constitution”.</li>
<li><strong><u>Article 342</u></strong> prescribes procedure to be followed in the matter of specification of scheduled tribes.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Among the tribal groups, several have adapted to modern life but there are tribal groups who are more vulnerable.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Dhebar Commission (1973)</u></strong> created a separate category “Primitive Tribal Groups (PTGs)” which was renamed in 2006 as “<strong><u>Particularly Vulnerable Tribal Groups (PVTGs</u></strong>)”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How are STs notified?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The first specification of Scheduled Tribes in relation to a particular State/ Union Territory is by a notified order of the President, after consultation with the State governments concerned.</li>
<li>These orders can be modified subsequently only through an Act of Parliament.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Status of STs in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Census 2011 has revealed that there are said to be 705 ethnic groups notified as Scheduled Tribes (STs).</li>
<li>Over 10 crore Indians are notified as STs, of which 1.04 crore live in urban areas.</li>
<li>The STs constitute 8.6% of the population and 11.3% of the rural population.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="uvIVi0e0Qc"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/what-is-the-reason-for-special-provisions-for-the-scheduled-tribes-in-the-constitution-of-india-are-these-provisions-successful-in-ameliorating-their-conditions-250-words/">What is the reason for special provisions for the Scheduled Tribes in the constitution of India? Are these provisions successful in ameliorating their conditions? (250 Words)</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="uvIVi0e0Qc" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/mains/what-is-the-reason-for-special-provisions-for-the-scheduled-tribes-in-the-constitution-of-india-are-these-provisions-successful-in-ameliorating-their-conditions-250-words/embed/#?secret=Y52cNVyCdp#?secret=uvIVi0e0Qc" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“What is the reason for special provisions for the Scheduled Tribes in the constitution of India? Are these provisions successful in ameliorating their conditions? (250 Words)” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/new-tribes-to-scheduled-tribes-list/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How the National Logistics Policy will speed up lumbering freight sector?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/how-the-national-logistics-policy-will-speed-up-lumbering-freight-sector/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NLP</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="logistics" class="alignnone wp-image-636221" height="263" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logistics-300x148.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logistics-300x148.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logistics.jpg 684w" width="533"/></strong></p>
<p>The government will announce the National Logistics Policy (NLP) this week, aiming to bring down logistics costs and address challenges plaguing importers and exporters.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Logistics? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Logistics refers to the overall process of managing <strong><u>how resources are acquired, stored, and transported</u></strong> to their final destination.</li>
<li>It involves identifying prospective distributors and suppliers and determining their effectiveness and accessibility.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need a logistics policy?</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="logistics" class="alignnone wp-image-636220" height="273" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 438px) 100vw, 438px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist-300x187.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist-300x187.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist-768x479.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/logist.jpg 827w" width="438"/></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Organizing and consolidating the sector:</strong> India’s logistics sector is largely unorganized and fragmented.</li>
<li><strong>Reducing logistics cost:</strong> This is why the country’s logistics costs are as high as 14-15% of the GDP, against 7-8% in developed nations such as the Singapore and the US, who leverage it to boost exports. The NLP aims to bring down India’s logistics cost to 8% in the next five years.</li>
<li><strong>Preventing waste of perishable items:</strong> As per some estimates in India, about 16% of agri-production is wasted at different stages of the supply chain.</li>
<li><strong>Warehousing development:</strong> Moreover, due to factors such as limited capacity and availability of warehouses, the cost of transaction increases.</li>
<li><strong>Multi-modal integration:</strong> The new policy is going about simplification, technology and will have a multimodal approach that will combine rail, water, and air — all modes of transport.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What role will technology play?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Advanced analytics:</strong> The NLP will aim to harness technologies such as AI and blockchain. It aims to create a data analytics centre for driving greater transparency and continuous monitoring of key logistics metrics.</li>
<li><strong>Single window portal:</strong> Under NLP, a portal will be created, where service providers such as warehousing providers, shipping experts, transporters, customs brokers, and various governmental agencies will be unified.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Will it boost cooperation between ministries?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Unifying multiple departments:</strong> Currently, the logistics value chain is managed by several ministries—road transport and highways, shipping, railways, and civil aviation.</li>
<li><strong>Single-point clearances:</strong> Agencies like the Central Drug Standard Control Organization and the Food Safety and Standard Authority of India provide clearances.</li>
<li><strong>Nationwide integration:</strong> The NLP could enhance their integration at the central level.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What about reducing the carbon footprint?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Energy-efficient transportation:</strong> The draft logistics policy lays emphasis on the shift to more energy-efficient means of transportation, as well as the use of greener fuels which could reduce the supply chain’s carbon footprint.</li>
<li><strong>Vehicular emission reduction:</strong> Moreover, the draft policy, released earlier, emphasized creating regulations for controlling vehicular noise, emissions, and wastage.</li>
<li><strong>Green warehousing principles:</strong> The new logistics policy also aims to incorporate green principles in the functioning of warehouses which contribute to nearly 10% of the logistics costs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Will it change India’s commodity transport?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Transport of crucial commodities:</strong> The proposed policy aims to focus on the transport of crucial commodities such as coal, steel, iron ore, food grains, steel, cement, fruits and vegetables.</li>
<li><strong>Creating nationwide clusters:</strong> The current logistical network for transporting them is mainly confined to regional clusters.</li>
<li><strong>Integrating national supply-chains:</strong> The NLP could help establish a link between the place of origin, and destination place and integrate the supply on a national level.</li>
<li><strong>Optimum logistics identification:</strong> The draft also proposes identification of the right mode of transport for each of these commodities to minimise losses during transport.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/how-the-national-logistics-policy-will-speed-up-lumbering-freight-sector/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Hindi not a competitor of regional languages: Home Minister</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hindi-not-a-competitor-regional-languages/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>National language debate</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-636219" height="223" sizes="(max-width: 426px) 100vw, 426px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hindi-300x157.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hindi-300x157.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hindi.jpg 500w" width="426"/></strong></p>
<p>Union Home Minister has appealed to guardians to speak to children in their mother tongue to enable them to learn Hindi without much effort, on the Hindi Divas.</p>
<h4>What did HM say on Hindi?</h4>
<ul>
<li>He said it was time that <strong><u>inferiority complex around Indian languages</u></strong>, instilled by the British, was overthrown from people’s conscience with the help of regional languages and Hindi.</li>
<li>He also said that <strong><u>Hindi was not a competitor but a “friend” of all the other regional languages</u></strong> in the country and they were mutually dependent on each other for their growth.</li>
<li>He said there was a concerted <strong><u>disinformation campaign to pit Hindi against other languages</u></strong> such as Marathi and Tamil, and underlined the need to strengthen local languages with Hindi.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Debate over Hindi</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Between September 12 and 14, 1949, that the Constituent Assembly debated the status of India’s languages.</li>
<li>Among the issues that were discussed were the use of the term ‘<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-national-language-debate/">national language’</a> instead of ‘official’ language.</li>
<li>Hindi author Seth Govind Das, who represented the Central Provinces and Berar, argued for ‘one language and one script’ and suggested that Hindi should replace English at the earliest.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the status of Hindi?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Finally, the Constituent Assembly adopted what was known as “<strong><u>Munshi-Ayyangar Formula</u></strong>.”</li>
<li>According to this, Hindi in the Devnagari script would be the official language of the Union.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Official, not national</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>English would continue to be used for all official purposes for the next 15 years, to enable a smooth transition for non-Hindi speaking states.</li>
<li>The deadline was 26 January 1965.</li>
<li>Under Article 343 of the Constitution, the official language of the Union shall be Hindi in Devanagari script.</li>
<li>The international form of Indian numerals will be used for official purposes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why has language become a sensitive issue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Self-identification:</strong> A strong identification with one’s regional language and an underlying fear of homogenisation is at the heart of the national language question in India. An individual conceptualises and communicates his thoughts in a language, enabling him to be an active part of society.</li>
<li><strong>Language defines primary group:</strong> People identify with one another based on language, thus giving them a primary group. A nation is the largest primary group that once can address.</li>
<li><strong>Learning abilities at stake:</strong> The dangers of imposing a language are manifold. It can affect the learning ability of non-native speakers thereby affecting their self-confidence.</li>
<li><strong>Threats to endangered languages:</strong> It can also endanger other languages and dialects and reduce diversity.</li>
<li><strong>Threats to diversity:</strong> National integration cannot come at the cost of people’s linguistic identities. Language is integral to culture and therefore privileging Hindi over all other languages spoken in India takes away from its diversity.</li>
<li><strong>Promises made by Constituent Assembly:</strong> Then PM Pt. Nehru had promised that Hindi would only serve as a linking language and it would not be imposed on non-Hindi speaking states as long as they were against it.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Benefits of having a national language</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Wide range of speakers:</strong> Hindi is still the most widely spoken language in the country with an estimated 258 million people declaring that Hindi is their native language and millions more comfortable with Hindi.</li>
<li><strong>Language as a unifying language:</strong> A complete usage of Hindi language whilst respecting the various native languages would also ensure better coordination and cooperation among all the states and act as a strong unifying factor and eliminate all regional differences.</li>
<li><strong>Reputation at international fora:</strong> When countries like Germany, Japan, France, Italy etc. use their respective language as a medium of communication even during International forums not only has the reputation of those countries have greatly enhanced but also those languages have gained a huge reputation worldwide.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues with Hindi</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inherent opposition to Hindi:</strong> The Constituent Assembly was bitterly divided on the question, with members from States that did not speak Hindi initially opposing the declaration of Hindi as a national language.</li>
<li><strong>Fear of imposition:</strong> Opponents were against English being done away with, fearing that it may lead to Hindi domination in regions that did not speak the language.</li>
<li><strong>Symbol of identity politics:</strong> The approach towards linguistic policy seems to be driven more by the politics of identity than values of aspiration or accommodation.</li>
<li><strong>Favour for majoritarianism:</strong> The primary argument in favour of Hindi has been reduced to assertions of slim majoritarianism.</li>
<li><strong>Few speakers, still dominant:</strong> Even then, there are concerns about the claim based on mere numerical strength, as only 25 per cent of Indians seem to recognise Hindi as their mother tongue (Census 2011).</li>
<li><strong>Demographic barriers:</strong> Today nearly 35% of people are migrating daily for work. In such a situation, we have to conceptualise a new form of language identity for our states.</li>
<li><strong>Economic barriers:</strong> Any idea of one link language, whether Hindi or English, will be economically disastrous for India. It will slow down migration and reduce the ease of capital flow.</li>
<li><strong>Multiple dialects:</strong> Only five states in India have Hindi as their’ native language’. However, in those states, too, the dialects of Hindi are associated with locals and their communities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why Hindi cannot be the national language?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multiple dialects:</strong> Hindi has largely been influenced by Persian — and then English, among other languages. Also, when the languages were enumerated, Hindi subsumed Bhojpuri, which is spoken by a little over five crore people.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inefficacy of Sanskrit:</strong> There were demands to make Sanskrit the official language, while some argued in favour of ‘Hindustani’.</li>
<li><strong>Issue over Script:</strong> There were differences of opinion over the script too. When opinion veered towards accepting Hindi, proponents of the language wanted the ‘Devanagari’ script to be adopted both for words and numerals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why this issue needs a rational consideration?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Linguistic chauvinism:</strong> Various policies on language have been framed both by the central and state governments that have been termed as forms of linguistic chauvinism.  Ex. Obsession for Marathi in Mumbai</li>
<li><strong>Secular fabric under threat:</strong> The states’ fear of the central government’s ideology of monopolising faith, education, and language will adversely affect the Indian political system, which is based on pluralism and accommodation.</li>
<li><strong>Monolingualism can prove disastrous: </strong>If there is a mechanical and monolithic idea of unity followed by any entity, such an entity generally generates great hostility beyond its immediate borders.  In neighbouring Bangladesh – then East Pakistan – the language movement against the imposition of Urdu on Bengali speakers was a key driver of Pakistan splitting into two nations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Language as a skill:</strong> Language should be looked at as an important skill to operate in a world which is more connected today than at any other point in time.</li>
<li><strong>Language not a cultural burden:</strong> A united nation has to have space for diversity. India is united in its diversity. Diversity is a great philosophical idea and should never be seen as a cultural burden.</li>
<li><strong>Linguistic heritage needs priority:</strong> This is not to contend that our linguistic heritage should be neglected or trivialised. Our metropolises must be recognized as multilingual entities.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hindi-not-a-competitor-regional-languages/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>