<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2022 01:02:24 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>What is the idea of Climate Reparation?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-idea-of-climate-reparation/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Climate reparation</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632165" height="361" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 100vw, 542px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-1024x684.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-768x513.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-1536x1025.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-1200x801.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation-1980x1322.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/reparation.jpg 2000w" width="542"/></p>
<p>Facing the worst <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-urban-deluge-floods/">flooding disaster</a> in its history, <strong><u>Pakistan has begun demanding reparations</u></strong>, or compensation, from the rich countries that are mainly responsible for causing climate change.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>On the face of it, Pakistan’s demand for reparations appears to be a long shot, but the principles being invoked are fairly <strong><u>well-established in environmental jurisprudence</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In fact, <strong><u>Pakistan is not alone</u></strong> in making this demand.</li>
<li>Almost the entire developing world has for years been insisting on setting up an <strong><u>international mechanism for financial reparation</u></strong> for loss and damage caused by climate disasters.</li>
<li>The issue has <strong><u>come up repeatedly at international negotiations</u></strong> for climate change, and on other platforms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Climate Reparation?</h4>
<ul>
<li>At its heart, the demand for compensation for loss and damage from climate disasters is an extension of the universally acknowledged <strong><u>“Polluter Pays” principle</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This makes the polluter liable for paying not just for the cost of remedial action, but also for <strong><u>compensating the victims of environmental damage caused by their actions.</u></strong></li>
<li>Climate justice is based on the <strong><u>notion of not being punished for someone else’s bad behaviour</u></strong>, but it does not sanction additional bad behaviour.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who are responsible for climate change?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the climate change framework, the burden of <strong><u>responsibility falls on those rich countries that have contributed most of the greenhouse gas emissions since 1850</u></strong>, generally considered to be the beginning of the industrial age.</li>
<li>The United States and the European Union, including the UK, account for over 50% of all emissions during this time.</li>
<li>If Russia, Canada, Japan, and Australia too are included, the combined contribution goes past 65%, or almost two-thirds of all emissions.</li>
<li>Historical responsibility is important because carbon dioxide remains in the atmosphere for hundreds of years, and it is the <strong><u>cumulative accumulation of carbon dioxide</u></strong> that causes global warming.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What about developing countries?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A country like India, currently the third largest emitter, <strong>accounts for only 3% of historical emissions</strong>.</li>
<li>China, which is the world’s biggest emitter for over 15 years now, has contributed about <strong><u>11% to total emissions since 1850.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>Why need climate reparations?</h4>
<ul>
<li>While the <strong><u>impact of climate change</u></strong> is global, it is much more <strong><u>severe on the poorer nations</u></strong> because of their geographical locations and weaker capacity to cope.</li>
<li>Countries that have had negligible contributions to historical emissions and <strong><u>have severe limitations of resources</u></strong> are the ones that face the most devastating impacts of climate change.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Institutional mechanism for Climate Reparations</h4>
<h4>(1) United Nations</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>UN Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC)</u></strong>, the 1994 international agreement that lays down the broad principles of the global effort to fight climate change.</li>
<li>It explicitly acknowledges this <strong><u>differentiated responsibility of nations</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It makes it very clear that <strong><u>rich countries must provide both the finance and the technology to the developing nations</u></strong> to help them tackle climate change.</li>
<li>It is this mandate that later evolved into the <strong><u>$100 billion amount that the rich countries agreed to provide</u></strong> every year to the developing world.</li>
<li>While this promise is <strong><u>yet to be met</u></strong>, this $100 billion per year amount is not meant for loss and damage.</li>
<li>Climate disasters were not a regular occurrence in 1994, and as such the <strong><u>UNFCCC does not make a mention of loss and damage. </u></strong></li>
<li>This particular demand emerged much later, and faced <strong><u>stiff resistance from the developed nations</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(2) Warsaw International Mechanism (WIM)</h4>
<ul>
<li>The WIM for Loss and Damages, set up in 2013, was the <strong><u>first formal acknowledgment</u></strong> of the need to <strong><u>compensate developing countries struck by climate disasters</u></strong>.</li>
<li>However, the <strong><u>progress</u></strong> on this front has been painfully <strong><u>slow</u></strong>.</li>
<li><strong><u>No funding mechanism</u></strong>, or even a promise to provide funds, has come about.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Pushback from Developed Countries</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is not hard to understand why the developed countries are dead against compensation claims.</li>
<li>They are struggling to put together even the $100 billion per year flow that they had <strong><u>reluctantly agreed to provide.</u></strong></li>
<li>Further, loss and damage claims can easily spiral into billions of dollars, or even more.</li>
<li>The report said that the United States alone is estimated to have “inflicted more than $1.9 trillion in damages to other countries” due to its emissions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with loss assessment</h4>
<ul>
<li>There are practical difficulties in estimating <strong><u>how much a country has actually suffered</u></strong> due to the actions of others.</li>
<li>To begin with, it has to be established that the <strong><u>disaster was caused by climate change</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Then there are <strong><u>non-economic losses</u></strong> as well, including <strong><u>loss of lives</u></strong>, <strong><u>displacement</u></strong> and <strong><u>migration</u></strong>, <strong><u>health impacts</u></strong>, and <strong><u>damage to cultural heritage</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Then there is this other step about assessing how much of the losses are due to the event itself, and <strong><u>what could be attributed to misgovernance</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>A lot of background work is going on to create the framework in which it would be possible to quantify the compensation due to an affected country.</li>
<li>What Pakistan has done, through its demands for reparations, is to call attention to this often neglected aspect.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-idea-of-climate-reparation/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Electricity Amendment Bill 2022 – Addressing the transition and equity</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/electricity/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of the bill</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>electricity reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="electricity" class="alignnone wp-image-629013" height="343" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download.jpeg" width="558"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Concerns of states on some provisions of the new Electricity Bill are justified. But the legislation proposes welcome correctives to longstanding problems of the power sector.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Important provisions of the bill</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Payment security</strong>: The Bill provides that electricity will not be scheduled or despatched if adequate payment security is not provided by the discom.   The central government may prescribe rules regarding payment security.</li>
<li><strong>Contract enforcement</strong>: The Bill empowers the CERC and SERCs to adjudicate disputes related to the performance of contracts.  These refer to contracts related to the sale, purchase, or transmission of electricity.  Further, the Commissions will have powers of a Civil Court.</li>
<li><strong>Renewable purchase obligation</strong>: The Act empowers SERCs to specify renewable purchase obligations (RPO) for discoms.  RPO refers to the mandate to procure a certain percentage of electricity from renewable sources.  The Bill adds that RPO should not be below a minimum percentage prescribed by the central government.  Failure to meet RPO will be punishable with a penalty between 25 paise and 50 paise per kilowatt of the shortfall.</li>
<li><strong>Selection committee for SERCs</strong>: Under the Act, the Chairperson of the Central Electricity Authority or the Chairperson of the CERC is one of the members of the selection committee to recommend appointments to the SERCs.  Under the Bill, instead of this person, the central government will nominate a member to the selection committee.  The nominee should not be below the rank of Additional Secretary to the central government.</li>
<li><strong>Composition of Commissions and APTEL</strong>: The Bill increases the number of members (including the chairperson) in SERCs from three to four.  Further, at least one member in both the CERC and SERCs must be from law background.  Under the Act, Appellate Tribunal for Electricity (APTEL) consists of a chairperson and three other members.  The Bill instead provides that the APTEL will have three or more members, as may be prescribed by the central government.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>State apprehensions of the bill </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multi state license: </strong>The clause pertaining to applicants seeking a distribution licence in more than one state. It states that the Central Electricity Regulatory Commission (CERC), and not the SERC, will grant the licence. This is problematic because a SERC is likely to be more aware of the field-level conditions in a state than its central counterpart.</li>
<li><strong>Centre can bypass state: </strong>The Bill has a provision empowering the Centre to give directions directly to the SERCs. Till now, the CERC received instructions from the Centre and the SERCs were under the state. The new Bill enables the Centre to bypass state governments. It’s not surprising that this is a matter of concern for the states.</li>
<li><strong>Direct appointment by centre:</strong> The Bill states that the SERC chairperson will now be a nominee of the central government and will be an additional secretary-level official. This gives the impression that the Centre is trying to control the appointments to the SERCs<strong>. </strong></li>
</ul>
<div class="mceTemp"></div>
<p><img alt="electricity" class="alignnone wp-image-629016" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 481px) 100vw, 481px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy-300x208.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy-300x208.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/power-dis-energy.jpg 650w" width="481"/></p>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/power-sector-reforms/"><strong>Why the bill is important? </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Compensation clause: </strong>The Bill states that if power purchase agreement PPAs are renegotiated, the affected party has to be compensated within 90 days from the date of submission of the petition.</li>
<li><strong>Uniformity in tariffs revision:</strong> New tariffs have to be made applicable from the beginning of the financial year. New tariffs often come into force in the middle of the financial year (due to delays in the issuing of orders by SERCs). This means that discoms do not earn their full revenues leading to cash flow problems.</li>
<li><strong>Easy tariff petition processing now:</strong> The Bill has proposed a reduction in the time for processing tariff petitions from 120 days to 90 days.</li>
<li><strong>Suo moto jurisdiction</strong>: Regulatory commissions have been given suo motu jurisdiction if tariff petitions are not filed within 30 days of the stipulated time. This too is a step in the right direction.</li>
<li><strong>More teeth to load dispatcher: </strong>the Bill proposes to give more teeth to the national load dispatcher. We need to strengthen the load dispatcher for the smooth functioning of the grid, especially with a huge renewable capacity where intermittency of generation is a major issue in the offing.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The rollout of the proposed amendments through a consensus-based approach would go a long way in overhauling the weakest link in the nation’s power supply chain.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Electricity Bill 2022 is a remedy worse than the disease afflicting India’s power sector. Critically analyse.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/electricity/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Effecting the Ban on Single-Use Plastics</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/effecting-the-ban-on-single-use-plastics/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Single use plastics</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Need for plastic waste management</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-629408" height="234" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 355px) 100vw, 355px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-300x198.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-300x198.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1024x675.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-768x506.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1536x1013.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1200x791.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban-1980x1306.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/single-use-plastic-ban.jpg 2000w" width="355"/></p>
<p>Since July 1, 2022, India has banned the manufacture, import, stocking, distribution, sale, and use of single-use plastics (SUP) items with low utility and high littering potential.</p>
<h4>What are single-use plastics?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Single-use plastics, often also referred to as <strong><u>disposable plastics</u></strong>, are commonly used for plastic packaging and include items intended to be <strong><u>used only once</u></strong> before they are thrown away or recycled.</li>
<li>These include, among other items, grocery bags, food packaging, bottles, straws, containers, cups and cutlery.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why are single-use plastics harmful?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The purpose of single-use plastics is to use them once or for a short period of time before disposing of them. Plastic waste has drastic impacts on the environment and human health.</li>
<li>There is a greater likelihood of single-use plastic products <strong><u>ending up in the sea</u></strong> than reusable ones.</li>
</ul>
<h4>SUP ban in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has taken resolute steps to mitigate pollution caused by littered single-use plastics.</li>
<li>A number of items are banned, including earbuds with plastic sticks, balloon sticks, plastic flags, candy sticks, ice cream sticks, polystyrene (thermocol) for decorations, plates, cups, glasses, cutlery such as forks, spoons, knives, straws etc.</li>
<li>India has also banned plastic or PVC banners less than 100 micron, stirrers, etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the impact on the environment?</h4>
<p><strong>[A] Solid Waste generation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The disposal of plastics is one of the least recognized and most highly problematic areas of plastic’s ecological impact.</li>
<li>Ironically, one of plastic’s most desirable traits: its <strong>durability and resistance to decomposition</strong>, is also the source of one of its greatest liabilities when it comes to the disposal of plastics.</li>
<li>A very small amount of total plastic production (less than 10%) is effectively recycled; the remaining plastic is sent to landfills.</li>
<li>It is destined to remain entombed.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>[B] Ecological Impact</strong></p>
<p><strong>(i) Groundwater and soil pollution</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Plastic is a material made to last forever, and due to the same chemical composition, plastic cannot biodegrade; it breaks down into smaller and smaller pieces.</li>
<li>When buried in a landfill, plastic lies untreated for years.</li>
<li>In the process, toxic chemicals from plastics drain out and seep into groundwater, flowing downstream into lakes and rivers.</li>
<li>The seeping of plastic also causes soil pollution and have now started resulting in presence of micro plastics in soil.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(ii) Water Pollution</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The increased presence of plastic on the ocean surface has resulted in more serious problems.</li>
<li>Since most of the plastic debris that reaches the ocean remains floating for years as it does not decompose quickly, it leads to the dropping of oxygen level in the water.</li>
<li>It has severely affected the survival of marine species.</li>
<li>When oceanic creatures and even birds consume plastic inadvertently, they choke on it which causes a steady decline in their population.</li>
<li>In addition to suffocation, ingestion, and other macro-particulate causes of death in larger birds, fish, and mammals.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>[C] Health Hazards</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Burning of plastic results into formation of a class of flame retardants called as Halogens.</li>
<li>Collectively, these harmful chemicals are known to cause the following severe health problems: cancer, neurological damage, endocrine disruption, birth defects and child developmental disorders etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Ban elsewhere</h4>
<ul>
<li>India is not the first country to ban single-use plastics.</li>
<li>Bangladesh became the first country to ban thin plastic bags in 2002; New Zealand banned plastic bags in July 2019.</li>
<li>China had issued a ban on plastic bags in 2020 with a phased implementation.</li>
<li>As of July 2019, 68 countries have plastic bag bans with varying degrees of enforcement.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the plastic waste management rules in India?</h4>
<ul>
<li>With effect from September 30, 2021 India has the Plastic Waste Management Amendment Rules, 2021.</li>
<li>It prohibited the manufacture, import, stocking, distribution, sale, and use of plastic carry bags whose thickness is less than 75 microns.</li>
<li>From December 31, 2022, plastic carry bags whose thickness is less than 120 microns will be banned.</li>
<li>It means that the ban does not cover all plastic bags; however, it requires the manufacturers to produce plastic bags thicker than 75 microns which was earlier 50 microns.</li>
<li>As per the notification, the standard shall be increased to 120 microns in December this year.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the role of the manufacturer?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In addition, the Ministry of Environment, Forests, and Climate Change notified the Plastic Waste Management Amendment Rules, 2022 on February 16, 2022.</li>
<li>Extended Producer Responsibility (EPR) is the responsibility of a producer for the environmentally sound management of the product until the end of its life.</li>
<li>The guidelines provide a framework to strengthen the circular economy of plastic packaging waste, promote the development of new alternatives to plastic packaging and provide the next steps for moving towards sustainable plastic packaging by businesses.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Various steps taken</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian government has taken steps to promote innovation and create an ecosystem for accelerated adoption and availability of alternatives across the country.</li>
<li>To ensure the effective enforcement of the ban, national and State-level control rooms will be established, as well as special enforcement teams for the purpose of checking the illegal sale and use of single-use plastics.</li>
<li>To prevent the movement of banned single-use plastic items between States and Union Territories, border checkpoints have been established.</li>
<li>In an effort to empower citizens to help curb the plastic menace, the Central Pollution Control Board (CPCB) has launched a grievance redressal application.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the challenges?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ban will succeed only if all stakeholders participate enthusiastically and engage in effective engagement and concerted actions.</li>
<li>However, if we look back at our past, almost 25 Indian States previously banned plastic at the state level.</li>
<li>However, these bans had a very limited impact in reality because of the widespread use of these items.</li>
<li>Now the challenge is to see how the local level authorities will enforce the ban in accordance with the guidelines.</li>
<li>Banned items such as earbuds with plastic sticks, plastic sticks for balloons, etc., are non-branded items and it is difficult to find out who the manufacturer is and who is accountable.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>The consumer needs to be informed about the ban through advertisements, newspaper or TV commercials, or on social media.</li>
<li>In order to find sustainable alternatives, companies need to invest in research and development.</li>
<li>The solution to the plastic pollution problem is not the responsibility of the government alone, but of industries, brands, manufacturers and most importantly consumers.</li>
<li>Finding alternatives to plastic seems a little difficult, however, greener alternatives to plastic may be considered a sustainable option.</li>
<li>For example, compostable and bio-degradable plastic, etc., may be considered as an option.</li>
<li>While the total ban on the use of plastic sounds a great idea, its feasibility seems difficult at this hour, especially in the absence of workable alternatives.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/effecting-the-ban-on-single-use-plastics/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Fruit Fly: Novel method to study Nuclear Matrix</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Nuclear Matrix</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-627770" height="489" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 566px) 100vw, 566px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly-300x259.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/fruitfly.jpg 665w" width="566"/></p>
<p>Now, using a novel method, Indian researchers have established a way of studying the nuclear matrix of the fruit fly (Drosophila melanogaster) without removing the nucleus from the embryo.</p>
<h4>Nuclear Matrix of fruit flies</h4>
<ul>
<li>Every cell that makes up an organism contains a copy of its genome.</li>
<li>This genome is packaged in special ways with the help of a structure known as the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>The nuclear matrix gives an organisation and architecture to the nucleus.</li>
<li>A familiar figure, the nuclear matrix of fruit flies, for instance, has been studied for many years, mainly by isolating it in nuclei that have been taken out from fruit fly embryos.</li>
<li>This allows comparative study of nuclear matrix in different cells within the embryo, giving a boost for fruit fly genetics.</li>
<li>Two of the most recent papers on this work have been published in the journals Nucleus and Molecular and Cell Proteomics.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What exactly is Nuclear Matrix?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The nuclear matrix is like a scaffolding.</li>
<li>Using biochemical means, if the nucleus is taken out and treated with an enzyme that digests all the DNA.</li>
<li>It is then washed with a solution of high salt concentration so that viable DNA proteins or protein-protein interactions are removed.</li>
<li>What is then left is a fibrous meshwork of proteins called the nuclear matrix.</li>
<li>This is like a building from which all movables have been sucked out, leaving only the beams, ceiling, and walls, plug points, etc.</li>
<li>Analogous to the building, the nuclear matrix creates the architecture in which the genome is packaged.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why study them?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Studying the nuclear matrix is, therefore, very important to get a better picture of how precisely development progresses every time a new individual is born.</li>
<li>We have 220 different types of cells in the body, but all contain identical genomes.</li>
<li>The same genome sequence is present in neurons, where it works for thinking; in the liver, the same sequence enacts metabolism; and in the intestine, it works to digest.</li>
<li>So, this information is packaged differently in different cell types.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fruit-fly-novel-method-to-study-nuclear-matrix/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Revisiting the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>S. Subramaniam Balaji vs. Tamil Nadu Judgment</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-627767" height="188" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-768x481.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji-400x250.jpg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/balaji.jpg 885w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has referred to a three-judge Bench a series of petitions seeking a judicial direction that political parties who make wild promises should also reveal in their poll manifestos where they will get the money to pay for them.</p>
<p>The reference is a shift from the court’s own stand in the S. Subramaniam Balaji vs Tamil Nadu judgment of 2013.</p>
<h4>Hefty promises: A no lesser corrupt practice</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the <strong><u>Balaji case judgment</u></strong>, a Division Bench of the Supreme Court had held that making promises in election manifestos <strong><u>do not amount to a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> under Section 123 of the Representation of People Act (RP).</li>
<li>However, the Supreme Court is now worried that <strong><u>freebies promised</u></strong> by political parties to win elections could <strong><u>bleed the public exchequer dry</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Court said that parties who form the government riding the wave created by their pre-poll promises of free gifts are bleeding the State finances dry.</li>
<li>Parties actually try to <strong><u>fulfil their outlandish promises using public money</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>The Supreme Court has therefore decided to revisit the Balaji verdict.</p>
<h4>What triggered the Balaji case?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The course of events started in 2006, during the run-up to the Tamil Nadu Assembly elections.</li>
<li>A party released its election manifesto announcing a scheme of free distribution of colour television sets (CTVs) to each and every household if voted to power.</li>
<li>The party swept to power in the polls and decided to implement its scheme and portioned off ₹750 crore from the budget for the project.</li>
<li>The government finally distributed 30,000 TV sets across the State.</li>
<li>In 2011, the rival party also announced its election manifesto with free gifts to “equalise” the gifts offered.</li>
<li>It promised grinders, mixies, electric fans, laptop computers, four gram gold thalis, a cheque of ₹50,000 for women’s marriage, green houses, 20 kg of rice to ration card holders and free cattle and sheep.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The Balaji case</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji, a resident of Tamil Nadu, challenged the schemes introduced by the parties in the Madras High Court.</li>
<li>He said that the <strong><u>expenditure was incurred by the State from the exchequer</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This was “<strong><u>unauthorised, impermissible and ultra vires the constitutional mandates</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>High Court dismissed his case</u></strong>, following which he had moved the apex court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did the case play out?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Balaji argued that <strong><u>the State cannot act</u></strong> in furtherance of “<strong><u>eccentric principles of socialistic philanthropy</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>He argued that the promises of <strong><u>free distribution of non-essential commodities</u></strong> in an election manifesto amounts to electoral bribe under Section 123 of the RP Act.</li>
<li>Money can be taken out of the Consolidated Fund of the State <strong><u>only for “public purposes”</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>distribution of goods to certain sections</u></strong> of people was <strong><u>violative of Article 14 of the Constitution</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Argument provided against the Balaji Case</h4>
<ul>
<li>In response, the State of Tamil Nadu countered that <strong><u>promises do not constitute corrupt practice. </u></strong></li>
<li>Political parties are not the State and ‘<strong><u>freebies’ is a nebulous term which has no legal status</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises implemented by the party after forming the government is an <strong><u>obligation under the Directives Principles of State Policy</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The State is only doing its duty to promote the <strong><u>welfare of its people</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The promises are <strong><u>implemented by framing various schemes/guidelines/eligibility</u></strong> criteria etc. as well as <strong><u>with the approval of the legislature. </u></strong></li>
<li>Thus, it <strong><u>cannot be construed as a waste of public money</u></strong> or be prohibited by any statute or scheme.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Outcome of the Judgement</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court’s judgment held that <strong><u>promises by a political party cannot constitute a ‘corrupt practice’</u></strong> on its part.</li>
<li>It would be <strong><u>“misleading” to generalize</u></strong> that all promises in the election manifesto would amount to corrupt practice.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>manifesto is a statement of the policy</u></strong> for a political party.</li>
<li>The question of implementing the manifesto arises only if the political party forms a government.</li>
<li>It is the promise of a future government and not of an individual candidate.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Scope for revisiting the judgment</h4>
<ul>
<li>The court agreed that <strong><u>freebies create an “uneven playing field”.</u></strong></li>
<li>It had asked the Election Commission of India to <strong><u>consult political parties</u></strong> and issue guidelines on the election manifesto and make it a <strong><u>part of the Model Code of Conduct</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the Court’s move to review the Balaji judgment significant?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In its order, the court foresees that “freebies may create a situation wherein the <strong><u>State governments cannot provide basic amenities due to lack of funds</u></strong> and the State is pushed towards imminent bankruptcy”.</li>
<li>The court said it wants a <strong><u>transparent debate</u></strong> before the three-judge Bench on whether an “enforceable” judicial order can stop political parties from promising and distributing ‘irrational freebies’.</li>
<li>The case is unique as the Supreme Court is exploring <strong><u>whether judicial parameters can be set on a purely political act of promising freebies.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/revisiting-the-s-subramaniam-balaji-vs-tamil-nadu-judgment/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Dynamic leadership of Bose should always be remembered</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bose/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Indian national army particuars</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Modern Indian history developments</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="bose" class="alignnone wp-image-632639" height="397" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 430px) 100vw, 430px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bosenehru-300x277.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bosenehru-300x277.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bosenehru.jpg 654w" width="430"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the year of ‘Azadi Ka Amrit Mahotsav’, the nation pays tribute to Subhas Bose on September 8 as his statue rises tall next to India Gate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Crux of this article in simple words</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The transfer of power to India took place on August 15, 1947. Had Bose and his Indian National Army (INA) succeeded, India would have attained freedom, not inherited it through a transfer of power.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Brief of historical account of his career</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bose was the ninth child in 14 and the sixth son to Janakinath Bose, a lawyer from the Kayasth caste.</li>
<li>He passed matriculation in 1913 from Cuttack and joined the Presidency College in Kolkata (then Calcutta).</li>
<li>The teachings of Swami Vivekananda and Ramakrishna Paramhansa led to a spiritual awakening in Bose at the young age of 15.</li>
<li>Subhash Chandra Bose reached Singapore on July 2, 1943, at the invitation of Rash Behari Bose. He took charge as the President of the Indian Independence League and took over as the leader for East Asia.</li>
<li>On October 23 1943, with the help of the Japanese Army, Netaji declared war on the United States and Britain.</li>
<li>He was fondly called Netaji and was arrested 11 times in his freedom struggle and died under mysterious circumstances in an air crash over Taipei.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="bose" class="alignnone wp-image-632641" height="246" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 467px) 100vw, 467px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-4-300x158.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-4-300x158.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-4.jpeg 310w" width="467"/>His vision for INA march in India </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Creating revolutionary conditions: </strong>Bose had hoped to capture Imphal. That would give the INA a large number of Indian soldiers. Once this was achieved, fighting in India would create revolutionary conditions.</li>
<li><strong>Organization of INA divisions at border: </strong>When the fighting commenced, the INA had only one division stationed on India’s borders. Another was on the move towards Burma. And the third was in the process of formation. All three divisions were expected to be in Burma by the time Imphal fell.</li>
<li><strong>Rapid invasion from north east:</strong> Bose was confident of raising three more divisions from among the Indian troops that would fall to him after the capture of Imphal. With six divisions, the INA would be the single largest force in the region. The rapid advance into India would create the right conditions for the Indian army to switch sides along with the people of the Northeast.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/history-of-popular-slogans-raised-during-freedom-struggle/"><strong>His famous quotes for value addition</strong></a></p>
<p>“It is our duty to pay for our liberty with our own blood.”</p>
<p>“No great change in history has ever been achieved by discussions”</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="bose" class="alignnone wp-image-632642" height="288" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 540px) 100vw, 540px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bose-300x160.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bose-300x160.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bose-768x409.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/bose.jpg 782w" width="540"/>Azad Hind Radio</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>This radio station was created to encourage countrymen to fight for freedom under the leadership of Subhas Chandra Bose.</li>
<li>The radio station used to broadcast news at weekly intervals in various languages like English, Hindi, Tamil, Punjabi, Urdu, etc.</li>
<li>The main aim for the formation of the Azad Hind Radio was to counter the broadcast of allied radio stations and to fill Indian nationals with pride and motivation to fight for freedom.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>The Rani Jhansi Regiment</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Netaji Subhas Chandra Bose was a firm believer of women’s power and women were also greatly inspired by his words.</li>
<li>He had always wanted to form an only women’s regiment and his dream came to fruition with the formation of the Rani Jhansi Regiment on 12th July 1943.</li>
<li>About 170 women cadets joined the force and their training camp was set in Singapore.</li>
<li>They were given ranks according to their educational background.</li>
<li>By November of 1943, this unit had more than 300 cadets as camps were also established in Rangoon and Bangkok.</li>
<li>The women cadets were given military and combat training, weapons training, and route marches. Some of them were also chosen for advanced training and some were also chosen for training as a nurse.</li>
<li>The Rani Jhansi Regiment mainly worked as care and relief givers.</li>
<li>The unit later disbanded after the fall of Rangoon and the withdrawal of the Azad Hind Government.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bose maintained that the Congress leaders wanted freedom in their lifetime. He believed that no revolutionary leader had the right to expect that. A movement, a fight, had to be passed on. Expecting freedom in one’s lifetime was bound to lead to compromises.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Netaji Subhas Bose was an exceptional leader who turned his vision into action. Critically analyse. </strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bose/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>[pib] CoE – SURVEI standardizes Drone images for land Survey</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/survei-standardizes-drone-images-for-land-survey/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CoE-SURVEI</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Centre of Excellence on Satellite and Unmanned Remote Vehicle Initiative (CoE-SURVEI) has developed an Artificial Intelligence-based software which can automatically detect change on the ground, including unauthorised constructions and encroachments in a time series using satellite imagery.</p>
<h4>CoE-SURVEI</h4>
<ul>
<li>The CoE-SURVEI, established by Directorate General Defence Estates at National Institute of Defence Estates Management, leverages the latest technologies in survey viz. satellite imagery, drone imagery and geo-spatial tools for effective land management and urban planning.</li>
<li>This change detection software has been developed by CoE-SURVEI in collaboration with knowledge partner Bhabha Atomic Research Centre (BARC), Visakhapatnam.</li>
<li>Presently, the tool uses National Remote Sensing Centre (NRSC) Cartosat-3 imagery with trained software.</li>
<li>The changes are detected by analysing satellite imagery of different time periods.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where is it used?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The application has been used by CoE in 62 Cantonments and a comparison has been done with the ground position in a recent period.</li>
<li>The software facilitates better control of unauthorised activities, ensures accountability of field staff and helps in reducing corrupt practices.</li>
<li>The CoE-SURVEI has also developed tools for vacant land analysis and 3D image analysis of hill cantonments</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/survei-standardizes-drone-images-for-land-survey/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Rajpath, Central Vista lawns renamed ‘Kartavya Path’</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rajpath-renamed-kartavya-path/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Kartavya Path</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632651" height="243" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 445px) 100vw, 445px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kartavya-300x164.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kartavya-300x164.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kartavya-768x419.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/kartavya.jpg 954w" width="445"/></p>
<p>Rajpath and <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/back-in-news-central-vista-project-2/">Central Vista Lawns</a> in the national capital will now be known as “Kartavya Path”, the New Delhi Municipal Council (NDMC) announces.</p>
<h4>Updating to Kartavya Path</h4>
<ul>
<li>The entire stretch and the area from the Netaji statue under the Grand Canopy to the Rashtrapati Bhavan will be known as Kartavya Path.</li>
<li>Kartavya Path, which will be opened to the public at the end of the official function, will exhibit landscapes, lawns with walkways, added green spaces, refurbished canals, amenity blocks, improved signages and vending kiosks.</li>
<li>New pedestrian underpasses, improved parking spaces, new exhibition panels, and upgraded night lighting are some other features that will enhance the public experience.</li>
<li>It also includes a number of sustainability features like solid waste management, storm-water management, recycling of used water, rainwater harvesting, water conservation and energy-efficient lighting systems, among others.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Kingsway to Rajpath</h4>
<ul>
<li>Called Kingsway during British rule, the three-km stretch was built as a ceremonial boulevard by Edwin Lutyens and Herbert Baker, the architects of New Delhi, more than a hundred years ago.</li>
<li>The capital of the Raj moved to New Delhi from Calcutta in 1911, and construction continued for several years thereafter.</li>
<li>Lutyens conceptualised the modern imperial city centred on a “ceremonial axis”, which was named Kingsway in honour of the then Emperor of India, George V.</li>
<li>He visited Delhi during the Durbar of 1911, where he formally proclaimed the decision to move the capital.</li>
<li>The nomenclature followed that of the Kingsway in London, an arterial road built in 1905, which was named in honour of King Edward VII, the father of George V.</li>
<li>Following Independence, the road was given its Hindi name, Rajpath, on which the Republic Day parades took place over the decades that followed.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why sudden renaming?</h4>
<ul>
<li>During his address from the Red Fort on August 15, Modi had stressed on the abolition of symbols of colonialism.</li>
<li>The new name and look of Rajpath, as well as the installation of the 28-foot statue of Netaji under the Grand Canopy under which a statue of George V once stood, are meant to represent that spirit of the proud new India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of all recent event</h4>
<ul>
<li>The construction of the Central Vista Redevelopment Project began in February 2021, with the new Parliament building and redevelopment of the Central Vista Avenue in the first phase.</li>
<li>The aim is to build an iconic avenue that truly befits the New India, the government has said about the Rs 608 crore Central Vista Avenue project.</li>
<li>It symbolizes a shift from erstwhile Rajpath being an icon of power to Kartavya Path being an example of public ownership and empowerment.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rajpath-renamed-kartavya-path/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>CSR needs positive reforms to support NGO’S</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/csr/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of funding</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>corporate governance</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="CSR" class="alignnone wp-image-632655" height="240" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 459px) 100vw, 459px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-300x157.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-300x157.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-1024x536.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-768x402.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-1536x804.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-2048x1072.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-1200x628.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/img_blog_35-1980x1036.jpg 1980w" width="459"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The evolving role of CSR in funding NGOs</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is NGO?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A non-governmental organization is an organization that generally is formed independent from government. They are typically non-profit entities, and many of them are active in humanitarianism or the social sciences; they can also include clubs and associations that provide services to their members and others.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/a-case-against-punishing-non-compliance-of-csr-guidelines/"><strong>What is CSR?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Corporate social responsibility CSR is a form of international private business self-regulation which aims to contribute to societal goals of a philanthropic, activist, or charitable nature by engaging in or supporting volunteering or ethically oriented practices.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why NGO’s are important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When COVID-19 spurred a nationwide lockdown in India in 2020, a grave need for localised social support emerged. Giving, both private and public, flowed to NGOs working towards combating pandemic-induced challenges such as loss of livelihood for vulnerable communities, food banks, and health and medical support.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>CSR key fact</strong></p>
<p><em>All companies with a net worth of Rs 500 crore or more, a turnover of Rs 1,000 crore or more, or net profit of Rs 5 crore or more, are required to spend 2 per cent of their average profits of the previous three years on CSR activities every year<strong>.</strong></em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="CSR" class="alignnone wp-image-632656" height="429" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-768x768.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-900x900.jpg 900w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-1200x1200.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118-1980x1980.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/csr-corporate-social-responsibility-sustainability-goals-market-ethics-resources-sincerity-long-term-vector-infographics-poster-design-banner_337664-118.jpg 2000w" width="429"/>Issues with CSR funding to NGO</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>No organization development: </strong>CSR funders mostly contribute little or no money to organisational development and limit what they pay for indirect costs to a fixed rate often below 5%. 2020 primary research showed that NGOs’ indirect costs range from 5% to 55%, depending on their mission and operating model, much as a corporate’s sales and administration costs vary significantly by industry and product.</li>
<li><strong>Regulatory framework:</strong> These practices are partly a consequence of CSR funders’ focus on regulatory compliance amendments to the CSR law in 2021 include substantial financial penalties for noncompliance.</li>
<li><strong>Errors on safety:</strong> Many CSRs make errors on safety with the unintended consequence of leaving an NGO with unpaid bills or worse still, drawing on its scarce core funding from other donors to pay for these essential costs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="CSR" class="alignnone wp-image-632657" height="237" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-1.jpeg" width="405"/>How to improve CSR governance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increase transparency: </strong>Transparency is the ultimate trust-builder, and should be considered a guiding principle for any socially responsible company. This concept should apply to goals, ongoing initiatives, and ultimate progress or results.</li>
<li><strong>Focus on equity: </strong>Equity is a vital lens through which to evaluate business practices and CSR strategy, at both a micro and macro level. Not only is ensuring that program furthers social and racial justice a cornerstone of the very essence of corporate responsibility, but study after study establishes that improved diversity and inclusion leads to better outcomes for everyone from increased innovation and competitiveness, to stronger ethics and team culture.</li>
<li><strong>Deepen community connections: </strong>Deepening your organization’s connection to those on the other side of your CSR projects will have far-reaching benefits. These could likely include developing a more impactful program, as you strengthen your understanding of the needs of the community served.</li>
<li><strong>Encourage creativity</strong>: Creativity as a principle may feel out of place in a discussion of how to improve CSR. Yet it’s a concept increasingly invoked in philanthropic thought leadership, and for good reason.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The idea is to move beyond signing cheques to recognising that, ultimately, what’s good for Indian society is also good for business.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. why the role of CSR is becoming important in NGO funding? What are the issues with CSR? Discuss the way forward.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/csr/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Concrete supply chain is needed for nutritional security</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/supply-chain/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Food security</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="supply chain" class="alignnone wp-image-632662" height="303" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 491px) 100vw, 491px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hd2g1flc_wheat-export-ban-pti_625x300_16_May_22-300x185.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hd2g1flc_wheat-export-ban-pti_625x300_16_May_22-300x185.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hd2g1flc_wheat-export-ban-pti_625x300_16_May_22-1024x630.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hd2g1flc_wheat-export-ban-pti_625x300_16_May_22-768x473.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hd2g1flc_wheat-export-ban-pti_625x300_16_May_22-1200x739.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hd2g1flc_wheat-export-ban-pti_625x300_16_May_22.jpg 1230w" width="491"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Disruption of supply chains due to Ukraine war has implications for India’s food security</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is supply chain in simple words?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A supply chain is the network of all the individuals, organizations, resources, activities and technology involved in the creation and sale of a product.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Is supply chain management related to agriculture?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Agribusiness, supply chain management (SCM) implies managing the relationships between the businesses responsible for the efficient production and supply of products from the farm level to the consumers to meet consumers’ requirements reliably in terms of quantity, quality and price.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="supply chain" class="alignnone wp-image-632663" height="267" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 450px) 100vw, 450px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupplyChain_FQU0520-1024x607-1-300x178.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupplyChain_FQU0520-1024x607-1-300x178.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupplyChain_FQU0520-1024x607-1-768x455.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupplyChain_FQU0520-1024x607-1.jpg 1024w" width="450"/>What are two types of food chain?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Agriculture food supply chains for fresh agricultural products: </strong>(such as fresh vegetables, flowers, fruit). In general, these chains may comprise growers, auctions, wholesalers, importers and exporters, retailers and speciality shops and their input and service suppliers. Basically, all of these stages leave the intrinsic characteristics of the product grown or produced untouched. The main processes are the handling, conditioned storing, packing, transportation and especially trading of these goods.</li>
<li><strong>Agriculture food supply chains for processed food products: </strong>(such as portioned meats, snacks, juices, desserts, canned food products). In these chains, agricultural products are used as raw materials for producing consumer products with higher added value. In most cases, conservation and conditioning processes extend the shelf-life of the products<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/food-procurement-and-distribution/"><strong><img alt="supply chain" class="alignnone wp-image-632665" height="249" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 442px) 100vw, 442px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513-768x433.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513-1200x676.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WHEAT_GRAINS_2-621x414_1647706483513.jpg 1598w" width="442"/>Supply chain issues </strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Shelf-life constraints for raw materials, intermediates and finished products and changes in product quality level while progressing the supply chain (decay).</li>
<li>High volume, low variety (although the variety is increasing) production systems.</li>
<li>Importance of production planning and scheduling focusing on high capacity utilization.</li>
<li>Highly sophisticated capital-intensive machinery leading to the need to maintain capacity utilization.</li>
<li>Variable process yield in quantity and quality due to biological variations, seasonality, random factors connected with weather, pests and other biological hazards.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What should we do to ensure nutritional security?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Strengthening and shortening food supply chains</strong>: reinforcing regional food systems, food processing, agricultural resilience and sustainability in a climate-changing world will require prioritising research and investments along these lines.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure</strong>: Lastly, infrastructure and institutions supporting producers, agripreneurs and agricultural micro, small and medium enterprises (MSMEs) in their production value chain are central to the transition.</li>
<li><strong>Potential for crop diversification</strong>: Data compiled in the agro-climatic zones reports of the Indian Council of Agricultural Research and the erstwhile Planning Commission of India reveal enormous potential for crop diversification and precision for enhanced crop productivity based on soil type, climate (temperature and rainfall), and captive water resources.</li>
<li><strong>Holistic policy approach: </strong>In the context of the intensifying economic, environmental and climate challenges and crisis, the need of the hour is a good theory of transition encompassing the spatial, social and scientific dimensions, supported by policy incentives and mechanisms for achieving a sustainable, resilient and food secure agriculture<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Agro-climatic approach: </strong>An agro-climatic approach to agricultural development is important for sustainability and better nutrition.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Transparency:</strong> The Indian government could ensure more transparency on food stocks and regulate the private sector.</li>
<li><strong>Set restriction on hoarding:</strong> For that, there is a need to set restrictions on the reserves that the private sector can hold, as they often tend to hoard food stocks to later sell at a profit.</li>
<li><strong>Speculation should be regulated</strong>: This will help prevent the opaqueness of private sector reserves, which often fuels speculation by large international financial actors.</li>
<li><strong>Positional limits:</strong> Internationally, positional limits could be set on speculators but that would require a multilateral accord, a topic which should be on the agenda at the next G-20 meeting.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What role supply chain play in nutritional security? Discuss the constraints in supply chain along with way forward.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/supply-chain/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Mandatory requirements for Packaged Commodities</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mandatory-packaged-commodities/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Rule for Packaged Commodities</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632653" height="420" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 372px) 100vw, 372px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/package-266x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/package-266x300.jpg 266w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/package.jpg 563w" width="372"/></p>
<p>The Department of Consumer Affairs, Legal Metrology Division has notified a draft amendment to the Legal Metrology (Packaged Commodities) Rules 2011 making some compulsions.</p>
<h4>Discrepancies over Packaged Commodities</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Division has observed that many manufacturers/packagers/importers <strong><u>do not clearly label necessary declarations or prime constituents</u></strong> on the front of packaged commodities.</li>
<li>It is common for consumers to assume that brands’ claims are accurate, but such <strong><u>claims are usually misleading.</u></strong></li>
<li>Such disclosure are deemed essential in order <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/five-new-rights-you-get-as-a-consumer/">to protect consumer rights</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the mandatory provisions under the Legal Metrology (Packaged Commodities) Rules, 2011?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is mandatory under the Rules, to ensure a number of declarations, such as the:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Name and address of the manufacturer/packer/importer,</li>
<li>Country of origin,</li>
<li>Common or generic name of the commodity,</li>
<li>Net quantity,</li>
<li>Month and year of manufacture</li>
<li>Maximum Retail Price (MRP) and</li>
<li>Consumer care information.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>As a consumer-oriented policy, all pre-packaged commodities should also be inspected.</li>
<li>Rule 9(1)(a) provides that the declaration on the package must be legible and prominent.</li>
<li>The consumers’ ‘right to be informed’ is violated when important declarations are not prominently displayed on the package.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the proposed amendments?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As many <strong><u>blended food and cosmetic products</u></strong> are sold on the market, the <strong><u>key constituents need to be mentioned</u></strong> on the product packaging.</li>
<li>Additionally, the front side of the package must contain the <strong><u>percentage of the composition of the unique selling proposition (USP). </u></strong></li>
<li>Also, packages displaying key constituents must display a <strong><u>percentage of the content</u></strong> used to make the product.</li>
<li>The new amendments has suggested that <strong><u>at least two prime components should be declared on the package’s front side</u></strong> along with the brand name.</li>
<li>Currently, manufacturers list the ingredients and nutritional information only on the <strong><u>back of the packaging</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This declaration <strong><u>must also include the percentage/quantity of the USPs of the product</u></strong> in the same font size as the declaration of the USPs. However, mechanical or electrical commodities are excluded from this sub-rule.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Consumer Rights</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-632652" height="317" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 436px) 100vw, 436px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/consumer-300x218.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/consumer-300x218.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/consumer.jpg 554w" width="436"/></p>
<p>Consumer right is an insight into what rights consumer holds when it comes to the seller who provides the goods.</p>
<p>In general, the consumer rights in India are listed below:</p>
<p><strong>(1) Right to Safety</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Means right to be protected against the marketing of goods and services, which are hazardous to life and property.</li>
<li>The purchased goods and services should not only meet their immediate needs, but also fulfil long term interests.</li>
<li>Before purchasing, consumers should insist on the quality of the products as well as on the guarantee of the products and services. They should preferably purchase quality marked products such as ISI, AGMARK, etc.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Right to be Informed</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Means right to be informed about the quality, quantity, potency, purity, standard and price of goods so as to protect the consumer against unfair trade practices.</li>
<li>Consumer should insist on getting all the information about the product or service before making a choice or a decision.</li>
<li>This will enable him to act wisely and responsibly and also enable him to desist from falling prey to high pressure selling techniques.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Right to Choose</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Means right to be assured, wherever possible of access to variety of goods and services at competitive price. In case of monopolies, it means right to be assured of satisfactory quality and service at a fair price.</li>
<li>It also includes right to basic goods and services. This is because unrestricted right of the minority to choose can mean a denial for the majority of its fair share.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Right to be Heard</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Means that consumer’s interests will receive due consideration at appropriate forums. It also includes right to be represented in various forums formed to consider the consumer’s welfare.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Right to Seek redressal</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Means right to seek redressal against unfair trade practices or unscrupulous exploitation of consumers. It also includes right to fair settlement of the genuine grievances of the consumer.</li>
<li>Consumers must make complaint for their genuine grievances. Many a times their complaint may be of small value but its impact on the society as a whole may be very large.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Right to Consumer Education</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Means the right to acquire the knowledge and skill to be an informed consumer throughout life.</li>
<li>Ignorance of consumers, particularly of rural consumers, is mainly responsible for their exploitation.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mandatory-packaged-commodities/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Positive Secularism is allowed: Student to SC in hijab case</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/positive-secularism-hijab-case/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Secularism in India</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Hijab Row</p></div></div><p>India believes in ‘positive secularism’ based on tolerance of all religious faiths and not ‘negative secularism’ followed in countries like France which holds that display of religion in public is offensive, said a student from Karnataka who has challenged the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-freedom-of-religion-and-attire/">ban on wearing hijab</a> to school.</p>
<h4>What is Positive Secularism?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Secularism is most commonly defined as the separation of religion from civic affairs and the state.</li>
<li>It may be broadened to a similar position seeking to remove or to minimize the role of religion in any public sphere.</li>
<li>Positive secularism is where the state plays an enabler role in the exercise of fundamental rights and the religious freedoms of all communities.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What did the petitioner argue?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The petitioner replied that the Constitution itself says that all religions have to be treated with equal respect.</li>
<li>It said that the Supreme Court has also held in the <strong><u>Aruna Roy Judgment</u></strong> that there should be no discrimination on the ground of any religion.</li>
<li>It went on to say that the State should show <strong>‘<u>reasonable accommodation</u>’</strong> of Muslim students’ right to wear hijab to school as a part of her <strong><u>right to expression, religion and dignity</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Circumstances where hijab can be prohibited in school</h4>
<p>The State can only restrict her right in three circumstances, the petition highlighted.</p>
<ol>
<li>One, to protect <strong><u>public order, morality and health</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Two, to <strong><u>protect another fundamental right</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Three, if such a <strong><u>restriction is authorised by a law</u></strong> made to regulate or restrict any economic, financial, political or secular activity which may be associated with religious practice or to provide for social welfare and reform.</li>
</ol>
<h4>What was the judgment announced by Karnataka HC?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The HC held that wearing hijab is <strong><u>not an essential religious practice</u></strong> in Islam and is not, therefore, protected under by the right to freedom of religion guaranteed by Article 25 of the Constitution.</li>
<li>The court said it was a <strong><u>reasonable restriction that was constitutionally permissible</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Bench also upheld the <strong><u>legality of the order prescribing guidelines for uniforms</u></strong> in schools and pre-university colleges under the provisions of the Karnataka Education Act, 1983.</li>
<li>The court said that <strong><u>school uniform will cease to be a uniform if hijab is also allowed</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="YzKC1QOxQZ"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-freedom-of-religion-and-attire/">[Burning Issue] Freedom of religion and attire</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="YzKC1QOxQZ" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-freedom-of-religion-and-attire/embed/#?secret=SFcf1ZbYEF#?secret=YzKC1QOxQZ" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Burning Issue] Freedom of religion and attire” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/positive-secularism-hijab-case/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India-Bangla Trade, now set for CEPA boost</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-bangla-trade-now-set-for-cepa-boost/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CEPA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Bilateral trade agreements</p></div></div><p><img alt="cepa" class="alignnone wp-image-632677" height="283" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 502px) 100vw, 502px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cepa-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cepa-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cepa.jpg 687w" width="502"/></p>
<p>India and Bangladesh will soon commence negotiations on a Bilateral Comprehensive Economic Partnership Agreement (CEPA).</p>
<h4>Glimpse of bilateral trade between India and Bangladesh</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2021-22, Bangladesh has emerged as the <strong><u>largest trade partner for India</u></strong> in South Asia and the <strong><u>fourth largest destination for Indian exports worldwide.</u></strong></li>
<li>India is <strong><u>Bangladesh’s second biggest trade partner</u></strong>, and its largest export market in Asia.</li>
<li>Despite Covid-19 related disruptions, bilateral trade grew at an unprecedented rate of almost 44 per cent from $10.78 billion in 2020-21 to $18.13 billion in 2021-22.</li>
<li>India’s main exports to Bangladesh are raw cotton, non-retail pure cotton yarn, and electricity, and its main imports from the country are pure vegetable oils, non-knit men’s suits, and textile scraps.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is CEPA?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The partnership agreement or cooperation agreement is more comprehensive than an Free Trade Agreement (FTA).</li>
<li>CECA/CEPA also looks into the regulatory aspect of trade and encompasses an agreement covering the regulatory issues.</li>
<li>CECA has the widest coverage. CEPA covers negotiation on the trade in services and investment and other areas of economic partnership.</li>
<li>It may even consider negotiation in areas such as trade facilitation and customs cooperation, competition, and IPR.</li>
<li>India has signed CEPAs with South Korea and Japan.</li>
</ul>
<h4>CEPA objectives</h4>
<ul>
<li>While informal talks on CEPA have been happening since 2018, officials said that the <strong><u>pandemic has brought urgency. </u></strong></li>
<li><strong><u>Chinese investments were an initial trigger</u></strong> for India, but New Delhi and Dhaka want to step up the pace following the economic shock faced by the two economies.</li>
<li>The CEPA is likely to focus on trade in goods, services, and investment, with a key objective being the <strong><u>reduction of the trade gap between the two countries</u></strong>.</li>
<li>As Bangladesh prepares to graduate into a <strong><u>developing nation by 2026</u></strong> — after which <strong><u>it may no longer qualify for trade benefits</u></strong> that it currently enjoys as a least-developed country — it is keen to clinch the CEPA in a year.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the existing frameworks?</h4>
<p>The current institutional frameworks for trade and investment include:</p>
<ul>
<li>During the visit of Prime Minister Modi to Bangladesh in June 2015, the <strong><u>bilateral trade agreement</u></strong> between the two countries was renewed for a period of five years with a provision for auto renewal.</li>
<li>Under the provisions of the <strong><u>South Asian Free Trade Area (SAFTA)</u></strong>, Bangladesh extends preferential tariffs to Indian exports of products outside the ‘sensitive list’ of 993 items.</li>
<li>In 2011, India announced <strong><u>duty-free, quota-free access to Bangladesh</u></strong> for all tariff lines except tobacco and alcohol.</li>
<li>An <strong><u>Agreement on Promotion and Protection of Investments</u></strong> has been in force since 2011.</li>
<li><strong><u>Joint Interpretative Notes</u></strong> to the agreement were signed during the visit of the Indian Finance Minister to Bangladesh in October 2017.</li>
<li>To facilitate trade and transit through inland waterways, a <strong><u>Protocol on Inland Waterways Trade and Transit (PIWTT)</u></strong> has been in place since 1972. It was renewed in 2015.</li>
<li><strong><u>Direct sea movement of containerized/ bulk/ dry cargo</u></strong> began after the signing of a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) on Coastal Shipping in June 2015.</li>
<li>MoUs were signed in 2015 on the <strong><u>use of the </u></strong><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bangladesh-offers-chittagong-port-for-use-to-india/"><strong>Chittagong</strong></a><strong><u> and Mongla Ports</u></strong> for Movement of Goods to and from India.</li>
<li>The MoU on <strong><u>Border Haats </u></strong>on the India-Bangladesh border was renewed in April 2017 during the visit of Prime Minister Hasina to India. Currently, four Border Haats — two each in Meghalaya (Kalaichar and Balat) and Tripura (Srinagar and Kamalasagar) — are functional.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Types of Trade Agreements</h4>
<p><strong>(1) Free Trade Agreement </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>A FTA is a pact between two or more nations to reduce barriers to imports and exports among them.</li>
<li>Under a free trade policy, goods and services can be bought and sold across international borders with little or no government tariffs, quotas, subsidies, or prohibitions to inhibit their exchange.</li>
<li>The concept of free trade is the opposite of trade protectionism or economic isolationism.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Preferential Trade Agreement</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In this type of agreement, two or more partners give preferential right of entry to certain products.</li>
<li>This is done by reducing duties on an agreed number of tariff lines.</li>
<li>Here a positive list is maintained i.e. the list of the products on which the two partners have agreed to provide preferential access.</li>
<li>Tariff may even be reduced to zero for some products even in a PTA.</li>
<li>India signed a PTA with Afghanistan.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Comprehensive Economic Partnership Agreement</strong></p>
<p>Discussed above.</p>
<p><strong>(4) Comprehensive Economic Cooperation Agreement</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>CECA generally cover negotiation on trade tariff and Tariff rate quotas (TRQs) rates only.</li>
<li>It is not as comprehensive as CEPA.</li>
<li>India has signed CECA with Malaysia.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Framework Agreement</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Framework agreement primarily defines the scope and provisions of orientation of the potential agreement between the trading partners.</li>
<li>It provides for some new area of discussions and set the period for future liberalisation.</li>
<li>India has previously signed framework agreements with the ASEAN, Japan etc.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Early Harvest Scheme</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>An Early Harvest Scheme (EHS) is a precursor to an FTA/CECA/CEPA between two trading partners. For example, early harvest scheme of RCEP has been rolled out.</li>
<li>At this stage, the negotiating countries identify certain products for tariff liberalization pending the conclusion of actual FTA negotiations.</li>
<li>An Early Harvest Scheme is thus a step towards enhanced engagement and confidence building.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-bangla-trade-now-set-for-cepa-boost/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Teachers with a passion for the profession are foundational to the positive educational change</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/teacher-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>TET</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>quality education</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="teacher" class="alignnone wp-image-633160" height="204" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 482px) 100vw, 482px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1789299_orig-300x127.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1789299_orig-300x127.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1789299_orig.jpg 425w" width="482"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Success of new education policy depends on how we recruit and assesss teachers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the issue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Recruitment of well-qualified teachers into the schooling system is the first prerequisite to ensure that students receive quality education.</li>
<li>However, teacher recruitment processes in the country are not adequately streamlined. There are diverse recruitment processes across regions, school stages, and school types central, state, and private schools.</li>
<li>This, in turn, leads to multiple criteria and processes for hiring teachers, thereby bringing a wide disparity in teacher quality across institutions and regions.</li>
<li>Many of the processes are also sub-optimal in measuring the competency of a candidate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Teacher hiring mechanism in place </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>One of the most common and widely-taken tests to ensure eligibility for recruitment is the Teacher Eligibility Test (TET), conducted at both the state (STET) and central levels (CTET).</li>
<li>TET is the equivalent of the licensure tests that are undertaken by teacher candidates in various countries.</li>
<li>However, in India, the test is required only for government school teacher recruitment at the elementary stage (Class 1-8).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="teacher" class="alignnone wp-image-633161" height="273" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 366px) 100vw, 366px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Competent-teachers-300x224.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Competent-teachers-300x224.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Competent-teachers-768x573.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Competent-teachers.jpg 800w" width="366"/>Issues</strong> <strong>in hiring mechanism </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>TET has been critiqued time and again for various reasons. These include low pass percentages, poor test quality, lengthy test papers and a serious lack of alignment with teacher preparation programmes.</li>
<li>The test was in the news recently because of the teachers’ recruitment scam in West Bengal.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="teacher" class="alignnone wp-image-633162" height="344" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 387px) 100vw, 387px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S0883035521001129-gr5-300x267.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S0883035521001129-gr5-300x267.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S0883035521001129-gr5.jpg 621w" width="387"/>What we need?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>A coherent strategy:</strong> to tie together the various tests and processes such as TET, teacher recruitment tests, classroom demonstrations and teacher interviews. This will enable a holistic assessment of teacher competence.</li>
<li><strong>Understanding what is competence</strong>: Framing a common understanding of what qualifies as teacher competence. Simply speaking, teacher competence can be understood as the core knowledge, skills, and dispositions expected of a teacher to effectively contribute to the teaching-learning process.</li>
<li><strong>Multiple methods of assessment</strong>: To evaluate several other skills and dispositions, one requires multiple methods of assessment including classroom demonstrations and teacher interviews. These assessments could help gauge skills like effective dissemination of a concept and selection of appropriate resources and learning materials.</li>
<li><strong>Teacher’s aptitude</strong>: Most importantly, such processes should help evaluate a teacher’s empathy towards students. Respecting learner diversity and skills in building a participative/democratic classroom culture are crucial requisites of a teacher. The recruitment process should assess the teacher’s aptitude in this respect.</li>
<li><strong>A comprehensive competency framework</strong>: That details the skills a teacher should have. This could be derived from a teacher education curriculum rooted in policy perspectives of the day. For instance, in the case of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-national-education-policy-2020-higher-education-and-regional-languages/">NEP</a>, the curriculum could be geared towards imparting training in classroom practices that make learning joyful.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Long-term benefits to adopting such a holistic model of teacher recruitment</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Better parity</strong>: It will ensure better parity in the quality of teachers recruited across the country.</li>
<li><strong>Equitable education</strong>: Will contribute to equitable education for students from diverse sections of society.</li>
<li><strong>Credibility is ensured</strong>: The recruitment process will also become credible if it is rooted in a framework that outlines the core competencies of becoming a teacher.</li>
<li><strong>Reduction in coaching centres:</strong> At the systemic level, this may also lead to a reduction in coaching centres as the assessment processes will be non-standardised and cannot be easily gleaned from coaching materials and guidebooks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Teachers with a passion for the profession are foundational to the positive educational change envisaged by the NEP. Setting up clear benchmarks of quality and well-designed recruitment processes hold the key to ensuring better teaching-learning outcomes.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you think on teacher’s quality today? Explain how dynamic teacher recruitment process will enhance teacher’s quality.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/teacher-2/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Global pandemic treaty to avert future mishap</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pandemic-treaty/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>future preparedness for pandemics</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="pandemic treaty" class="alignnone wp-image-633175" height="338" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 643px) 100vw, 643px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/157943-msvocffheg-1619027775-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/157943-msvocffheg-1619027775-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/157943-msvocffheg-1619027775-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/157943-msvocffheg-1619027775-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/157943-msvocffheg-1619027775.jpg 1200w" width="643"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The outline of an essential global pandemic treaty.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Purpose of the treaty</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A pandemic treaty under the umbrella of the World Health Organization would build coherence and avoid fragmentation of response.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Severity of this pandemic demands such treaty</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>COVID-19 would count as being among some of the most severe pandemics the world has seen in the last 100 years. An estimated <strong>18 million</strong> people may have died from COVID-19, according various credible estimates, a scale of loss not seen since the Second World War.</li>
<li>Further, with over <strong>120 million</strong> people pushed into extreme poverty, and a massive global recession, no single government or institution has been able to address this emergency singlehandedly.</li>
<li>This has given us a larger perspective of how nobody is safe until everybody is safe.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em><strong>Catchy line for value addition</strong></em></p>
<p><em>Nobody is safe until everybody is safe</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="pandemic treaty" class="alignnone wp-image-633179" height="237" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 426px) 100vw, 426px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/charles_michel-1024x569-1-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/charles_michel-1024x569-1-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/charles_michel-1024x569-1-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/charles_michel-1024x569-1.jpg 1024w" width="426"/>There is widespread inequity in healthcare </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Gross inequity in distribution: </strong>Health-care systems have been stretched beyond their capacity and gross health inequity has been observed in the distribution of vaccines, diagnostics, and therapeutics across the world.</li>
<li><strong>Irreversible consequences</strong>: While high-income economies are still recovering from the aftereffects, the socioeconomic consequences of the novel coronavirus pandemic are irreversible in low and low middle-income countries.</li>
<li><strong>The monopolies</strong>: Held by pharma majors such as Pfizer, BioNTech, and Moderna created at least nine new billionaires since the beginning of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/yojana-archive-the-pandemic-global-synergy/">COVID-19 pandemic</a> and made over $1,000 a second in profits, even as fewer of their vaccines reached people in low-income countries.</li>
<li><strong>Skewed distribution</strong>: As of March 2022, only 3% of people in low-income countries had been vaccinated with at least one dose, compared to 60.18% in high-income countries. The international target to vaccinate 70% of the world’s population against COVID-19 by mid-2022 was missed because poorer countries were at the “back of the queue” when vaccines were rolled out.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="https://www.civilsdaily.com/yojana-archive-the-pandemic-global-synergy/" class="alignnone wp-image-633182" height="398" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 598px) 100vw, 598px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/3000-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/3000-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/3000-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/3000-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/3000-1536x1024.jpeg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/3000-2048x1365.jpeg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/3000-1200x800.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/3000-1980x1320.jpeg 1980w" width="598"/>India’s lead role</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dynamic response</strong>: India’s response to the COVID-19 pandemic and reinstating global equity by leveraging its own potential has set an example to legislators worldwide.</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vaccine-diplomacy-that-needs-specific-clarifications/">Vaccine diplomacy</a>:</strong> India produces nearly 60% of the world’s vaccines and is said to account for 60%-80% of the United Nations’ annual vaccine procurement “vaccine diplomacy” or “vaccine maitri” with a commitment against health inequity.</li>
<li><strong>We lead by example</strong>: India was unfettered in its resolve to continue the shipment of vaccines and other diagnostics even when it was experiencing a vaccine shortage for domestic use. There was only a brief period of weeks during the peak of the second wave in India when the vaccine mission was halted.</li>
<li><strong>A classic example of global cooperation:</strong> As of 2021, India shipped 594.35 lakh doses of ‘Made-in-India’ COVID-19 vaccines to 72 countries a classic example of global cooperation. Among these, 81.25 lakh doses were gifts, 339.67 lakh doses were commercially distributed and 173.43 lakh doses were delivered via the Covax programme under the aegis of Gavi, the Vaccine Alliance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why the treaty is needed for?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Data sharing</strong>: A treaty should cover crucial aspects such as data sharing and genome sequencing of emerging viruses.</li>
<li><strong>Rapid response mechanism</strong>: It should formally commit governments and parliaments to implement an early warning system and a properly funded rapid response mechanism.</li>
<li><strong>Health investments</strong>: Further, it should mobilise nation states to agree on a set of common metrics that are related to health investments and a return on those investments. These investments should aim to reduce the public-private sector gap.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A global pandemic treaty will not only reduce socioeconomic inequalities across nation states but also enhance a global pandemic preparedness for future health emergencies. India must take the lead in this.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Nobody is safe until everybody is safe. What do you understand by this? Why there is need of global pandemic treaty?.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pandemic-treaty/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>To make the language of learning a choice that is made democratically</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/language/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>anglicist orientalist controversy</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>qulaity education outcomes</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="language" class="alignnone wp-image-633186" height="283" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 531px) 100vw, 531px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/79_334374782-300x160.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/79_334374782-300x160.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/79_334374782.jpg 750w" width="531"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>English should be taught effectively not as the medium, but as a second language</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-national-education-policy-2020-higher-education-and-regional-languages/"><strong>What is the debate?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Over the years, there has been a raging debate over the need for children to have their mother tongue as the medium of instruction in schools.</li>
<li>While educationists have emphasised the importance of learning in the mother tongue to enhance a child’s learning and overcome glaring inequities, there has been an equally steady demand for English-medium schools in several States.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="language" class="alignnone wp-image-633189" height="502" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 355px) 100vw, 355px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/image-3-212x300.png" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/image-3-212x300.png 212w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/image-3.png 361w" width="355"/>Historic context to this debate </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Orientalist: </strong>Orientalists were the group of people who wanted to give education to Indian people in the Indian language. The emphasis was on the knowledge of the East. They wanted Indians to learn about Indian philosophy, science, and literature. In the Initial stage, company officials favoured oriental learning<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Anglicist: </strong>Anglicists were those people who supported the teaching of modern western education to Indian people in the English language. People who favoured Anglicists were Thomas Babington, Macaulay, James’s mill, Charles wood, Charles Trevelyan, and Elphinstone. The Anglicists were supported by the most advanced Indians like Raja Ram Mohan Roy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="language" class="alignnone wp-image-633190" height="233" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 419px) 100vw, 419px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SCH_7123-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SCH_7123-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SCH_7123-768x428.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SCH_7123.jpg 821w" width="419"/>Why mother tongue is important? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Suitability to child: </strong>There is an almost-complete consensus among educationists, linguistic experts and psychologists that the mother tongue, or the language of the region where the child lives, is the only appropriate language of learning for the child.</li>
<li><strong>Incomprehension</strong>: A child can be taught any number of languages, particularly later in life, but the medium of learning should be the mother tongue. As a number of classrooms today are stalked by the curse of incomprehension.</li>
<li><strong>Pressure of English language</strong>: There are a growing number of schools, mostly private, that teach in English. Government schools too in States like Tamil Nadu, unable to bear the pressure from parents and to stop students from migrating to private schools, are switching to English medium.</li>
<li><strong>Development in every way: </strong>The mother tongue, home language or the first language educationally means the language which the child is using to connect to the world, to people, to nature, to the environment, and to make sense of everything that’s going on. This is the language which helps the child to build, grow and develop in every way.</li>
<li><strong>Inability to learn:</strong> English medium education is a profound tragedy in Indian education today. Millions are languishing because of their inability to learn in English not English as a language but as a medium through which they acquire any knowledge of any subject.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why English Should Be the Medium of Instruction in Schools, Colleges?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Connectivity with The Rest of the World</strong>: To communicate and be on par with the world, the first language that stands common is English. With English, a student can remain on par with what is happening across the globe. Lack of English knowledge or alone mother tongue does not allow children to progress with the rest of the world.</li>
<li><strong>Technologies Can Be Used Only With English Instruction</strong>: Most of the modern technologies are invented, reinvented and modernized in foreign shores. The inventors keep the English language for the instruction manual of the technological gadget so that the gadget can be used worldwide.</li>
<li><strong>Higher Education Emphasizes on The English language</strong>: The main focus of teaching medium in higher secondary as well as in graduation and post-graduation colleges in India. There is no doubt that lecturers also teach in Hindi or other regional languages. However, question design comes in both English and regional language. But most of the classes are taught in English.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How multilingual approach helps</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Firstly, multilingualism gives equal status to all languages and there’s enough work, history and research on this.</li>
<li>Second, children come from different backgrounds, and in some cases, they are first-generation learners with not much support at home.</li>
<li>The multilingual approach thus, is much more flexible, closer to the child, and inclusive. It is democratic, and it accepts that the teacher is not coming from a place of authority and is only correcting spellings and pronunciations<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>This myth must be broken that our education system is class and caste neutral. A powerful political movement will have to take place to make the language of learning a choice that is made democratically.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Should the mother tongue or English be the medium of instruction? Critically explain.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/language/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India ranks 132 in HDI as score drops</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-ranks-132-hdi-as-score-drops/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>HDI</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-633464" class="wp-caption alignnone" id="attachment_633464" style="width: 375px"><img alt="hdi" class="wp-image-633464" height="286" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 375px) 100vw, 375px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hdi-300x229.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hdi-300x229.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hdi.jpg 662w" width="375"/><figcaption class="wp-caption-text" id="caption-attachment-633464">hdi</figcaption></figure>
<p>India ranks 132 out of 191 countries in the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-three-decades-of-human-development-index-hdi/">Human Development Index (HDI)</a> 2021, after registering a decline in its score over two consecutive years for the first time in three decades.</p>
<h4>What is Human Development Index (HDI)?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The HDI combines indicators of life expectancy, education or access to knowledge and income or standard of living, and captures the level and changes to the quality of life.</li>
<li>The index initially launched as an alternative measure to the gross domestic product, is the making of two acclaimed economists from Pakistan and India, namely Mahbub ul Haq and Amartya Sen.</li>
<li>It stresses the centrality of human deve­lop­ment in the growth process and was first rolled out by the United Nations Development Programme in 1990.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Dimensions of the Human Development Index – HDI</h4>
<ul>
<li>The idea that progress should be conceived as a process of enlarging people’s choices and enhancing their capabilities is the central premise of the HDI.</li>
<li>Since its launch, the HDI has been an important marker of attempts to broaden measures of progress.</li>
<li>The HDI considers three main dimensions to evaluate the development of a country:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Long and healthy life</li>
<li>Education</li>
<li>Standard of living</li>
</ol>
<h4>Limitations of HDI</h4>
<p>HDR has been always disputable and has caught the public-eye, whenever it was published. It has many reasons.</p>
<p>One of them is that the concept of human development is much deeper and richer than what can be caught in any index or set of indicators. Another argument is that its concept has not changed since 1990 when it was also defined in the first.</p>
<p><strong>(1) An incomplete indicator</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Human development is incomplete without human freedom and that while the need for qualities judgement is clear; there is no simple quantitative measure available yet to capture the many aspects of human freedom.</li>
<li>HDI also does not specifically reflect quality of life factors, such as empowerment movements or overall feelings of security or happiness.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Limited idea of development</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The HDI is not reflecting the human development idea accurately.</li>
<li>It is an index restricted to the socio-economic sphere of life<strong>; </strong>the political and civil spheres are in the most part kept separate.</li>
<li>Hence there is a sub-estimation of inequality among countries, which means that this dimension is not being taken into consideration appropriately.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) A vague concept</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Concerning data quality and the exact construction of the index HDI is conceptually weak and empirically unsound.</li>
<li>This strong critic comes from the idea that both components of HDI are problematic. The GNP in developing countries suffers from incomplete coverage, measurement errors and biases.</li>
<li>The definition and measurement of literacy are different among countries and also, this data has not been available since 1970 in a significant number of countries.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Data quality issues</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The HDI, as a combination of only four relatively simple indicators, doesn’t only raise a questions what other indicators should be included, but also how to ensure quality and comparable input data.</li>
<li>It is logical that the UNDP try to collect their data from international organizations concentrating in collecting data in specific fields.</li>
<li>Quality and trustworthiness of those data is disputable, especially when we get the information from UN non-democratic members, as for example Cuba or China.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) A tool for mere comparison</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The concept of HDI was set up mainly for relative comparison of countries in one particular time.</li>
<li>HDI is much better when distinguishing between countries with low and middle human development, instead of countries at the top of the ranking.</li>
<li>Therefore, the original notion was not to set up an absolute ranking, but let’s quite free hands in comparison of the results.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Development has to be greener</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The human development approach has not adequately incorporated environmental conditions which may threaten long-term achievements on human development. The most pervasive failure was on environmental sustainability.</li>
<li>However, for the first time in 2020, the UNDP introduced a new metric to reflect the impact caused by each country’s per-capita carbon emissions and its material footprint.</li>
<li>This is Planetary Pressures-adjusted HDI or PHDI. It measured the amount of fossil fuels, metals and other resources used to make the goods and services it consumes.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(7) Wealth can never equate welfare</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Higher national wealth does not indicate welfare. GNI may not necessarily increase economic welfare; it depends on how it is spent.</li>
<li>For example, if a country spends more on military spending – this is reflected in higher GNI, but welfare could actually be lower.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of HDI</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is one of the few multidimensional indices as it includes indicators such as literacy rate, enrollment ratio, life expectancy rate, infant mortality rate, etc.</li>
<li>It acts as a true yardstick to measure development in real sense.</li>
<li>Unlike per capital income, which only indicates that a rise in per capital income implies economic development; HDI considers many other vital social indicators and helps in measuring a nation’s well-being.</li>
<li>It helps as a differentiating factor to distinguish and classify different nations on the basis of their HDI ranks.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>Both sustainable development and poverty eradication are both long-term and urgent endeavours, requiring not only the gradual and substantial redirection of country policies but a rapid response to pressing problems.</li>
<li>Ideally, sustainable development could provide an overarching framework within which all sub-goals (eg poverty eradication, social equality, ecosystem maintenance, climate compatibility) are framed.</li>
<li>It is not a subset of development; it is development (in a modern world of resource limits).</li>
<li>Environmental issues are not one factor among many but the meta-context within which poverty and other goals are sought.</li>
<li>Investing more in public research could lead to technological solutions to poverty and sustainability problems becoming more rapidly and openly available.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-ranks-132-hdi-as-score-drops/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Naga team continues talks on Constitution</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/naga-team-continues-talks-on-constitution/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Naga Peace Process</p></div></div><p><img alt="naga" class="wp-image-633463" height="561" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 357px) 100vw, 357px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/naga-191x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/naga-191x300.jpg 191w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/naga.jpg 398w" width="357"/></p>
<p>The Government of India is ready to incorporate the Yehzabo, the Naga Constitution, into the Indian Constitution and has agreed for a civil and cultural flag for the Nagas.</p>
<h4>Who are the Naga?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The term Naga was created by the British for administrative convenience to refer to a group of tribes with similar origins but distinct cultures, dialects, and customs.</li>
<li>The Naga tribes are accumulated in Nagaland, Arunachal Pradesh, Manipur, and Myanmar.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-naga-peace-talks/">Naga separatists</a> group has timely reiterated that the ‘Naga National flag’ and ‘Yehzabo’ (Constitution) are non-negotiable issues.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Has the GoI agreed to this?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Centre is clear that <strong><u>there cannot be two Constitutions</u></strong> and two flags in the country.</li>
<li>The Yehzabo will be incorporated into the Indian Constitution by presenting a Bill in Parliament.</li>
<li>As far as flag is concerned, it will only be used for civil and cultural functions, but not in any government function.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did the Naga insurgency begin?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Residing in the Naga Hills of Assam during the advent of the British and the annexation of Assam in 1820, the Nagas did not consider themselves a part of British India.</li>
<li>The British adopted a way of governance over the Nagas that involved keeping in place their traditional ways of life, customs, and laws while putting British administrators at the top.</li>
<li>At the time of the withdrawal of the British, insecurity grew among the Naga tribes about the future of their cultural autonomy after India’s independence.</li>
<li>This was accompanied by the fear of the entry of “plains people” or “outsiders” into their territory.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Do you know?</strong></p>
<p>In a memorandum to the <strong><em>Simon Commission in 1929</em></strong>, representatives of Naga tribes demanded that Nagas be left free after Independence and not be included in the Indian Union.</p></blockquote>
<h4>Collective actions of the Nagas</h4>
<ul>
<li>Above mentioned factors gave rise to the <strong>formation of the Naga Hills District Tribal Council</strong> in 1945, which was renamed the Naga National Council (NNC) in 1946.</li>
<li>Amid uncertainties over the post-independence future of the Nagas, a section of the NNC, led by Naga leader A.Z. Phizo <strong>declared the independence</strong> of the Nagas on August 14, 1947.</li>
<li>The <strong>underground insurgency</strong> began in the early 1950s when Mr. Phizo founded the Naga Federal Government (NFG) and its armed wing, the Naga Federal Army (NFA).</li>
</ul>
<h4>Outcome of the then insurgency</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Central Government sent the <strong>armed forces into Naga areas</strong> to curb the insurgency.</li>
<li>It imposed the contentious <strong>Armed Forces Special Powers Act (AFSPA)</strong> which is still in place in parts of Nagaland.</li>
<li>The Nagas, led by Mr. Phizo, demanding an independent state outside of India, <strong>boycotted the 1952 and 1957 general elections</strong> and armed clashes grew.</li>
<li>Unlike other groups in the north east which were accepting some form of autonomy under the Constitution, Nagas rejected this in <strong>favour of sovereignty</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Negotiations with the govt</h4>
<ul>
<li>Some leaders among the NNC formed their own group to hold discussions with the government, leading to the formation of the State of Nagaland in 1963.</li>
<li>This, however, did not satisfy many in the NNC and NFG, who, following years of negotiations with the government, eventually signed the Shillong Accord of 1975, agreeing to surrender arms and accept the Constitution.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When did the NSCN come into the picture?</h4>
<ul>
<li>This signing of the Shillong Accord was <strong>not agreeable with many top leaders</strong> of the NNC and those operating from Myanmar.</li>
<li>A/c to them, the agreement <strong>did not address the issue of Naga sovereignty and</strong> coerced them to accept the Constitution.</li>
<li>Three NNC <strong>rebel leaders, formed the National Socialist Council Of Nagaland (NSCN)</strong> to continue the armed movement for ‘independence’.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Again split in NSCN</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 1988, after years of infighting and violent clashes along tribal lines and over the main cause of the movement, the NSCN split into two factions.</li>
<li>One, led by Mr. Muiwah and Swu called the NSCN-IM and the other, led by Mr. Khaplang called the NSCN-K.</li>
<li>The NSCN-IM demanded and continues to <strong>demand for ‘Greater Nagaland’ or Nagalim.</strong></li>
<li>It wants to <strong>extend Nagaland’s borders</strong> by including Naga-dominated areas in the neighbouring States of Assam, Manipur and Arunachal Pradesh.</li>
<li>The NSCN-IM has now grown to become the <strong><u>most powerful insurgent group</u></strong>, also playing a role in the creation of smaller groups in other States.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where do the peace talks stand now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 1997, the Government of India got the NSCN-IM to sign a ceasefire agreement to begin the holding of talks with the aim of signing a Naga Peace Accord.</li>
<li>After this ceasefire, there have been over a hundred rounds of talks spanning over 24 years between the Centre and the insurgent group, while a <strong>solution is still awaited</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues of contention</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Independence celebration:</strong> Nagas across Nagaland, Manipur, Assam and Arunachal Pradesh celebrate August 14 as Independence Day. According to Naga historians, Gandhi agreed that the Nagas would celebrate their independence a day ahead of India, on August 14, 1947.</li>
<li><strong>Naga flag:</strong> In the Naga narrative, passed down generations by word of mouth, the Naga flag was not designed by a mortal but is of divine origin.</li>
<li><strong>Secessionist tendencies: </strong>A large section of the Nagas still holds dear the idea of the Naga identity and their tribal roots.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way ahead</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Naga struggle claimed thousands of lives over decades and devastated countless homes, all over the idea of a sovereign Naga nation.</li>
<li>If the NSCN (I-M) accedes to economic and political packages alone, without a separate flag and constitution, it remains to be seen whether it will be seen as a solution, or as a defeat.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/naga-team-continues-talks-on-constitution/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Floods in Pakistan and the pulls and pressures of India-Pak Disaster Diplomacy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/floods-india-pakistan-disaster-diplomacy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Disaster Diplomacy</p></div></div><figure aria-describedby="caption-attachment-633462" class="wp-caption alignnone" id="attachment_633462" style="width: 447px"><img alt="pakistan" class="wp-image-633462" height="252" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 447px) 100vw, 447px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pak-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pak-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pak-768x434.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/pak.jpg 917w" width="447"/><figcaption class="wp-caption-text" id="caption-attachment-633462">Pakistan</figcaption></figure>
<p>Prime Minister Modi has tweeted his condolences and hoped for an early restoration of normalcy in flood devastated Pakistan.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The statement by the PM last month came as a <strong><u>surprise to many</u></strong>.</li>
<li>This is on the grounds of <strong><u>steady deterioration of ties</u></strong> over the last eight years since Modi came to power.</li>
</ul>
<h4>PM Modi and Pakistan</h4>
<p><strong>(A) Early failure</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>PM Modi had famously begun his tenure with an invitation to Pakistan’s then PM Nawaz Sharif for the swearing-in ceremony in May 2014.</li>
<li>Sharif had come to India, along with the leaders of other SAARC nations.</li>
<li>This gesture promised a <strong><u>new beginning for the bilateral relationship</u></strong> that had suffered a severe setback after the <strong><u>26/11 terrorist attacks</u></strong> in Mumbai in 2008.</li>
<li>However, a string of incidents followed, the terrorist attacks in <strong><u>Pathankot and Uri</u></strong> — impacted the relationship negatively, and New Delhi made it clear that “<strong><u>talks and terror can’t go together</u></strong>”.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(B) India strengthens resolute</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Ties have been hit further over the last few years, especially after the <strong><u>Pulwama terror attack</u></strong> in February 2019, and the <strong><u>abrogation of Article 370</u></strong> in August that year.</li>
<li>That led to the <strong><u>downsizing of the High Commissions</u></strong> in both capitals; there are n<strong><u>o full-time High Commissioners</u></strong> in either country now.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Change of PM in Pak</h4>
<ul>
<li>After the ouster of Imran Khan, and the coming to power of the <strong><u>new coalition government</u></strong> led by PM Shehbaz Sharif, some positive noises have emanated from Islamabad.</li>
<li>India however reiterated the desired peace and stability in a region free of terrorism.</li>
<li>New Pak PM criticized his predecessor, Imran Khan, for not making “serious and diplomatic efforts” when India abrogated Article 370 in August 2019.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Responses to disasters</h4>
<p>In the past, when natural disasters struck India and Pakistan, the two countries at times reached out to each other with offers of help.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Bhuj earthquake:</strong> For example, in January-February 2001, after the earthquake hit Bhuj in Gujarat, Pakistan had reached out with help, and had sent tents and blankets for the survivors.</li>
<li><strong>2005 earthquake:</strong> A powerful earthquake struck both India and Pakistan, India sent aircraft with relief supplies to Pakistan and pledged $ 25 million through the United Nations to support Pakistan’s relief efforts.</li>
</ul>
<p>In 2010, when a “superflood” — the worst in recent decades until the deluge of 2022 — hit Pakistan, India offered $ 5 million in help, but Islamabad declined to accept it.</p>
<h4>The case for help now</h4>
<ul>
<li>Though there has not been much follow-up activity, the PM Modi’s outreach by way of a message created a potential opening for “<strong><u>disaster diplomacy</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>Pakistan’s Finance Minister said that the government can consider importing vegetables and other edible items from India following the destruction of standing crops due to the floods.</li>
<li>Prices of vegetables and fruit have gone through the roof as supplies from Balochistan, Sindh, and south Punjab especially, have been badly affected.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why should India respond?</h4>
<ul>
<li>For the Indian government, the case for extending humanitarian help ties in well with its desire to project itself as the “<strong><u>first responder</u></strong>” in times of disaster and crisis in the neighbourhood.</li>
<li>In recent months and years, India has extended its hand of help and cooperation to the Maldives, Bangladesh, Sri Lanka, Myanmar, Nepal, Bhutan, and Afghanistan.</li>
<li>Trucks filled with Indian grain have travelled to Taliban-ruled Afghanistan via Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is Pakistan’s position?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Pakistan’s establishment (none other but Pak Army) has <strong><u>discussed the possibility</u></strong> of getting food grains through international organisations, who want to send relief material from India.</li>
<li>The help from India can be at the <strong><u>micro and short-term level</u></strong>: food, fuel, tents, medicines, and emergency essential supplies.</li>
<li>At the <strong><u>macro and medium-to-long-term</u></strong>, it could involve help in the reconstruction of damaged homes and properties, and the archaeological site of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/floods-mohenjo-daro-world-heritage-tag/">Mohenjo Daro</a>, part of the cultural heritage of both countries.</li>
<li>India’s <strong><u>healthcare</u></strong> can be of help in the post-floods scenario — dengue is already on the rise, and diseases such as typhoid are expected to spike sharply.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues in re-engagement</h4>
<ul>
<li>Some in the Indian establishment believe that the government’s <strong><u>stated policy</u></strong> of talks and terror can’t go together, and the <strong><u>extending of help to Pakistan are at odds with each other</u></strong>.</li>
<li>For New Delhi, the decision is as much about <strong><u>projecting power as a global responder</u></strong> as with managing the ruling party’s domestic political base.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/floods-india-pakistan-disaster-diplomacy/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India- China disengage at LAC friction points in Ladakh</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-china-disengagementt-lac-in-ladakh/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>LAC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India-China border issues</p></div></div><p><img alt="lac" class="alignnone wp-image-633461" height="308" sizes="(max-width: 499px) 100vw, 499px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lac-300x185.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lac-300x185.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/lac.jpg 667w" width="499"/></p>
<p>India and China have announced that their Armies have begun to disengage from Patrolling Point-15 in the Gogra-Hot springs area at LAC.</p>
<h4>What is LAC- the Line of Actual Control?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The LAC is the demarcation that separates Indian-controlled territory from Chinese-controlled territory.</li>
<li>India considers the LAC to be <strong><u>3,488 km long</u></strong>, while the Chinese consider it to be only around 2,000 km.</li>
<li>It is divided into three sectors: the eastern sector which spans Arunachal Pradesh and Sikkim, the middle sector in Uttarakhand and Himachal Pradesh, and the western sector in Ladakh.</li>
<li>The LAC is <strong><u>only a concept</u></strong> – it is <strong><u>not agreed upon by the two countries</u></strong>, <strong><u>neither delineated on a map nor demarcated on the ground.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the disagreement?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The alignment of the LAC in the eastern sector is along the 1914 McMahon Line, and there are minor disputes about the positions on the ground as per the principle of the high Himalayan watershed.</li>
<li>The major disagreements are in the western sector where the LAC emerged from two letters written by Chinese Prime Minister Zhou Enlai to PM Jawaharlal Nehru in 1959, after he had first mentioned such a ‘line’ in 1956.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When did India accept the LAC?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The LAC was discussed during Chinese Premier Li Peng’s <strong><u>1991</u></strong> visit to India, where <strong><u>PM P V Narasimha Rao</u></strong> and Li reached an understanding to maintain peace and tranquillity at the LAC.</li>
<li>India formally accepted the concept of the LAC when Rao paid a return visit to Beijing in 1993 and the two sides signed the <strong><u>Agreement to Maintain Peace and Tranquillity at the LAC.</u></strong></li>
<li>The reference to the LAC was unqualified to make it clear that it was not referring to the LAC of 1959 or 1962 but to the <strong><u>‘LAC’ at the time when the agreement was signed</u></strong>.</li>
<li>To reconcile the differences about some areas, the two countries agreed that the Joint Working Group on the border issue would take up the task of clarifying the alignment of the LAC.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How was the disengagement carried on?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As per the understanding reached earlier on disengagement, a <strong><u>buffer zone is to be created</u></strong> at the friction points.</li>
<li>Once troops are withdrawn by both sides, <strong><u>new patrolling norms</u></strong> are to be worked out after complete disengagement and de-escalation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why sudden disengagement?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The move comes <strong><u>ahead of the </u></strong><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/shanghai-cooperation-organisation-sco/"><strong>Shanghai Cooperation Organisation (SCO)</strong></a><strong><u> summit</u></strong> in Uzbekistan next week.</li>
<li>However, neither side has, so far, confirmed if the two leaders would hold bilateral talks on the sidelines of the summit.</li>
<li>The leaders have not spoken to each other since a November 2019 meeting during the BRICS Summit in Brasilia and the beginning of the stand-off in April 2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of the disengagement</h4>
<ul>
<li>Since the <strong><u>stand-off began in May 2020</u></strong>, the two sides have so far held 16 rounds of talks.</li>
<li>Earlier, disengagement was undertaken from both sides of Pangong Tso in February 2021, and from PP-17 in the Gogra-Hot springs area in August, in addition to Galwan in 2020 after the violent clash.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>friction points that remain now are Demchok and Depsang</u></strong>, which China has constantly refused to accept, maintaining that they are not a part of the current stand-off.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What was the dispute over LAC?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In what was the worst clash between the two countries in over 40 years, the Galwan incident reverberated around the world.</li>
<li>The casualties in the clash were the first in the disputed Sino-Indian border since 1975.</li>
<li>The Galwan episode led to a rapid build-up of forces on both sides of the Line of Actual Control.</li>
<li>This incident is being seen as major punctuation in the bilateral relations between India and China and what does the future hold for both neighbors.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did India change its stance on the Line of Actual Control?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian and Chinese patrols were coming in more frequent contact during the mid-1980s.</li>
<li>This was after the government formed a China Study Group in 1976 which revised the patrolling limits, rules of engagement and pattern of Indian presence along the border.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Is the LAC also the claim line for both countries?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Not for India. <strong><u>India’s claim line</u></strong> is the line seen in the official boundary marked on the maps as released by the Survey of India, <strong><u>including both Aksai Chin and Gilgit-Baltistan</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In China’s case, it corresponds mostly to its claim line, but in the eastern sector, it claims entire Arunachal Pradesh as South Tibet.</li>
<li>However, the claim lines come into question when a discussion on the final international boundaries takes place, and not when the conversation is about a working border, say the LAC.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why are these claim lines controversial in Ladakh?</h4>
<ul>
<li>When the Shimla Agreement on the McMahon Line was signed by British India, Aksai Chin in Ladakh province of the princely state of <strong><u>J&amp;K was not part of British India</u></strong>, although it was a part of the British Empire.</li>
<li>Thus, the eastern boundary was well defined in 1914 but in the west in Ladakh, it was not.</li>
<li>India, in July 1948, had two maps: one had <strong><u>no boundary shown in the western sector</u></strong>, only a partial colour wash; the second one extended the colour wash in yellow to the entire state of J&amp;K, but mentioned “boundary undefined”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>The impasse in India-China relations <strong><u>CANNOT be overcome by more talks</u></strong> through diplomatic and military channels, and possibly require the intervention of the top leadership of both countries.</li>
<li>Therefore, as Dr. Jaishankar put it, the management of the fissures within Asia will require <strong><u>adherence to established laws, norms, and rules.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-china-disengagementt-lac-in-ladakh/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>