<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 01:42:52 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>What it will take to fulfill India’s Solar Power Dream?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-it-will-take-to-fulfill-indias-solar-power-dream/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Solar energy targets of India</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>From less than 10 MW in 2010, India has added significant PV capacity over the past decade, achieving over 50 GW by 2022.</p>
<h4>Solar energy in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>Solar photovoltaics (PV) has driven India’s push towards the adoption of cleaner energy generation technologies.</li>
<li><strong><u>India is targeting about 500 GW by 2030</u></strong>, of renewable energy deployment, out of which ~280 GW is expected from solar PV.</li>
<li>This necessitates the deployment of nearly 30 GW of solar capacity every year until 2030.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Key components</h4>
<ul>
<li>A typical solar PV value chain consists of first fabricating polysilicon ingots which need to be transformed into thin Silicon wafers that are needed to manufacture the PV mini-modules.</li>
<li>The mini-modules are then assembled into market-ready and field-deployable modules.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Various challenges</h4>
<p>There are challenges that need to be overcome for the sustainability of the PV economy.</p>
<p><strong>(1) PV Modules</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Indian solar deployment or installation companies <strong><u>depend heavily on imports</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It currently <strong><u>imports 100% of silicon wafers and around 80% of cells</u></strong> even at the current deployment levels.</li>
<li>India currently <strong><u>does not have enough module</u></strong> and cell manufacturing capacity.</li>
<li>India’s current solar module <strong><u>manufacturing capacity is limited to ~15 GW per year</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>demand-supply gap widens</u></strong> as we move up the value chain — for example, India only produces ~3.5 GW of cells currently.</li>
<li>India has <strong><u>no manufacturing capacity</u></strong> for solar wafers and polysilicon ingots.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Field deployment</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Also, out of the 15 GW of module manufacturing capacity, <strong><u>only 3-4 GW of modules</u></strong> are <strong><u>technologically competitive and worthy of deployment</u></strong> in grid-based projects.</li>
<li>India remains dependent on the import of solar modules for field deployment.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Size and technology</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Most of the Indian industry is currently tuned to handling M2 wafer size, which is roughly 156 x 156 mm2, while the global industry is already moving towards M10 and M12 sizes, which are 182 x 182 mm2 and 210 x 210 mm2 respectively.</li>
<li>The bigger size has an advantage in terms of silicon cost per wafer, as this effectively means lower loss of silicon during ingot to wafer processing.</li>
<li>In terms of cell technology, most of the manufacturing still uses Al-BSF technology, which can typically give efficiencies of ~18-19% at the cell level and ~16-17% at the module level.</li>
<li>By contrast, cell manufacturing worldwide has moved to PERC (22-23%), HJT(~24%), TOPCON (23-24%) and other newer technologies, yielding module efficiency of &gt;21%.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Land issue</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Producing more solar power for the same module size means more solar power from the same land area.</li>
<li>Land, the most expensive part of solar projects, is scarce in India — and Indian industry has no choice but to move towards newer and superior technologies as part of expansion plans.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Raw materials supply</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is a <strong><u>huge gap on the raw material supply</u></strong> chain side as well.</li>
<li>Silicon wafer, the most expensive raw material, is not manufactured in India.</li>
<li>India will have to work on technology tie-ups to make the right grade of silicon for solar cell manufacturing — and since &gt;90% of the world’s solar wafer manufacturing currently happens in China.</li>
<li>It is not clear how and where India will get the technology.</li>
<li>Other key raw materials such as <strong><u>metallic pastes of silver and aluminium</u></strong> to form the electrical contacts too, <strong><u>are almost 100% imported</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Thus, <strong><u>India is more of an assembly hub than a manufacturing</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Lack of investment</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India has hardly invested in this sector which can help the industry to try and test the technologies in a cost-effective manner.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Current govt policy</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>government has identified this gap</u></strong>, and is rolling out various policy initiatives to push and motivate the industry to <strong><u>work towards self-reliance</u></strong> in solar manufacturing, both for cells and modules.</li>
<li>Key initiatives include:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>40% duty on the import of modules and</li>
<li>25% duty on the import of cells, and</li>
<li>Production Linked Incentive (PLI) scheme to support manufacturing capex</li>
<li>Compulsion to procure modules only from an approved list of manufacturers (ALMM) for projects that are connected to state/ central government grids</li>
<li>Only India-based manufacturers have been approved</li>
</ol>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s path to become a manufacturing hub for the same <strong><u>requires more than just putting some tax barriers and commercial incentives</u></strong> in the form of PLI schemes, etc.</li>
<li>It will warrant <strong><u>strong industry-academia collaboration</u></strong> in an innovative manner to start developing home-grown technologies which could, in the short-term.</li>
<li>It needs to <strong><u>work with the industry</u></strong> to provide them with trained human resource, process learnings, root-cause analysis through right testing and, in the long term, develop India’s own technologies.</li>
<li>High-end technology development requires <strong><u>substantial investment</u></strong> in several clusters which operate in industry-like working and management conditions, appropriate emoluments, and clear deliverables.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-it-will-take-to-fulfill-indias-solar-power-dream/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>China’s problem with top US senator visiting Taiwan</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/chinas-problem-with-top-us-senator-visiting-taiwan/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>US meddling in China-Tawian friction</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-612017" height="262" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 420px) 100vw, 420px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/twn.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/twn.jpg 420w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/twn-300x187.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/twn-400x250.jpg 400w" width="420"/></p>
<p>The Speaker of the House of Representatives, Nancy Pelosi, landed in Taiwan, ignoring Chinese threats and a warning by President Xi Jinping to “not play with fire”.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Pelosi’s visit to Taiwan is the highest-level visit by an American official to the island in a quarter century.</li>
<li>The senior US politician has been critical of China on multiple fronts over the decades.</li>
</ul>
<h4>US defiance of One China Policy</h4>
<ul>
<li>The US has maintained a ‘One China’ policy since the 1970s, under which it <strong><u>recognises Taiwan as a part of China. </u></strong></li>
<li>But it has <strong><u>unofficial ties with Taiwan</u></strong> as well — a strategy that is known as strategic or deliberate ambiguity.</li>
<li><strong><u>Beijing considers Taiwan a part of China</u></strong>, threatens it frequently, and has not ruled out taking the island by military force at any time.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why does China have a problem with Pelosi visiting Taiwan?</h4>
<ul>
<li>For China, the presence of a <strong><u>senior American figure in Taiwan</u></strong> would indicate some kind of <strong><u>US support for Taiwan’s independence. </u></strong></li>
<li>This move severely <strong><u>undermined China’s perception of sovereignty</u></strong> and territorial integrity.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Brief history of China-Taiwan Tensions</h4>
<ul>
<li>Taiwan is an island about 160 km off the coast of southeastern China, opposite the Chinese cities of Fuzhou, Quanzhou, and Xiamen.</li>
<li>It was administered by the imperial Qing dynasty, but its control passed to the Japanese in 1895.</li>
<li>After the defeat of Japan in <strong><u>World War II, the island passed back into Chinese hands</u></strong>.</li>
<li>After the communists led by Mao Zedong won the civil war in mainland China, Chiang Kai-shek, the leader of the nationalist Kuomintang party, fled to Taiwan in 1949.</li>
<li>Chiang Kai-shek set up the government of the Republic of China on the island, and remained President until 1975.</li>
<li>Beijing has <strong><u>never recognised the existence of Taiwan</u></strong> as an independent political entity, arguing that <strong><u>it was always a Chinese province</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Taiwanese stance</h4>
<ul>
<li>Taiwan says that the modern Chinese state was only formed after the revolution of 1911.</li>
<li>It was <strong><u>not a part of that state or of the People’s Republic of China</u></strong> that was <strong><u>established after the communist revolution.</u></strong></li>
<li>While the political tensions have continued, <strong><u>China and Taiwan have had economic ties</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Many migrants from Taiwan work in China, and China has investments in Taiwan.</li>
<li>No doubt, <strong><u>cultural ties</u></strong> are indispensable.</li>
<li>In recent years, Taiwan’s government has said only the <strong><u>island’s 23 million people have the right to decide their future</u></strong> and that it will defend itself when attacked.</li>
<li>Since 2016, <strong><u>Taiwan has elected a party that leans towards independence</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How does the world, and US, view Taiwan?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>UN does NOT recognise Taiwan</u></strong> as a separate country; in fact, only 13 countries around the world — mainly in South America, the Caribbean, Oceania, and the Vatican — do.</li>
<li>In June, President Biden said that the <strong><u>US would defend Taiwan if it was invaded</u></strong>, but it was clarified soon afterward <strong><u>but</u></strong> <strong><u>America does not support Taiwan’s independence</u></strong>.</li>
<li>While the <strong><u>US has no formal ties with Taipei</u></strong>, it remains Taiwan’s most important <strong><u>international backer and arms supplier.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/chinas-problem-with-top-us-senator-visiting-taiwan/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Macrovariable projections in uncertain times</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/macrovariable-projections-in-uncertain-times/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Stagflation</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Challenges in projection of economic macrovariables</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>The Fed has raised its benchmark interest rate again by a whopping 0.75%. The Reserve Bank of India has also been forced to raise interest rates further but also take other steps.</p>
<h4>Two challenges for policymakers</h4>
<ul>
<li>Decisions in the Monetary Policy Committee (MPC) meeting are based on what the members of the MPC see as the likely course of the economy in the months ahead.</li>
<li>But, the trajectory of the world economy, and its likely impact on the Indian economy, is imponderable.</li>
<li>So, Indian policymakers would face two crucial problems.</li>
<li><strong>1] Uncertainty due to war and Covid-19:</strong> First, the main <strong>uncertainty is due to Russia’s war</strong> on Ukraine and the resultant economic sanctions on Russia, as well as the zero-COVID-19 policy in China that repeatedly implements lockdowns leading to global supply bottlenecks.</li>
<li><strong>2] Uncertainty in data:</strong> Policy has to base itself on data.</li>
<li>If it is deficient, it introduces additional uncertainty, making projections for the future difficult and causing policies to fail.</li>
<li>This will compound the problem that results from the global uncertainty.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Role of uncertainties related to Covid and Ukraine war</h4>
<ul>
<li>Since early 2020, the SARS-COV-2 virus has caused global uncertainty.</li>
<li> In a globalised interdependent world, production was hit resulting in price rise (inflation) and loss of real incomes.</li>
<li>This has resulted in decline in demand and, in a vicious cycle, a further slowing down of the economy.</li>
<li>As prices have risen globally and economies slowed down, many <strong>countries have faced stagflation.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Decline in uncertainty:</strong> The uncertainty due to the novel coronavirus has declined in spite of waves of attack persisting because the impact of new virus mutants of the virus is milder and there is also immunity due to vaccination.</li>
<li>However, China is an exception with its zero-COVID policy.</li>
<li> It has been implementing strict lockdowns in the last six months, even when only a few cases of the disease have been detected.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The uncertainties due to Ukraine conflict</h4>
<ul>
<li>The war in Ukraine and western sanctions on Russia have caused huge uncertainty since February 2022 (when Russia invaded Ukraine) and displaced the disease-related uncertainty, i.e., COVID-19.</li>
<li>The reason is that the war is a proxy war between two powerful capitalist blocs.</li>
<li>There is needless continuing suffering of the people of Ukraine, with a bombardment of cities, and this could escalate.</li>
<li>The war and the sanctions have already affected the world economy and the Europeans in particular.</li>
<li>The <strong>U.S. economy has entered technical recession</strong> with two quarters of GDP decline.</li>
<li>As supplies of critical items supplied by Russia and Ukraine have been hit, prices have soared.</li>
<li>Europe, the United States and India have experienced or are experiencing high inflation.</li>
<li>The <strong>biggest disruption is in energy supplies from Russia,</strong> impacting production.</li>
<li>The availability of<strong> food, fertilizers, metals,</strong> etc., have been hit as Ukraine and Russia are important sources.</li>
<li>To weaken Russia, sanctions may be imposed on countries that carry out trade with it.</li>
<li>Many Indian entities may face the heat since India has increased its imports from Russia, which undermines sanctions.</li>
<li>China may also face sanctions since it has increased trade with Russia and is backing it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Data related uncertainties</h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian policymakers also face data-related issues.</li>
<li>It is not only available with a big lag on most macroeconomic variables but for many variables, data are either not available or has huge errors.</li>
<li><strong>Errors in data:</strong> Policymakers rely on high frequency data to proxy for actual data.</li>
<li>For example, very little data are available for quarterly GDP data which is used to <strong>calculate the growth rate of the economy.</strong></li>
<li>First, except for agriculture,<strong> unorganised sector data is not available. </strong></li>
<li>Second, for the organised sector, <strong>very limited data are available. </strong></li>
<li>Third, projections from the previous year or proxies are used — both these <strong>introduce errors when there are repeated shocks</strong> to the economy, such as the pandemic and now the war.</li>
<li><strong>Issues with price data: Price data</strong> too are problematic.</li>
<li>The services sector is under-represented.</li>
<li><strong>Prices of many services have risen</strong> and expenditures on them have increased dramatically, thus changing their weight in the consumption basket.</li>
<li><strong>Common CPI:</strong> Further, the<strong> consumer price index is common</strong> for the upper classes and the poor.</li>
<li> Earlier, there was a different index for various categories of people, which reflected the differential impact of inflation on people.</li>
<li>This gave a truer picture of the economy and peoples’ distress.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>Indian policymakers face the unenviable task of predicting the course of the economy for the next few months and even the year (or years) ahead because of the shocks and faulty and inadequate data. The problem is compounded by international factors.</p>
<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/macrovariable-projections-in-uncertain-times/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Online Dispute Resolution in new-age digital commerce</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/addressing-the-challenges-in-new-age-digital-commerce/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>ONDC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Online Dispute Resolution</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>Despite the rapid advancement of digital platforms on the one hand and the pervasiveness of the Internet-enabled phone on the other, small enterprises such as local <i>kirana </i>stores have not gained from this. Online purchases from “near and now” inventory from the local store remain in a digital vacuum.</p>
<h4>Online revolution in country</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increased smartphone use</strong>: The rise in smartphone use fuelled by affordable data plans has catalysed an online revolution in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Pandemic accelerated digital inclusion:</strong> The novel coronavirus pandemic has further accelerated the process of digital inclusion.</li>
<li>It is now not only routine to transact online it is also common to learn online, have medical consultations online, and even resolve disputes online.</li>
<li><strong>Increased scope for innovation in digital space:</strong> These realisations have given India the opportunity to disrupt the status quo with its innovative abilities.</li>
<li>Systems such as the Unique Identification Authority of India (UIDAI) and Aadhaar, the Unified Payments Interface (UPI) and the Ayushman Bharat Digital Mission have reengineered markets.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why mall and medium sided businesses have not benefited from digital revolution?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Despite the rapid advancement of digital platforms small enterprises such as local kirana stores have not gained from this.</li>
<li><strong>Cost of infrastructure:</strong> This is because, to sell on numerous platforms, sellers must <strong>maintain a separate infrastructure,</strong> which only adds costs and limits participation.</li>
<li><strong>Distinct terms and conditions of platforms:</strong> The distinct terms and conditions of each platform further limit the sellers’ flexibility.</li>
<li>Consequently, small and medium-sized businesses have lost their freedom to choose and participate in the country’s e-commerce system at their will and on their terms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward: Open Network for Digital Commerce</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Department for Promotion of Industry and Internal Trade (DPIIT) of the Government of India established the Open Network for Digital Commerce (ONDC)<strong> to level the playing field</strong> by developing open e-commerce and enabling access to small businesses and dealers.</li>
<li>The ONDC began its pilot in five cities in April 2022, i.e., New Delhi, Bengaluru, Coimbatore, Bhopal and Shillong.</li>
<li>Currently, the pilot has expanded to 18 cities, and there are immediate plans to add more cities.</li>
<li>The ONDC network makes it possible for products and services from all participating e-commerce platforms to be displayed in search results across all network apps.</li>
<li>For instance, a consumer shopping for a product on an e-commerce app named “X” would also receive results from e-commerce app named “Y”, if both X and Y integrated their platforms with the ONDC.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Dispute resolution through ODR</h4>
<ul>
<li>Disputes will be the obvious by-product of this e-commerce revolution.</li>
<li>Therefore, it is imperative to support this initiative with a modern-day, cost-effective, timely and high-speed dispute resolution system.</li>
<li><strong>Online Dispute Resolution, or ODR</strong> as it is popularly called, has the propensity to work alongside the incumbent setup and deliver quick, affordable and enforceable outcomes.</li>
<li>The ODR is not restricted to the use of legal mechanisms such as mediation, conciliation and arbitration in an online environment but can be tailormade for the specific use case keeping the participants in mind.</li>
<li>ODR commonly involves case management systems, integration of communication technologies such as email, SMS, WhatsApp, Interactive Voice Response, audio/video conferencing.</li>
<li>With appropriate data sets in place, it can also involve advanced automation, the use of technologies such as artificial intelligence and machine learning to enable resolutions at the same time as it would take to initiate a transaction over the network.</li>
<li>Many e-commerce companies have turned to the ODR with the realisation that in order to maximise transactions it is important to ensure a positive dispute resolution experience.</li>
<li>Adoption in India: The ODR is no more a distant dream for India as well.</li>
<li>The National Payments Corporation of India (NPCI) has mandated platforms in the UPI ecosystem <strong>to adopt the ODR for complaints and grievances connected to failed transactions</strong>.</li>
<li> Ingram, SEBI SCORES (or the Securities and Exchange Board of India SEBI COm plaints REdress System), RBI CMS (or the Reserve Bank of India Complaint Management System), MahaRERA (or the Maharashtra Real Estate Regulatory Authority), MSME Samadhaan (or the Micro Small and Medium Enterprises Delayed Payment Monitoring System), and RTIOnline (or the Right to Information Online) are other examples of ODR systems that are widely used in the country.</li>
<li><strong>Mitigating litigation risks</strong>: The ODR will help mitigate litigation risk and provide valuable insights into problems faced by consumers.</li>
<li>Consumers are provided with another choice for effective redress of their grievances, thereby building trust, confidence and brand loyalty.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Advantages of ONDC</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Wider choice for consumers:</strong> The ONDC achieves the dual objective of wider choice for consumers on the one hand and access to a wider consumer base for sellers on the other.</li>
<li>With India’s e-commerce industry set to reach $200 billion by 2027, this shift from a platform-centric paradigm to democratisation of the nation’s online market will catalyse the <strong>inclusion of millions of small business owners and kirana businesses.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>A dispute resolution framework that includes a customised ODR process can play a role in the network achieving its steep five-year target of adding $48 billion in gross merchandise value to India’s e-commerce market, a network of 90 crore buyers and 12 crore sellers with the least hiccups.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/addressing-the-challenges-in-new-age-digital-commerce/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India, Bangladesh, Pakistan: What east can teach west</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-bangladesh-pakistan-what-east-can-teach-west/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Not much</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- India-Bangladesh ties</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>The bilateral relationship between India and Bangladesh dominated by endless contentions at the turn of the millennium has transformed into a very productive partnership.</p>
<h4>Contrast between India’s relations with Bangladesh and Pakistan</h4>
<ul>
<li>The persistence of cross-border terrorism, the conflict over Kashmir, the militarisation of the frontier, little connectivity, poor trade relations and no formal inter-governmental negotiations paint a bleak picture of the India-Pak border.</li>
<li>The inability of successive generations of Indian and Pakistani leaders to bring a closure to Partition in the west makes the talk of a “100-year war” credible.</li>
<li>The only trend that can counter this pessimism is the good news from<strong> India’s eastern frontier with Bangladesh.</strong></li>
<li>In contrast to the talk of a 100-year war between India and Pakistan, India and Bangladesh have proclaimed a “sonali adhyay” or <strong>“golden chapter” in bilateral relations.</strong></li>
<li>While the <strong>unresolved land and maritime territorial disputes</strong> constitute one of the main problems in India’s relations with Pakistan, their resolution with Bangladesh transformed the context of bilateral relations.</li>
<li>For both Delhi and Dhaka, the reinvention of the bilateral relationship has been one of the most significant successes of their recent foreign policies</li>
</ul>
<h4>Rebuilding the Bangladesh-India ties after 2010</h4>
<ul>
<li>The work on rebuilding ties began in earnest in 2010, when Sheikh Hasina came to India after taking charge of Bangladesh as prime minister for the second time in 2009.</li>
<li><strong>Addressing bilateral problems:</strong> Both sides embarked on an extraordinary effort to address most bilateral problems—including border settlement, river water sharing, cross-border terrorism, market access to Bangladeshi goods, and connectivity.</li>
<li>The land boundary deal got parliamentary approval in 2015 in India.</li>
<li>India also accepted the award of the Permanent Court of Arbitration in The Hague on settling the<strong> maritime boundary dispute between Delhi and Dhaka. </strong></li>
<li><strong>Security cooperation:</strong> Cooperation on cross-border terrorism that began a couple of years earlier helped build <strong>much-needed political trust</strong> between the two national security establishments.</li>
<li><strong>Connectivity:</strong> On the connectivity front, we have seen a substantive movement towards reopening the border that was largely shut down after the 1965 war between India and Pakistan.</li>
<li>Trans-boundary bus services, reopening of railway lines, and the revitalisation of waterways are restoring connectivity in the eastern subcontinent that was severed.</li>
<li><strong>Bilateral trade:</strong> Bilateral trade volumes have grown by leaps and bounds in recent years touching nearly<strong> $16 billion last year.</strong></li>
<li>Bangladesh is one of <strong>India’s top export markets.</strong></li>
<li> India and Bangladesh have also developed <strong>inter-connected power grids</strong> facilitating Dhaka’s purchase of power from India.</li>
<li>It currently buys about <strong>1200 MW of power</strong> from India and an additional 1500 MW is in the pipeline.</li>
<li><strong>Development of the northeastern India:</strong> Today the northeastern states have realised the immense benefits of deeper economic engagement with Bangladesh — none of them more important than ending the <strong>geographic isolation of the region.</strong></li>
<li>Assam today is at the forefront of imagining a bolder agenda for deepening economic ties with Bangladesh.</li>
<li><strong>Peace and prosperity in the region:</strong> For India, the expansive partnership with Bangladesh has significantly eased its security challenges and laid the basis for peace and prosperity in the eastern subcontinent.</li>
<li>For Bangladesh, discarding the temptation to balance India and embark on a cooperative strategy has allowed Dhaka <strong>to focus on its economic growth</strong> and lift itself in the regional and global hierarchy.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Consolidating the gains:</strong> Rather than regret the unfortunate dynamic on the western frontier and bemoan Pakistan’s reluctance to let the SAARC become a vehicle for regional cooperation, Delhi should focus on <strong>consolidating the “golden moment” in the east.</strong></li>
<li>The<strong> issues that need resolution</strong> are protecting the rights of minorities, sharing the waters of more than 50 rivers, promoting cross-border investments, managing one of the longest borders in the world, <strong>facilitating trade and preventing illegal migration</strong>, countering forces of religious extremism, promoting maritime security in the Bay of Bengal, expanding defence cooperation, and mitigating climate change in the shared regional environment to name a few.</li>
<li>Solving problems and tending to the relationship must necessarily be a continuous effort rather than episodic.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>Nor can Delhi and Dhaka take each other for granted and let domestic politics overwhelm the logic of bilateral cooperation. The 75th anniversary of independence offers Delhi and Dhaka a special opportunity to elevate the ambition for their bilateral partnership.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-bangladesh-pakistan-what-east-can-teach-west/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India’s ‘wheat waiver’ WTO demand is risk-fraught</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-wheat-waiver-wto-demand-is-risk-fraught/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>WTO waiver</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Public Stockholding of Food issue at WTO</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>The WTO ministerial meeting in June at Geneva did precious little to address the issue of public stockholding of food.</p>
<h4>Public stockholding issue at WTO</h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s PSH policy is based on<strong> procuring food from farmers at an administered price</strong> (minimum support price or MSP), which is generally higher than the market price.</li>
<li><strong>PSH’s’ twin objectives:</strong> The PSH policy serves the twin objectives of offering remunerative prices to farmers and providing subsidised food to the underprivileged.</li>
<li><strong>Trade distortion subsidy:</strong> Under WTO law, such price support-based procurement from farmers is counted as a trade-distorting subsidy, and if given beyond the permissible limit, breaches WTO law.</li>
<li>India in the World Trade Organization (WTO) — and rightly so — has been to find a permanent solution to the issue of public stockholding (PSH) of food to protect India’s food security (PSH policy).</li>
<li><strong>Peace clause:</strong> Currently, India has temporary relief due to a<strong> ‘peace clause’</strong> which bars countries from bringing legal challenges against price support-based procurement for food security purposes.</li>
<li>The WTO ministerial meeting in June at Geneva did precious little to address this issue.</li>
<li> India’s concerns about the PSH issue have been taken on board.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s concerns</h4>
<ul>
<li>For India, the real issue is not about maintaining adequate food stocks, which WTO rules do not prohibit, provided food is stocked by employing non-trade distorting instruments such as providing income support to farmers (cash transfers independent of crop production).</li>
<li><strong>Use of MSP:</strong> India’s concern is that it should have the policy space to hold public food stocks using the MSP, which is a price support instrument.</li>
<li>However, there is no mention of price support in the Geneva declaration.</li>
<li>India’s demand for a permanent solution to the PSH policy has acquired a new dimension.</li>
<li>India insists that it should also be <strong>allowed to export food</strong>, most notably wheat, from the pool of the foodgrain procured under the MSP.</li>
<li>However, WTO law proscribes countries from <strong>exporting foodgrain procured at subsidised prices.</strong></li>
<li>Paragraph 4 of the 2013 WTO decision on PSH for food security purposes, clearly states that countries procuring food for food-security purposes shall ensure that such procured food does not “distort trade or adversely affect the food security of other Members”.</li>
<li>The same spirit is reflected in paragraph 10 of the Geneva ministerial food security declaration, which states that countries may release surplus food stocks in the international market in accordance with WTO law.</li>
<li> However, it is very unlikely that such a request will be acceded to.</li>
<li>As per Article IX.3 of the WTO Agreement, waivers can be adopted only in “<strong>exceptional circumstances</strong>”.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>Developed countries have historically opposed India’s PSH programme as they apprehend that India might divert some of its public stock to the international market, thus depressing global prices.</li>
<li>India actively pushing for exporting food from its official granaries gives fresh ammunition to the PSH solution opponents.</li>
<li>Thus,<strong> India should revisit its stand</strong> on asking for a waiver for wheat exports from its public stockholding, which, in any case, was not a part of India’s PSH policy.</li>
<li>Spending scarce negotiating capital on this issue might dilute India’s core agenda of pushing for a permanent solution for its PSH programme to attain the goal of food security and providing remunerative prices to the farmers.</li>
<li>Negotiations at the WTO require crystal clarity of the core objectives that should be relentlessly pursued.</li>
<li>Adding newer objectives and shifting goalposts might result in falling between two stools.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>Instead of asking for the waiver to export wheat from public stockholding, the laudable objective of helping countries facing food crises can be accomplished by strengthening India’s commitment to the United Nations World Food Programme.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-wheat-waiver-wto-demand-is-risk-fraught/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India’s response to Sri Lanka and Myanmar crises is a study in contrast</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-response-to-sri-lanka-and-myanmar-crises-is-a-study-in-contrast/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Not much</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- Crisis in Myanmar and issues with India's response to it</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>There is a stark contrast contrast between the Indian response to the crisis in Sri Lanka and the dawning civil war in Myanmar.</p>
<h4>Crisis in Myanmar</h4>
<ul>
<li>According to UN human rights monitors, over 2,000 people have been killed, around 14,000 are in prison, including 90 lawmakers, over 7,00,000 are refugees and half a million internally displaced.</li>
<li>Humanitarian aid to coup opponents is blocked.</li>
<li>The economy is in free fall.</li>
<li>Though the<strong> international community</strong> has not accepted the junta or its nominees as official representatives of Myanmar, it has not recognised the unity government as the legitimate successor of the pre-coup elected administration either.</li>
<li>Its armed wing, the recently-formed <strong>People’s Defence Force (PDF)</strong>, exists in a shadowy limbo.</li>
<li>If it is too weak to impose significant costs on the junta, one root cause is the <strong>lack of support from neighbours</strong>.</li>
<li>As against Europe’s military support for Ukraine’s defence, no Asian country has stepped up to support the unity government and PDF.</li>
<li><strong>Role of ASEAN:</strong>  It is ASEAN which shouldered the responsibility to mediate in Myanmar, whereas India took the initiative with Sri Lanka.</li>
<li>But ASEAN has been largely unsuccessful.</li>
<li>The<strong> five-point consensus</strong> that the junta agreed on with the regional grouping included an immediate end to violence and resumption of negotiations between the ousted administration and the Tatmadaw.</li>
<li>ASEAN’s reaction has been weak at best.</li>
<li>The US, EU, Australia and Canada announced targeted sanctions on the junta, and the EU imposed an embargo on arms sales to the country. ASEAN did not.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s response and issues with it</h4>
<ul>
<li>The contrast between the Indian response to the crisis in Sri Lanka and the dawning civil war in Myanmar could not be starker.</li>
<li><strong>There is no support</strong> from the India administration for Mizoram’s aid effort, and apparently there is no Indian policy vis a vis the coup either.</li>
<li><strong>Cooperation against cross-border insurgency:</strong> Given our land and sea borders with Myanmar, and the troubled history of cross-border insurgencies between our two countries, the India’s inertia is alarming, though not entirely surprising.</li>
<li>Successive Indian administrations maintained relations with the junta in the hope that they would cooperate against cross-border Indian armed groups.</li>
<li>But these<strong> insurgencies have reduced. </strong></li>
<li>In fact, over the 10 years of Myanmar’s partial democracy, from 2011 to 2021, cross-border support for Indian insurgents dipped sharply.</li>
<li><strong>Direct security interest:</strong> In other words, we have<strong> a direct security interest in the restoration of our neighbour’s democracy.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Stringent sanctions: Sanctions</strong> that will starve the junta are a first step that Myanmar’s neighbours are yet to try.</li>
<li>While ASEAN has the initiative, all<strong> Myanmar’s neighbours need to unite on sanctions,</strong> especially nations such as Japan, Australia and India that are members of the Quad along with the US.</li>
<li>Myanmar ought to have topped the recent Quad summit’s agenda and it is shameful that it did not.</li>
<li>It is still not too late to call a virtual emergency meeting of Quad heads of state, along with ASEAN heads of state, to agree to stringent sanctions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>Our neighbourhood is more unstable today than it has been for decades. Four of our bordering countries are in free fall, while China’s grip comes closer to our shores by the hour. Can India afford to fiddle while wildfires ignite around us?</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-response-to-sri-lanka-and-myanmar-crises-is-a-study-in-contrast/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>A new global vision for G20</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/a-new-global-vision-for-g20/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>G-20</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- New framework for G20</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>While India has taken a clear view of the role of the G20, there is concern that the agenda, themes and focus areas which India will set for 2023 lack vision.</p>
<h4>What is G-20?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Formed in 1999, the G20 is an international forum of the governments and central bank governors from 20 major economies.</li>
<li>Collectively, the G20 economies account for around 85 percent of the Gross World Product (GWP), 80 percent of world trade.</li>
<li>To tackle the problems or address issues that plague the world, the heads of governments of the G20 nations periodically participate in summits.</li>
<li>In addition to it, the group also hosts separate meetings of the finance ministers and foreign ministers.</li>
<li>The G20 has no permanent staff of its own and its chairmanship rotates annually between nations divided into regional groupings.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of G20 in shaping global order</h4>
<ul>
<li>The G20 plays an important role in shaping and strengthening global architecture and governance on all major international economic issues.</li>
<li>It recognises that global prosperity is<strong> interdependent</strong> and economic <strong>opportunities and challenges are interlinked.</strong></li>
<li>The challenge is to craft new approaches to overcome the acute global discord.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why we need new model of cooperation</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multilateral commitments are faltering:</strong> Governance in a world that is steadily becoming more equal needs institutional innovation.</li>
<li>This is because the role of the United Nations and the World Trade Organization in securing cooperation between donor and recipient country groups is losing centrality.</li>
<li> There are now <strong>three socio-economic systems</strong> — the G7, China-Russia, and India and the others — and they will jointly set the global agenda.</li>
<li><strong>Strategic competition:</strong> Ukraine conflict, rival finance, the expanding influence of the trade and value chains dominated by the U.S. and China, and the <strong>reluctance of developing countries to take sides in the strategic competition</strong> as they have a real choice requires fresh thinking.</li>
<li><strong>Preventing the clash of ideas through reorientation</strong>: The primary role of the G20, which accounts for 95% of the world’s patents, 85% of global GDP, 75% of international trade and 65% of the world population, needs to be reoriented to prevent a clash of ideas to the detriment of the global good.</li>
<li>The solution lies in <strong>a new conceptual model</strong> seeking agreement on an agenda limited to principles rather than long negotiated anodyne text.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What should be on agenda when India hosts G20 in 2023</h4>
<h4>1] Underlining the need for new framework</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Redefining common concerns:</strong> First, the presumed equality that we are all in the same boat, recognised in the case of climate change, needs to be expanded to other areas with a global impact redefining ‘common concerns’.</li>
<li>Second, emerging economies are no longer to be considered the source of problems needing external solutions but source of solutions to shared problems.</li>
<li>Third, the BRICS provides an appropriate model for governance institutions suitable for the 21st century where a narrow group of states dominated by one power will not shape the agenda.</li>
<li>Ensuring adequate food, housing, education, health, water and sanitation and work for all should guide international cooperation.</li>
<li><strong>Principles of common but differentiated responsibilities</strong> for improving the quality of life of all households can guide deliberations in other fora on problems that seem intractable in multilateralism based on trade and aid.</li>
</ul>
<h4>2] Collaboration around science and technology</h4>
<ul>
<li> The global agenda has been tilted towards investment, whereas <strong>science and technology are the driving force for economic diversification</strong>, sustainably urbanising the world, and ushering the hydrogen economy and new crop varieties as the answer to both human well-being and global climate change.</li>
<li> A forum to exchange experiences on societal benefits and growth as complementary goals would lead to fresh thinking on employment and environment.</li>
</ul>
<h4>3] Redefining digital access as universal service</h4>
<ul>
<li>Harnessing the potential of the digital-information-technology revolution requires redefining digital access as a “universal service” that goes beyond physical connectivity to sharing specific opportunities available.</li>
<li>For global society to reap the fruits of the new set of network technologies,<strong> open access software</strong> should be offered for more cost-effective service delivery options, good governance and sustainable development.</li>
</ul>
<h4>4] Collaboration in space technology</h4>
<ul>
<li>Space is the next frontier for finding solutions to problems of <strong>natural resource management</strong> ranging from climate change-related natural disasters, supporting agricultural innovation to urban and infrastructure planning.</li>
<li><strong> Analysing Earth observation data</strong> will require regional and international collaboration through existing centres which have massive computing capacities, machine learning and artificial intelligence.</li>
</ul>
<h4>5] Collaboration in health sector</h4>
<ul>
<li>Public health has to learn from the COVID-19 fiasco with infectious diseases representing a market failure.</li>
<li>A major global challenge is the rapidly growing antimicrobial resistance which needs <strong>new antibiotics and collaboration between existing biotechnology facilities.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>6]  Avoiding strategic competition</h4>
<ul>
<li>Overriding priority to development suggests avoiding strategic competition.</li>
<li>Countries in the region will support building on the 1971 UNGA Declaration designating for all time the Indian Ocean as a zone of peace and non-extension into the region of rivalries and conflicts that are foreign to it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>7] Reviving Global Financial Transaction Tax</h4>
<ul>
<li> A<strong> Global Financial Transaction Tax</strong>, considered by the G20 in 2011, needs to be revived to be paid to a Green Technology Fund for Least Developed Countries.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>Given the significance of G20 for the global order it should lead the way in formulating the new framework based on collaboration in areas such as science and technology, innovation and away from aid and trade.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/a-new-global-vision-for-g20/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Lessons for India from the Taiwan standoff</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/lessons-for-india-from-the-taiwan-standoff/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Not much</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- Lessons for India in China-Taiwan crisis</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>The brief visit by the United States House Speaker, Nancy Pelosi, to Taiwan, against stern warnings issued by China, has the potential to increase the already deteriorating relationship between the U.S. and China. For those of us in India watching the events as they unfold around Taiwan, there are valuable lessons to be learnt.</p>
<h4>Background</h4>
<ul>
<li>The crisis that began with the visit of Ms. Pelosi to Taipei is still unfolding and there is little clarity today on how it will wind down.</li>
<li> For China, its <strong>claims about a rising superpower</strong> might ring hollow if it is unable to unify its claimed territories, in particular Taiwan.</li>
<li>For the U.S., it is about<strong> re-establishing steadily-diminishing American credibility</strong> in the eyes of its friends and foes.</li>
<li>For Taiwan, it is about standing up to Chinese bullying and making its red lines clear to Beijing.</li>
<li><strong>Lessons for India:</strong> To be fair, there is growing recognition in New Delhi that it is important to meet the challenge posed by a belligerent China, but there appears to be a lack of clarity on how to meet this challenge.</li>
<li>To that extent, the Taiwan crisis offers New Delhi three lessons, at the very least.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Takeaways for India</h4>
<h4>1] Articulate red lines</h4>
<ul>
<li>The most important lesson from the Taiwan standoff for policymakers in New Delhi is the importance of articulating red lines and <strong>sovereign positions in an unambiguous manner.</strong></li>
<li> New Delhi needs to unambiguously highlight the threat from China and the sources of such a threat.</li>
<li>Any absence of such clarity will be cleverly utilised by Beijing to push Indian limits, as we have already seen.</li>
<li><strong>Stop confusing international community</strong>: Even worse, ambiguous messaging by India also <strong>confuses its friends in the international community.</strong></li>
<li>If India <strong>does not clearly articulate that China is in illegal occupation of its territory</strong>, how can it expect its friends in the international community to support India diplomatically or otherwise?</li>
<li>In other words, India’s current policy amounts to poor messaging, and confusing to its own people as well as the larger international community, and is therefore counterproductive.</li>
</ul>
<h4>2] Avoid appeasement</h4>
<ul>
<li>Taiwan could have avoided the ongoing confrontation and the economic blockade during Chinese retaliatory military exercises around its territory by avoiding Ms. Pelosi’s visit to Taipei, or perhaps even keeping it low key.</li>
<li>Appeasement of China, Taiwan knows, is not the answer to Beijing’s aggression.</li>
<li> India’s policy of meeting/hosting Chinese leaders while the Chinese People’s Liberation Army (PLA) continue(d) to violate established territorial norms on the LAC is a deeply flawed one.</li>
<li>Unilaterally catering to Chinese sensitivities even during the standoffs between the two militaries is a mistake.</li>
<li>For instance, the parliamentary delegation visits and legislature-level dialogues between India and Taiwan have not taken place since 2017.</li>
<li>S<strong>oft-peddling of the Quad was a mistake:</strong> During the 2000s, India (as well as Australia) decided to soft-peddle the Quad in the face of strong Chinese objections.</li>
<li>It is only in the last two years or so that we have witnessed renewed enthusiasm around the Quad.</li>
<li>In retrospect, appeasing Beijing by almost abandoning the Quad was bad strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4>3] Economic relationship is a two way process</h4>
<ul>
<li>Given that the economic relationship is a two-way process and that, as a matter of fact, the trade deficit is in China’s favour, China too has a lot to lose from a damaged trade relationship with India.</li>
<li>More so, if the Taiwan example (as well as the India-China standoff in 2020) is anything to go by, trade can continue to take place despite tensions and without India making any compromises vis-à-vis its sovereign claims.</li>
<li>India for sure should do business with China, but not on China’s own terms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>The recent crisis offers valuable lessons for India in its dealing with China.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/lessons-for-india-from-the-taiwan-standoff/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>RBI, government must act in coordination during an economically challenging period</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rbi-government-must-act-in-coordination-during-an-economically-challenging-period/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Standing Deposit Facility rate</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Dealing with economically challenging period</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>In the recent MPC meeting, the policy rate hike was widely expected, more anticipated were the MPC and the RBI Governor’s forward guidance on the trajectory of policy — on both monetary policy and liquidity instruments. So, how do we see monetary policy evolve over the rest of the year and beyond?</p>
<h4>Tightening of monetary policy</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Repo rate at 5.4 per cent:</strong> In its latest meeting, the members of the monetary policy committee voted unanimously to increase the policy repo rate by 50 basis points to<strong> 5.4 per cent.</strong></li>
<li>The repo rate was 5.15 per cent in February 2020.</li>
<li>So, in effect, the RBI’s policy has not only been normalised, but has actually tightened <strong>compared to the pre-pandemic level.</strong></li>
<li> Even the lower bound of the rate corridor, the <strong>Standing Deposit Facility (SDF) rate,</strong> at 5.25 per cent is now above the pre-pandemic repo rate.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Forward guidance on stance</h4>
<ul>
<li>The MPS indicated the retaining the policy stance rather than shifting to “neutral”.</li>
<li>This <strong>retention of stance</strong> might be interpreted as being a bit more hawkish than “neutral”, which implies that rates might be both increased or cut, depending on economic conditions.</li>
<li>Now that policy is largely normalised, the <strong>pace of tightening</strong> is likely to moderate.</li>
<li>The urgency of aggressive rate hikes and tightening of liquidity has somewhat moderated, although risks remain.</li>
<li>RBI’s research suggests that the “real natural rate” — the rate at which policy is neither loose nor tight – is 0.8-1 per cent.</li>
<li>This operative interest rate is usually the<strong> three-month T-bill rate,</strong> which in “normal” times averages 10-15 basis points above the repo rate.</li>
<li>Considering that monetary policy is calibrated over a one-year horizon and using the RBI’s inflation forecast of 5 per cent for the first quarter of 2023-24, <strong>the “natural” repo rate will be around 5.85 per cent.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>Inflation and growth conditions</h4>
<ul>
<li>The RBI’s growth projection for 2022-23 has been retained at 7.2 per cent, with growth frontloaded in the first half.</li>
<li>CPI inflation is still forecast to average 6.7 per cent.</li>
<li>Inflationary pressures are likely to wane in the second half of 2022-23, particularly if the recent drop in industrial metals prices persists over the next few months.</li>
<li>A more or less normal monsoon might help in keeping food prices stable. However, risks remain.</li>
<li><strong>Robust growth prospects</strong>: Demand for consumption goods seems to be resilient, enabling some further pass-through of input costs.</li>
<li>Combine this with tight labour markets and rising wage costs in some tech-oriented sectors.</li>
<li>High frequency indicators of economic activity have recovered after some weakness in June.</li>
<li>In addition to resilient demand, there is evidence of a closing of the “output gap”.</li>
<li><strong>Global growth:</strong> Global growth and trade are forecast to significantly slow down in 2022 and 2023, largely due<strong> to aggressive tightening by G-10 central banks</strong> and a slowdown in China.</li>
<li>The IMF predicts global trade volume (both merchandise and services) to slow to 4.1 per cent and 3.2 per cent in 2022 and 2023, down from 10.1 per cent in 2021.</li>
<li>With world growth and trade flows moderating, along with a drop in commodities prices,<strong> India’s export growth is likely to be lower than last year.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>External financial condition</h4>
<ul>
<li>The current account deficit remains a concern.</li>
<li>India’s<strong> external balance sheet</strong> remains quite robust, as is evident from various balance of payments and debt metrics, and reportedly <strong>low unhedged foreign currency borrowings.</strong></li>
<li>Continued <strong>tightening by global central banks</strong>, particularly the US Federal Reserve over the rest of 2022, will keep India’s external financial conditions tight and likely <strong>limit portfolio capital flows. </strong></li>
<li>However, there are some signs emanating from these central banks that the hitherto front-loaded tightening might moderate going forward.</li>
<li>This will <strong>take some pressure off the rupee,</strong> though, exchange rate volatility management will remain a part of the overall monetary policy management framework.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Challenge of surplus liquidity</h4>
<ul>
<li>During the earlier phase of policy normalisation and the recent tightening, liquidity management has played an important role in influencing short-term money market interest rates.</li>
<li><strong>The current latent surplus liquidity</strong> — the existing funds with banks and the Union government’s unspent revenues parked with RBI — is over Rs 5 lakh crore.</li>
<li>While the extent of liquidity surplus during the Covid months has come down, these levels are still much higher than RBI estimates of non-inflationary levels of surplus, <strong>which is around Rs 1.8-2.4 lakh crore. </strong></li>
<li>This will gradually fall with cash withdrawals and some potential RBI dollar sales in the coming months.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>The central bank, in coordination with the government, has ensured an orderly evolution of economic conditions during a very complex and challenging environment. The exit process now will also need the same adroit use of policy instruments.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Standing Deposit Facility rate</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) in April 2022 introduced the <strong>Standing Deposit Facility (SDF)</strong>, an additional tool for absorbing liquidity, at an interest rate of 3.75 per cent.</li>
<li>The main purpose of SDF is to reduce the excess liquidity  in the system, and control inflation.</li>
<li>In 2018, the amended Section 17 of the RBI Act empowered the Reserve Bank to introduce the SDF –<strong> an additional tool for absorbing liquidity without any collateral. </strong></li>
<li>By removing the binding collateral constraint on the RBI, the SDF strengthens the operating framework of monetary policy.</li>
<li>The SDF is also a financial stability tool in addition to its role in liquidity management.</li>
<li>The SDF replaced the fixed rate reverse repo (FRRR) as the floor of the liquidity adjustment facility corridor.</li>
<li>The SDF rate will be 25 bps below the policy rate (Repo rate), and it will be applicable to overnight deposits at this stage.</li>
<li>It would, however, retain the flexibility to absorb liquidity of longer tenors as and when the need arises, with appropriate pricing.</li>
</ul>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rbi-government-must-act-in-coordination-during-an-economically-challenging-period/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Using a rupee route to get around a dominating dollar</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/using-a-rupee-route-to-get-around-a-dominating-dollar/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Foreign Exchange Management (Deposit) Regulations, 2016</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Trade and settlement of payments in rupee</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>A number of countries, including India, are now considering the use of other currencies to avoid the U.S. dollar and its hegemonic role in settling international transactions.</p>
<h4>Currency hierarchy</h4>
<ul>
<li>For India, currency hierarchy goes back to colonial times when the Indian rupee was virtually <strong>linked to the British pound</strong> rather than to gold which it earned through exports.</li>
<li>In the post-War period, the neo-colonial currency hierarchy has been clubbed with the continued use, primarily of the U.S. dollar, for the majority of international transactions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Rupee settlement of trade</h4>
<ul>
<li>In recent times, India has been taking an active interest in having the rupee used for trade and the settlement of payments with other countries, which include Russia, now facing sanctions.</li>
<li>The Reserve Bank of India has recently taken a proactive stand to have rupee settlement of trade (circular dated July 11, 2022).</li>
<li>While options for invoicing in rupees were already legal in terms of Regulation 7(1) of the <strong>Foreign Exchange Management (Deposit) Regulations, 2016,</strong> the current circular aims to operationalise the special<strong> Vostro accounts with Russian banks in India</strong>, in a bid to promote trade and also gain a better status for the rupee as an international currency.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Opportunities for India</h4>
<ul>
<li>The advantages India is currently seeking in these arrangements include avoidance of transactions in the highly priced dollar which has an exchange value of ₹80, impacting the Indian economy with inflation, capital flight and the <strong>drop in foreign exchange reserves</strong> by $70 billion since September 2021.</li>
<li> Buying oil with a depreciated ruble, and at discounts, is not only cost-saving but also saves transport time with the use of multi-modal routes using land, sea and air routes.</li>
<li>In addition, India is looking forward to trade expansion in sanctions-affected Russia.</li>
<li>With India having a trade deficit with Russia, which has been around $<strong>3.52 billion</strong> on average over the last two financial years, India’s opportunities include the possible use, by Russia, of the surpluses in the Vostro rupee account in Russian banks for additional purchases from India.</li>
<li><strong>Past attempts</strong>: Attempts to use the rupee for invoicing and trading is, however, not new to India.</li>
<li>A comprehensive bilateral trade and payments agreement was signed by India in 1953 with the Soviet bloc countries.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Challenges</h4>
<ul>
<li>There are quite a few problems that may prevail in implementing the desired rupee payments and avoiding dollar transactions.</li>
<li><strong>Willingness of banks and private parties:</strong> Apart from issues that concern an agreed<strong> exchange rate</strong> between the rupee and the ruble (R-R), two volatile currencies, there is also the question of the willingness of private parties (companies, banks) to accept the rupee for trade and settlements.</li>
<li> If Russia opens its door for exports from India, the ‘R-R’ route may prove attractive for Indian exporters.</li>
<li><strong>Concerns of the US:</strong> There are official concerns for reactions, particularly from the U.S., to deals, especially for purchase of the S-400 defence equipment.</li>
<li><strong>Reaction of the Europe:</strong> Moreover, the deals between India and Russia, especially on oil, can be considered by the West as ‘indirect back door support’ — as India is importing Russian crude<strong> at 30% discount,</strong> processing at refineries in Gujarat which include Reliance, and then exporting those to the West.</li>
<li><strong>Trade deficit:</strong> There were attempts even before the novel coronavirus pandemic to initiate a clearing account on the BRICS platform.</li>
<li>The quantitative implications indicate a skewed pattern of transactions — with China having most of the trade surplus.</li>
<li>It is a pattern similar to what is happening in India-Russia trade at the moment.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>The India-Soviet agreements of the past may provide a clue on how the current ‘R-R’ trade and the problems can be managed by initiating a push for Indian exports to Russia and, of course, avoiding all deals in dollars — benefiting both trade partners and countering, globally, the on-going currency hierarchy.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/using-a-rupee-route-to-get-around-a-dominating-dollar/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Personal Data Protection Bill</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/implications-of-withdrawal-of-the-personal-data-protection-bill/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>European Union’s Digital Services Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- Need for personal data protection act</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>In a surprise development last week, the Government withdrew the Personal Data Protection (PDP) Bill, 2019, thereby abruptly halting the country’s quest for a national data protection law that had been in the works for over five years.</p>
<h4>Reasons for withdrawal of the Bill</h4>
<ul>
<li>The short circular issued by the Minister of Electronics and Information Technology states that considering the report of the Joint Parliamentary Committee (JPC) — it had proposed 81 amendments and made 12 recommendations — <strong>“a comprehensive legal framework is being worked on”. </strong></li>
<li>There is no elaboration on what such a “comprehensive legal framework” entails.</li>
<li><strong>Possible plan of action: </strong>The Government could enact a fresh privacy legislation or <strong>a comprehensive data protection law</strong> (covering both personal and non-personal data).</li>
<li><strong>Subsuming data protection in IT Act:</strong> Alternatively, it could subsume data protection under its ongoing attempts at revising the existing Information Technology Act, 2000.</li>
<li><strong>Digital markets law:</strong> It could also enact a digital markets law, along the lines of the<strong> European Union’s Digital Services Act</strong>, focusing on competition and innovation in the digital space.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Background of the introduction of Personal Data Protection Bill</h4>
<ul>
<li>When the Supreme Court of India affirmed the right to privacy in  <strong>K.S. Puttaswamy judgment in 2017</strong>, the nine-judge Bench of the Court referred to the Government’s Office Memorandum constituting the<strong> B.N. Srikrishna Committee</strong> to suggest a draft Data Protection Bill.</li>
<li>The committee released its draft Personal Data Protection Bill in 2018, which was the first public articulation of a data protection law in India.</li>
<li>When the Supreme Court upheld the constitutionality of the Aadhaar Act, the majority emphasised that it believed that “there is a need for a proper legislative mechanism for data protection”.</li>
<li>In December 2019, the Government introduced the PDP Bill, 2019 in the Lok Sabha as a comprehensive personal data protection regime.</li>
<li>The Bill was referred to the JPC for its recommendations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What were the issues with the Bill?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Power to exemption with state:</strong> The Bill’s expansive exemptions <strong>allowed the state to exempt the entire application of the law</strong> simply as if it was “expedient” to do so in the interest of national security or public order.</li>
<li><strong>Powers without accountability:</strong> The PDP Bill, 2019 as well as the JPC’s version established a strong regulator (the Data Protection Authority) with a lot of power, but very little independence or accountability.</li>
<li><strong>Data localisation:</strong> The Bill imposed a s<strong>trong data localisation mandate</strong>, requiring companies to store all sensitive personal data and critical personal data (which was not defined) in India.</li>
<li><strong>Subsuming the personal and non-personal data:</strong> The JPC recommended subsuming the regulation of personal data and non-personal data within a single legislation, even though it undermined the Puttaswamy mandate to ensure protection of personal data.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why we need data protection law?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increasing internet use:</strong> India currently has over <strong>750 million Internet users</strong>, with the number only expected to increase in the future.</li>
<li>The Government is also making a strong push for a <strong>‘Digital India’,</strong> with increased focus on digitisation of access to health, ration, banking, insurance, especially after the COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
<li>There is<strong> a greater focus on the inter-linking of data,</strong> whether through facial recognition, Aadhaar, or the Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022.</li>
<li><strong>Data breaches:</strong> At the same time, India has among the highest data breaches in the world.</li>
<li>Without a data protection law in place, the data of millions of Indians continues to be at risk of being exploited, sold, and misused without their consent.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of writ proceeding against corporate action:</strong> Unlike state action, corporate action or misconduct is not subject to writ proceedings in India.</li>
<li>This is because fundamental rights are, by and large, not enforceable against private non-state entities.</li>
<li>This leaves individuals with limited remedies against private actors.</li>
<li>A personal data protection legislation would remedy this lacuna by providing individuals with proper grievance redress options and creating sufficient deterrence among private actors.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>It is imperative that the Government soon introduces a fresh data protection legislation, drawn after proper public consultation. Such a law should take into consideration the criticisms that have been raised by civil society as well as the private sector.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/implications-of-withdrawal-of-the-personal-data-protection-bill/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India’s tax-GDP ratio may be too high</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-tax-gdp-ratio-may-be-too-high/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Tax buoyancy</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 3- Tax-to-GDP ratio</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>What the data conclusively show is that the debate on the Indian economy should shift away from simplistic notions (borrowed from the West?) of the tax-GDP ratio being low in India.</p>
<h4>India’s low tax-to-GDP ratio</h4>
<ul>
<li>One of the stylised beliefs in India, and amongst some leading economic commentators both in India and abroad, is that our tax/GDP ratio is lower than what it “should” be.</li>
<li>This low tax-to-GDP ratio is blamed for a<strong> lower rate of investment</strong>, a<strong> higher fiscal deficit</strong>, and lower GDP growth — and all because the tax ratio is too low.</li>
<li>There can be reasonable doubts about the presumed links.</li>
<li>There are three important fiscal variables in the economy — <strong>taxes, fiscal deficit, and debt. </strong></li>
<li>They are inter-related — lower tax revenue means higher fiscal deficit, for the same level of expenditures, and higher deficit means higher debt.</li>
<li>All three, directly or indirectly, are assumed <strong>to affect growth and/or inflation.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>Analysing India’s tax-to-GDP ratio</h4>
<ul>
<li>Two common observations on tax-to-GDP for India — first, it is low at around<strong> 10-11 per cent of GDP</strong> and it has stayed at close to that level for the last 20 years.</li>
<li>In 2019, it hit a decade low of 10 per cent of GDP, the same as in 2014.</li>
<li>Second, in comparison with our peers, it is much lower.</li>
<li>Hence, logic dictates that we should strive to increase it.</li>
<li>But which country should we compare India with?</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with comparing tax-to-GDP with other countries</h4>
<ul>
<li>A common observation is to look at the tax-GDP ratio in G20 countries.</li>
<li><strong>Function of average level of per capita income:</strong> This is the beginning of a set of misinterpretations committed either knowingly, or unknowingly.</li>
<li>Because simple logic dictates that tax collected is <strong>a function of the average level of per capita income.</strong></li>
<li>Per capita income in the G20 varies from around $2,100 (India) to around $65,000 (US).</li>
<li>The 10-11 per cent figure for India is the tax/GDP <strong>ratio for taxes administered at the central level.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Challenges in data collection</strong>: Taxes in India, as in many other large, especially federal, countries, are collected at both a federal and state level.</li>
<li>And many economies have local (municipal) taxes as well. The tax collected is the sum of all these taxes.</li>
<li>Until now, collecting such disaggregated data for a large set of countries was challenging.</li>
<li>However, in a recent web publication, the IMF on their World Revenue Longitudinal Data set has published such data for all countries, from 1990-2019.</li>
<li>In this pre-pandemic year, among G20 economies, India’s tax-GDP (Xtax) ratio of 16.7 per cent was higher than that of China (15.9 per cent), Mexico (14.1 per cent), Indonesia (11.0 per cent), Saudi Arabia (5.9 per cent) and Turkey (15.9 per cent).</li>
<li>A more informative indicator of whether a country is taxing too much or too little in comparison with others is to look at the <strong>tax-GDP ratio adjusted for PPP per capita income.</strong></li>
<li>Prediction via a simple regression of tax-to-GDP on log PPP per capita GDP can yield one estimate of the tax gap — the difference between actual and actual adjusted for level of income.</li>
<li>The world average tax gap is -1.3 per cent;<strong> India is +1.2 per cent for the nine years 2011-2019.</strong></li>
<li>So, India’s tax GDP ratio averages 2.5 percentage points more than an average economy.</li>
<li>For every year for which data are available 1990-2019, India has had a positive tax gap — there is little evidence that a higher tax/GDP ratio helps growth.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How corporate tax cut helped India</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Corporate tax cut 2019:</strong> For years, the advocacy in India was to increase revenue from corporate tax which is one of three major components of tax revenue, the other being income and indirect taxes.</li>
<li>In September 2019, Finance Minister going well against Indian established conventional wisdom, lowered the corporate tax rate by around 10 percentage points.</li>
<li><strong>Avoiding triple whammy</strong>: Opponents said that empirical evidence around the world (for example, the US) meant that <strong>if tax rates were lowered, revenues would decline, the fisc would increase, as would inequality.</strong></li>
<li>A triple whammy that is best avoided.</li>
<li>However, now, three years later, we can assess the efficacy (or not) of this bold experiment.</li>
<li>For the three months April-June 2022, corporate tax revenues, y-o-y, are up 30 per cent.</li>
<li>Using fiscal 2019-20 as a base, corporate tax revenue has increased by 66 per cent, GDP by 33 per cent —<strong> an average tax buoyancy of 2.0 over three years. </strong></li>
<li>The previous largest tax buoyancy was in 2006-7 when the world was buoyant.</li>
<li>Tentatively, the tax-GDP ratio in the fiscal year 2022-23 will <strong>average over 18 per cent in India</strong>, a level close to Japan and the US.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>In India, the debate should shift to expenditures, and quality of expenditures (and perhaps to reform of the direct tax code). In this regard, suggestion that freebies be critically examined is most timely and welcome.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<hr/>
<h4> Back2Basics: Tax buoyancy and tax elasticity</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tax buoyancy:</strong> The buoyancy of a tax system <b>measures the total response of tax revenue both to changes in</b>. <b>national income and to discretionary changes in tax policies over time</b>, and it is traditionally interpreted as the percentage change in revenue associated to a one percent change in income.</li>
<li>Tax elasticity: It refers to changes in tax revenue in response to <strong>changes in tax rate. </strong></li>
<li>For example, how tax revenue changes if the government reduces corporate income tax from 30 per cent to 25 per cent indicate tax elasticity.</li>
</ul>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-tax-gdp-ratio-may-be-too-high/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian breed of Pet Dogs</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-indian-breed-of-pet-dogs/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Various breeds mentioned</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p>Mudhol hounds, a breed of hunting dogs native to north Karnataka, could be inducted into the Special Protection Group (SPG), the elite force protecting the Prime Minister of India.</p>
<blockquote>
<h4><em>Try this PYQ:</em></h4>
<p><strong><em>Q.What is/are unique about ‘Kharai camel’, a breed found in India?</em></strong></p>
<ol>
<li><em> It is capable of swimming up to three kilometres in seawater.</em></li>
<li><em> It survives by grazing on mangroves.</em></li>
<li><em> It lives in the wild and cannot be domesticated.</em></li>
</ol>
<p><em>Select the correct answer using the code given below:</em></p>
<p><em>(a) 1 and 2 only </em></p>
<p><em>(b) 3 only </em></p>
<p><em>(c) 1 and 3 only </em></p>
<p><em>(d) 1, 2 and 3</em></p>
<p><strong><em>Answer: (a)</em></strong></p></blockquote>
<h4>Famous Indian dog breeds</h4>
<p><strong>(1)Mudhol hounds</strong></p>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273224" height="203" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 321px) 100vw, 321px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/mudhol.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/mudhol.jpg 668w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/mudhol-300x190.jpg 300w" width="321"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The Mudhol hounds come from the region bordering Karnataka and Maharashtra.</li>
<li>According to a popular legend Ch. Shivaji Maharaj bred and used these dogs in his army.</li>
<li>The breed was named after the erstwhile princely state of Mudhol, which was part of the Bombay Presidency in British India.</li>
<li>The last king of the state, King Malojirao Ghorpade, presented a pair of these puppies to King George V when he visited the UK and it was the English emperor who christened the dogs as Mudhol hounds.</li>
<li>Mudhol hounds have narrow heads that are disproportionately smaller to their bodies but are tall in height.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2)Himachali hounds</strong></p>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273223" height="243" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 252px) 100vw, 252px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/hima.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/hima.jpg 442w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/hima-300x289.jpg 300w" width="252"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The Himachali hounds are locally known as the ‘Gaddi’ dog and come from the Himalayan region. They are massive, mastiff-like dogs with thick fur to protect them from the cold.</li>
<li>They look similar to the Tibetan mastiff but are less bulky.</li>
<li>‘Gaddi’ means shepherd in Urdu, and these dogs are primarily guarding livestock.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3)Rajapalayam</strong></p>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273222" height="231" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/rpm.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/rpm.jpg 382w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/rpm-292x300.jpg 292w" width="225"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The breed Rajapalayam is believed to have originated from Tamil Nadu, and named after the state’s Rajapalayam city in the Virudhunagar district.</li>
<li>A rare breed, these dogs are only found in certain pockets of the state.</li>
<li>These dogs are white, lean, muscular, and have historically made good hunters.</li>
<li>They are believed to have fought alongside the Polygar soldiers against the British East India Company during the Polygar wars from 1799 to 1805.</li>
<li>This is why the Rajapalayam dogs are also known as ‘Polygar hounds’.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(4) Kanni and Chippiparai</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273221" height="221" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 296px) 100vw, 296px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/kanni.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/kanni.jpg 532w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/kanni-300x224.jpg 300w" width="296"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The Kanni dog is another breed from Tamil Nadu, and its name translates to “pure” in Tamil after its fierce loyalty.</li>
<li>Like the Rajapalayam, Kanni dogs specialise in hunting hares, wild boars, and blackbucks.</li>
<li>However, since the Wildlife Protection Act of 1972 was passed, these dogs have been acting as guard dogs.</li>
<li>The Kennel Club of India, which maintains a registry of purebred dogs in India, has registered this dog under two names — Kanni and Chippiparai.</li>
</ul>
<h4>(5)Combai</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-273220" height="180" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/comba.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/comba.jpg 445w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/comba-300x202.jpg 300w" width="268"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The Combai dogs also originate from Tamil Nadu. They are tan-coloured with a black snout and appear shorter and stouter than the Rajapalayam. They are classified as terriers.</li>
<li>Like the Kanni and Rajapalayam, these dogs are rare and a dying breed and were historically used for boar hunting and guarding purposes.</li>
<li>The CRPF recently recruited Combai dogs into their Dog Breeding and Training School.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-indian-breed-of-pet-dogs/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Long road ahead: Towards women empowerment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/long-road-ahead-towards-women-empowerment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Global Gender Gap Report 2022.</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Women issues,Affirmative actions.</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-623245" height="365" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 548px) 100vw, 548px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/wemp1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/wemp1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/wemp1.jpg 650w" width="548"/>Context</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Gender parity is not recovering, according to the <strong>Global Gender Gap Report 2022.</strong> It will take another <strong>132 years to close the global gender gap</strong>.</li>
<li>As crises are compounding, women’s workforce outcomes are suffering and the risk of <strong>global gender parity</strong> backsliding further intensifies.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Why in news?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India has one of the world’s lowest female labour force participation rates (LFPR).</li>
<li>This means the productive potential of half of the population goes unutilized.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What is women’s empowerment all about?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Women’s empowerment can be defined to promoting women’s sense of <strong>self-worth</strong>, their ability to determine their <strong>own choices</strong>, and their right to influence <strong>social change</strong> for themselves and others.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Why it is needed?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Human resource</strong>: Empowerment of women is a necessity for the very development of a society, since it enhances both the quality and the quantity of human resources available for development.</li>
<li><strong>Sustainable development:</strong> Women’s empowerment and achieving gender equality is essential for our society to ensure the sustainable development of the country.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-623247" height="409" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 403px) 100vw, 403px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/positive-296x300.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/positive-296x300.jpeg 296w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/positive.jpeg 453w" width="403"/>Constraints in women empowerment </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Illiteracy</strong>: Illiteracy has been found as major constraints for the attainment of women Empowerment in the nation. It is the rate of literacy which governs the reservation, takeover and competition among women for their right in country. Female child are less privileged for attaining schools.</li>
<li><strong>Discriminatory nature of male towards female</strong>: In India, since the olden days, the men have been in control of politics, social, economical as well as cultural and traditional spheres of life.</li>
<li><strong>Religious and cultural beliefs</strong>: This is another important constraint of women’s empowerment in India which tightens up the female population. It is because of unknowing believes and following superstitions.</li>
<li><strong>Less participation of women in political field</strong>: In particular, women them self involves less in the political filed. Their participation is very insignificant in political issues and right as compared to male population.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What happens if we don’t act?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Economical losses</strong>: Evidence shows that economic disempowerment of women can result in losses of 10% of GDP in industrialized economies and over 30% in South Asia and in the Middle East and North Africa.</li>
<li><strong>Work opportunities</strong>: India’s GDP could grow by nearly ₹3 trillion if women were brought into the labour market and given access to formal, ‘decent’ work opportunities.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Case study </strong></p>
<p><strong>Mahila Sanatkar</strong> a craftswomen cooperative located in Hyderabad.</p>
<p><strong>Economic and social  effects</strong>: It  is  noticeable  some  social  results  such  as  <strong>skill building, self-confidence  enhancement,  the  mobility acquired  by the  women.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong>What is needed to improve women’s welfare?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Community sensitization:</strong> Persistent effort must be directed toward community sensitization to root out patriarchal social norms.</li>
<li><strong>Directional efforts</strong>: In addition to enforcing existing regulations like minimum wages, there must be supportive ancillary policies including childcare; secure transport; lighting; safety at work; and quotas in hiring, corporate boards, and politics to foster more  women  in  leadership.</li>
<li><strong>Universal social mobilization</strong>: Identification and inclusion of the poor remains a challenge. There is need to develop community resource persons for participatory identification of poor.</li>
<li><strong>Training, Capacity Building &amp; Skill Upgradation</strong>: There is lack of appropriate training plans, quality training and availability of expert training institutions.</li>
<li><strong>Universal Financial Inclusion</strong>: Lack of uniform financial management systems at all tiers of SHGs has impacted the growth in bank accounts, improvement in financial literacy, and absorption capacity of community members.</li>
<li><strong>Multiple &amp; Diversified Livelihoods</strong>: There is lack of progressive leadership for inclusiveness of small-sized enterprises at the federal level. Market/ forward linkages, is largely missing.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>If we improve women’s labour force participation, not only do we harness the massive productive potential of half of the population, but their earnings will yield enormous dividends for the future of the country and economy<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What do you consider as true women empowerment? Assess the constraints for the same and give directional efforts needed to overcome it.  </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/long-road-ahead-towards-women-empowerment/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian Olympic Association (IOA)</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-olympic-association-ioa/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>IOC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Olympics and India</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-623259" height="210" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ioa-300x210.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ioa-300x210.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ioa.jpg 465w" width="300"/></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has ordered status quo on the implementation of a Delhi High Court order to hand over the affairs of the Indian Olympic Association (IOA) to a Committee of Administrators (CoA).</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The FIFA had recently gone ahead and suspended the AIFF, citing “third party interference”, leaving an air of uncertainty on the prospect of India hosting the Under-17 Women’s World Cup in October.</li>
<li>The governance of the AIFF had similarly been transferred to a CoA by the Supreme Court.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Delhi HC case</h4>
<ul>
<li>The high court had passed the order on a petition seeking a direction for redrafting of the IOA constitution in accordance with the National Sports Code, 2021.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Controversy with IOC</h4>
<ul>
<li>According to IOC rules, if any national body is governed by a non-elected body, it is seen as interference by a third party.</li>
<li>The moment the CoA takes charge, there is 99 per cent chance that India and our sportspersons will get suspended from all international events and Olympic Games.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Olympics and India</h4>
<ul>
<li>India first participated in the Olympics in 1900 in Paris.</li>
<li>The country was represented by Norman Pritchard, an Anglo Indian who was holidaying in Paris during that time.</li>
<li>The seeds for creation of an organisation for coordinating the Olympic movement in India was related to India’s participation in the 1920 and 1924 Olympics.</li>
<li>Back then, Sir Dorabji Tata suggested the need for a Sports body at National level for promoting Olympic Sport in united India.</li>
<li>After the 1920 Games, the Committee sending the team to these Games met, and, on the advice of Sir Dorabji Tata, invited Dr. A.G. Noehren (Physical Education Director of YMCA India) to also join them.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Establishment of Indian Olympic Association (IOA)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Subsequently, in 1923-24, a provisional All India Olympic Committee was set-up, which organised the All India Olympic Games in February 1924.</li>
<li>Eight athletes from these Games were selected to represent India at the 1924 Paris Summer Olympics, accompanied by manager Harry Crowe Buck.</li>
<li>This gave impetus to the development and institutionalization of sports in India, and, in 1927, the Indian Olympic Association (IOA) was formed, with Sir Dorabji Tata as its founding President and Dr. A.G. Noehren as Secretary.</li>
<li>The same year as it was formed, 1927, the Indian Olympic Association was officially recognised by the International Olympic Committee.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="cItjbZQe0Z"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/better-time-for-sports-in-india-pm/">Better time for Sports in India: PM</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="cItjbZQe0Z" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/better-time-for-sports-in-india-pm/embed/#?secret=0nFyJRmfx4#?secret=cItjbZQe0Z" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“Better time for Sports in India: PM” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indian-olympic-association-ioa/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Labour policies need to change for better quality livelihoods</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/labour-policies-need-to-change-for-better-quality-livelihoods/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Universal basic income.</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Social security ,Inclusive growth.</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-623256" height="356" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 521px) 100vw, 521px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/labour-300x205.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/labour-300x205.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/labour.jpg 660w" width="521"/>Context</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>One of the biggest economic fallout of the pandemic has been the deteriorating labour market conditions.</li>
<li>Given the ebb and flow of the pandemic, the growth recovery is likely to be fragmented and will weigh on the number and types of jobs available.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What is quality and sustainable livelihood?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>“A livelihood comprises the capabilities, assets and activities required for a means of living. A livelihood is sustainable when it can cope with and recover from stresses and shocks and maintain or enhance its capabilities and assets both now and in the future, while not undermining the natural resource base.’’</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Sustainable livelihoods objectives</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>improved access to high-quality education, information, technologies and training and better nutrition and health;</li>
<li>a more supportive and cohesive social environment;</li>
<li>more secure access to, and better management of, natural resources;</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Definition of labour welfare </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Labour welfare relates to taking care of the well-being of workers by employers, trade unions, governmental and non-governmental institutions and agencies.</li>
<li>Welfare includes anything that is done for the comfort and improvement of employees and is provided over and above the wages.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Why labour law is needed </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Labour law aims to correct the imbalance of power between the worker and the employer; to prevent the employer from dismissing the worker without good cause; to set up and preserve the processes by which workers are recognized as ‘equal’ partners in negotiations about their working conditions etc<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Constitutional mandate </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Article 41</strong> – The state shall within the limits of its economic capacity and development make effective provision for securing the right to work, to education and to public assistance in cases of unemployment, old age, sickness and disablement and in other cases of underserved want.</li>
<li><strong>Article 42</strong> – The state shall make provision for securing just and humane conditions of work and for maternity relief.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Challenges in labour welfare in India </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Technical glitches:</strong> Under the Constitution of India, Labour is a subject in the concurrent list where both the Central and State Governments are competent to enact legislations. As a result, a large number of labour laws have been enacted catering to different aspects of labour e.g. occupational health, safety, employment etc.</li>
<li><strong>Loopholes:</strong> Because of the predominantly heavy handed labour regulations (also called as Inspector Raj) with exploitable gaps, the MNCs and domestic organizations have resorted to alternate ways i.e. employing contract labour at less than half the payroll of a permanent employee.</li>
<li><strong>Gaps in labour laws:</strong> One of the main reasons for labour reforms is the concept of contract labour. Trade Unions suggest that this concept itself should be removed. There is stringent hiring and firing process defined in Industry Disputes Act. It makes it mandatory for the organization to seek Government permission before removing an employee.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Global best practices  </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Universal basic income pilot project:</strong> For two years Finland’s government gave 2,000 unemployed citizens €560 a month with no strings attached. It was the first nationwide basic income experiment. The concept is slowly becoming difficult for people to ignore.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>How will dynamic policies and labour codes respond?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Labour productivity</strong>: It is likely to improve with both employees and employers developing a sense of being partners in wealth creation.</li>
<li><strong>Labour reform</strong>: A transparent environment in terms of workers’ compensation, clear definition of employee rights and employer duties.</li>
<li><strong>Compliance un-burdening</strong>: Simplified labour codes making compliance easier are likely to attract investments.</li>
<li><strong>Formalization of the economy</strong>: With more workers in the organized sector, leakage in terms of direct as well as indirect taxes may be plugged.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The guiding principle for India’s labour policy reformers should not merely be ring fencing jobs but safeguarding workers through <strong>social assistance, re-employment</strong> support (such as that which is provided in several Western nations) and <strong>skill building</strong>, and supporting employers in employee training and development.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. Why there is need to make labour policies more dynamic? Do you think universal basic income approach will be the best way forward for achieving quality livelihood?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/labour-policies-need-to-change-for-better-quality-livelihoods/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Species in news: Great Indian Bustard</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/species-great-indian-bustard/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Great Indian Bustard</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-623258" height="274" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/bst-300x274.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/bst-300x274.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/bst.jpg 669w" width="300"/></strong></p>
<p>The critically endangered Great Indian Bustard (GIB) has adopted an altogether new behaviour of giving clutch of two eggs at a time after getting additional protein diet during the monsoon season.</p>
<h4>Great Indian Bustards</h4>
<ul>
<li>GIBs are the largest among the four bustard species found in India, the other three being MacQueen’s bustard, lesser florican, and the Bengal florican.</li>
<li>GIBs’ historic range included much of the Indian sub-continent but it has now shrunken to just 10 percent of it. Among the heaviest birds with flight, GIBs prefer grasslands as their habitats.</li>
<li>GIBs are considered the flagship bird species of grassland.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Protection accorded</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Birdlife International:</strong> uplisted from Endangered to Critically Endangered (2011)</li>
<li><strong>Protection under CITES</strong>: Appendix I</li>
<li><strong>IUCN status:</strong> Critically Endangered</li>
<li><strong>Protection under Wildlife (Protection) Act:</strong> Schedule I</li>
</ul>
<h4>Threats</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Overhead power transmission</strong></li>
<li><strong>Poor vision:</strong> Due to their poor frontal vision, can’t detect powerlines in time and their weight makes in-flight quick maneuvers difficult.</li>
<li><strong>Windmills:</strong> Coincidentally, Kutch and Thar desert are the places that have witnessed the creation of huge renewable energy infrastructure.</li>
<li><strong>Noise pollution:</strong> Noise affects the mating and courtship practices of the GIB.</li>
<li><strong>Changes in the landscape:</strong> by way of farmers cultivating their land, which otherwise used to remain fallow due to frequent droughts in Kutch.</li>
<li><strong>Cultivation changes:</strong> Cultivation of cotton and wheat instead of pulses and fodder are also cited as reasons for falling GIB numbers.</li>
</ul>
<h4>On the brink of extinction</h4>
<ul>
<li>The GIB population in India had fallen to just 150.</li>
<li>Pakistan is also believed to host a few GIBs and yet openly supports their hunting.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Supreme Court’s intervention</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court has ordered that all overhead power transmission lines in core and potential GIB habitats in Rajasthan and Gujarat should be undergrounded.</li>
<li>The SC also formed a three-member committee to help power companies comply with the order.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conservation measures</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2015, the Central government launched the GIB species recovery program.</li>
<li>Under the program, the WII and Rajasthan Forest departments have jointly set up conservation breeding centers where GIB eggs are harvested from the wild.</li>
<li>They have been incubated artificially and hatchlings raised in a controlled environment.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ</h4>
<p><strong>Q.Consider the following pairs:</strong></p>
<p><strong>Protected Area: Well-known for </strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Bhiterkanika, Odisha — Salt Water Crocodile</li>
<li>Desert National Park, Rajasthan — Great Indian Bustard</li>
<li>Eravikulam, Kerala — Hoolock Gibbon</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Which of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched? (CSP 2014)</strong></p>
<p>(a) 1 only</p>
<p>(b) 1 and 2</p>
<p>(c) 2 only</p>
<p>(d) 1, 2 and 3</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/species-great-indian-bustard/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Mystery of milk price going up when WPI inflation is down</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mystery-of-milk-price-going-up-when-wpi-inflation-is-down/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Milk inflation</p></div></div><p>Milk prices are rising, as producers and marketers pass on higher costs to consumers.  Amul and Mother Dairy raised milk prices by ₹2 each this week, the second such hike this year.</p>
<h4>Why are milk prices going up?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>High operating cost:</strong> For dairy companies and cooperatives, the cost of operation and production of milk has increased.</li>
<li><strong>Fodder price hike:</strong> Prices of cattle feed, which includes maize, wheat and soybean, are up 20% over the year.</li>
<li><strong>High procurement cost:</strong> Given the rise in input costs, its member unions from where it procures milk have increased farmers’ price in the range of 8-9% year-on-year.</li>
<li><strong>Cost sharing:</strong> In an already inflationary environment, dairies are compelled to pass on price increases to consumers as procurement prices go up.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Has demand for milk picked up as well?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A better rate of vaccination, resumption of offices, schools and even opening up of channels such as hotels and restaurants have led to higher out-of-home consumption of foods and beverages in the last two to three quarters.</li>
<li>This has led to greater demand for milk and other dairy beverages.</li>
<li>Analysts cited higher skimmed milk prices in the international markets that they said make exports of the commodity out of India more attractive.</li>
<li>A combination of these factors is pushing up milk procurement prices, and leading to higher retail prices.</li>
</ul>
<h4>But isn’t wholesale inflation cooling down nowadays?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Yes; India’s wholesale price-based inflation eased to 13.93% in July.</li>
<li>In fact, <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/concept-of-inflation-deflation-wpi-cpi-iip/">WPI</a> inflation in milk eased in July to 5.45% compared  to  6.35%  in  June,  though it remained high compared to February.</li>
<li>However, companies also pass on hikes with a lag to lessen the impact on demand. Amul says the increase is less than 4% — below the food inflation rate of 8-9%.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When will milk prices cool down?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Milk procurement is also dependent on the flush season that runs between September to February.</li>
<li>This is the peak lactating period for cattle due to better availability of green fodder and water.</li>
<li>As a result, the period in general sees higher milk production and availability.</li>
<li>The onset of  the  flush  season  could offer some relief to dairy companies in the second half of the current fiscal year.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What does this mean for consumers?</h4>
<ul>
<li>For households, an  increase  in milk prices obviously means shelling out more money; this in a country that is among largest consumers of milk.</li>
<li>In fact,  by July,  dairy companies had raised milk selling prices by 5-8% in a six-month window.</li>
<li>Consumer demand typically sees an impact in the first few days after price hikes are initiated. However, recovery happens gradually.</li>
<li>Consequently, higher milk procurement prices could also hurt companies that make bakery products or food items that use milk or milk solids.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Also read</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="8WGId0RAeu"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/concept-of-inflation-deflation-wpi-cpi-iip/">Concept of Inflation/Deflation/WPI/CPI/IIP</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="8WGId0RAeu" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/concept-of-inflation-deflation-wpi-cpi-iip/embed/#?secret=OhM3d1XKbJ#?secret=8WGId0RAeu" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“Concept of Inflation/Deflation/WPI/CPI/IIP” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/mystery-of-milk-price-going-up-when-wpi-inflation-is-down/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Thin line between freebies and public welfare</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/thin-line-between-freebies-and-public-welfare/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Social security,Populist measures.</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-623266" height="268" sizes="(max-width: 536px) 100vw, 536px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/frb-1-300x150.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/frb-1-300x150.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/frb-1-768x384.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/frb-1.jpg 832w" width="536"/>Context</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>‘Revdi Culture’ (sweet) or Govt’s Basic Responsibility? What Prioritising Welfare Is Really About</li>
<li>While hearing a petition demanding the de-recognition of political parties that promise “irrational freebies” to voters, the Supreme Court recently drew attention to the substantial fiscal cost of freebies.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What are freebies? </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>A freebie is any public policy intervention that will have a long-term impact on production as well as productivity.</li>
<li>Any public policy intervention that doesn’t support medium-term to long-term production and productivity may be termed as a freebie.</li>
<li>The term Freebies is not new; rather it is a prevalent culture in Indian politics (in the name of socialism).</li>
<li>The political parties are always trying to outdo each other in luring the Indian voters with</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Examples of freebies</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Promise of Rs 15 lakh in our bank accounts</li>
<li>Free TV, Laptops</li>
<li>Free electricity</li>
<li>Loan waivers</li>
<li>Offering free public transport ride to all women in Delhi</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Why are such policies popular among the public?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Failure of economic</strong> policies: The answer lies in the utter failure of our economic policies to create decent livelihood for a vast majority of Indians.</li>
<li><strong>Quest for decent livelihood</strong>: The already low income had to be reoriented towards spending a disproportionately higher amount on education and health, from which, the state increasingly withdrew.</li>
<li><strong>Prevailing unemployment</strong>:  Employment surveys have shown that employment growth initially slowed down from the 1990s, and then has turned negative over the past few years.</li>
<li><strong>Increased cost of living:</strong> Real income growth of the marginal sections has actually slowed down since 1991 reforms.</li>
<li><strong>Increased consumerism</strong>: The poor today also spend on things which appear to be luxuries; cellphones and data-packs are two such examples which are shown as signs of India’s increased affluence.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Thin line between freebie and public welfare </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Using freebies to lure voters is not good.</li>
<li>Voter’s greediness may lead to a problem in choosing a good leader.</li>
<li>When we don’t have a good leader then democracy will be a mockery.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Negative implications </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Never ending trail</strong>: The continuity of freebies is another major disadvantage as parties keep on coming up with lucrative offers to lure more number of votes to minimize the risk of losing in the elections.</li>
<li><strong>Burden on exchequer</strong>: People forget that such benefits are been given at the cost of exchequer and from the tax paid.</li>
<li><strong>Ultimate loss of poors</strong>: The politicians and middlemen wipe away the benefits and the poor have to suffer as they are deprived from their share of benefits which was to be achieved out of the money.</li>
<li><strong>Inflationary practice</strong>: Such distribution freebie commodity largely disrupts demand-supply dynamics.</li>
<li><strong>Lethargy in population:</strong> Freebies actually have the tendency to turn the nation’s population into: Lethargy and devoid of entrepreneurship.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Rational elements in freebies </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Social investment:</strong><strong> </strong>Aid to the poor is seen as a wasteful expenditure. But low interest rates for corporates to get cheap loans or the ‘sop’ of cutting corporate taxes are never criticized.</li>
<li><strong>Socialistic policy:</strong><strong> </strong>This attitude comes from decades of operating within the dominant discourse of market capitalism.</li>
<li><strong>Election manifesto</strong>: Proponents of such policies would argue that poll promises are essential for voters to know what the party would do if it comes to power and have the chance to weigh options.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Why they need to stop?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Winning election and good governance are two different things. The role of freebies to avail good governance is definitely questionable.</li>
<li>The social, political and economic consequences of freebies are very short-lived in nature.</li>
<li>There are many freebies and subsidies schemes available in many States but we still find starvation deaths, lack of electricity, poor education and health service.</li>
<li>Hence the sorrow of the masses of India cannot be solved by freebies or by incentives<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is nothing wrong in having a policy-led elaborate social security programme that seeks to help the poor get out of poverty.</li>
<li>But such a programme needs well thought out preparation and cannot be conjured up just before an election.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Do you think freebies are justified under the name of social security? Critically evaluate the rising freebie culture in India with its negative implications.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> <a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/thin-line-between-freebies-and-public-welfare/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>