<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 01:11:07 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Without social justice constructive women empowerment is a futile exercise here is why</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-empowerment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Women empowerment</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637728" height="341" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609-768x447.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609.jpg 1000w" width="585"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Despite notable progress in closing the gender pay gap over time in India, the gap remains high by international standards. Asymmetries still abound in the country’s labor market stopping women empowerment .</li>
<li>Time to reassess the progress made in to close the Gender pay gap.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The third International Equal Pay Day is observed globally on September 18, 2022.</li>
<li>It is a United Nations-recognized event to highlight the issue of gender pay gap.</li>
<li>International Labor Organization’s “Global Wage Report 2020–21” which suggests the crisis inflicted massive downward pressure on wages and disproportionately affected women’s total wages compared to</li>
<li>This greater wage reduction for women means that the pre-existing gender pay gap has widened.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637732" height="325" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200.jpg 1200w" width="584"/>Covid-19 Impact</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While it is difficult to tell exactly what the economic damage from the global covid-19 pandemic has been, it is clear that its impact has been uneven, with women being among the worst affected in terms of their income security.</li>
<li>Many women reverted to full-time care of children and the elderly during the pandemic, foregoing their livelihoods to do so.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is gender pay gap?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The gender pay gap or gender wage gap measures the difference between the average earnings of women and men in the workforce.</li>
<li>In simple term it is a measure of what women are paid relative to men.</li>
<li>Women are generally found to be paid less than men.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is the gender pay gap?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Education: </strong>low investment o girl education<strong>, </strong>Girl children are kept out of schools, or made drop out of school at early age, girl is considered as burden on family in many societies.</li>
<li><strong>workforce </strong>: even if they are educated they are not allowed to work by their families, very limited or no decision making power, lack of women friendly work environment, discriminatory practices at workplaces.</li>
<li><strong>Household:</strong> early marriage , responsibilities of the household at early age , spending more times on domestic chores,</li>
<li><strong>Healthcare: </strong>malnutrition, anemia, Maternity, child care, looking after health of the elderly family members etc.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p>These are some of the reasons which affect education, skills, experience and the career prospectus of women as compared to men and contribute to widen the gender wage gap.</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637730" height="297" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 100vw, 527px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India.jpg 1919w" width="527"/>Discrimination as factor</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A part of gender pay gap attributed to education, skills or experience, a large part of the gender pay gap can still purely because of discrimination based on one’s gender or sex.</li>
<li>Gender-based discriminatory practices include: lower wages paid to women for work of equal value; undervaluation of women’s work in highly feminized occupations and enterprises, and motherhood pay gap lower wages for mothers compared to non-mother.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637734" height="466" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 837px) 100vw, 837px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1.jpg 1200w" width="837"/>Status in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The gender pay gap in India is among the widest in the world.</li>
<li>Indian women earned, on an average, 48% less compared to their male counterparts in 1993-94</li>
<li>According to labor force survey data of the National Sample Survey Office (NSSO) gap declined to 28% in 2018-19.</li>
<li>Periodic Labor Force Survey (PLFS) 2020-21 show an increase in the gap by 7% between 2018-19 and 2020-21.</li>
<li>Recently, the World Economic Forum (WEF) ranked India at 135 out of 146 countries in its Global Gender Gap (GGG) Index for 2022.</li>
<li>According to the estimates of the World Inequality Report 2022, in India, men earn 82 per cent of the labor income whereas women earn 18 per cent of it.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637731" height="392" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 696px) 100vw, 696px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8477553337_67c076bed2_o-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8477553337_67c076bed2_o-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8477553337_67c076bed2_o.jpg 639w" width="696"/>Steps taken by India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Minimum Wages Act in 1948</strong>: It is an act of parliament<strong>, </strong>aimed at statutory fixation of minimum wages that must be paid to skilled and unskilled labours. Payment of wages below the minimum wage rate amounts to forced labour.</li>
<li><strong>Equal Remuneration Act in 1976: </strong>This act of parliament provides for the payment of equal remuneration to men and women workers for the prevention of discrimination. It helps in bridging the gap between unequal remuneration faced by the women of our country.</li>
<li><strong>Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA) 2005:</strong> MGNREGA contributed to the rapid rise in overall rural and agricultural wages in the country. It benefited rural women workers and helped reduce the gender pay gap, both directly and indirectly. Directly, by raising the pay levels of women workers and indirectly to women involved in agricultural occupations through higher earnings.</li>
<li><strong>The Maternity Benefit (Amendment) Act 2017</strong>: has increased the duration of paid maternity leave available for women employees to 26 weeks from 12 weeks for all women working in establishments employing 10 or more workers. This is expected to reduce the motherhood pay gap among mothers in the median and high end wage earners working in the formal economy also it will help in women empowerment.</li>
<li><strong>Skill India Mission</strong>: To equip women with market-relevant skills to bridge the learning to-livelihood gap and the gender pay gap.</li>
<li>In 2019, India carried out comprehensive reforms in both the legislation and enacted the Code on Wages.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While the gender pay gap is slowly narrowing, acceleration and bold actions to prevent the widening of gender pay gap is the need of the hour.</li>
<li>Equal pay for work of equal value is necessary to close the gender pay gap.</li>
<li>Closing the gender pay gap is key to achieving <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/women-empowerment-issues-jobsreservation-education/">social justice for working women</a>, as well as economic growth for the nation as a whole</li>
<li>Without social justice women empowerment is a futile exercise.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Define gender equality .Equal pay for equal work is necessary to bridge the gender pay gap India .Comment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-empowerment/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Asian Palm Oil Alliance (APOA) formed by 5 South Asian Countries</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/asian-palm-oil-alliance-apoa-formed-by-5-south-asian-countries/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Palm Oil, APOA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>Edible oil trade associations from five palm oil importing countries in South Asia – India, Pakistan, Sri Lanka, Bangladesh and Nepal – on Thursday announced the setting up of Asian Palm Oil Alliance (APOA).</p>
<h4><strong>What is Oil Palm?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Palm oil is an edible vegetable oil derived from the mesocarp of the fruit of the oil palms.</li>
<li>The oil is used in food manufacturing, in beauty products, and as biofuel.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is APOA?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Through APOA, the countries aim at safeguarding the economic and business interests of the palm oil consuming countries and will work towards increasing the consumption of palm oil in member countries.</li>
<li>The idea is to gain collecting bargaining power and make imports sustainable.</li>
<li>APOA held its first general body meeting on the side-lines of the Globoil Summit.</li>
<li>The industry associations of Asian palm oil importing countries, unlike their counterparts in Europe, are not involved in shaping the global discourse on sustainable palm oil in a collective way.</li>
<li>The alliance would work towards ensuring that palm oil is recognised as a high-quality, economical, and healthy vegetable oil and to change the negative image of palm oil.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why such move?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s annual imports of edible oil is around 13-14 million tonne (MT).</li>
<li>Around 8 MT of palm oil is imported from Indonesia and Malaysia, while other oils, such as soya and sunflower, come from Argentina, Brazil, Ukraine and Russia.</li>
<li>Asia accounts for around 40% of the global palm oil consumption while Europe accounts for 12% of palm oil trade.</li>
<li>Indonesia and Malaysia are the biggest palm oil exporters in the world.</li>
<li>India is the largest importer of palm oil in Asia, accounting for 15% of global imports, followed by China (9%), Pakistan (4%) and Bangladesh (2%).</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ:</h4>
<p><strong>Q.Among the agricultural commodities imported by India, which one of the following accounts for the highest imports in terms of value in the last five years?</strong></p>
<p>(a) Spices</p>
<p>(b) Fresh fruits</p>
<p>(c) Pulses</p>
<p>(d) Vegetable oils</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/asian-palm-oil-alliance-apoa-formed-by-5-south-asian-countries/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why India Inc. needs a neurodiverse workplace ?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/neurodiverse/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>human right of neuro-diverse people</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="neurodiverse" class="alignnone wp-image-640541" height="562" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 423px) 100vw, 423px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/neurodiversity-226x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/neurodiversity-226x300.jpg 226w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/neurodiversity.jpg 386w" width="423"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Discrimination in employment is a worldwide phenomenon. Gender, ethnic, racist discrimination are well known but discrimination towards neurodiverse persons are hardly debated in public forums. Despite having special abilities companies are not using their potentials.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/what-is-neurodiversity-202111232645#:~:text=The%20word%20neurodiversity%20refers%20to,as%20ADHD%20or%20learning%20disabilities." rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>What is </strong><strong>neurodiversity?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Harvard Health Publishing defines, neurodiversity as a notion that every person interacts and experiences their surroundings differently; there is no right way of thinking, learning, or/and behaving. These differences should not be construed as defects or disorders.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a neuro-diverse workplace?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Neurodiversity in the workplace refers to including people with neuro-divergent conditions such as attention-deﬁcit/hyperactivity disorder, autism spectrum disorders, dyslexia, dyspraxia, dyscalculia and Asperger’s Syndrome.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are those Conditions that make them different from normal humans?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Autism:</strong> A mental condition in which a person finds it difficult to communicate or form relationships with other people. Signs of autism include not responding to their name, avoiding eye contact, not smiling when you smile at them.</li>
<li><strong>Dyslexia:</strong> a difficulty that some people have with reading and spelling signs include confusion over letters that look similar and putting letters the wrong way round , confusing the order of letters in words, reading slowly or making errors when reading aloud</li>
<li><strong>Asperger’s syndrome:</strong> A developmental disorder related to autism and characterized by awkwardness in social interaction, pedantry in speech, and preoccupation with very narrow interests. Less severe symptoms than Autism syndrome.</li>
<li><strong>Dyscalculia:</strong> A brain disorder in which a wide range of difficulties with math, including weaknesses in understanding the meaning of numbers, and difficulty applying mathematical principles to solve problems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="neurodiverse" class="alignnone wp-image-640542" height="373" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 622px) 100vw, 622px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2869adc7-4764-4e36-8262-2e9c6a04820a-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2869adc7-4764-4e36-8262-2e9c6a04820a-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2869adc7-4764-4e36-8262-2e9c6a04820a.jpg 600w" width="622"/>How they can be naturally efficient and creative?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>More efficient: </strong>Studies have shown that teams with both neurodivergent and neurotypical members are far more efficient than teams that comprise neurotypical employees alone.</li>
<li><strong>Ability to focus: </strong>Neurodivergent individuals possess excellent attention to detail and an uncanny ability to focus on complex and repetitive tasks over a more extended period than their neurotypical peers.</li>
<li><strong>Ability to work at faster speed: </strong>A study by the University of Montreal found that in a test involving completing a visual pattern, people on the autism spectrum could finish their task 40% faster than those who were not on the spectrum.</li>
<li><strong>Robust spatial reasoning</strong>: People with dyslexia can think about objects in three dimensions and analyses such objects even with limited information.</li>
<li><strong>Out of box thinking</strong>: They have problem-solving capabilities which allow them to see multiple solutions to a problem. They are often out-of-the-box thinkers with average or above-average intelligence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Current Status of people living with neurodivergent conditions</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>People suffer with the Condition: </strong>According to a recent report, nearly 2 million people in India suffer from this neurological and developmental disorder and are therefore identified as autistic. Another study by Deloitte estimates that nearly 20% of the world is neurodiverse. In the U.S., it is estimated that 85% of people on the autism spectrum are unemployed compared with 4.2% of the overall population</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-discrimination-report/"><strong>Discrimination at employment</strong>:</a> Even with all the necessary skill sets and degrees, these persons are denied a job because they may react to situations differently from non-neurodiverse persons.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of awareness: </strong>Lack of awareness about neurodivergent conditions, and how the people with condition may react and lack of and accommodating environment. Hence, there is an urgency to create a work environment that welcomes neurodiverse individuals<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="neurodiverse" class="alignnone wp-image-640543" height="371" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 589px) 100vw, 589px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-300x189.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-300x189.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-1024x646.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-768x484.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-1536x969.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic-1200x757.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Neurodiversity-graphic.jpg 1903w" width="589"/>Current work profile of companies and workplaces</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A 2019 McKinsey study revealed that companies with gender diversity were 25% more likely to have above-average profitability while those with ethnic diversity out-rival their competitors by 36%.</li>
<li>Another report titled ‘India’s Best Workplaces in Diversity, Equity &amp; Inclusion 2021’ states that diverse teams perform better, boost leadership integrity, heighten trust in the organization’s management and multiply revenue growth.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="neurodiverse" class="alignnone wp-image-640544" height="392" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960x0-300x201.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960x0-300x201.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960x0-768x514.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/960x0.jpg 959w" width="585"/>Few Examples show that things are changing</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Competitive environment</strong>: Organisations embracing neurodiversity enjoy a competitive edge in several areas such as efficiency, creativity, and culture.</li>
<li><strong>Various MNC’s hiring program</strong>: Companies such as Deloitte, Microsoft, SAP, JPMorgan Chase, and E&amp;Y have introduced neurodiversity hiring programs.</li>
<li><strong>Indian company: </strong>Indian-origin companies Hatti Kaapi and Lemon Tree Hotels have also included a neurodiverse workforce.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to create more inclusive workplaces?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Creating neurodivergent friendly offices</strong>: .Many employees with neurodiversity may find the hustle and bustle of a traditional office disturbing. Therefore, neurodivergent friendly offices catering to the employees’ diverse sensory responses can help ensure that these employees are comfortable in office spaces.</li>
<li><strong>Openness:</strong> Creating the right environment is an ever-evolving exercise that requires openness and a will to change on the employer’s part. This flexibility can result in exceptional benefit with minimal or no additional costs.</li>
<li><strong>Wider Inclusivity</strong>: To ensure higher profitability and be respected as a responsible employer globally, companies need to widen their definition of inclusivity by providing higher participation of a neurodiverse workforce.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Organizations must not only remove barriers that obstruct the progress of such individuals but also create conducive conditions for them to achieve their true potential and providing proper infrastructure so that they can perform at their optimal levels.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. People with neurodiversity are discriminated not only socially but also economically, Comment. What measures could be taken to bridge this gap within the society?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/neurodiverse/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Soft power, the new race every country wants to win</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/soft-power/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>na</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Soft power</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="soft power" class="alignnone wp-image-640548" height="224" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 533px) 100vw, 533px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/quote-the-image-of-a-country-is-not-just-about-economic-and-military-strength-the-soft-face-narendra-modi-130-43-87-300x126.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/quote-the-image-of-a-country-is-not-just-about-economic-and-military-strength-the-soft-face-narendra-modi-130-43-87-300x126.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/quote-the-image-of-a-country-is-not-just-about-economic-and-military-strength-the-soft-face-narendra-modi-130-43-87-768x323.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/quote-the-image-of-a-country-is-not-just-about-economic-and-military-strength-the-soft-face-narendra-modi-130-43-87.jpg 843w" width="533"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Increased interest, especially by smaller nations in the world, in investing more and doing well in elite sports in international sporting events boosts a nation’s chances of attaining soft power.</li>
<li>India’s medal tally at recent International sports events demonstrate the country’s soft power on the global stage and encourage working towards the status of a great “geopolitical actor”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.bridgeindia.org.uk/the-rise-of-india-as-a-global-soft-power/" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>What is soft power?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Origin:</strong>
<ul>
<li>As far back as the 4<sup>th</sup> century BC, Kautilya (chankyaniti) had propounded the concept of Saam(advice or cajole),daam(pay or bribe),dand(punish),bhed(exploit secrets) which acquired western touch and can be understood by Soft power, smart power, hard power, and sharp power respectively.</li>
<li>Joseph Nye introduced the concept of “soft power” in the late 1980s. For Nye, power is the ability to influence the behavior of others to get the outcomes you want.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Meaning:</strong></li>
<li>Soft power is the ability of a country to persuade others to do what it wants without force or coercion.</li>
<li>Soft power is the ability to influence the behavior of others to get the outcomes you want.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="soft power" class="alignnone wp-image-640547" height="327" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 491px) 100vw, 491px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1332880749.jpg 1200w" width="491"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-yoga-indias-soft-power/">Why Soft power is so significant?</a></strong></h4>
<p>Use of ‘Soft Power’ includes the number of cultural missions such as language schools, Olympic Medals and the quality of a country’s overall growth. Soft power produces following things:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Familiarity</strong>: If people know more about your country, culture, sports, and its talents, businesses, and resources, then soft power is enhanced.</li>
<li><strong>Reputation</strong>: For a nation to be attractive and a role model for others, its overall reputation must be strong and positive.</li>
<li><strong>Influence</strong>: A direct measure of the perceived presence and impact that your country has in other countries</li>
<li><strong>Business/Innovation/Sports</strong>: The attractiveness of a country’s economic model, its digital engagement with the world, performance in sports etc.</li>
<li><strong>Government</strong>: Showcases the ability of country’s political leadership and what it delivers to its people in different arenas.</li>
<li><strong>Multi-Alignment:</strong> As a country rises up the ‘Soft Power’ list, more and more outside parties align themselves with the common goals of that country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why the Sports being used as a tool of soft power in modern international relations?</strong></h4>
<p>Sport can be used as tool of soft power both internationally and domestically.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>International platform</strong>: Sports provide a platform for countries to showcase their culture, values and tradition.</li>
<li><strong>Puts a Better image of a country</strong>: Sports as a tool to achieve social, political, and financial goals, and improve the image of the country<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>International exposure: </strong>The focus on culture and peaceful values in sports make it a useful tool for countries to use soft power to achieve international goals and improve their public diplomacy.</li>
<li><strong>Reducing differences</strong>: Sports provides a platform for trust-building; and reconciliation, integration and anti-racism.</li>
<li><strong>Learning from China’s Case</strong>:</li>
<li>Dongfeng Liu (International Professor of Sport Management) in his survey on China’s performance in the Olympics he found that a country’s Olympic achievement has a positive effect on its national soft power.</li>
<li>As china is a communist country and reputation about human rights is not good, so China uses its superiority in elite sports to build “people-to-people” relations with other countries. For example, athletes from African countries such as Madagascar are trained in swimming, badminton, table tennis, etc. in China, which helps Beijing create a positive impact on a wider population and result in better formal relations as well.</li>
<li>There is also China’s memorandum of understanding with countries such as Kenya so that Chinese runners can train with Kenyan athletes, as they are among the best in the world when it comes to long-distance running.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="soft power" class="alignnone wp-image-640550" height="512" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/80906-yutjpg-1554537206-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/80906-yutjpg-1554537206-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/80906-yutjpg-1554537206.jpg 640w" width="683"/>Introspection on India’s performance at recent International Sports events</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is being said that the golden period of Indian sports may have begun as at the Tokyo Olympics and then the Birmingham 2022 Commonwealth Games (CWG) are examples of a good performance.</li>
<li>India’s medal tally in the Tokyo Olympics Games — seven — was its most decorated Olympic Games in Indian history.</li>
<li>At the Commonwealth games (CWG) 2022, Indian athletes won 61 medals, including 22 gold.</li>
<li>India has one of the world’s poorest population-to-medal ratios when it comes to the Olympics.</li>
<li>Ensuring competent coaches, and having adequate funding and more sports academics still remain major issues even decades later</li>
<li>India spends only three paise per day per capita on sports. In contrast China spends 1 per day per capita.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What can be done to increase the country’s sporting performance and soft power</strong><strong>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Train Indian players overseas:</strong></li>
<li>India should concentrate on forging MoUs with nations that excel in specific sports and train Indian players overseas.</li>
<li>For example, Australia and the United Kingdom can assist us in swimming given their standing here.</li>
<li>When it comes to running, negotiating collaborative training agreements with African countries such as Kenya would be ideal.</li>
<li><strong>No Politics over assistance: </strong></li>
<li>There should be no politics in seeking or even offering assistance.</li>
<li>For example China has requested Indian assistance in improving cricket development in China (Chongqing city).</li>
<li><strong>Private Investment</strong>:</li>
<li>Private investment needs to be harnessed to develop infrastructure. The better a country performs in sporting events the greater a sports person’s interest in their sports atmosphere. This also creates a huge market for private players to invest in.</li>
<li>For example, leading corporate houses in India have already shown how their active participation and investment can improve sporting performance as a result of unique corporate sports programmes.</li>
<li><strong>Public –private partnership at grass root :</strong></li>
<li>The Government should also work on a public-private partnership (PPP) model to create basic sporting infrastructure.</li>
<li>As recommended by NITI Aayog, at the district level too so that talent can be captured at an early stage.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sports as a tool of soft power had always been a key element of leadership from the ancient times. Sports provide an international platform to develop an attitude of unity in a divided multi-polar modern world.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Sports provide an international platform to develop an attitude of unity and influence others in a divided multi-polar modern world. Discuss in this context that soft power is not an end but a means to an end.</strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p></blockquote>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/soft-power/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>In news: Rotterdam Convention</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rotterdam-convention-chemicals-pic/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Rotterdam convention, PIC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>International trade of two new hazardous pesticides — Iprodione and Terbufos — has been recommended for “prior informed consent” (PIC) procedure under the Rotterdam convention.</p>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In India, the use of these chemicals was permitted by the 2015 Anupam Verma committee report. The country is among the largest exporters of Terbufos.</li>
<li>The chemicals are dangerous for humans and aquatic animals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Rotterdam Convention</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Rotterdam Convention is formally known as the Convention on the Prior Informed Consent Procedure for Certain Hazardous Chemicals and Pesticides in International Trade.</li>
<li>It is a multilateral treaty to promote shared responsibilities in relation to importation of hazardous chemicals.</li>
<li>The convention promotes open exchange of information and calls on exporters of hazardous chemicals to use proper labelling, include directions on safe handling, and inform purchasers of any known restrictions or bans.</li>
<li>Signatory nations can decide whether to allow or ban the importation of chemicals listed in the treaty, and exporting countries are obliged to make sure that producers within their jurisdiction comply.</li>
<li>India is a party to the convention, with 161 other parties.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Prior Informed Consent (PIC) procedure?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PIC procedure is a mechanism for formally obtaining and disseminating the decisions of importing parties on their willingness to receive future shipments of hazardous chemicals.</li>
<li>The PIC procedure is a mechanism for formally obtaining and disseminating the decisions of importing Parties as to whether they wish to receive future shipments of those chemicals listed in the Convention.</li>
<li>For each of the chemicals listed in Annex III and subject to the PIC procedure a decision guidance document (DGD) is prepared and sent to all Parties.</li>
<li>All Parties are required to take a decision as to whether or not they will allow future import of each of the chemicals in Annex III of the Convention.</li>
<li>These decisions are known as import responses.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Which are the new chemicals listed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Iprodione, a fungicide used on vines, fruits, trees and vegetables, has been classified as carcinogenic and toxic for reproduction.</li>
<li>Terbufos is a soil insecticide used commonly on sorghum, maize, beet and potatoes. It has also been found to pose risk to aquatic organisms due to its toxicity.</li>
<li>Both pesticides, which are used in agriculture, are known for their harmful impacts on human health and the environment.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rotterdam-convention-chemicals-pic/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>PM Modi pitches for ‘Full Transit Right’ among SCO members</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pm-modi-pitches-for-full-transit-right-among-sco-members/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>International North–South Transport Corridor (INSTC)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>With Pakistan PM listening, Prime Minister Modi urged <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/iran-belarus-to-be-newest-sco-members/">Shanghai Cooperation Organisation</a> member states to “give each other full right to transit”.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>PM Modi framed the <strong><u>right to transit in the context of connectivity</u></strong> and how it could help establish reliable and resilient supply chains in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did PM pitch this?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lack of <strong><u>transit across Pakistan’s territory has been a challenge for India</u></strong> to access Central Asian markets.</li>
<li>Iran’s President also said that despite the impressive potential, infrastructural connections in the <strong><u>field of transit between members of the SCO are not so extensive.</u></strong></li>
<li>Iran already provides special priority to the development of the North-South Corridor and has made huge investments.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is International North-South Transport Corridor (INSTC)?</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-637170" height="259" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 411px) 100vw, 411px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/instc--300x189.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/instc--300x189.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/instc-.jpg 580w" width="411"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The INSTC is a <strong><u>7,200 km-long multimodal transportation network</u></strong> encompassing <strong><u>sea, road, and rail routes</u></strong> to offer the shortest route of connectivity.</li>
<li>It was <strong><u>established on 12th September 2000 in St. Petersburg</u></strong>, <strong><u>by Iran, Russia and India</u></strong> for the purpose of promoting transportation cooperation among the Member States.</li>
<li>It links the <strong><u>Indian Ocean to the Caspian Sea via the Persian Gulf</u></strong> onwards into Russia and Northern Europe.</li>
<li>It will move freight between India, Iran, Afghanistan, Armenia, Azerbaijan, Russia, Central Asia and Europe.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of INSTC</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Trade facilitation:</strong> INSTC is aimed at reducing the carriage cost between India and Russia by about 30 percent and bringing down the transit time by more than half.</li>
<li><strong>New corridor in making:</strong> It has the potential to transform the economies of countries along the corridor into specialized manufacturing, logistics, and transit hubs by facilitating access to newer markets.</li>
<li><strong>Multimodal transit:</strong> The recent Suez Canal blockade, which cost the global economy hefty damage amounting to US$9 billion, has amplified the optimistic outlook towards the INSTC as a cheaper and faster alternative multimodal transit corridor.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Benefits offered to India</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Export promotion:</strong> The INSTC connects India with Central Asia, and Russia, and has the potential to expand up to the Baltic, Nordic, and Arctic regions, increasing the scope of trade multifold.</li>
<li><strong>Ease of trade:</strong> For India, it provides a shorter trade route with Iran, Russia, and beyond to Europe, creating scope for increased economic engagement.</li>
<li><strong>Alternative Route to Central Asia:</strong> It opens up a permanent alternative route for India to trade with Afghanistan and Central Asia, given the hurdles in the direct route through Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pm-modi-pitches-for-full-transit-right-among-sco-members/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre defers new Foreign Trade Policy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-defers-new-foreign-trade-policy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Foreign Trade Policy</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The government has extended the launch of new Foreign Trade Policy (FTP) (2022-27) by six more months and would continue with the existing one.</p>
<h4><strong>Why such delay in Foreign Trade Policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Geopolitical uncertainty:</strong> The geo-political situation is not suitable for long-term foreign trade policy, said Union Commerce Minister.</li>
<li><strong>Global recession:</strong> Currently, fears of a recession in major economies like the US and Europe have escalated a panic among investors.</li>
<li><strong>Decline in USD inflows:</strong> Foreign investors have begun to pull back their money from equities.</li>
<li><strong>Rupee depreciation:</strong> The US Dollar is at a 22-year high, while the Rupee hit a new all-time low of $81.6.</li>
<li><strong>Huge trade deficit:</strong> The trade deficit widened by more than 2-folds to $125.22 billion (April – August 2022) compared to $53.78 billion in the same period last year.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Foreign Trade Policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s Foreign Trade Policy (FTP) is a set of guidelines for goods and services imported and exported.</li>
<li>These are developed by the Directorate General of Foreign Trade (DGFT), the Ministry of Commerce and Industry’s regulating body for the promotion and facilitation of exports and imports.</li>
<li>FTPs are enforceable under the Foreign Trade Development and Regulation Act 1992.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is India’s Foreign Trade Policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In line with the ‘Make in India,’ ‘Digital India,’ ‘Skill India,’ ‘Startup India,’ and ‘Ease of Doing Business initiatives, the Foreign Trade Policy (2015-20) was launched on April 1, 2015.</li>
<li>It provides a framework for increasing exports of goods and services, creating jobs, and increasing value addition in the country.</li>
<li>The FTP statement outlines the market and product strategy as well as the steps needed to promote trade, expand infrastructure, and improve the entire trade ecosystem.</li>
<li>It aims to help India respond to external problems while staying on top of fast-changing international trading infrastructure and to make trade a major contributor to the country’s economic growth and development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues with FTP (2015-2020)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Acting on Washington’s protest, a WTO dispute settlement panel ruled in 2019 that India’s export <strong><u>subsidy measures are in violation of WTO norms</u></strong> and must be repealed.</li>
<li><strong><u>Tax incentives</u></strong> under the popular <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-rodtep-scheme/">Merchandise Exports from India Scheme (MEIS)</a> (now renamed as RODTEP Scheme)and Service Exports from India Scheme (SEIS) programmes were among them.</li>
<li>The panel found that because India’s per capita gross national product exceeds $1,000 per year, it may no longer grant subsidies based on export performance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>WTO-compliance:</strong> With incentives under MEIS and SEIS in the cloud, WTO-compliant tax benefits are a must.</li>
<li><strong>Access to credit:</strong> Credit availability has long been a need of exporters, particularly MSMEs.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure upgrade:</strong> China’s network of ports, motorways, and high-speed trains, which are among the greatest in the world, is one of the reasons it is a manufacturing and export powerhouse.</li>
<li><strong>Digitization and e-commerce boost:</strong> India requires innovative trading procedures as a result of Covid-19 breaking old supply channels.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-defers-new-foreign-trade-policy/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Sustainable port development promises blue economy to bloom</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/port-development/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Sustainable coast management</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is politically hard, but developmentally critical, to run port development projects with coastal management sustainably.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="port" class="alignnone wp-image-632083" height="314" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 419px) 100vw, 419px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/media-handler.jpg 1200w" width="419"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-ports-development/">What is a port?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A port is a maritime facility comprising one or more wharves or loading areas, where ships load and discharge cargo and passengers. Although usually situated on a sea coast or estuary, ports can also be found far inland, such as Hamburg, Manchester and Duluth; these access the sea via rivers or canals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is meant by port management?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A port management analysis involves an understanding of the port conditions, including intra-port distribution, and routes and hinterland connections outside the port.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why ports are important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Ports infrastructure is key to the development of any nation. India has a coastline spanning about 7,500 km. around 90 percent of India’s external trade by volume and 70 percent by value are handled by ports.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="port" class="alignnone wp-image-632085" height="303" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 502px) 100vw, 502px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Jawaharlal_Nehru_Trust_Port-300x181.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Jawaharlal_Nehru_Trust_Port-300x181.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Jawaharlal_Nehru_Trust_Port.jpg 640w" width="502"/>What are concerns with port projects?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Displacement: </strong>Some 350 families that have lost homes to coastal erosion last year, and those living in makeshift schools and camps are just a foretaste of things to come if coastal erosion and extreme cyclones continue unabated.</li>
<li><strong>Ecological impact</strong>: A further danger is an irreversibly destroyed ecology, triggering deadlier hazards of nature. Ports without adequate safeguards in a highly delicate ecology unleash destruction on marine life and the livelihoods of the local population.</li>
<li><strong>Coastal erosion</strong>: Visakhapatnam and Chennai show how siltation, coastal erosion and accretion can be exacerbated by deepening of harbour channels in ecologically sensitive areas.</li>
<li><strong>Oil spills:</strong> During the operation of ports, spillage or leakages from the loading and unloading of cargo and pollution from oil spills are common due to poor adherence to environmental laws and standards.</li>
<li><strong>Ecosystem threat</strong>: The water discharged during the cleaning of a ship and the discharge of ballast water is a threat to marine ecosystems</li>
<li><strong>Impact on fisheries: </strong>Dredging cause’s environmental problems (increased sedimentation) affecting local productivity of the local waters and its fisheries</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Value addition example </strong></p>
<p>A just published study shows that during 2006-20, the sea gobbled some 2.62 square kilometres or close to 650 acres from the Thiruvananthapuram coast alone.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong><img alt="port" class="alignnone wp-image-632086" height="291" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 455px) 100vw, 455px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1953413479_27757193ef_o-800x512-1-300x192.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1953413479_27757193ef_o-800x512-1-300x192.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1953413479_27757193ef_o-800x512-1-768x492.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1953413479_27757193ef_o-800x512-1.jpg 800w" width="455"/>Steps to take</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Compensation:</strong> The first order of business, as in infrastructure projects worldwide, is that the project provides compensation to the displaced people and restores their rights.</li>
<li><strong>Reversing marine damage:</strong> Second, the gross neglect of the damage to invaluable marine biodiversity must be redressed with an acceptable EIA, including inputs from experts in biology, ecology, and oceanography.</li>
<li><strong>Safeguard to place:</strong> Third, there needs to be an independent assessment of safeguards that port authorities must put in place as a precondition for any further construction.</li>
<li><strong>Blue Economy:</strong>Blue Economy as a concept includes all the economic activities related to oceans, seas, and coastal areas and emerges from a need for integrated conservation and sustainability in the management of the maritime domain.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Master plan</strong>: Countries should adopt a National Long-term Mater plan addressing the aspects of smarter, greener, safer sustainable port development and productivity improvement.</li>
<li><strong>Planning:</strong> Port development and investment should be driven by setting specific and realistic goals, such as building a stable infrastructure focused on reducing trade costs and contribute to achieving sustainable transport.</li>
<li><strong>Cooperation of multiple sectors</strong>: In order to establish a comprehensive port development master plan, cooperation with financial, environmental, technical, energy, transportation and urban development authorities is essential and must reflect the needs of users, including shippers and shipping lines.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To address existing challenges, we should provide research, analysis and technical assistance to help ports and the maritime transport sector especially in developing countries to improve operations and become more sustainable and resilient to crises, including climate change.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. What do you understand by sustainable port development and port productivity? Discuss the challenges in achieving the same along with way forward.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/port-development/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why our urban centres need to be better planned</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-centres/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>smart city mission</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>urban planning</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="urban centres " class="alignnone wp-image-639704" height="677" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 875px) 100vw, 875px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-300x232.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-300x232.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1024x793.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-768x595.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1536x1190.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1162x900.jpg 1162w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1200x929.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1980x1534.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities..jpg 2000w" width="875"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian urban centres need to plan for migration, climate change. Healthcare, affordable housing, sustainability and inclusion hold the key reimagining them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does urban planning mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Urban planning encompasses the preparation of plans for and the regulation and management of towns, cities, and metropolitan regions. It attempts to organize socio-spatial relations across different scales of government and governance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are ‘Happy Cities’?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A term that follows the Green City, Sustainable City, Liveable City, in the lingo of urban planning</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="urban centres " class="alignnone wp-image-639706" height="451" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Kampung_Admiralty_by_Ramboll_Studio_Dreiseitl__WOHA_and_Storm._Image__Patrick_Bingham-Hall_1-300x209.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Kampung_Admiralty_by_Ramboll_Studio_Dreiseitl__WOHA_and_Storm._Image__Patrick_Bingham-Hall_1-300x209.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Kampung_Admiralty_by_Ramboll_Studio_Dreiseitl__WOHA_and_Storm._Image__Patrick_Bingham-Hall_1.jpg 750w" width="647"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/smart-cities-mission-and-the-public-health/">What is a smart city?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A smart city is one that uses information and communication technologies to enhance citizen engagement. It is a neo-vision which seeks to improve the delivery of services in urban areas. The following story maps out the steps being taken by India to explore this concept in practice.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Fast Facts -Urbanization in India</strong></h4>
<p>Most Urbanized States: Tamil Nadu 43.9%; Maharashtra 4%; Gujarat  37.4%.</p>
<p>3 out of world’s 21 mega cities: Mumbai (19 mill); Delhi (15 mill); Kolkata (14 mill)</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Global best practices in urban planning </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garden_city_movement" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>The Garden City movement:</strong> </a>In the West, the Garden City movement (initiated by Ebenezer Howard in 1898) sought to decentralise the working environment in the city centre with a push for providing healthier living spaces for factory workers. The ideal garden city was planned on a concentric pattern with open spaces, public parks and boulevards, housing 32,000 people on 6,000 acres, linked to a central city with over 50,000 people. Once a garden city reached maximum capacity, another city would be developed nearby.</li>
<li><strong>Neighbourhood concept</strong>: In the US, the garden city movement evolved into the neighbourhood concept, where residential houses and streets were organised around a local school or community centre, with a push for lowering traffic and providing safe roads. London has a metropolitan green belt around the city, covering 5,13,860 hectares of land, to offset pollution and congestion and maintain biodiversity. Why can’t Indian cities have something similar, instead of ring roads and urban sprawls?</li>
<li><strong>La ville du quart d’heure: </strong>Paris has taken this forward with the “15-minute city” (‘la ville du quart d’heure’). The idea is rather simple, every Parisian should be able to do their shopping, work, and recreational activities and fulfil their cultural needs within a 15-minute walk or bike ride this means that the number of vehicular trips gets reduced significantly.</li>
<li><strong>Investment in pedestrian infrastructure and non-motorised transport zones</strong>: A city would then be planned for pedestrians, instead of cars and motors. This requires an extensive usage of mixed-use developments, along with investment in pedestrian infrastructure and non-motorised transport zones. Instead of widening highways, this approach would push for widening pedestrian walkways.</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="urban centres " class="alignnone wp-image-639707" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-300x208.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-300x208.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-1024x711.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-768x533.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-1200x833.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000.jpg 1440w" width="560"/></p>
<h4><strong>What should be adopted for India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Every Indian city should ideally have a Master Plan</strong>: A strategic urban planning document which would be updated every decade or two. The document would entail how a city is supposed to grow, vertically and horizontally, across zones, while offering a high quality of life in a sustainable manner. Such plans would also consider poverty mitigation, affordable housing and liveability for urban migrants.</li>
<li><strong>Urban land use needs to be better</strong>: One look at satellite map imagery will show that India’s urban growth is increasingly haphazard, with informal, unplanned and sprawling neighbourhoods developing in paddy fields and along linear infrastructure (arterial roads, open spaces). India’s hidden urbanisation, driven partly by our stringent definition of the word, along with weak enforcement of building codes, has meant that the local government is often playing catch-up, unable to provide urban services and infrastructure to keep up with growth.</li>
<li><strong>Public land availability</strong>: Meanwhile, in places where there are formally recognised towns and urban neighbourhoods, outdated planning practices have meant that land utilisation is poor. Consider the case of Mumbai, where almost 1/4th of the land is open public space while over half of it is the underutilised space around buildings, which is enclosed by walls and hived off from public access. Such open spaces, if available, would help cities like Mumbai achieve similar ratios as globally benchmarked cities (Amsterdam, Barcelona) in public land availability (typically above 40 per cent).</li>
<li><strong>India’s urban density will also need to be thought through</strong>: Dense construction on the peripheries of our major cities (for instance, dense construction in Delhi’s suburbs, like Noida and Gurugram) will inevitably mean that public services are stretched and emissions (due to transportation to the main city) remain high. Such urbanisation will unavoidably lock India into a high emissions future while making our cities prone to extreme heat and flooding.</li>
<li><strong>Then there is climate change: </strong>According to the World Bank, climate change may reduce India’s GDP by 3 per cent, while depressing the living standards of its citizens by 2050. Many urban experts cite technological solutions that may save our cities a chain of sea walls, river embankments and reclamations, for instance from such potential calamities. However, structural engineering simply may not be an economically and environmentally feasible option everywhere instead, our focus must be on conservation.</li>
<li><strong>Climate resilience perspective</strong> Bengaluru, with its network of interconnected lakes, could have considered Bangkok-style ferries instead of draining out its lakes. All ongoing and upcoming urban infrastructure projects must be reconsidered from a future climate resilience perspective does the ongoing sea reclamation for the upcoming coastal road in Mumbai make sense if sea levels are rising?</li>
<li><strong>Establishing a sense of cityhood</strong>: By making a push for a city as a co-created space will also require building up institutional capacity.</li>
<li><strong>Addressing lack of town planning education: </strong>India would ideally require 3,00,000 town and country planners by 2031 (there are just 5,000 town planners currently). Much of this problem is fundamentally due to a lack of town planning education in the country there are just 26 institutes that provide this course, producing 700 town planners each year. We already have a shortage of 1.1 million planners. More schools are needed, with a push for local IITs and NITs to have a standalone planning department. With over 8,000 towns and cities, there is a clear unmet need.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="urban centres" class="alignnone wp-image-639709" height="347" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 616px) 100vw, 616px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432-1-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432-1.jpg 768w" width="616"/>Conclusion </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Our policymakers also need to be cognisant of the historical context of our urban development a push for glass buildings or utilising granite may not always be suitable for our cities. Why can’t our cities look distinctly Indian, inspired by our historical architecture? Renewing our cities will require us to rethink various urban topics, including urban design, urban healthcare, affordable housing, sustainability and inclusion among others. Our urban future depends on getting this right.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Renewing our cities will require us to rethink various urban topics, including urban design, urban healthcare, affordable housing, sustainability and inclusion among others. Elaborate.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-centres/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Karnataka brings law giving Quota for Locals</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/karnataka-brings-law-giving-quota-for-locals/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Quota for Locals</p></div></div><p>The Karnataka government recently tabled The Kannada Language Comprehensive Development Bill which gives preference to Kannadigas in government jobs and also provides for a reservation to locals in private jobs generated in the state.</p>
<h4><strong>What does the Karnataka legislation envisage?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Apart from ensuring job guarantee to Kannada speakers, the Bill pushes for the use of Kannada in institutes of higher learning and for sops to industries that employ locals.</li>
<li>Features highlighted in the Bill include reservation in higher, technical and professional education to those who studied in Kannada medium schools.</li>
<li>It seeks introduction of Kannada as essential language for seeking employment in the state government.</li>
<li>Also, industries will be entitled to concessions, tax rebates and deferment of taxes if they provide reservation for Kannadigas, as per the state’s industrial policy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Quota for Locals?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Ans.</strong> Constitutional provision for Equal Treatment</p>
<ul>
<li>Article 16 of the Constitution guarantees equal treatment under the law in matters of public employment. It prohibits the state from discriminating on grounds of place of birth or residence.</li>
<li>Article 16(2) states that “no citizen shall, on grounds only of religion, race, caste, sex, descent, place of birth, residence or any of them, be ineligible for, or discriminated against in respect of, any employment or office under the State”.</li>
<li>The provision is supplemented by the other clauses in the Constitution that guarantee equality.</li>
<li>However, Article 16(3) of the Constitution provides an exception by saying that Parliament may make a law “prescribing” a requirement of residence for jobs in a particular state.</li>
<li>This power vests solely in the Parliament, not state legislatures.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why does the Constitution prohibit reservation based on domicile?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When the Constitution came into force, India turned itself into one nation from a geographical unit of individual principalities and the idea of the universality of Indian citizenship took root.</li>
<li>India has single citizenship, and it gives citizens the liberty to move around freely in any part of the country.</li>
<li>Hence the requirement of a place of birth or residence cannot be qualification for granting public employment in any state.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>But are reservations not granted on other grounds such as caste?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Equality enshrined in the Constitution is not mathematical equality and does not mean all citizens will be treated alike without any distinction.</li>
<li>To this effect, the Constitution underlines two distinct aspects which together form the essence of equality law:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Non-discrimination among equals, and</li>
<li>Affirmative action to equalize the unequal</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Supreme Court rulings on quota for locals</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court has ruled against reservation based on place of birth or residence.</li>
<li>In 1984, ruling in Dr Pradeep Jain v Union of India, the issue of legislation for “sons of the soil” was discussed.</li>
<li>The court expressed an opinion that such policies would be unconstitutional but did not expressly rule on it as the case was on different aspects of the right to equality.</li>
<li>In a subsequent ruling in Sunanda Reddy v State of Andhra Pradesh (1995), the Supreme Court affirmed the observation in 1984 ruling to strike down a state government policy that gave 5% extra weightage to candidates.</li>
<li>In 2002, the Supreme Court invalidated appointment of government teachers in Rajasthan in which the state selection board gave preference to “applicants belonging to the district or the rural areas of the district concerned”.</li>
<li>In 2019, the Allahabad HC struck down a recruitment notification by the UP PSC which prescribed preference for women who are “original residents” of the UP alone.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why it is a bad idea?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Against Equality as well as meritocracy</strong>: It goes against the Constitution of India. In fact, it violates several fundamental rights, such as freedom to move anywhere, the right not to be discriminated on the basis of place of birth, the right to be treated equally before laws and the right to pursue one’s livelihood.</li>
<li><strong>Migration criteria not justified</strong>: The actual data on inter-State migration shows that inter-State migration is relatively low in India. Migration often bring skills, motivation, energy which may be in short supply or lacking locally.</li>
<li><strong>Free movement of labour</strong>: A more analytical aspect to highlight is that free movement of labour partly compensates for the uneven economic progress of different States. The idea also goes against the established fact that migration of labour is good for the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Un-ease of doing business</strong>: Local reservation in the private sector may not be the ideal solution to tackle the unemployment crisis. In fact, it can deter the corporate sector from investing in states that come up with such a rule.</li>
<li><strong>Scapegoating the private sector: </strong>What distinguishes the private sector from the public sector is the inherent competition and a hunger for improvement. In such a scenario, chief ministers should do well to engage with the private sector in a much more holistic manner, and not burden it with unfeasible rules.</li>
<li><strong>MSMEs to be hit harder: </strong>MSMEs could be the hardest hit. They do not have the necessary capital to relocate and many studies have shown that more than 50 per cent of employees are not residents of the state.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Arguments in favour of quota in private</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Avoiding encroachments:</strong> Often the privileged castes (or groups) use nefarious arguments to protect their interests.</li>
<li><strong>Foul argument of merit:</strong> Reservations once accepted in the constitutional framework are not a charity that is to be kept away from the ‘meritocracy’ of ‘private’ operations.</li>
<li><strong>Ensuring equal opportunity:</strong> Like all other constitutional guarantees, one may feel the necessity to get ensured of equal opportunity in all spaces.</li>
<li><strong>Preventing exclusion:</strong> Giving preference and quotas for socially and educationally deprived sections in the private space is, therefore, in keeping with this fundamental tenet.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The politics of identity and polarization on region/religious lines seems inadequate for the elections.</li>
<li>The philosophy and pragmatism of universal excellence through equality of opportunity for education and advancement across the nation is part of our founding faith and constitutional creed.</li>
<li>Clearly, this is not the appropriate domain of being “vocal for local”.</li>
<li>Although some reservations may still be necessary for the socio-political condition in India, reservation on the basis of domicile or residence within a State would be highly discriminatory.</li>
<li>It is more likely that such politically motivated steps would be overturned by the judiciary as has been done several times in the past.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/karnataka-brings-law-giving-quota-for-locals/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SC takes up pleas against Places of Worship Act</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-takes-up-pleas-against-places-of-worship-act/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Places of Worship Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Issues with the Act</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has set the ball rolling on a series of petitions challenging the validity of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-places-of-worship-act/">Places of Worship Act of 1991</a>, a parliamentary law that protects the identity and character of religious places as on August 15, 1947.</p>
<h4>What are the petitions about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>A slew of petitions has been filed against the Act.</li>
<li>The Act has fixed a retrospective cut-off date illegally barring Hindus, Jains, Buddhists and Sikhs from approaching courts to re-claim their places of worship which were invaded and encroached.</li>
<li>The main objective of these petitions is to set right a historical wrong committed by barbaric invaders.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Places of Worship Act, 1991</h4>
<ul>
<li>It was passed in 1991 by the P V Narasimha Rao-led government.</li>
<li>The law seeks to maintain the “religious character” of places of worship as it was in 1947 — except in the case of the Ram Janmabhoomi-Babri Masjid dispute, which was already in court.</li>
<li>The law was brought in at the peak of the Ram Mandir movement, exactly a year before the demolition of the Babri Masjid.</li>
<li>Introducing the law, then Home Minister S B Chavan said in Parliament that it was adopted to curb communal tension.</li>
</ul>
<p>What are its provisions?</p>
<h4>What are its provisions?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Anti-conversion:</strong> Section 3 of the Act bars the conversion, in full or part, of a place of worship of any religious denomination into a place of worship of a different religious denomination — or even a different segment of the same religious denomination.</li>
<li><strong>Holiness of a place:</strong> Section 4(1) declares that the religious character of a place of worship “shall continue to be the same as it existed” on August 15, 1947.</li>
<li><strong>Litigation:</strong> Section 4(2) says any suit or legal proceeding with respect to the conversion of the religious character of any place existing on August 15, 1947, pending before any court, shall abate — and no fresh suit or legal proceedings shall be instituted.</li>
<li><strong>Exception for Ayodhya:</strong> Section 5 stipulates that the Act shall not apply to the Ramjanmabhoomi-Babri Masjid case, and to any suit, appeal or proceeding relating to it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the law under challenge?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>cut-off date of August 15, 1947, is “arbitrary, irrational and retrospective</u></strong>” and prohibits Hindus, Jains, Buddhists, and Sikhs from approaching courts to “reclaim” their places of worship.</li>
<li>Such places, he argued, were “<strong><u>invaded” and “encroached” upon by “fundamentalist barbaric invaders</u></strong>”.</li>
<li>The right-wing politicians have opposed the law even when it was introduced, arguing that the Centre has no power to legislate on “pilgrimages” or “burial grounds” which is under the state list.</li>
<li>Another criticism against the law is that the cut-off is the date of Independence, which means that the status quo determined by a colonial power is considered final.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-takes-up-pleas-against-places-of-worship-act/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Process of sustainable tourism should be holistic and inclusive</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tourism-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Incredible India</p></div></div><p>“<em>To other Country, I may go as a tourist. But to India I come as a pilgrim</em>”, the words of Martin Luther King says a lot about India’s wisdom and tourism potential.</p>
<h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The three-day National Conference of State Tourism Minister was held at Dharamshala , a first of its kind meeting aimed  to discuss, debate and deliberate on modes and mechanisms to develop tourism in India .</li>
<li>The three-day National Conference concluded with the adoption of “Dharamshala Declaration” which affirms commitment toward developing “sustainable and responsible tourism” and positions India as a “global leader in the tourism sector by 2047”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism is travel for pleasure or business; also the theory and practice of touring, the business of attracting, accommodating, and entertaining tourists, and the business of operating tours.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Types of tourism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Domestic tourism</strong>: Refers to activities of a visitor within their country of residence and outside of their home (e.g. a Indian visiting other parts of India)</li>
<li><strong>Inbound tourism</strong>: Refers to the activities of a visitor from outside of country of residence (e.g. a Spaniard visiting Britain).</li>
<li><strong>Outbound tourism</strong>: Refers to the activities of a resident visitor outside of their country of residence (e.g. an Indian visiting an overseas country).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640662" height="327" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/89a08406-3919-11ed-8b5b-641320d18bc4_1663701869341.jpg 550w" width="580"/>What does sustainable tourism mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sustainable tourism is defined by the UN Environment Program and UN World Tourism Organization as “tourism that takes full account of its current and future economic, social and environmental impacts, addressing the needs of visitors, the industry, the environment and host communities.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the main importance of tourism?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism boosts the revenue of the economy, creates thousands of jobs, develops the infrastructures of a country, and plants a sense of cultural exchange between foreigners and citizens.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640663" height="379" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 605px) 100vw, 605px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/candle-night-dinner-camp-stay-osian-dunes-desert-cities-in-rajasthan.jpg 1024w" width="605"/>Why tourism is needed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Tourism is not a fad. It is a compulsion driven by the urge to discover new places. Because we have this compulsion to venture into the unknown, we need each other. When humans travel, meet and exchange ideas, civilization flourishes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is “The Dharamshala Declaration” is all about?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Aim of the declaration: </strong>The Dharamshala Declaration aims to recognise India’s role in contributing towards global tourism as well as focusing on recovery by also promoting domestic tourism.</li>
<li><strong>Action plan:</strong> In the declaration, the Tourism Ministry has come up with a with a action plan to encourage more Indians to travel domestically and explore India’s natural, cultural, and spiritual beauty while simultaneously reaching the goal of an ‘Ek Bharat Shrestha Bharat’ (interaction and mutual understanding).</li>
<li><strong>Strategy: </strong>The Tourism Ministry has also been working with the Ministry of External Affairs to identify 20 Indian missions abroad with the highest tourist footfalls to India and build country-specific strategies to attract foreign tourists.</li>
<li><strong>Plan according to G-20: </strong>The Dharamshala Declaration affirms the plan to position India as a major tourism destination during its presidency of G-20 next year. India’s age-old dictum of ‘Atithi Devo Bhava’ will come to the fore as it welcomes delegates from the 20 countries/European Union.</li>
<li><strong>Necessary steps:</strong> The Ministry of Tourism also plans to work with other Ministries to bring in necessary interventions such as visa reforms, ease of travel, travel-friendly and improved immigration facilities at airports.</li>
<li><strong>National Tourism policy</strong><strong>:</strong> Drafted with a holistic vision and strategy to revive India’s tourism and targets to contribute USD 1 trillion to the GDP by 2047.<strong><br/>
</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640666" height="519" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 692px) 100vw, 692px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1200x900.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/osian-jodhpur-aayush-kaushik-fJunL3RAR-g-unsplash-scaled-1-1980x1485.jpg 1980w" width="692"/>A draft on National <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gujarats-mice-tourism-policy/">Tourism Policy 2022</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Framework:</strong></li>
<li>Draft on National Tourism Policy 2022 aims at improving the framework conditions for tourism development in the country.</li>
<li>Supporting tourism industries, strengthening tourism support functions and developing tourism sub-sectors.</li>
<li>Impetus to digitalisation, innovation and technology through the National Digital Tourism Mission and skilling through the Tourism and Hospitality Sector Skill Mission.</li>
<li>The policy also gives a special impetus to private sector participation through public-private-partnerships (PPP)</li>
<li><strong>Guiding Principles</strong> :</li>
<li>Promoting sustainable, responsible and inclusive tourism in line with our civilisational ethos From Gautama to Gandhi, India has always spoken about the inherent need to live harmoniously with nature and within our means.</li>
<li>The National Green Tourism Mission aims at institutionalising green approach.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.incredibleindia.org/content/incredible-india-v2/en.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong><img alt="tourism" class="alignnone wp-image-640665" height="375" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 666px) 100vw, 666px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism-768x433.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/goa-tourism.jpg 1170w" width="666"/>Tourism Potential in India</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Employement generation:</strong> India has huge tourism potential. If capitalised properly it can emerge as one of the leading sectors to contribute to GDP and also has the potential to augment employment.</li>
<li><strong>The Pandemic cost and recovery: </strong>The pandemic has caused conspicuous losses for this sector but over the past few months, all the major tourism indices such as domestic air passenger traffic, hotel occupancy and tourist footfalls have shown signs of recovery and are going back to pre-pandemic levels.</li>
<li><strong>Short term estimate:</strong> By 2024, in short term the country is estimated to contribute USD 150 billion to the GDP from tourism, USD 30 billion in Foreign Exchange earnings and can get 15 million foreign tourist arrivals..</li>
<li><strong>Medium term by 2030:</strong> It is estimated to grow at seven to nine per cent Compound Annual Growth Rate in the coming decade. In the medium term, that is 2030, the tourism-related goals are USD 250 billion GDP contribution; 137 million jobs, 56 million foreign tourist arrivals and USD 56 billion in foreign exchange earnings.</li>
<li><strong>Visionary schemes</strong>: The visionary schemes like Swadesh Darshan or Dekho Apna Desh have the potential to increase tourism value while maintaining cultural integrity and ecological sustainability of the places.</li>
<li><strong>Dekho Apna Desh</strong>: Dekho apna desh rolled out in 2020 envisages encouraging domestic tourism, urging people to visit places in India. India is a land of rich cultural heritage.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>If the goal of positioning of India as one of the world’s best tourism destinations by 2047, there is need to integrate various schemes of different ministries. Need to involve various stakeholders, and local communities; necessary interventions at urban and rural level should be a priority.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Since the positive and negative outcomes of tourism depend on human factors, including the attitude and behavior of both tourists and hosts, in this context discuss India’s potential to become a global leader in tourism sector.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tourism-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Carl-Gustaf M4 to be produced in India</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gustaf-m4-to-be-produced-in-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Carl-Gustaf M4</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="gustaf" class="alignnone wp-image-641101 size-full" height="853" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav.jpg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav-300x237.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav-1024x809.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gustav-768x607.jpg 768w" width="1080"/></p>
<p>Swedish defense major SAAB announced plans to manufacture its Carl-Gustaf M4 weapon system in India.</p>
<h4>What is the Carl-Gustaf M4?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Carl-Gustaf recoilless rifle is a man-portable, multi-role weapon system that allows dismounted soldiers to effectively deal with multiple challenges on the modern battlefield.</li>
<li>A proven performer in battle, the Carl-Gustaf M4 is said to be adaptable and flexible.</li>
<li>The Indian Army has been using the iconic Carl-Gustaf since 1976 and currently operates the Mk2 and Mk3 versions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Key features of Carl-Gustaf M4</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lightweight, robust, reliable, effective and easy to use</li>
<li>Tactical flexibility through a wide range of ammunition</li>
<li>Combat proven system</li>
<li>Ammunition: Anti-armour, anti-structure, anti-personnel, support</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In recent years, the Indian government has taken several steps to boost the defense manufacturing sector under the ‘Make in India’ and <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-self-reliance-in-defence/">‘Atmanirbhar Bharat’</a></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gustaf-m4-to-be-produced-in-india/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Jaldoot App to capture data on Groundwater Levels</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/jaldoot-app-to-capture-data-on-groundwater-levels/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Jaldoot App</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-641102" height="451" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 372px) 100vw, 372px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-248x300.jpg 248w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-845x1024.jpg 845w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-768x931.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/jaldoot-743x900.jpg 743w" width="372"/></p>
<p>With the rapidly declining water table threatening to push many regions into drought, the Union government on has launched a mobile application — Jaldoot.</p>
<h4>Jaldoot App</h4>
<ul>
<li>Jaldoot is jointly developed by the Rural Development and Panchayati Raj Ministries to monitor the groundwater levels across the country.</li>
<li>The App will enable Gram Rojgar Sahyak to measure the water level of well twice a year pre-monsoon and post-monsoon.</li>
<li>Jaldoots, that is, officers assigned to measure the water levels, should also upload the geo-tagged photographs through the app on every occasion of measurement.</li>
<li>This Mobile app will work in both online and offline mode.</li>
<li>So water level can be captured even without internet connectivity and captured date will be stored in mobile and when mobile comes in the connectivity area, data will synchronize with the central server.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Utility of the app</h4>
<ul>
<li>The despite promoting watershed development, afforestation, waterbody development and renovation, rainwater harvesting like initiatives, the ground water level in various parts of the country has depleted.</li>
<li>The regular data to be input by the Jaldoots would be integrated with the database of National Water Informatics Centre (NWIC), which can be utilised for analysis and display.</li>
<li>The app will facilitate in observing water tables across the country and the resulting data can be utilised for Gram Panchayat Development Plan and Mahatma Gandhi NREGA Plans.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/jaldoot-app-to-capture-data-on-groundwater-levels/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Places in news: Ram Setu</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-ram-setu/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ram Setu</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p><img alt="ram setu" class="alignnone wp-image-641104 size-full" height="313" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 556px) 100vw, 556px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/setu.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/setu.jpg 556w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/setu-300x169.jpg 300w" width="556"/></p>
<p>A movie has once again generated buzz around the chain of shoals off the southeast coast of India that many believe is the Ram Setu or the bridge to Lanka mentioned in the Ramayana.</p>
<h4>The Ram Setu</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Ram Setu, also known as Adam’s Bridge, is a 48-km chain of limestone shoals between Rameswaram on India’s southeast coast and Mannar Island near Sri Lanka’s northwest coast.</li>
<li>The structure has significance in both Hindu and Muslim mythology – while Hindus believe this is the bridge (Setu) built by Lord Ram and his army to cross to Lanka and fight Ravan.</li>
<li>As per Islamic legend, Adam used this bridge to reach Adam’s Peak in Sri Lanka, where he stood on one foot for 1,000 years in repentance.</li>
</ul>
<p>Factual details of the bridge</p>
<ul>
<li>Scientists believe Ram Setu is a natural structure formed due to tectonic movements and sand getting trapped in corals.</li>
<li>However, over the years, evidence has been offered to claim that the bridge is man-made.</li>
<li>The bridge is not entirely natural, Hindu right wing outfits argue, which proves that it was indeed built by Lord Ram.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When was the structure came into highlights?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Ram Setu issue snowballed into a major controversy when the Sethusamudram Project, flagged off during the UPA I government.</li>
<li>The project aimed to reduce travel time between the eastern and western coasts of India, as ships would no longer have to circle Sri Lanka to travel between the Bay of Bengal and Arabian Sea.</li>
<li>The project was perceived as an attack on Hindu sentiments.</li>
<li>Various studies have been proposed on the Ram Setu, with the most recent being in 2021, when the government approved an underwater research project to ascertain its origins.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Ecological arguments against the project</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Sethusamudram project has been opposed on environmental grounds.</li>
<li>Some claims that it will harm marine life, and that dredging of the line of shoals will make India’s coast more vulnerable to tsunamis.</li>
<li>In March 2018, the Centre told the Supreme Court that the Ram Setu will not be affected in the execution of the Sethusamudram Shipping Canal project.</li>
</ul>
<h4>NASA images, and other proofs</h4>
<ul>
<li>Images of the Ram Setu clicked by NASA have been used over and over again to claim that this proves the existence of a man-made bridge.</li>
<li>NASA has repeatedly clarified that it does not agree with these claims.</li>
<li>Remote sensing images or photographs from orbit cannot provide direct information about the origin or age of a chain of islands.</li>
<li>It certainly cannot be determined whether humans were involved in producing any of the patterns seen.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/places-in-news-ram-setu/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Maharashtra Election Symbols Issue</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/maharashtra-election-symbols-issue/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Allocation of election symbols</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>In a blow to one faction, a Constitution Bench of the Supreme Court allowed the Election Commission (EC) to take a decision on the Maharashtra CM claim that his faction represents the “real” party.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Bench led by Justice D.Y. Chandrachud rejected the plea to stay the EC proceedings under the Election Symbols (Reservation and Allotment) Order of 1968.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A party has lost a large number of members in the rebellion that eventually caused the fall of the government in Maharashtra.</li>
<li>The rebel has claimed to be the only original leader of the party on the basis of the support of more than two-thirds of the party’s legislators in the Maharashtra Assembly.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Options for ECI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ECI in all likelihood can freeze the symbol so that neither of the two sides is able to use it until a final decision is made.</li>
<li>EC hearings are long and detailed, and may take at least six months.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>EC’s powers in Election Symbol Dispute</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The question of a split in a political party outside the legislature is dealt by Para 15 of the Symbols Order, 1968.</li>
<li>It states that the ECI may take into account all the available facts and circumstances and undertake a test of majority.</li>
<li>The decision of the ECI shall be binding on all such rival sections or groups emerged after the split.</li>
<li>This applies to disputes in recognised national and state parties.</li>
<li>For splits in registered but unrecognized parties, the EC usually advises the warring factions to resolve their differences internally or to approach the court.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How did the EC deal with such matters before the Symbols Order came into effect?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Before 1968, the EC issued notifications and executive orders under the Conduct of Election Rules, 1961.</li>
<li>The most high-profile split of a party before 1968 was that of the CPI in 1964.</li>
<li>A breakaway group approached the ECI in December 1964 urging it to recognise them as CPI(Marxist). They provided a list of MPs and MLAs of Andhra Pradesh, Kerala and West Bengal who supported them.</li>
<li>The ECI recognised the faction as CPI(M) after it found that the votes secured by the MPs and MLAs supporting the breakaway group added up to more than 4% in the 3 states.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the first case decided under Para 15 of the 1968 Order?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It was the first split in the Indian National Congress in 1969.</li>
<li>Indira Gandhi’s tensions with a rival group within the party came to a head with the death of President Dr Zakir Hussain on May 3, 1969.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Is there a way other than the test of majority to resolve a dispute over election symbols?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In almost all disputes decided by the EC so far, a clear majority of party delegates/office bearers, MPs and MLAs have supported one of the factions.</li>
<li>Whenever the EC could not test the strength of rival groups based on support within the party organisation (because of disputes regarding the list of office bearers), it fell back on testing the majority only among elected MPs and MLAs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What happens to the group that doesn’t get the parent party’s symbol?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The EC in 1997 did not recognise the new parties as either state or national parties.</li>
<li>It felt that merely having MPs and MLAs is not enough, as the elected representatives had fought and won polls on tickets of their parent (undivided) parties.</li>
<li>The EC introduced a new rule under which the splinter group of the party — other than the group that got the party symbol — had to register itself as a separate party.</li>
<li>It could lay claim to national or state party status only on the basis of its performance in the state or central elections after registration.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/maharashtra-election-symbols-issue/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why India has lashed out at the US over its F-16 package to Pakistan?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-india-has-lashed-out-at-the-us-over-its-f-16-package/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>F-16</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>US's double standards over Pakistan</p></div></div><p><img alt="f-16" class="alignnone wp-image-641100 size-full" height="447" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f-16.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f-16.jpg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/f-16-300x224.jpg 300w" width="600"/></p>
<p>EAM S Jaishankar has lashed out at the US for its decision to provide Pakistan with a $450 million package for F-16 case fighter aircraft upgrade.</p>
<h4>F-16 and Pakistan</h4>
<ul>
<li>The F-16 is a single-engine multirole fighter aircraft originally developed by General Dynamics for the United States Air Force (USAF).</li>
<li>Designed as an air superiority day fighter, it evolved into a successful all-weather multirole aircraft.</li>
<li>The F-16 were inducted into Pakistan Air Force in 1983 during the Soviet-Afghan War.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Suspicion over US move</h4>
<ul>
<li>This is the first American military assistance package to Pakistan after the Trump Administration.</li>
<li>Mr Trump ended defence and security co-operation with Pakistan in 2018 after accusing it of giving only “lies and deceit” for the billions of dollars that the US had “foolishly” given it.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What specific reasons has the Biden Administration given for its decision?</h4>
<ul>
<li>As per US version, the proposed sale does not include any new capabilities, weapons, or munitions.</li>
<li>The upgrade package aimed to retain interoperability with US and partner forces in ongoing counter-terrorism efforts and in preparation for future contingency operations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did US provide F-16 to the US?</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has been concerned about the F-16s from the time the US first gave Pakistan F-16s as a reward for its assistance in the first Afghan war.</li>
<li>The US then had supplied weapons and money to Pakistan to unleash armies of jihadists against the Soviet Army.</li>
<li>When the US objective was achieved with the Soviet Union’s departure from Afghanistan, the US too resized its relations with Pakistan.</li>
<li>The Pressler Amendment, aimed against Pakistan’s nuclear ambitions, froze it out of military assistance.</li>
<li>A decade later, the Bush Administration not only approved the release of previously blocked F-16s, but also provided a refurbishment package, and sale of new F-16s.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India’s concerns</h4>
<ul>
<li>As pointed out by EAM, how the F-16s help in counter-terrorism remains unclear.</li>
<li>Jaishankar questioned the merits of the US-Pakistan partnership.</li>
<li>He said that the relations had “not served” either country (but created more troubles for India).</li>
<li>This move by the US will alter the basic military balance in the region.</li>
<li>The decision to provide military aid to Pakistan incensed India as the F-16 was used against Indian warplanes following the 2019 Balakot air strikes.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<ul>
<li>Washington’s $450 million package has only resurrected old prejudices centred on the US not being a dependable ally for ever.</li>
<li>India needs to respond firmly and in no uncertain terms to the PAF’s F-16 upgrade programme to convey the message that India cannot be taken for granted.</li>
<li>India will have to effectively enhance the conventional combat capability of the IAF to continue to meet the challenge of a resurgent PAF.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/why-india-has-lashed-out-at-the-us-over-its-f-16-package/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India and UNSC</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-quest-for-permanent-membership-of-unsc/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UN Security council</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>International Relations</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641313" height="506" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 843px) 100vw, 843px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5edc92b402a52-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5edc92b402a52-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/5edc92b402a52.jpg 500w" width="843"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is greater support for India to be a permanent member of the UN Security Council and also a broad global consensus over the need to reform the Council, said External Affairs Minister S Jaishankar. India has once again renewed its bid for permanent membership of UNSC.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong style="font-size: 32px; letter-spacing: -0.0415625em; font-family: 'Inter var', -apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, sans-serif;">What is UNSC?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The United Nations Security Council (UNSC) is one of the six principal organs of the United Nations (UN) and is charged with ensuring international peace and security, recommending the admission of new UN members to the General Assembly, and approving any changes to the UN Charter.</li>
<li>Its powers include establishing peacekeeping operations, enacting international sanctions, and authorizing military action. The UNSC is the only UN body with the authority to issue binding resolutions on member states.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641314" height="509" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 697px) 100vw, 697px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_11largeimg_1702223617-300x219.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_11largeimg_1702223617-300x219.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2021_11largeimg_1702223617.jpg 660w" width="697"/>What is the composition of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/g4-countries-call-for-unsc-reforms/">UNSC</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Presently there five permanent members (P-5) with veto and 10 non-permanent members without veto elected for tenure of 2 years.</li>
<li>India has been the non-permanent member multiple times. Presently India is serving its tenure that will end in December 2022.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641315" height="469" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 833px) 100vw, 833px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1658498206-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1658498206-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1658498206.jpg 715w" width="833"/>Who are P-5 members?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The victors of World War 2 – USA, RUSSIA, CHINA, UK, FRANCE.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the hurdles that India facing?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Elite club:</strong> Most exclusive club in international relations. All other clubs have been breached. Until a quarter century ago, the nuclear weapon club had five members, the same five as the P-5.India, Pakistan, North Korea and Israel have since joined the club. But UNSC is unbreachable till date.</li>
<li><strong>All are reluctant: </strong>The inescapable fact is that none of the P-5 wants the UNSC’s ranks to be increased. One or the other of them might make some noise about supporting one or more of the aspirants. Each is confident that someone among them will torpedo the enlargement of the club. Declarations of support for India’s candidature need to be taken with a fistful of salt.</li>
<li><strong>Veto issue: </strong>Former UN Secretary-General Kofi Annan bluntly told India not to expect to get the veto power. Though India has said it will not accept a seat without veto power.</li>
<li><strong>China-Pakistan axis: </strong>China, which has historically blocked India’s aspirations to become a permanent member of the UNSC. Beijing has an “all-weather ally” in Islamabad, another neighbour who also strongly opposes India’s candidature to the UNSC.</li>
<li><strong>Odd man out: </strong>Four out of the five permanent members of the United Nations Security Council have bilaterally expressed official affirmations of support for India’s candidature to a permanent seat in an expanded UN Security Council.</li>
<li><strong>Coffee club opposition: </strong>Members like Italy, South Korea, Canada, Spain, Mexico, Turkey, Argentina, Pakistan, and others, who have together formed the Uniting for Consensus (UfC) movement. Also known as the Coffee Club, the movement argues that bids for permanent seats by India, Japan, Germany, and Brazil (G4 countries) must not be considered without first reaching an international consensus regarding the form and size of the new Security council.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="UNSC" class="alignnone wp-image-641318" height="310" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/India_Jaishankar_UNSC_1200x768.jpeg 770w" width="550"/>What are the Efforts taken by India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Text based negotiation: </strong>External affairs minister is canvassing for the country’s candidature, meeting his counterparts from several countries. He has repeated the call, made often in the past, for a text-based negotiation on what has been euphemistically referred to as the reform of the United Nations Security Council (UNSC), i.e., negotiation on a written document outlining the proposed reform instead of just holding forth verbally.</li>
<li><strong>Woking together with G-4: </strong>INDIA, JAPAN, GEMANY, BRAZIL works together to get permanent UNSC seat however these efforts are opposed by coffee club.</li>
<li><strong>Multilateral engagements: </strong>By expanding its footprint in multilateral organisations, India is gearing up to become a global rule-maker.</li>
<li>Distinguished group of experts suggested a few years ago that a new category of semi-permanent members should be created. Countries would be elected for a period of eight to 10 years and would be eligible for re-election. India ought to give serious consideration to this idea.</li>
<li><strong>With or without veto: </strong>According to former foreign secretary Chinmaya gharekhan, if by some miracle we are offered or manage to obtain permanent membership without veto, we must grab it. Even a permanent membership without veto will be tremendously helpful in protecting our interests.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Looking at the present geopolitical divide India’s dream of seat at the highest table is unlikely to get fulfilled in near future. India must analyse the utility of UNSC membership for securing its national interest. India should not give up anything in bargain against UNSC seat which harms its international interest.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. India’s quest for UNSC is like “Sisyphus carrying the boulder  just to see how it falls”. In this context Analyse the utility of Permanent seat at UNSC.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-quest-for-permanent-membership-of-unsc/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Advantage of Market Based Economic Dispatch</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/market-based-economic-dispatch-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economics,Energy,Infrastructure</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641126" height="316" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-3-1.jpg" width="565"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The game changing scheme is being proposed by the central government in power sector governance. The scheme under consideration is the market-based economic dispatch (MBED). When it comes to any drastic change in the power sector, a clash between the Centre and the states is inevitable.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Market Based Economic Dispatch (MBED)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Market Based Economic Dispatch (MBED) is new approach towards power distribution to help distribution companies save costs and transition to a new form of power market.</li>
<li>It is a shift to a centralised framework, marks a radical departure from the current decentralised, voluntary pool-based electricity market.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641122" height="291" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/download-1-2.jpg" width="508"/>What is the framework under MBED?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The cheapest power from across the country will be dispatched to meet the system wide demand. The architecture would also lead to a “Market clearing price”.</li>
<li>Sellers and buyers will place their bids for the day market, and an outcome of this will be the discovery of the market clearing price.</li>
<li>This process is expected to generate significant savings for consumers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Present system of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/assessment-of-discoms/">power Distribution?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Under the present regime, each distribution company (Discom) is bound by the power purchase agreements (PPAs) that it holds.</li>
<li>It can schedule power only from its own PPAs, starting from the cheapest PPA and then moving up; it cannot schedule power from the PPA of some other distribution company.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> <img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641124" height="365" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-2.jpg" width="488"/></strong><strong>What are the drawbacks of present system?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Financial Burdon:</strong></li>
<li>The Indian government responded to COVID-19’s economic shock with a stimulus package of Rs.20-lakh crore, out of which Rs.90,000 crore was earmarked for discoms (later upgraded to Rs.1,25,000 crore). While it was called a stimulus, it is really a loan, meant to be used by discoms to pay off generators.</li>
<li>Discoms owe one lakh crore rupees to generators, and without such an infusion the chain will collapse.</li>
<li><strong>States are defaulters:</strong></li>
<li>State governments are the biggest defaulters, responsible for an estimated a third of trade receivables, besides not paying subsidies in full or on time.</li>
<li>On an annual cash flow basis, the shortfall in subsidy payments appears very low, only about 1% but cumulative unpaid subsidies, with modest carrying costs, make discoms poorer by over Rs.70,000 crore just over the last 10 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Market Based Economic Dispatch" class="alignnone wp-image-641125" height="323" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-12-1.jpg" width="570"/>What will be the Advantages of MBED?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Centralized approach: </strong>The centralised dispatch will be done with the assistance of electricity exchanges. Each discom and each generator will place a bid in the day-ahead market of the electricity exchanges, which will indicate how much power is being demanded/ supplied at what price.</li>
<li><strong>Pan India market: </strong>These bids will enable the load dispatcher to construct a pan India demand and supply curve, the intersection of which will determine the market clearing price (MCP). All generators whose variable cost of generation is below the MCP will be asked to dispatch and all of them will receive the same MCP irrespective of what they had bid. Generators whose variable cost is higher than the MCP will sit idle.</li>
<li><strong>No loss to discom: </strong>The MBED is so devised that its operation will not affect the current finances of either the discoms or the generators for the following reasons.</li>
<li>First, the fixed cost of the generators will still be paid by the discoms outside the market as determined by the regulator.</li>
<li>Second, if the MCP comes out to be Rs 3 per unit, and if in the case of any PPA, the variable cost is Rs 2.75 per unit, then the generator will compensate the discom to the extent of Rs 0.25 per unit. Similarly, if the MCP so determined is Rs 2.50 per unit, then the discom will compensate the generator to the extent of Rs 0.25 per unit.</li>
<li><strong>Increasing efficiency: </strong>The logic is that by adopting MBED, only the relatively efficient plants will generate, without affecting the revenues of either the discoms or generators. Hence, the total cost of generation under the MBED system would be less.</li>
<li><strong>Less pollution: </strong>There would be less coal consumption and less carbon dioxide injected into the atmosphere.</li>
<li><strong>Easy integration with renewable: </strong>It would also mean less movement of coal leading to decongestion of railway tracks. Further, there would be enhanced renewable integration since the balancing area would shift from state to national level.</li>
<li><strong>Single market clearing price (MCP): </strong>Incidentally, since there are three electricity exchanges in operation today, there would be three different MCPs determined. What we need is a single MCP for which there will be an institution called the “market coupler”. It will be the job of the coupler to determine a national MCP based on what has arrived at the three different exchanges.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why states are opposing?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>High generation cost: </strong>The reason is the state-owned generators are relatively inefficient and may have to sit idle as their variable cost of generation is likely to be more than the MCP.</li>
<li><strong>Political backlash: </strong>Today, the states are operating their own generators to the hilt, even though they are inefficient, and drawing only the balance from the more efficient interstate generating stations. Keeping state generators idle has its own political implications and no state would be enamoured of this idea.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Power distribution companies (discom) are sinkhole of government finances. Every year budgetary support is needed to this loss-making companies , With due consultation, all states and union territories need to adopt and implement the MBED and save the resources for other development activities.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. </strong><strong>India has became the power surplus nation, however power distribution and financial unsustainability is still a nightmare for union and states. Elaborate.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/market-based-economic-dispatch-2/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Indian Railways powerful experiment on AC III tier economy class coaches</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ac-iii-tier-economy-class-coaches/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economics, Infrastructure,Transport</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="AC III tier economy class coaches" class="alignnone wp-image-641307" height="361" sizes="(max-width: 633px) 100vw, 633px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-300x171.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-300x171.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1024x583.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-768x437.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1536x874.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-2048x1166.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1200x683.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Vasco_Chennai_Express_-_AC_3_tier_coach-1980x1127.jpg 1980w" width="633"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian Railways’ experiment to introduce AC III tier economy class coaches has started to pay off. Since its introduction, in the last one year, these coaches have earned the Railways more than Rs.230 crore in revenue.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="AC III tier economy class" class="alignnone wp-image-641094" height="289" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-6.jpg" width="514"/>What is </strong><strong>AC III tier economy class coach?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AC 3 tier economy class in Indian Railways is a milestone concerning pocket-friendly traveling experience for common man.</li>
<li>With fare slightly more than sleeper class and lower than conventional AC class.</li>
<li>The objective of the railway is to move sleeper class passengers to a comfortable AC class with luxurious facilities. AC-3 tier comprises air-conditioned coaches with 64 sleeping berths.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>When it is introduced?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Indian Railway has introduced the first AC III tier Economy Class for North Central Railway Zone in 2021 to provide a convenient traveling experience to the passengers<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>As of now 7 trains are equipped with AC III tier economy class coaches are running on the tracks</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="AC III tier economy class coaches" class="alignnone wp-image-641308" height="377" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 669px) 100vw, 669px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/coach_1630084530874_1630084539038.jpg 1600w" width="669"/>Features of the AC </strong>III<strong> tier economy coach</strong><strong>:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pocket friendly</strong>: According to the Indian Railways, the fair in these coaches are cheaper than the normal AC three-tier coach. Fares in AC III tier economy are 6%-7% cheaper than the AC III tier class. The economy class has a capacity of 83 berths compared to 72 in the regular coach.</li>
<li><strong>Divyang friendly and modern designs: </strong>The coaches were specially designed for the convenience of the divyangs. Providing Improved and modular design of berths and ergonomically designed ladder for accessing the middle and upper berths etc.</li>
<li><strong>Modern features: </strong>In these, modern arrangements have been made for mobile phones and magazine holders, fire safety, personalised reading lights, AC vents, USB points, mobile charging points.</li>
<li><strong>Optimum Speed</strong>: These air-conditioned three-tier economy class coaches are capable of running at an optimum speed of 160 kilometers per hour.</li>
<li><strong>More Capacity:</strong> The economy class has a capacity of 83 berths compared to 72 in the regular coach.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the current status of AC </strong><strong>III tier class?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>AC- III tier, the favorite mode of train travel of people falling in the bottom rung of the middle class, is the only class that earns the Railways profit among all its passenger services.</li>
<li>The AC III tier is the only class of service which has generated consistent profits for the Railways. Between FY16 and FY20,</li>
<li>AC III tier coaches carried only 1% of the total passengers, but were responsible for 21% of the earnings from travelers. Such a low-passenger, high-revenue dichotomy was not seen in any other class.</li>
<li>It is not as expensive as the other AC classes and at the same time, its share in revenue has not been impacted by the relatively low pricing</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong style="letter-spacing: -0.0415625em;"><img alt="AC III tier economy class coaches" class="alignnone wp-image-641309" height="464" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 619px) 100vw, 619px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84998782-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84998782-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84998782.jpg 400w" width="619"/>Revenue of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vande-bharat-production-to-begin/">Indian railways</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The overall revenue of Indian Railways at the end of August 2022 was Rs 95,486.58 crore, showing an increase 38 per cent over the corresponding period of last year.</li>
<li>Goods revenue climbed by Rs 10,780.03 crore (or 20 per cent) to Rs 65,505.02 crore till August-end this year</li>
<li>The revenue from passenger traffic was Rs 25,276.54 crore, an increase of Rs 13,574.44 crore (116 per cent) year-on-year.</li>
<li>Passenger traffic also increased compared to last year in both the segments — reserved and unreserved</li>
<li>Railways’ total revenue during the entire last fiscal (2021-22) stood at Rs.1,91,278.29 crore.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the issues faced by Indian railways to increase its revenue?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cross Subsidized: </strong>The cross-subsidiszation in respect of second class, ordinary class and suburban services has increased continuously in the past five years with subsidy on ordinary class being the maximum,</li>
<li><strong>Concessional fare</strong>: The revenue forgone in passenger earnings due to concessions to various categories of passengers (physically challenged persons, patients, senior citizens, Izzat monthly season tickets, press correspondents, sport persons and war widows among others) increased from Rs 1,994.83 crore in 2018-19 to Rs 2,058.61 crore in 2019-20.</li>
<li><strong>Low -Revenue dichotomy in Expensive class:</strong> A high-passenger, low-revenue dichotomy was seen in the inexpensive classes. For instance, over 90% passengers travelled by second class which accounted for only 37% of the earnings.</li>
<li><strong>Operational Los</strong><strong>s</strong>: Operational losses (in crore) incurred while operating various classes of service. For instance, in operating AC first class service, the Railways incurred a loss of 403 crore in FY20</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Adding more AC III tier economy class coaches is a step in the right direction as it has shown positive result in revenue generation for railways and it provides a travel with dignity to a common man. But If Indian railway has to benefit it have to work extensively on operational loss incurred out of low Revenue dichotomy in Expensive classes.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. Indian Railways is often referred to as the lifeline of the country but runs at a loss when it comes to running class-divided coaches. In this context discuss the utility of class divided coaches.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ac-iii-tier-economy-class-coaches/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>