<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2022 18:22:01 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Implications of withdrawal of the Personal Data Protection Bill</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/implications-of-withdrawal-of-the-personal-data-protection-bill/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>European Union’s Digital Services Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- Need for personal data protection act</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>In a surprise development last week, the Government withdrew the Personal Data Protection (PDP) Bill, 2019, thereby abruptly halting the country’s quest for a national data protection law that had been in the works for over five years.</p>
<h4>Reasons for withdrawal of the Bill</h4>
<ul>
<li>The short circular issued by the Minister of Electronics and Information Technology states that considering the report of the Joint Parliamentary Committee (JPC) — it had proposed 81 amendments and made 12 recommendations — <strong>“a comprehensive legal framework is being worked on”. </strong></li>
<li>There is no elaboration on what such a “comprehensive legal framework” entails.</li>
<li><strong>Possible plan of action: </strong>The Government could enact a fresh privacy legislation or <strong>a comprehensive data protection law</strong> (covering both personal and non-personal data).</li>
<li><strong>Subsuming data protection in IT Act:</strong> Alternatively, it could subsume data protection under its ongoing attempts at revising the existing Information Technology Act, 2000.</li>
<li><strong>Digital markets law:</strong> It could also enact a digital markets law, along the lines of the<strong> European Union’s Digital Services Act</strong>, focusing on competition and innovation in the digital space.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Background of the introduction of Personal Data Protection Bill</h4>
<ul>
<li>When the Supreme Court of India affirmed the right to privacy in  <strong>K.S. Puttaswamy judgment in 2017</strong>, the nine-judge Bench of the Court referred to the Government’s Office Memorandum constituting the<strong> B.N. Srikrishna Committee</strong> to suggest a draft Data Protection Bill.</li>
<li>The committee released its draft Personal Data Protection Bill in 2018, which was the first public articulation of a data protection law in India.</li>
<li>When the Supreme Court upheld the constitutionality of the Aadhaar Act, the majority emphasised that it believed that “there is a need for a proper legislative mechanism for data protection”.</li>
<li>In December 2019, the Government introduced the PDP Bill, 2019 in the Lok Sabha as a comprehensive personal data protection regime.</li>
<li>The Bill was referred to the JPC for its recommendations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What were the issues with the Bill?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Power to exemption with state:</strong> The Bill’s expansive exemptions <strong>allowed the state to exempt the entire application of the law</strong> simply as if it was “expedient” to do so in the interest of national security or public order.</li>
<li><strong>Powers without accountability:</strong> The PDP Bill, 2019 as well as the JPC’s version established a strong regulator (the Data Protection Authority) with a lot of power, but very little independence or accountability.</li>
<li><strong>Data localisation:</strong> The Bill imposed a s<strong>trong data localisation mandate</strong>, requiring companies to store all sensitive personal data and critical personal data (which was not defined) in India.</li>
<li><strong>Subsuming the personal and non-personal data:</strong> The JPC recommended subsuming the regulation of personal data and non-personal data within a single legislation, even though it undermined the Puttaswamy mandate to ensure protection of personal data.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why we need data protection law?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increasing internet use:</strong> India currently has over <strong>750 million Internet users</strong>, with the number only expected to increase in the future.</li>
<li>The Government is also making a strong push for a <strong>‘Digital India’,</strong> with increased focus on digitisation of access to health, ration, banking, insurance, especially after the COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
<li>There is<strong> a greater focus on the inter-linking of data,</strong> whether through facial recognition, Aadhaar, or the Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022.</li>
<li><strong>Data breaches:</strong> At the same time, India has among the highest data breaches in the world.</li>
<li>Without a data protection law in place, the data of millions of Indians continues to be at risk of being exploited, sold, and misused without their consent.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of writ proceeding against corporate action:</strong> Unlike state action, corporate action or misconduct is not subject to writ proceedings in India.</li>
<li>This is because fundamental rights are, by and large, not enforceable against private non-state entities.</li>
<li>This leaves individuals with limited remedies against private actors.</li>
<li>A personal data protection legislation would remedy this lacuna by providing individuals with proper grievance redress options and creating sufficient deterrence among private actors.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>It is imperative that the Government soon introduces a fresh data protection legislation, drawn after proper public consultation. Such a law should take into consideration the criticisms that have been raised by civil society as well as the private sector.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/implications-of-withdrawal-of-the-personal-data-protection-bill/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The Portuguese Civil Code of 1867 is a colonial burden on Goa</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/the-portuguese-civil-code-of-1867-is-a-colonial-burden-on-goa/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Article 44</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Paper 2- Uniform civil code issue</p></div></div><h4>Context</h4>
<p>The Portuguese Civil Code of 1867, the so-called “common civil code” of Goa, is in the news again. A 28-member parliamentary standing committee recently visited the state to study it in the context of the demand for a uniform civil code.</p>
<h4>Background</h4>
<ul>
<li>Long before the arrival of the British imperialists in India, the Portuguese had occupied certain territories in the coastal regions with its capital in Cochin, later shifted to Goa.</li>
<li>They did not interfere with the local customs relating to family relations and framed, in the mid-19th century, <strong>three separate codes of religion-based customary laws</strong> of Goa, Daman and Diu.</li>
<li>The three codes were formally enforced as the law by royal decrees issued by the King of Portugal.</li>
<li><strong>The Portuguese Civil Code of 1867</strong> was extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by a royal decree of November 18, 1869, declaring that the code would apply to the natives subject to the local usages and customs “so far as they are not inconsistent with morality or public order”.</li>
<li> In 1910, the Portuguese parliament enacted two civil marriage and divorce decrees and, in 1946, a canonical marriage decree for Catholics.</li>
<li>All of these too were extended to Goa, Daman and Diu.</li>
<li>The family law applied by the Portuguese, both at home and in the occupied Indian territories,<strong> was thus not a uniform code</strong> but a loose conglomeration of civil and religious laws.</li>
</ul>
<h4>After Indian independence</h4>
<ul>
<li>Fourteen years after the advent of Independence, Goa and its affiliated territories were liberated and <strong>turned into a Union Territory (UT)</strong> under central rule.</li>
<li> The<strong> Goa, Daman and Diu Administration Act of 1962</strong> declared that all laws in force in these territories before their liberation would continue to be in force “until amended or repealed by a competent legislature or other competent authority” (Section 5).</li>
<li>None of the pre-liberation family laws was, however, amended or repealed.</li>
<li>Nor was any central law on family rights, including the <strong>four Hindu law Acts of 1955-56</strong>, extended to any of the three territories.</li>
<li><strong>In 1987,</strong> the Goa, Daman and Diu Reorganisation Act made Goa a full-fledged state with its own legislative assembly and <strong>left Daman and Diu as a UT.</strong></li>
<li>Twenty-five years later, the Goa state legislature enacted the Succession, <strong>Special Notaries and Inventory Proceedings Act,</strong> amending certain provisions, mainly procedural, of the 155-year old civil code.</li>
<li>In 2019, the <strong>UT of Daman and Diu was merged</strong> with another such territory – Dadra and Nagar Haveli (also ruled in the past by Portugal) — to form a single UT under central rule.</li>
<li>As laid down in Section 17 of the unifying Act, this development did not in any way change the family law system prevailing in either of these places since their liberation from foreign rule.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Need for uniform civil code</h4>
<ul>
<li>The law ministry has told the concerned standing committee of Parliament that the Portuguese civil code and its later amendments as in force in Goa may — if required — be duly reviewed.</li>
<li>Uniform civil code: What has been said now by the law ministry about Goa is in the context of implementing the constitutional directive of <strong>Article 44</strong> for a uniform civil code for the citizens throughout the territory of India.</li>
<li>However, while the 21st Law Commission had already given its opinion against the feasibility and need of such a code at this juncture</li>
<li>In recent months, the ministry has told Parliament about its reference on this issue to the Law Commission.</li>
<li>There is no justification for retaining over a century-old archaic law, 75 years after the independence of India.</li>
<li>Hindu law Acts of 1955-56 governing<strong> four religious communities in the rest of the country</strong> needs to be extended to the same communities in Goa, Daman and Diu.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Conclusion</h4>
<p>The ministry has now reportedly told the parliamentary committee that enacting a uniform civil code would be possible only when a “sizeable majority” of the people seeks such a change.</p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/the-portuguese-civil-code-of-1867-is-a-colonial-burden-on-goa/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Drugs shortage haunts HIV-positive community</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/drugs-shortage-haunts-hiv-positive-community/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>ART therapy</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>People living with HIV are facing an acute shortage of life-saving drugs, say protesters who have been camping outside the National AIDS Control Organisation (NACO) office.</p>
<h4>What is NACO?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The NACO established in 1992 is a division of India’s Ministry of Health and Family Welfare.</li>
<li>It provides leadership to HIV/AIDS control programme in India through 35 HIV/AIDS Prevention and Control Societies.</li>
<li>It is the nodal organisation for formulation of policy and implementation of programs for prevention and control of HIV/AIDS in India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Functions of NACO</h4>
<ul>
<li>Along with drug control authorities and NACO provides joint surveillance of Blood Bank licensing, Blood Donation activities and Transfusion Transmitted infection testing and reporting.</li>
<li>NACO also undertakes HIV estimations biennially (every 2 years) in collaboration with the Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR) – National Institute of Medical Statistics (NIMS).</li>
<li>The first round of HIV estimation in India was done in 1998, while the last round was done in 2017.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Activists allege rationing of medicines, arbitrary change in the drug regimen and even complete deprivation of life-saving paediatric drugs.</li>
<li>They fear that treatment will be interrupted, leading to drug resistance and deaths from AIDS.</li>
</ul>
<h4>NACO stand</h4>
<ul>
<li>The protesters noted that the NACO, in its public communication, had claimed that 95% of the recipients had not faced any shortage.</li>
<li>Going by the figure, 5% of 14.5 lakh, or 72,500 people, are being affected by the current shortage and stock-out.</li>
<li>The impact is severe and far-reaching.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What drugs are protestors talking about?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Protestors are for a stock-out of ART (antiretroviral) drugs such as <strong><u>Dolutegravir</u></strong> 50 mg, <strong><u>Lopinavir/Ritonavir</u></strong> (adult and child doses), and <strong><u>Abacavir</u></strong> in several states.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is ART?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The medicines that treat HIV are called antiretroviral drugs.</li>
<li>There are more than two dozen of them, and they fall into seven main types.</li>
<li>Each drug fights the virus in your body in a slightly different way.</li>
<li>Research shows that a combination, or “cocktail,” of drugs is the best way to control HIV and lower the chances that the virus will become resistant to treatment.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: HIV/AIDS</h4>
<ul>
<li>HIV (human immunodeficiency virus) is a virus that attacks cells that help the body fight infection, making a person more vulnerable to other infections and diseases.</li>
<li>First identified in 1981, HIV is the cause of one of humanity’s deadliest and most persistent epidemics.</li>
<li>It is spread by contact with certain bodily fluids of a person with HIV, most commonly during unprotected sex, or through sharing injection drug equipment.</li>
<li>If left untreated, HIV can lead to the disease AIDS (acquired immunodeficiency syndrome).</li>
<li>The human body can’t get rid of HIV and no effective HIV cure exists.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Treating HIV</h4>
<ul>
<li>However, by taking HIV medicine (called antiretroviral therapy or ART), people with HIV can live long and healthy lives and prevent transmitting HIV to their sexual partners.</li>
<li>In addition, there are effective methods to prevent getting HIV through sex or drug use, including pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) and post-exposure prophylaxis (PEP).</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/drugs-shortage-haunts-hiv-positive-community/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Langya Virus?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-langya-virus/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Langya virus</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Zoonotic Diseases</p></div></div><p>A new virus, Langya henipavirus, is suspected to have caused infections in 35 people in China’s Shandong and Henan provinces over roughly a two-year period to 2021.</p>
<h4>Langya Virus</h4>
<ul>
<li>It’s related to Hendra and Nipah viruses, which cause disease in humans.</li>
<li>However, there’s much we don’t know about the new virus – known as LayV for short – including whether it spreads from human to human.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How sick are people getting?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Symptoms reported appeared to be mostly mild – fever, fatigue, cough, loss of appetite, muscle aches, nausea and headache – although we don’t know how long the patients were unwell.</li>
<li>A smaller proportion had potentially more serious complications, including pneumonia, and abnormalities in liver and kidney function.</li>
<li>However, the severity of these abnormalities, the need for hospitalization, and whether any cases were fatal were not reported.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where did this virus come from?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The authors also investigated whether domestic or wild animals may have been the source of the virus.</li>
<li>Although they found a small number of goats and dogs that may have been infected with the virus in the past, there was more direct evidence a significant proportion of wild shrews were harbouring the virus.</li>
<li>This suggests humans may have caught the virus from wild shrews.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Does this virus actually cause this disease?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The researchers used a modern technique known as <strong><u>metagenomic analysis</u></strong> to find this new virus.</li>
<li>Researchers sequence all genetic material then discard the “known” sequences (for example, human DNA) to look for “unknown” sequences that might represent a new virus.</li>
<li>This raises the question about how scientists can tell whether a particular virus causes the disease.</li>
<li>Researchers used “<strong><u>Koch’s Postulates</u></strong>” to determine whether a particular micro-organism causes disease:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>it must be found in people with the disease and not in well people</li>
<li>it must be able to be isolated from people with the disease</li>
<li>the isolate from people with the disease must cause the disease if given to a healthy person (or animal)</li>
<li>it must be able to be re-isolated from the healthy person after they become ill.</li>
</ol>
<h4>What can we learn from related viruses?</h4>
<ul>
<li>This new virus appears to be a close cousin of two other viruses that are significant in humans: Nipah virus and Hendra virus.</li>
<li>This family of viruses was the inspiration for the fictional MEV-1 virus in the film Contagion.</li>
<li>Hendra virus was first reported in Queensland in 1994, when it caused the deaths of 14 horses and the trainer Vic Rail.</li>
<li>Nipah virus is more significant globally, with outbreaks frequently reported in Bangladesh.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What lies ahead?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Little is known about this new virus, and the currently reported cases are likely to be the tip of the iceberg.</li>
<li>At this stage, there is no indication the virus can spread from human to human.</li>
<li>Further work is required to determine how severe the infection can be, how it spreads, and how widespread it might be in China and the region.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-langya-virus/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What happens after a Cooperative Bank to shuts down?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-happens-after-a-cooperative-bank-to-shuts-down/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Deposit Insurance Programme, Banking License</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) announced it had cancelled the banking licence of a Pune-based Rupee Cooperative Bank, and directed the Registrar of Cooperative Societies to liquidate the bank.</p>
<h4>What is a Banking Licence?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Financial institutions wishing to carry out banking operations such as accepting deposits or lending have to obtain a licence from India’s central bank.</li>
<li>The RBI issues the licence under the Banking Regulation Act of 1949 after carrying out a series of checks about the financial suitability of the applicant institution.</li>
<li>Parameters like capital adequacy ratio (CAR) — the ratio of a bank’s available capital to its risk weighted credit exposure — and loan to deposit ratio (LDR) — the ratio of a bank’s total loans to total deposits in the same period — are checked before the licence is granted.</li>
<li>The 1949 Act in particular stresses on adequate capital and protection of the public interest before the licence is granted.</li>
<li>No company other than one that has been issued a banking licence is allowed to use the word bank in its name while doing business.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Cancelling the licence of a Bank</h4>
<ul>
<li>RBI, which issues the licence, has the power to cancel it as well, in case the bank fails to satisfy laid-down conditions.</li>
<li>This could mean an increase in bad debts — and if the RBI feels a bank does not have enough capital to cover its exposure and pay its depositors, its licence can be suspended or cancelled.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did RBI cancel the licence of Rupee Cooperative Bank?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The RBI audits banks every year, and can take action if it notes an increase in bad debts or other suspicious activities in their books.</li>
<li>In its press release, the RBI gave the reasons for the cancellation of the bank’s licence:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>The bank does not have adequate capital and earning prospects.</li>
<li>The bank has failed to comply with the requirements of certain sections of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949;</li>
<li>The continuance of the bank is prejudicial to the interests of its positions;</li>
<li>The bank with its present financial position would be unable to pay its present depositors in full; and</li>
<li>Public interest would be adversely affected if the bank is allowed to carry on its banking business any further.</li>
</ol>
<blockquote><p><em>Section 22 of the Act deals with “licensing of banking companies”, section 11 is about “requirement as to minimum paid-up capital and reserves”, and section 56 is about the applicability of the Act to cooperative societies, subject to modifications.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4>Was cancellation of the licence the only option left for RBI?</h4>
<ul>
<li>RBI had issued notice to that Cooperative Bank in 2013, and issued directions under the Banking Regulation Act before cancelling its licence.</li>
<li>All banking activities like withdrawal were suspended, the then board of directors was superseded.</li>
<li>The banker took a number of steps to revive the bank, including filing of criminal cases against defaulting directors, employees, and seizing of their properties.</li>
<li>The RBI extended the licence of the bank every three months as these steps were being taken.</li>
<li>The administrator also tried to merge the bank with a financially stable bank. But the bad debts scared away most suitors.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What will happen to the depositors’ money in Rupee Cooperative Bank?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The limiting of withdrawals by RBI had made things difficult for depositors, especially because cooperative banks are preferred by those from the lower income group.</li>
<li>The big question before the over 5.5 lakh depositors now is about the fate of their money.</li>
<li>The RBI has said that depositors with Rs 5 lakh or less in the bank, would get back all of their money through the Deposit Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation (DICGC).</li>
<li>Those who have larger deposits in the bank will not get back their money beyond Rs 5 lakh.</li>
<li>In this group are about 4,600 depositors with a total Rs 340 crore in deposits in the bank.</li>
<li>These people stand to suffer major losses.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Deposit Insurance Programme</h4>
<ul>
<li>The bank savings are insured under the Deposit Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation (DICGC) Act providing full coverage to around 98 per cent of bank accounts.</li>
<li>Earlier, account holders had to wait for years till the liquidation or restructuring of a distressed lender to get their deposits that are insured against default.</li>
<li>Last year, the government raised the insurance amount to Rs 5 lakh from Rs 1 lakh.</li>
<li>Prior to that, the DICGC had revised the deposit insurance cover to Rs 1 lakh on May 1, 1993 — raising it from Rs 30,000, which had been the cover from 1980 onward.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What are new changes?</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Earlier, out of the amount deposited in the bank, only Rs 50,000 was guaranteed, which was then raised to Rs 1 lakh.</li>
<li>Understanding the concern of the poor, understanding the concern of the middle class, we increased this amount to Rs 5 lakh.</li>
<li>If a bank is weak or is even about to go bankrupt, depositors will get their money of up to Rs five lakhs within 90 days.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-happens-after-a-cooperative-bank-to-shuts-down/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Significance of India’s talks with NATO</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/significance-of-indias-talks-with-nato/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NATO</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India-NATO relations</p></div></div><p>It has been learnt that India had held its first political dialogue with the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) in Brussels on December 12, 2019.</p>
<p>The idea was to ensure the dialogue was primarily political in character, and to avoid making any commitment on military or other bilateral cooperation.</p>
<h4><strong>What is NATO?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>NATO is a military alliance established by the North Atlantic Treaty (also called the Washington Treaty) of April 4, 1949.</li>
<li>It sought to create a counterweight to Soviet armies stationed in Central and Eastern Europe after World War II.</li>
<li>Its original members were Belgium, Canada, Denmark, France, Iceland, Italy, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, Norway, Portugal, the United Kingdom, and the United States.</li>
<li>NATO has spread a web of partners, namely Egypt, Israel, Sweden, Austria, Switzerland and Finland.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why was it founded?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Ans.</strong> Communist sweep in Europe post-WWII and rise of Soviet dominance</p>
<ul>
<li>After World War II in 1945, Western Europe was economically exhausted and militarily weak, and newly powerful communist parties had arisen in France and Italy.</li>
<li>By contrast, the Soviet Union had emerged from the war with its armies dominating all the states of central and Eastern Europe.</li>
<li>By 1948 communists under Moscow’s sponsorship had consolidated their control of the governments of those countries and suppressed all non-communist political activity.</li>
<li>What became known as the Iron Curtain, a term popularized by Winston Churchill, had descended over central and Eastern Europe.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Ideology of NATO</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>NATO ensures that the security of its European member countries is inseparably linked to that of its North American member countries.</li>
<li>It commits the Allies to democracy, individual liberty and the rule of law, as well as to the peaceful resolution of disputes.</li>
<li>It also provides a unique forum for dialogue and cooperation across the Atlantic.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Key feature: Article 5</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Article 5 was a key part of the 1949 North Atlantic Treaty, or Washington Treaty, and was meant to offer a collective defence against a potential invasion of Western Europe.</li>
<li>It states: (NATO members) will assist the party or parties so attacked by taking forthwith, individually and in concert with the other parties, such action as it deems necessary, including the use of armed force, to restore and maintain the security of the North Atlantic area.</li>
<li>However, since then, it has only been invoked once, soon after the 9/11 attack in the United States.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the significance of India’s talks with NATO?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s talks with NATO hold significance given that the North Atlantic alliance has been engaging both China and Pakistan in bilateral dialogue.</li>
<li>There was a view here that given the role of Beijing and Islamabad in New Delhi’s strategic imperatives, reaching out to NATO would add a key dimension to <strong><u>India’s growing engagement with US and Europe</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Until December 2019, <strong><u>NATO had held nine rounds of talks with Beijing</u></strong>, and the Chinese Ambassador in Brussels and NATO’s Deputy Secretary General engaged with each other every quarter.</li>
<li>NATO had also been in <strong><u>political dialogue and military cooperation with Pakistan</u></strong>; it opened selective training for Pakistani officers and its military delegation visited Pakistan in November 2019 for military staff talks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Was there any common ground?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In New Delhi’s assessment, there was a convergence in the perspectives of both India and NATO on China, terrorism, and Afghanistan, including Pakistan’s role in Afghanistan.</li>
<li>The first dialogue, it is learnt, revealed <strong><u>three critical issues</u></strong> on which India expected only limited common ground with NATO:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>NATO’s perspective:</strong> It was not China, but Russia whose aggressive actions continued to be the main threat to Euro-Atlantic security, and NATO had faced difficulties to convene meetings of the NATO-Russia Council due to Russian refusal to place issues such as Ukraine and Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty on the agenda.</li>
<li><strong>Divergence among NATO countries:</strong> NATOs view on China was seen as mixed; while it did deliberate on China’s rise, the conclusion was that China presented both a challenge and an opportunity.</li>
<li><strong>Divergences over Taliban:</strong> In Afghanistan, NATO saw the Taliban as a political entity, which was not in line with India’s stance. This was almost two years before the Taliban announced an interim government in Afghanistan in September 2021.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>India-NATO talks: Is there a common ground on China?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In its first round of talks with NATO, New Delhi realised it did not share a common ground with the grouping on Russia and the Taliban.</li>
<li>With <strong><u>NATO’s views on China are mixed</u></strong>, given the divergent views of its members, India’s Quad membership is aimed at countering Beijing.</li>
<li>Otherwise, the alliance’s engagement with China and Pakistan separately would leave it with lopsided perspectives on regional and global security matters of concern to India, sourced said.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the next steps?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>NATO delegation have expressed interest to continue engagement with India on a mutually agreed agenda.</li>
<li>In NATO’s view, India, given its geo-strategic position and unique perspectives on various issues, was relevant to international security and could be an important partner in informing the alliance about India’s own region and beyond.</li>
<li>As far as India is concerned, it was felt New Delhi may consider proposals emanating from NATO, if any, on bilateral cooperation in areas of interest to India, based on the progress achieved in the initial rounds.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/significance-of-indias-talks-with-nato/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>UN appoints new leader of UNMOGIP</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/un-appoints-new-leader-of-unmogip/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UNMOGIP</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Internationalization of Kashmir Issue</p></div></div><p>The United Nations (UN) has appointed Rear Admiral Guillermo Pablo Rios of Argentina as the Head of Mission and Chief Military Observer for the United Nations Military Observer Group in India and Pakistan (UNMOGIP).</p>
<h4>What is UNMOGIP?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The first group of UN military observers arrived in the mission area on 24 January of 1949 to supervise the ceasefire between India and Pakistan in the Indian state of Jammu and Kashmir.</li>
<li>These observers, under the command of the Military Adviser appointed by the UN Secretary-General, formed the nucleus of the United Nations Military Observer Group in India and Pakistan (UNMOGIP).</li>
</ul>
<h4>Functions of UNMOGIP</h4>
<ul>
<li>Following renewed hostilities of 1971, UNMOGIP has remained in the area to observe developments pertaining to the strict observance of the ceasefire of 17 December 1971 and report thereon to the UN Secretary-General.</li>
<li>The Karachi Agreement of July 1949 firmed up the role of UN-level military observers and permitted supervision of the Ceasefire Line established in Jammu and Kashmir.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Indian contentions with UNMOGIP</h4>
<ul>
<li>India has <strong><u>not officially gone to the UNMOGIP since 1972</u></strong> with complaints against Pakistan.</li>
<li>India officially maintains that the UNMOGIP’s role was “<strong><u>overtaken” by the Simla Agreement of 1972</u></strong> that <strong><u>established the Line of Control</u></strong> or the LoC.</li>
<li>This with minor deviations followed the earlier Ceasefire Line.</li>
<li>Pakistan, however, did not accept the Indian argument and continued to seek cooperation from the UNMOGIP.</li>
<li>As a result of these divergent policies, Pakistan continues to lodge complaints with the UNMOGIP against alleged Indian ceasefire violations.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Substantiation of India’s stance</h4>
<ul>
<li>Since the Simla Agreement of 1972, India has adopted a <strong><u>non-recognition policy towards third parties</u></strong> in their bilateral exchanges with Pakistan over the question regarding the state of Jammu and Kashmir.</li>
<li>Kashmir and the Pakistan-sponsored terrorism within now is largely an internal matter of India.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/un-appoints-new-leader-of-unmogip/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-criminal-procedure-identification-act-2022/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>While the Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022 was enacted earlier this year, the Ministry of Home Affairs notified it to come into effect from August 4, 2022. It also repeals the existing Identification of Prisoners Act, 1920.</p>
<h4>What is the Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022?</h4>
<ul>
<li>This act provides legal sanction to law enforcement agencies for “taking measurements of convicts and other persons for the purposes of identification and investigation of criminal matters”.</li>
<li>The Minister of Home Affairs has observed that with advancements in forensics, there was a need to recognise more kinds of “measurements” that can be used by law enforcement agencies for investigation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the use of identification details in criminal trials?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Measurements and photographs for identification have three main purposes:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>To establish the identity of the culprit against the person being arrested</li>
<li>To identify suspected repetition of similar offences by the same person and third</li>
<li>To establish a previous conviction</li>
</ol>
<h4>What was the previous Identification of Prisoners Act, 1920?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Even though the police has powers of arrest, mere <strong><u>arrest does not give Police the right to search a person</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The police requires <strong><u>legal sanction to search the person</u></strong> and collect evidence.</li>
<li>These legal sanctions are designed so as <strong><u>to maintain a balance between the rights of an individual and the interests of society</u></strong> in prosecution and prevention of offences.</li>
<li>The Identification of Prisoners Act, 1920 became a necessity when the <strong><u>recording of newer forms of evidence such as fingerprints, footprints and measurements started</u></strong> becoming more accurate and reliable.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What was the need to replace this Act?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Over the years, the need to amend/update the Identification of Prisoners Act, 1920 has been voiced several times.</li>
<li>In 1980, the <strong><u>87th Report of the Law Commission of India</u></strong> undertook a review of this legislation and recommended several amendments.</li>
<li>This was done in the backdrop of the <strong><u>State of UP vs Ram Babu Misra case</u></strong>, where the Supreme Court had highlighted the need for amending this law.</li>
<li>The first set of recommendations laid out the need to amend the Act to expand the scope of measurements <strong><u>to include “palm impressions”, “specimen of signature or writing” and “specimen of voice”. </u></strong></li>
<li>The second set of recommendations raised the <strong><u>need of allowing measurements to be taken for proceedings</u></strong> other than those under the Code of Criminal Procedure (CrPC).</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the main highlights and differences in both the legislations?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Like the Identification of Prisoners Act, 1920, the new Criminal Procedure (Identification) Act, 2022 provides for legal sanction to law enforcement agencies for the collection of measurements.</li>
<li>The purpose is to create a useable database of these measurements.</li>
<li>At the State level, each State is required to notify an appropriate agency to collect and preserve this database of measurements.</li>
<li>At the national level, the National Crime Records Bureau (NCRB) is the designated agency to manage, process, share and disseminate the records collected at the State level.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are some of the concerns with the present legislation?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The new legislation has raised some <strong><u>concerns related to the protection of fundamental rights</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The legislation comes in the backdrop of the <strong><u>right to privacy</u></strong> being recognised as a fundamental right.</li>
<li>A fundamental facet of the right to privacy is <strong><u>protection from the invasion of one’s physical privacy</u></strong>.</li>
<li>As per the Puttaswamy judgment, there is a need for the measure to be taken in pursuance of a legitimate aim of the state, be backed by the law and be “necessary and proportionate” to the aim being sought to be achieved.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(1) Various tests behind</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In this case, while the first two tests are satisfied, as:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>“<strong><u>prevention and investigation of crime</u></strong>” is a legitimate aim of the state</li>
<li>“<strong><u>measurements</u></strong>” are being taken under a valid legislation,</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Satisfaction of the third test of “<strong><u>necessity and proportionality</u></strong>” has been challenged on multiple counts.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) A probable police state in making</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Analysis and measurement of behavioural attributes have raised concerns that data processing may go beyond recording of core “measurements”.</li>
<li>That is some of these measurements could be processed for <strong><u>predictive policing</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Includes petty offences</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The current law allows for “measurements” to be taken if a person has been convicted/arrested for any offence, including petty offences.</li>
<li>The necessity of taking measurements of such persons for investigation of offences is unclear, and such discretion is likely to result in abuse of the law at lower levels.</li>
<li>This would definitely overburden the systems used for collection and storage of these measurements.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Period of storage of data</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Given that these records will be stored for 75 years from the time of collection, the law has been criticised as being disproportionate.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(5) Surveillance state</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Such collection can also result in mass surveillance, with the database under this law being combined with other databases such as those of the Crime and Criminal Tracking Network and Systems (CCTNS).</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(6) Promotes self-incrimination</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Concerns are being raised that the <strong><u>present law violates the right against self-incrimination</u></strong> enshrined in Article 20(3) of the Constitution of India.</li>
<li>However, this argument is nebulous since the Supreme Court has already settled this point.</li>
<li>In the State of Bombay vs Kathi Kalu Oghad, the Supreme Court had conclusively held that “non-communicative” evidence i.e. evidence which does not convey information within the personal knowledge of the accused cannot be understood to be leading to self-incrimination.</li>
<li>Therefore, no challenge lies to the law on this ground.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Way forward</h4>
<ul>
<li>Extensive pre-legislative consultation is must for any sensitive law as such.</li>
<li>Privacy and data protection-related concerns must be addressed in the Rules formulated under the legislation and through model Prison Manuals that States can refer to.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-criminal-procedure-identification-act-2022/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Efficiency of police institution is decreasing</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/efficiency-of-police-institution-is-decreasing/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Malimath Committee</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Police reforms due in India</p></div></div><p><strong>Context </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is a widely shared view that the All India Services, which provided the ‘steel frame’ of governance in a democratic India, particularly on the police front, <strong>are failing to deliver.</strong></li>
<li>This is because of <strong>the declining decision-making</strong> ability of its officers, their smugness arising from notions of total employment security, and the inadequacy of parameters used for evaluating their performance.</li>
<li>Anti-corruption bureau Was Constituted To Shield Corrupt Politicians, Officers From Lokayukta: Karnataka High Court</li>
</ul>
<h4>Role of Police</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Law enforcement</strong>: The basic role of the police is to function as a law enforcement agency and render impartial service to law, without any heed to wishes, indications or desires expressed by the government which either come in conflict with or do not conform to the provisions contained in the constitution or laws.</li>
<li><strong>Service delivery</strong>: The police should have duly recognised service-oriented role in providing relief to people in distress situations. They should be trained and equipped to perform the service oriented functions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with police institution</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Public relationship</strong>: The police-public relations relationship, which is crucial to effective policing, is troubled by a severe lack of confidence.</li>
<li><strong>Public perception towards police</strong>: Most people believe police to be abusive and also believe that police personnel misuse their power in order to bring order to society.</li>
<li><strong>Police Accountability: </strong>Police priorities are constantly changed at the request of political leaders. This obstructs police officers’ ability to make professional decisions</li>
<li><strong>Overburdened force and vacancies</strong>: A high percentage of vacancies in police departments exacerbates an already-existing problem of overworked officers. Given India’s low police strength per lakh population in comparison to international standards, each police officer is also responsible for a huge group of people.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure</strong>: The weapons used by lower police forces are obsolete and cannot match modern weaponry used by anti-social elements.</li>
<li><strong>Custodial Death</strong>: There are many cases on custodial death means Death by torture/pressure in police/judicial custody.</li>
<li><strong>The dilemmas and challenges</strong>:</li>
</ul>
<p>(1) The Ubiquitous infrastructure (2) Explosion of police tasks (3) Dis-functionalism of rural police (4) Anomalous personnel system (5) The colossal ignorance of either side (6) The fragility of the equipment (7) The paradox of para militarism (8) Non-development to policing</p>
<p><strong>Steps taken till now </strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Establishment of a Central Police Committee:</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>A Central Police Committee to look after the functions of consultancy and monitoring be</p>
<p>Created because an expert agency is required by the Central Government and the State</p>
<p>Security Commissions to advise them on matters relating to:</p>
<p>(i) Police Organisation and police reforms of a general nature;</p>
<p>(ii) Central grants and loans to the State Police Forces for their modernisation and Development; and</p>
<p>(iii) Budgetary allotments to State Police Forces.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enactment of a Model Police Act</strong>:</li>
</ul>
<p>The Police Act of 1861 replaced by a new Police Act, which not only changes the</p>
<p>System of superintendence and control over the police but also enlarges the role of the</p>
<p>Police to make it function as an agency which promotes the rule of law in the country and</p>
<p>Renders impartial service to the community.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The Prime Minister’s call for making the police a SMART force: standing for a force which is</strong>:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Strict and Sensitive,</li>
<li>Modern and Mobile,</li>
<li>Alert and Accountable,</li>
<li>Reliable and Responsive,</li>
<li>Tech-savvy and trained.</li>
</ol>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="601"><strong>Malimath committee</strong>:
<ul>
<li>Government had set up (November, 2000) a Committee under the Chairmanship</li>
<li>of Justice V.S. Malimath , a former Chief Justice of the Karnataka and Kerala High</li>
<li>Courts to consider and recommend measures for revamping <strong>the Criminal Justice System.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Key recommendations :</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Strengthening of training infrastructure, forensic</li>
<li>Science laboratory and Finger Print Bureau,</li>
<li>Enactment of the new Police Act,</li>
<li>Setting up of Central Law Enforcement agency to take care of federal crimes</li>
<li>Separation of the investigation wing from the law and order wing in the police stations,</li>
<li>Improvement in the investigation by creating more posts.</li>
</ul>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h4>Some suggestions for better policing:</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Screen for Implicit Bias and Aggression:</strong> State legislatures should pass legislation that requires current and prospective police officers to undergo mandatory implicit bias testing</li>
<li><strong>Focus on Collaborative Approaches to Policing</strong>: Police departments should rely upon collaborative approaches that respect the dignity of individuals within the community; focus on problem-solving; and are generally more community centered and build community trust.</li>
<li><strong>Encourage Consistent Monitoring and Screening</strong>: Police departments should create early warning systems for detecting patterns of behaviour, such as complaints filed against officers or personal hardships like divorce, which indicate potential vulnerabilities for the officer and the department.</li>
<li><strong>Use Video Recording to Promote Accountability: </strong>Legislatures should require that police interrogations be electronically recorded “during the time in which a reasonable person in the subject’s position would consider themselves to be in custody and a law enforcement officer’s questioning is likely to elicit incriminating responses.</li>
<li><strong>Increase the use of special prosecutors in police misconduct investigations</strong></li>
<li><strong>Enhancing the collection of data on fatalities involving police</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India is the target of an ever-growing list of terrorist groups, insurgent forces and criminal networks.</li>
<li>Even petty criminals are now in possession of hi-tech gadgets that allow them better access and reduce their chances of being caught.</li>
<li>In such an environment, the need for skill and competency up-gradation of the police force is a sine qua non.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><em>Q. What is smart policing? Considering the rise in custodial deaths give some suggestions to improve criminal justice delivery system in India.</em></h4>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/efficiency-of-police-institution-is-decreasing/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Importance of medical education</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/importance-of-medical-education/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Medical education in India</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong>increasing population (1.32 billion ) and the occurrence of diseases,</strong> demands Indian medical education and the training approach to be modified and ensure enhancing practical clinical skills, than just sticking with predominantly theoretical or classroom training.</li>
<li>The <strong>demand for medicine to be taught in language beside English</strong> has been made repeatedly over the years, and was reiterated by union home minister recently.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Definition</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Medical education consists of training aimed at ensuring physicians acquire the competencies, skills and aptitudes that that allow them to practice professionally and ethically at the highest level.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Goal of medical education</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The goal of basic medical education is to ensure that medical students have acquired the knowledge, skills, and professional behaviors that prepare them for a spectrum of career choices, including, but not limited to, patient care, public health, clinical or basic research, leadership and management, or medical education.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why medical education in India needs urgent reforms</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Current Status</strong>: Despite being home <strong>to one of the oldest</strong> medicinal systems in the world, India is still struggling to bring its medical education at par with the leaders around the world. The 541 medical colleges in the country haven’t been able to reach <strong>the standard of education</strong> that could meet the healthcare needs of the country.</li>
<li><strong>Deficiency: </strong>The <strong>doctor-patient ratio of 1:1655 in India as against WHO norm of 1:1000</strong> clearly shows the deficit of MBBS. While the government is working towards a solution and targeting to reach the required ratio<strong>, there is a need to relook at the overall medical education.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Post pandemic scenario:</strong> The lag in formal medical education has come up evidently post-pandemic when the nation saw the medical fraternity struggling to fill the doctor deficit.</li>
<li><strong>Structural issues:</strong> It also brought forth the <strong>outdated learning</strong> methods that most of the medical institutes were using. Due to lockdown and fear of Covid-19 spread, a lot of institutes cancelled lectures and practical sessions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Current challenges faced by medical education in India </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Limited government seats:</strong> The number of seats available for medical education in India is far less than the number of aspirants who leave school with the dream of becoming doctors.</li>
<li><strong>What data speaks: </strong>Of the 1.6 million students who appeared in the National Eligibility cum Entrance Test (NEET) in 2021, only 88,120 made it into the 562 medical colleges in the country. Others had to enrol in non-medical courses in India or seek admission to foreign medical colleges. While the number of medical colleges has now increased to 596 (with 89,875 seats), the entry barrier is still high.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of skills</strong>: Though the institutes are managing to hire professors and lecturers, there is a lack of technical skills. Finding faculties in clinical and non-clinical disciplines is difficult and there are very few faculty development programs for upskilling the existing lot.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of infrastructure</strong>: The gap in digital learning infrastructure is currently the biggest challenge the sector is facing. There is an urgent need to adopt technology and have resources available to facilitate e-learning.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of research and innovation</strong>: The medical research and innovation needs an added push as there haven’t been many ground-breaking research here. The education system needs to focus more on increasing the quality of research. Additionally since industry academia partnership is not available, hence innovation also takes a back-seat.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em>A recent analysis estimates that India has only 4.8 fully qualified and actively serving doctors per 10,000 population.</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Government steps in tackling these challenges and issues </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>NMC bill:</strong> The National Medical Commission Bill, 2019 was passed recently by the parliament. The bill sets up the National Medical Commission (NMC) which will act as an umbrella regulatory body in the medical education system. The NMC will subsume the MCI and will regulate medical education and practice in India. Apart from this, it also provides for reforms in the medical education system.</li>
<li><strong>MCI suggestion:</strong> The Medical Council of India (MCI) launched the globally recognized <strong>Competency-based medical education</strong> (CBME) for MBBS students in 2019. The CBME curriculum seeks to step away from a content-based syllabus and more towards one that is more practical and aligned with the country’s increasing health demands.</li>
<li><strong>Schemes:</strong> 22 new All India Institutes of Medical Sciences (AIIMS) were developed under this initiative, and MBBS classes have already commenced at 18 of the new AIIMS.</li>
</ul>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="601">
<h4><strong>About NMC<br/>
</strong></h4>
<p>The Aim of the National Medical Commission are to (i) improve access to quality and affordable medical education, (ii) ensure availability of adequate and high quality medical professionals in all parts of the country; (iii) promote equitable and universal healthcare that encourages community health perspective and makes services of medical professionals accessible to all the citizens; (iv) encourages medical professionals to adopt latest medical research in their work and to contribute to research; (v) objectively assess medical institutions  periodically in a transparent manner; (vi) maintain a medical register for India; (vi) enforce high ethical standards in all aspects of medical services; (vii) have an effective grievance redressal mechanism.</p></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h4><strong>Steps to be taken</strong><strong> </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To cater to any unprecedented demand in the future and to bring up the quality of education, the Indian medical education system undoubtedly needs major reforms.</li>
<li>While the focus needs to be put on improving the curriculum to bring competency-based education, there are several ways that can help bring reform in the current medical education system. Some of these are;</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Leveraging technology to offer digital learning solutions</li>
<li>Capitalizing on e-learning and facilitating infrastructure to support it</li>
<li>Revising curriculum to have more practical training, competency-based skill development</li>
<li>Inculcating problem-solving approach by situational/case-based examination</li>
<li>A broad-based faculty development program to sharpen the competency of teachers</li>
<li>Eliminating caste-based reservation and paving way for merit-based admission</li>
<li>Industry academia collaboration to facilitate innovation</li>
</ol>
<h4>Way forward<strong><br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There should be a substantial step-up in public investment in medical education.</li>
<li>By establishing new medical colleges, the government can increase student intake as well as enhance equitable access to medical education.</li>
<li>Besides, it must allocate adequate financial resources to strengthen the overall capacity of existing medical colleges to enrich student learning and improve output.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this question for mains</h4>
<p><em><strong>Q. Considering the large diaspora of medical students across the globe do you consider there are problems in Indian medical education system? If there are any ,discuss them along with current health status and steps needed to counter them .</strong></em></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/importance-of-medical-education/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Need of uniform civil code</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/need-of-uniform-civil-code/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UCC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Portuguese Civil Code of 1867, the so-called<strong> “common civil code” of Goa</strong>, is in the news again. A 28-member parliamentary standing committee headed by senior BJP leader and Rajya Sabha member, Sushil Kumar Modi, recently visited the state to study it in the context of the <strong>demand for a uniform civil code.</strong></li>
<li><strong>India Needs Uniform Civil Code; One Nation, One Law Will Restore Equality and Gender Parity</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Definition</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Uniform Civil Code (UCC) calls for the formulation of <strong>one law for India, which would be applicable to all religious communities</strong> in matters such as marriage, divorce, inheritance, adoption. <strong>The code comes under Article 44 of the Constitution</strong>, which lays down that the state shall endeavour to secure <strong>a Uniform Civil Code for the citizens throughout the territory of India.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Importance of article 44</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The objective of Article 44 of the Directive Principles in the Indian Constitution was to <strong>address the discrimination against vulnerable groups and harmonise diverse cultural groups across the country.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Brief history of UCC </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The origin of the UCC dates back to colonial India when the British government submitted its report in 1835 stressing <strong>the need for uniformity in the codification of Indian law</strong> relating to crimes, evidence, and contracts, specifically recommending that personal laws of Hindus and Muslims be kept outside such codification.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Objectives of UCC:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Bringing simplicity in personal laws</strong>: When enacted the code will work to simplify laws that are segregated at present on the basis of religious beliefs like the Hindu code bill, Shariat law, and others.</li>
<li><strong>Uniformity across country: </strong>The code will simplify the complex laws around marriage ceremonies, inheritance, succession, adoptions <strong>making them one for all</strong>.  The same civil law will then be applicable to all citizens irrespective of their faith.</li>
<li><strong>National integration</strong>: The UCC aims to provide protection to vulnerable sections as envisaged by Babasaheb Ambedkar including women and religious minorities, while also promoting <strong>nationalistic fervour through unity.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why it is needed now </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>To counter the gender disparity produced by specific personal laws:</strong> India has a history of severely patriarchal and misogynistic traditions perpetuated by society and ancient religious norms that continue to dominate family life.</li>
<li><strong>Plugging the loopholes in legal system:</strong> By legalising personal laws, we’ve established a parallel court system based on thousands of ancient values. By eliminating all loopholes, the universal civil code would tip the balance in favour of society<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Reaffirming equality to everyone:</strong> While <strong>Muslims are permitted to marry many times</strong> in India, <strong>a Hindu or a Christian will face prosecution for doing the same.</strong> Similarly, there are significant disparities between many religious-related regulations.</li>
<li><strong>Addressing problem of vote bank politics:</strong> If all religions are subject to the same laws, there will be no room for <strong>politicising issues of discrimination, concessions, or special privileges</strong> enjoyed by a particular community on the basis of their religious personal laws.</li>
<li><strong>Infusing secularism</strong>: At the moment, we practise selective secularism, which means that we are secular in some areas but not in others. <strong>A Uniform Civil Code requires all citizens of India to adhere to the same set of laws</strong>, regardless of whether they follow Hinduism, Islam, Christianity or Sikhism.</li>
</ul>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="601">
<h4><strong>SC verdict on UCC: </strong><strong>Daniel Latifi Case<br/>
</strong></h4>
<p>This case demonstrates how universally applicable law should prevail over unjust religious laws. In this case, Muslim Women’s Act (MWA) was challenged for violation of Articles 14, 15 &amp; 21 of the Constitution. The primary point of contention was the amount paid throughout the iddat period. The Supreme Court upheld the act’s constitutionality but interpreted it in accordance with Section 125 of the CrPC, holding that the amount received by a wife during the iddat period should be sufficient to support her during the iddat period as well as for the remainder of her life or until she remarries.</p></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong>Challenges ahead in its application</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Less education to understand this:</strong> India is a country of a diverse culture where the beliefs of the people are too vehement but with the right communication and education to all the religious groups, the implementation can take place efficiently and effectively.</li>
<li><strong>Apprehension of some people</strong>: Fear of the certain section of society who are subjected to the special rights, shall be addressed since such rights will have no impact or interference by enactment of the Uniform Civil Code, which shall be ensured to the society as this is one of their Fundamental Rights as under Article 15 of the Indian Constitution.</li>
</ul>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="601">
<h4><strong>Case study of Goa:</strong></h4>
<p>It is pertinent to note that the State of Goa is the <strong>first </strong>State to implement a uniform civil code since its liberation from the Portuguese in 1961. <strong>The Supreme Court has even hailed Goa</strong> as a <strong>shining example</strong> where the uniform civil code is applicable to all, regardless of religion except while protecting certain limited rights.</p></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>With so much diversity, India needs something like a UCC which can work as an agent to promote uniformity and to some extent mute the sound pollution created by the religious radical forces.</li>
<li>On individual level, it is important to understand UCC is with the objective of One Nation, One Lawsided by oneness among the people rather than a mere tool to overcome oppression and discrimination against women or a target on a particular religion.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this question:<br/>
</strong></h4>
<p> </p>
<p><em><strong>What is uniform civil code? Do you think that right time has arrived to implement it? Discuss challenges in its implementation with your suggestions to overcome the same.</strong></em></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/need-of-uniform-civil-code/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>In news: Ongole Cattle Breed</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/in-news-ongole-cattle-breed/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ongole Cattle</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Indigenous cattle breedss</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-619914" height="268" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 407px) 100vw, 407px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ongole.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ongole.jpg 407w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/ongole-300x198.jpg 300w" width="407"/></strong></p>
<p>Ongole breed of cattle had remained indispensable for all farm operations for centuries in Prakasam district of Andhra Pradesh in view of their draught power.</p>
<h4>Ongole Cattle</h4>
<ul>
<li>Ongole cattle are an indigenous cattle breed that originates from Prakasam District in the state of Andhra Pradesh.</li>
<li>The breed derives its name from the place the breed originates from, Ongole.</li>
<li>The Ongole breed of cattle <strong><u>Bos Indicus</u></strong>, has a great demand as it is said to possess resistance to both foot and mouth disease and mad cow disease.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What’s so special about this breed?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Cattle breeders use the fighting ability of the bulls to choose the right stock for breeding in terms of purity and strength.</li>
<li>Ongole cattle are known for their toughness, rapid growth rate, and natural tolerance to tropical heat and disease resistance.</li>
<li>It was perhaps the first Indian breed of cattle to gain worldwide recognition.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Ongole milk is rich in A2 (allele of Beta Casein).</li>
<li>They fetches a premium price of over ₹150 per litre as it enables consumers build immunity against viral and other diseases.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Global Prominence</h4>
<ul>
<li>Ongole bulls have gone as far as America, the Netherlands, Malaysia, Brazil, Argentina, Colombia, Mexico, Paraguay, Indonesia, West Indies, Australia, Fiji, Mauritius, Indo-China and Philippines.</li>
<li>The Brahmana bull in America is an off-breed of the Ongole.</li>
<li>The population of Ongole off-breed in Brazil is said to number several million.</li>
<li>The famous Santa Gertrudis breed developed in Texas, USA have Ongole blood.</li>
<li>It has gained global prominence, particularly in Brazil which imported barely hundred animals and produced multiple superior breeds like the world famous Zebu.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/in-news-ongole-cattle-breed/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre to file review petition on Eco-Sensitive Zones in SC</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-to-file-review-petition-on-eco-sensitive-zones-in-sc/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Eco-sensitive Zones (ESZs)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>Union Minister of Environment, Forest and Climate Change has said that the Ministry will file a review petition in the Supreme Court urging a relook into its judgment on eco-sensitive zones.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court has earlier directed that every protected forest, national park and wildlife sanctuary across the country should have a mandatory eco-sensitive zone (ESZ) of a minimum one km starting from their demarcated boundaries.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why such move?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The purpose of declaring ESZs around national parks, forests and sanctuaries is to create some kind of a “shock absorber” for the protected areas.</li>
<li>These zones would act as a transition zone from areas of high protection to those involving lesser protection.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the Eco-sensitive Zones (ESZs)?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Eco-Sensitive Zones (ESZs) or Ecologically Fragile Areas (EFAs) are areas notified by the MoEFCC around Protected Areas, National Parks and Wildlife Sanctuaries.</li>
<li>The purpose of declaring ESZs is to create some kind of “shock absorbers” to the protected areas by regulating and managing the activities around such areas.</li>
<li>They also act as a transition zone from areas of high protection to areas involving lesser protection.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How are they demarcated?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 does not mention the word “Eco-Sensitive Zones”.</li>
<li>However, Section 3(2)(v) of the Act, says that Central Government can restrict areas in which any industries, operations or processes or class of industries, operations or processes shall be carried out or shall not, subject to certain safeguards.</li>
<li>Besides Rule 5(1) of the Environment (Protection) Rules, 1986 states that central government can prohibit or restrict the location of industries and carrying on certain operations or processes on the basis of certain considerations.</li>
<li>The same criteria have been used by the government to declare No Development Zones (NDZs).</li>
</ul>
<h4>Defining its boundaries</h4>
<ul>
<li>An ESZ could go up to 10 kilometres around a protected area as provided in the Wildlife Conservation Strategy, 2002.</li>
<li>Moreover, in the case where sensitive corridors, connectivity and ecologically important patches, crucial for landscape linkage, are beyond 10 km width, these should be included in the ESZs.</li>
<li>Further, even in the context of a particular Protected Area, the distribution of an area of ESZ and the extent of regulation may not be uniform all around and it could be of variable width and extent.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-to-file-review-petition-on-eco-sensitive-zones-in-sc/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SMILE-75 scheme to rehabilitate Beggars</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/smile-75-scheme-to-rehabilitate-beggars/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>SMILE Scheme</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The Social Justice and Empowerment Ministry has launched the ‘SMILE-75’ initiative for comprehensive rehabilitation of persons engaged in begging in 75 identified municipalities as a part of the celebrations of 75 years of Independence.</p>
<h4>SMILE Scheme</h4>
<ul>
<li>SMILE is an acronym for Support for Marginalised Individuals for Livelihood and Enterprise.</li>
<li>This scheme is a sub-scheme under the ‘Central Sector Scheme for Comprehensive Rehabilitation of persons engaged in the act of Begging’.</li>
<li>It also focuses on rehabilitation, provision of medical facilities and intervention, counselling, education, skill development, economic linkages to transgender persons.</li>
<li>It covers several comprehensive measures including welfare measures for persons who are engaged in the act of begging.</li>
<li>The focus of the scheme is extensively on rehabilitation, provision of medical facilities, counselling, basic documentation, education, skill development, economic linkages and so on.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Its implementation</h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme would be implemented with the support of State/UT Governments/Local Urban Bodies, Voluntary Organizations, Community Based Organizations (CBOs), institutions and others.</li>
<li>The scheme provides for the use of the existing shelter homes available with the State/UT Governments and Urban local bodies for rehabilitation of the persons engaged in the act of Begging.</li>
<li>In case of the non-availability of existing shelter homes, new dedicated shelter homes are to be set up by the implementing agencies.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/smile-75-scheme-to-rehabilitate-beggars/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Essential Commodities Act?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/essential-commodities-act-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Essential Commodities Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Centre has invoked the Essential Commodities Act of 1955 to ask States to monitor and verify the stocks of Arhar/Tur Dal available with traders.</p>
<h4><strong>Essential Commodities Act</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ECA, 1955 was established to ensure the delivery of certain commodities or products, the supply of which, if obstructed due to hoarding or black marketing, would affect the normal life of the people.</li>
<li>The list of items under the Act includes drugs, fertilizers, pulses, and edible oils, as well as petroleum and petroleum products.</li>
<li>The Centre can include new commodities as and when the need arises, and takes them off the list once the situation improves.</li>
<li>Additionally, the government can also fix the maximum retail price (MRP) of any packaged product that it declares an “essential commodity”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How ECA works?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Centre notifying stock limit holding</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>If the Centre finds that a certain commodity is in short supply and its price is spiking, it can notify stock-holding limits on it for a specified period.</li>
<li>The States act on this notification to specify limits and take steps to ensure that these are adhered to.</li>
<li>Anybody trading or dealing in the commodity, be it wholesalers, retailers or even importers are prevented from stockpiling it beyond a certain quantity.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) States can opt-out</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>A State can, however, choose not to impose any restrictions.</li>
<li>But once it does, traders have to immediately sell into the market any stocks held beyond the mandated quantity.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What happens for non-compliance?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As not all shopkeepers and traders comply, State agencies conduct raids to get everyone to toe the line and the errant are punished.</li>
<li>The excess stocks are auctioned or sold through fair price shops.</li>
<li>This improves supplies and brings down prices.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p>Ex: The Union Government has brought masks and hand-sanitizers under the ECA to make sure that these products, key for preventing the spread of Covid-19 infection, are available to people at the right price and in the right quality. Later this move was reverted.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>What about Food Items?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Items covered:</strong></p>
<p>Rice, wheat, atta, gram dal, arhar dal, moong dal, urad dal, masoor, dal, tea, sugar, salt, Vanaspati, groundnut oil, mustard oil, milk, soya oil, palm oil, sunflower oil, gur, potato, onion and tomato.</p>
<p><strong>(2) Price Stabilization Fund (PSF):</strong></p>
<p>The government utilizes the buffer of agri-horticultural commodities like pulses, onion, etc. built under Price Stabilization Fund (PSF) to help moderate the volatility in prices.</p>
<h4><strong>Recent amendments to the ECA</strong></h4>
<p>In 2020, the EC Act was amended for the stock limit to be imposed only under exceptional circumstances such as famine or other calamities.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Exceptional circumstances:</strong> It allowed the centre to delist certain commodities as essential, allowing the government to regulate their supply and prices only in cases of war, famine, extraordinary price rises, or natural calamities.</li>
<li><strong>Commodities de-regulated:</strong> The commodities that have been deregulated are food items, including cereals, pulses, potatoes, onion, edible oilseeds, and oils.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Exceptions provided</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The government regulation of stocks will be based on rising prices, and can only be imposed if there is</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>A 100% increase in retail price in the case of horticultural produce and</li>
<li>A 50% increase in retail price in the case of non-perishable agricultural food items</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>These restrictions will not apply to stocks of food held for public distribution in India.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/essential-commodities-act-india/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Explained: Baloch Freedom Movement</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-baloch-freedom-movement/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Balochistan, BLA, Khan of Kelat</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Baloch Freedom Movement</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-619915" height="839" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/baloch.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/baloch.jpg 800w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/baloch-286x300.jpg 286w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/08/baloch-768x805.jpg 768w" width="800"/></p>
<p>Baloch separatism under the Baloch Liberation Army (BLA) has been an ongoing issue in Pakistan since the birth of the nation in 1947.</p>
<h4><strong>Who are the BLA fighters?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The BLA <strong>announced itself in 2005</strong> with a rocket attack on a paramilitary camp in Balochistan Kohlu during a visit by then President Pervez Musharraf.</li>
<li>It is a nationalist militant group that has been waging an insurgency for <strong><u>Baloch self-determination and a separate homeland</u></strong> for the Baloch people.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Rise of Baloch nationalism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While the BLA’s armed insurgency is about two decades old, demands of Baloch nationalists for political autonomy and <strong><u>threats of secession date back to 1947</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Khan of Kalat (who claimed sovereignty over the four princely states of Kalat, Lasbela, Kharan and Makran) held out for independence, and the Pakistan Army forced his accession in March 1948.</li>
<li>Between 1973 and 1977, the Zulfikar Ali Bhutto-led government sent in the Pakistan Army to crush a leftist guerilla war <strong><u>inspired by the liberation of Bangladesh</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The tribal sardars of Balochistan, who had been at the forefront of Baloch nationalism, and were co-opted by the state in the late 1970s, grew rebellious again.</li>
<li>The insurgency gathered momentum from 2006, after the Pakistan Army killed the Bugti sardar, Nawab Akbar Khan Bugti, who had been also been a chief minister and governor of the province.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why it is gaining momentum now?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Pakistan Army’s operations against Baloch nationalists</u></strong> over the last two decades have seen <strong><u>hundreds of disappearances, and other alleged human rights violations.</u></strong></li>
<li>Baloch nationalists also see the <strong><u>sudden influx of jihadist groups</u></strong> in the province as a move by the Pakistan security establishment to counter their nationalist demands.</li>
<li>In 2012, the <strong><u>US Congress</u></strong> convened a hearing on Balochistan and <strong>supported the demand for a free Baloch land</strong>.</li>
<li>In a significant shift in policy, back then in 2016, <strong><u>PM Modi had made a reference to the Baloch freedom struggle in his Independence Day speech</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why does Balochistan matters?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Balochistan <strong>borders Afghanistan and Iran</strong>.</li>
<li>The people are mostly tribal with secular principles and are <strong><u>admirers of ties with India</u></strong>.</li>
<li>With gas, oil, copper and gold deposits, it is the <strong><u>most resource-rich of Pakistan’s four provinces</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It <strong><u>makes up half of Pakistan’s area</u></strong>, but has only 3.6% of its population.</li>
<li><u>Pakistan alleges that the</u> <u>insurgency is backed by India</u>.</li>
<li>This is the region where a former <strong><u>Indian Navy officer Kulbhushan Jadhav was abducted from Iran and charged for espionage</u></strong> supporting Baloch activism in Pakistan.</li>
<li>Many <strong>Baloch activists had been</strong> <strong><u>seeking asylum and has applied for Indian citizenship</u></strong>. New Delhi neither confirmed nor deny the reports.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why did BLA target the Chinese now?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The BLA claimed it attacks Chinese nationals because Beijing <strong>ignored warnings not to enter deals and agreements regarding Balochistan </strong>before the province had been “liberated”.</li>
<li>Baloch people see China-Pakistan Economic Corridor (<strong>CPEC) as a neo-colonist move against their sovereignty.</strong></li>
<li>Among China’s major projects in Balochistan is the port of Gwadar, strategically located near the Strait of Hormuz – a crucial oil shipping route in the Arabian Sea.</li>
<li>The security of its nationals in Pakistan has become a major issue for Beijing, especially since it launched the CPEC.</li>
<li>Such attacks has literally <strong><u>stalled the work in progress of CPEC projects making it a sheer failure</u></strong><u>.</u></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Significance of recent events</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is rare that the <strong><u>BLA deployed female suicide bombers</u></strong>. Recent attack was done by a highly educated lady and mother of two.</li>
<li>This is also the first time that a <strong><u>non-jihadist ethno-nationalist group</u></strong> has deployed a woman suicide bomber <strong><u>in the manner of Sri Lanka’s LTTE</u></strong>.</li>
<li>According to security experts familiar with the Baloch insurgency, it marks a <strong><u>worsening security situation in Pakistan. </u></strong></li>
<li>As the training camps are alleged by Pakistan to be in Afghanistan, the incident may also be a pointer to <strong><u>Pakistan’s loss of control over the Talibans</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-baloch-freedom-movement/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Govt. to enumerate Sanitation Workers</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/govt-to-enumerate-sanitation-workers/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Rashtriya Garima Abhiyan</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Plight of sanitation workers in India</p></div></div><p>The Ministry of Social Justice and Empowerment (MoSJ&amp;E) is now preparing to undertake a nationwide survey to enumerate all people engaged in the hazardous cleaning of sewers and septic tanks.</p>
<h4>Why such move?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Cleaning of sewers and septic tanks has led to at least 351 deaths since 2017.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Various initiatives for sanitation workers</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ministry now has proper <strong><u>distinction between sanitation work and manual scavenging</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The practice of <strong><u>manual scavenging no longer takes place</u></strong> in the country as all manual scavengers had been accounted for and enrolled into the rehabilitation scheme, said the ministry.</li>
<li>The enumeration of sanitization workers is soon to be conducted across 500 AMRUT (Atal Mission for Rejuvenation and Urban Transformation) cities, as a part of <strong><u>National Action Plan for Mechanised Sanitation Ecosystem (NAMASTE).</u></strong></li>
<li>The NAMASTE scheme aims to eradicate unsafe sewer and septic tank cleaning practices.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Manual Scavenging in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>Manual scavenging is the practice of removing human excreta by hand from sewers or septic tanks.</li>
<li>India <strong><u>banned</u></strong> the practice under the <strong>Prohibition of Employment as Manual Scavengers and their Rehabilitation Act, 2013 (PEMSR). </strong></li>
<li>The Act bans the use of any individual for manually cleaning, carrying, disposing of or otherwise handling in any manner, human excreta till its disposal.</li>
<li>In 2013, the definition of manual scavengers was also broadened to include people employed to clean septic tanks, ditches, or railway tracks.</li>
<li>The Act recognizes manual scavenging as a “<strong><u>dehumanizing practice</u></strong>,” and cites a need to “<strong>correct the historical injustice and indignity suffered by the manual scavengers</strong>.”</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is it still prevalent in India?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low awareness:</strong> Manual scavenging is mostly done by the marginalized section of the society and they are generally not aware about their rights.</li>
<li><strong>Enforcement issues:</strong> The lack of enforcement of the Act and exploitation of unskilled labourers are the reasons why the practice is still prevalent in India.</li>
<li><strong>High cost of automated:</strong> The Mumbai civic body charges anywhere between Rs 20,000 and Rs 30,000 to clean septic tanks.</li>
<li><strong>Cheaper availability:</strong> The unskilled labourers, meanwhile, are much cheaper to hire and contractors illegally employ them at a daily wage of Rs 300-500.</li>
<li><strong>Caste dynamics:</strong> Caste hierarchy still exists and it reinforces the caste’s relation with occupation. Almost all the manual scavengers belong to lower castes.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Various policy initiatives</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Prohibition of Employment as Manual Scavengers and their Rehabilitation (Amendment) Bill, 2020:</strong> It proposes to completely mechanise sewer cleaning, introduce ways for ‘on-site’ protection and provide compensation to manual scavengers in case of sewer deaths.</li>
<li><strong>Prohibition of Employment as Manual Scavengers and their Rehabilitation Act, 2013:</strong> Superseding the 1993 Act, the 2013 Act goes beyond prohibitions on dry latrines, and outlaws all manual excrement cleaning of insanitary latrines, open drains, or pits.</li>
<li><strong>Rashtriya Garima Abhiyan:</strong> It started national wide march “Maila Mukti Yatra” for total eradication of manual scavenging from 30th November 2012 from Bhopal.</li>
<li><strong>Prevention of Atrocities Act:</strong> In 1989, the Prevention of Atrocities Act became an integrated guard for sanitation workers since majority of the manual scavengers belonged to the Scheduled Caste.</li>
<li><strong>Compensation:</strong> As per the Prohibition of Employment of Manual Scavengers and their Rehabilitation (PEMSR) Act, 2013 and the Supreme Court’s decision in the Safai Karamchari Andolan vs Union of India case, a compensation of Rs 10 lakh is awarded to the victims family.</li>
<li><strong>National Commission for Safai Karamcharis (NCSK):</strong> It is currently a temporary non-statutory body that investigates the conditions of Safai Karamcharis (waste collectors) in India and makes recommendations to the Government.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/govt-to-enumerate-sanitation-workers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Reaping our demographic dividend</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/reaping-our-demographic-dividend/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India's demographic dividend</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s <strong>biggest strength is its ‘demographic dividend’</strong> and people need to fully leverage it to fast-track the country’s progress in various sectors</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The 2022 edition of <strong>the World Population Prospects (WPP) of</strong> the United Nations has projected that <strong>India may surpass China as the world’s most populous country next year.</strong></li>
<li>The report estimates that India will have a population of 1.66 billion in 2050, ahead of China’s 1.317 billion around that time<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is demographic dividend?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Demographic dividend, as defined by the <strong>United Nations Population Fund</strong>, is “<strong>the economic growth potential that can result from shifts in a population’s age structure</strong>, mainly when the share of the <strong>working-age population is larger than the non-working-age</strong> share of the population”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Current status for India </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India entered the <strong>demographic dividend opportunity</strong> window in 2005-06 and will remain there till 2055-56.</li>
<li>This is the period when the <strong>working age ratio is equal to or more than 150%</strong> and the <strong>dependency ratio is equal to or lower than 66.7%, </strong>generally taken as the cut-off for the demographic dividend window.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How India can leverage this dividend</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Investment in right direction </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Investments in human and physical infrastructure will need to be scaled up dramatically to promote entrepreneurship and create jobs.</li>
<li>Investment in education is crucial for ensuring that working-age people are prepared for the demands of the economy.</li>
<li>Increase spending on health</li>
<li>Increase investments in Research and Development</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Absorption of labour into productive employment</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Promote entrepreneurship and job creation</li>
<li>Service sector like tourism, logistics should be promoted</li>
<li>Skill development of the working-age population so that they can turn out to be productive for the country’s economy</li>
</ul>
<h4>Challenges in reaping this</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Drastic quality improvement:</strong> India’s challenge is to create conditions for faster growth of productive jobs outside of agriculture, especially in the organized manufacturing and in services.</li>
<li><strong>Severe shortages</strong>: India currently faces a severe shortage of well trained, skilled workers. Large sections of the educated workforce have little or no job skills, making them largely Unemployable.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dismal health sector:</strong> A closer look implies various factors such as poor health which although obvious, play a major role in the poor performance of working population.</li>
<li><strong>Socio economic dimensions:</strong> The status of institutions in India regarding caste discrimination, gender inequalities, widening income gap between the rich and the poor, religious differences, inefficient and slow legal system- all contribute to the poor standard of living of the masses.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Government steps </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>National Skill Development Corporation (NSDC</strong>): incorporated on 31st July, 2008, is a first-of-its-kind Public Private Partnership (PPP) in India set up to facilitate the development and upgrading of the skills of the growing Indian workforce through skill training programs.</li>
<li><strong>National Skill Development Agency</strong>: Currently, skill development efforts are spread across approximately20 separate ministries, 35 State Governments and Union Territories and the private sector.</li>
<li><strong>National Skill Certification and Money Reward Scheme: </strong>encouragement is given for skill development for youth by providing monetary rewards for successful completion of approved training programs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Strategies exist to exploit the demographic window of opportunity that India has today, but they need to be adopted and implemented.</li>
<li>The dreams of huge income flow and resultant economic growth due to demographic dividend could be realized only when we inculcate the required skills in the work force to make it as competent as its counterparts in the developed world.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Important data for mains </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>India’s working-age population has numerically outstripped its non-working age population.</strong></li>
<li><strong>India’s total fertility rate (TFR)</strong> has declined from 2.2 in 2015-16 to 2.0 in 2019-21, indicating the <strong>significant progress of population control measures</strong>, revealed the report of the fifth round of the <strong>National Family Health Survey (NFHS-5).</strong></li>
<li><strong>The</strong> <strong>TFR is the average number of children born to a woman in her lifetime.</strong></li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Mains question </strong></h4>
<p><strong><em>Q. Do you think the right has come that India should adopt moving away policy from population control towards reaping its demographic dividends? Critically examine.</em></strong></p></blockquote>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/reaping-our-demographic-dividend/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Labour welfare necessity</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/labour-welfare-necessity/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Labour welfare initiatives</p></div></div><p><strong>Context </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>One of the biggest economic fallout of the pandemic has been the deteriorating labour market conditions.</li>
<li>In the years ahead when the health crisis subsides and the economy witnesses a rebound, the healing of the labour market may take some more time. This is because the impact of recovery on this market is always felt with a lag.</li>
<li>Given the ebb and flow of the pandemic, the growth recovery is likely to be fragmented and will weigh on the number and types of jobs available.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Definition</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Labour welfare relates to taking care of the well-being of workers by employers, trade unions, governmental and non-governmental institutions and agencies.</li>
<li>Welfare includes anything that is done for the comfort and improvement of employees and is provided over and above the wages.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are labour rights?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Labour rights or workers’ rights are both legal rights and human rights relating to labour relations between workers and employers. These rights are codified in national and international labour and employment law. In general, these rights influence working conditions in relations of employment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why labour law is needed </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Labour law aims to correct the imbalance of power between the worker and the employer; to prevent the employer from dismissing the worker without good cause; to set up and preserve the processes by which workers are recognized as ‘equal’ partners in negotiations about their working conditions etc<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Constitutional mandate </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Article 41</strong> – The state shall within the limits of its economic capacity and development make effective provision for securing the right to work, to education and to public assistance in cases of unemployment, old age, sickness and disablement and in other cases of underserved want.</li>
<li><strong>Article 42</strong> – The state shall make provision for securing just and humane conditions of work and for maternity relief.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Necessity for welfare </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There were only 25 million during the initial period of industrial growth, while the strength of the workers is increasing year after year and hence, need for a mechanism to look into the welfare of the labour.</li>
<li>Workers put in long hours of work in unhealthy surrounding and the drudgery of the factory work continues to have adverse effect. To counter these welfare measures were felt necessary.</li>
<li>As a result of hardwork, they fall prey to alchoholism, gambling and other immoral activities results in absenteeism and other problems in the organisation. Hence the need was felt.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Scope for labour welfare in India </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Contribute to the productivity of labour and efficiency of the enterprise.</li>
<li>Raise the standard of living of workers by indirectly reducing the burden on their purse.</li>
<li>Be in tune and harmony with similar services obtaining in a neighbouring community where an enterprise is situated.</li>
<li>Be based on an intelligent prediction of the future needs of industrial work and be so designed as to offer a cushion to absorb the shock of industrialization and urbanization</li>
<li>Be administratively viable and essentially development in outlook.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Government steps in this direction </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Social Security Measures: </strong>The social security measures would help man to face the contingencies as such it is difficult for him either to work or to get work and support himself and his family. Thus social security measure provides a self balancing social insurance or assistance from public funds.</li>
<li><strong>Social Insurance</strong>: is described as the giving in return for contribution, benefits up to subsistence level, as of right and without a means test, so that an individual may build freely upon it.</li>
<li><strong>Social Assistance</strong>: is provided as an supplement to social insurance for those needy persons who cannot get social insurance payments and is offered after a means test.</li>
<li><strong>Public Service</strong>: is a programme constituting the third main type of social security. They are financed directly by the government from its general revenues in form of cash payments or services to every member of the community falling within a defined category.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Case study of Finland </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Universal basic income pilot project:</strong> For two years Finland’s government gave 2,000 unemployed citizens €560 a month with no strings attached. It was the first nationwide basic income experiment. The concept is slowly becoming difficult for people to ignore.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges in labour welfare in India </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Technical glitches:</strong> Under the Constitution of India, Labour is a subject in the concurrent list where both the Central and State Governments are competent to enact legislation. As a result, a large number of labour laws have been enacted catering to different aspects of labour e.g. occupational health, safety, employment etc.</li>
<li><strong>Loopholes:</strong> Because of the predominantly heavy-handed labour regulations (also called as Inspector Raj) with exploitable gaps, the MNCs and domestic organizations have resorted to alternate ways i.e. employing contract labour at less than half the payroll of a permanent employee.</li>
<li><strong>Gaps in labour laws:</strong> One of the main reasons for labour reforms is the concept of contract labour. Trade Unions suggest that this concept itself should be removed. There is stringent hiring and firing process defined in Industry Disputes Act. It makes it mandatory for the organization to seek Government permission before removing an employee.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Labour Welfare helps labourers improve their working conditions, providing social security and raising their standard of living.</li>
<li>Raise the employee’s morale use the workforce more effectively besides removing dissatisfaction help to develop loyalty in workers towards the organization.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Mains question </strong></h4>
<p><em>Q.What is labour welfare according to you? Why it is needed? Explain the challenges in front of Indian labour reforms<strong>.</strong></em></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/labour-welfare-necessity/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India @75 –Relooking our democracy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-75-relooking-our-democracy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><h4><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As we celebrate the nation @75 , we must also reflect on the mixed nature of our democracy</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Definition of democracy</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>“Government of the people, by the people and for the people” were the words used by Abraham Lincoln in the year 1863 while talking about democracy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Purpose of democracy </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cornerstones of democracy include freedom of assembly, association, property rights, freedom of religion and speech, inclusiveness and equality, citizenship, consent of the governed, voting rights, freedom from unwarranted governmental deprivation of the right to life and liberty, and minority rights.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India is a parliamentary democratic secular republic in which the president of India is the head of state &amp; first citizen of India and the prime minister of India is the head of government.</li>
<li>It is based on the federal structure of government, although the word is not used in the Constitution itself.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How it has performed </strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1)</strong> <strong>Political front</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India is the world’s the largest democracy proved success in accommodation of group and regional demands in a complex, quasi-federal, polity.</li>
<li>During the first general election in the 1951 India had 54 political parties and now it has grown up to 464 in the 2014 general election as an evident of deepening of the democratic process.</li>
<li>In the first General election 1951, 173 million citizens were given right to vote.</li>
<li>In the 16<sup>th</sup> general election in 2014, the size of the electorate had increased to 814 million.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Social front </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The democratic process has brought about a shift of political power from the middle and higher castes and classes of urban society to backward classes who are now the politically most influential ones in the country.</li>
<li>They have won reservations for themselves in legislatures and government services as were accorded to the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes after independence through Constitutional provisions.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Economic Front</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>These include strategic affairs and security, politico-legal democratic governance as well as society and economy.</li>
<li>India has been able to emerge as a regional power in Asia and super power in south Asia backed by its economic, military and nuclear capabilities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Contradictions in democracy </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Performance of Bureaucracy:</strong> Dishonest officials to protect themselves from the consequences of their wrong-doings have largely exploited constitutional protection for the Services under Article 311.</li>
<li><strong>Administration of Justice:</strong> Judicial system has not been able to meet even the modest expectations of the society. Its delays and costs are frustrating, its processes slow and uncertain. People are pushed to seek recourse to Extra-legal methods for relief. Trial system both on the civil and criminal side has utterly broken down.</li>
<li><strong>Areas of Concern:</strong> There is a fundamental breach of the constitutional faith on the part of the Governments and their method of governance lies in the neglect of the people who are the ultimate source of all political authority.</li>
<li><strong>Regionalism:</strong> Issues of national integrity and security have not received adequate and thoughtful attention. Mechanisms for the assessment of early warning symptoms of social unrest are absent.</li>
<li><strong>Corruption:</strong> The increasing instability of elected governments is attributable to opportunistic politics and unprincipled defections.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Some positive suggestions to government </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Feedback</strong>: The Government should hear criticism rather than rejecting it outrightly. Suggestions on eroding democratic values need a thoughtful, and respectful response.</li>
<li><strong>Freedom of press:</strong> The press and the judiciary which are considered the pillars of India’s Democracy, require to be independent of any executive interference.</li>
<li><strong>Opposition:</strong> strong democracy requires strong opposition. Without an alternative choice, the very objective of election to provide a check on arbitrary power gets defeated.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The institutionalization of constitutional democracy has helped the people of India realize the importance of democracy and inculcate democratic sensibilities among them.</li>
<li>At the same time, it is important that all the government organs work in harmony to uphold the trust people of the country have held in them and ensure the objectives of true democracy.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Mains question </strong></h4>
<p><em>Q.We are celebrating Azadi ka amrit mahotsav India @75, trace the journey of democracy critically by providing some suggestions for robust democracy.</em></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-75-relooking-our-democracy/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>