<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 18:13:33 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Is Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022 Flawless?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/draft-telecommunications-bill/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Right to Privacy</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Cyber security,Right to privacy,Technology</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641528" height="415" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 622px) 100vw, 622px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-10.03.31.jpeg 1200w" width="622"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Keeping an eye on the telecommunication regulatory framework Supreme Court issued substantive legal reform on surveillance laws in India. Union government has published the Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022 to replace the Telegraph Act, 1885.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Over two decades ago, allegations of surveillance against politicians led to a CBI inquiry and report against V P Singh’s government. The allegations revealed that imaginary reasons were given for ordering phone tapping without authorization.</li>
<li>Last years, many publications reported that phones of several dozen Indian journalists, lawyers and human rights activists had been compromised using an invasive Israeli-developed malware called Pegasus.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641527" height="406" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.58.jpeg 1024w" width="608"/>What is Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The draft Indian Telecommunication Bill, 2022 is an attempt by the Department of Telecommunications (DoT) to consolidate various legislations presently governing the telecommunication landscape in India.</li>
<li>The Bill seeks to replace three laws, the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885, the Indian Wireless Telegraphy Act, 1933 and the Telegraph Wires (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1950.</li>
<li>The new regulatory framework is to bring the law at par with technological advancements and remove obsolete provisions from the colonial era laws.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the current laws governing communication surveillance in India?</strong></h4>
<p>Communication surveillance in India takes place primarily under two laws:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Telegraph Act, 1885</strong>: It deals with interception of calls.</li>
<li><strong>Call interception:</strong>Under Section 5(2) of this law, the government can intercept calls only in certain situations.</li>
<li><strong>For sovereignty:</strong>They include the interests of the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the state, friendly relations with foreign states or public order, or for preventing incitement to the commission of an offense.</li>
<li><strong>Free speech restrictions:</strong>These are the same restrictions imposed on free speech under Article 19(2) of the Constitution.</li>
<li><strong>Exceptions for journalists:</strong>A provision in Section 5(2) states that even this lawful interception cannot take place against journalists.</li>
<li><strong>Information Technology Act, 2000: </strong>It was enacted to deal with surveillance of all electronic communication, following the Supreme Court’s intervention in 1996.</li>
<li><strong>Electronic surveillance:</strong>Section 69 of the IT Act and the IT (Procedure for Safeguards for Interception, Monitoring, and Decryption of Information) Rules, 2009 were enacted to further the legal framework for electronic surveillance.</li>
<li><strong>Data interception:</strong>Under the IT Act, all electronic transmission of data can be intercepted.</li>
<li>Section 69 of the IT Act adds another aspect that makes it broader — interception, monitoring, and decryption of digital information “for the investigation of an offense”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641524" height="631" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-278x300.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-278x300.jpeg 278w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-768x829.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56-834x900.jpeg 834w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.52.56.jpeg 949w" width="585"/>How the loopholes in the current system breaching the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-privacy/">Data Privacy?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>No comprehensive data Protection Law: </strong></li>
<li>No comprehensive data protection law leaving ambiguities over several laws.</li>
<li>A comprehensive data protection law to address the gaps in existing frameworks for surveillance is yet to enact.</li>
<li><strong>Unaccountable, opaque exercise of surveillance: </strong></li>
<li>The Telegraph Act contains broad and excessive powers of interception and surveillance of communications carried out through any telegraph.</li>
<li>The surveillance power is principally contained under Section 5(2), and has resulted in an unaccountable, opaque and unconstitutional exercise of surveillance that has led to accusations across the political spectrum.</li>
<li><strong>Less transparency:</strong></li>
<li>Ministry of Home Affairs refuses to disclose even aggregate data on the number of surveillance orders issued by it each year illegally gathered evidence is being sought to prosecute people.</li>
<li>For instance, the Bombay High Court about three years ago noted in a case that premier investigating agencies such as the CBI have used, interception orders (that) neither have sanction of law nor issued for legitimate aim.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022" class="alignnone wp-image-641526" height="398" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 596px) 100vw, 596px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-1024x682.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00-1200x800.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.53.00.jpeg 1280w" width="596"/>Key features of</strong> <strong>the</strong> <strong>Draft Telecommunications Bill, 2022</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Broad Definitions: </strong></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>The Bill introduces a broad definition of ‘telecommunication services’.</li>
<li>It now includes internet-based services, in-flight and maritime connectivity, interpersonal communications services, machine to machine communication services, and over-the-top (OTT) based communication services that are made available to users by telecommunication</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>KYC and caller id requirements: </strong></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>The Bill requires licensed entities to ensure that they identify the persons to whom they provide telecommunication services.</li>
<li>The Bill places an obligation on telecommunication service providers to do this through a ‘verifiable mode’, as prescribed by the government.</li>
<li><strong>Licensing, registration, and authorization:</strong></li>
<li>Under the Bill, four types of permissions are identified – license, registration, authorization and assignment.</li>
<li>While the Bill does not differentiate between the four types of permissions, it clarifies that a license is only required for providing telecommunication services or operating telecommunication networks</li>
<li><strong>Wide ranging powers of Central Government: </strong></li>
<li>The Bill includes wide-ranging powers for the central and state governments in the event of a public emergency or in interest of public safety.</li>
<li>These powers include taking temporary possession of any telecommunication services, suspension of transmission in cases of public emergency, interception/detainment/disclosure of messages, suspension of communications, or otherwise transmit certain announcements for public safety and national security purposes.</li>
<li><strong>User protection and duties: </strong>User has been declared as an important policy objective of the Government. It places a duty on users to not furnish false information, suppress material information or impersonate others when proving identity to avail telecommunication services.</li>
<li><strong>Offences and penalties</strong>: Any offence under the Bill may be punished with a fine, imprisonment, suspension of telecommunication services or a combination of the above. For companies, the employees who were responsible for the conduct or the business relating to the offence at the time the offence was committed will be punished.</li>
<li><strong>Dispute resolution mechanism</strong>: The Bill provides for the right of appeal before the appellate authority. It also creates an enabling provision for the Central Government to set up an alternate dispute resolution mechanism such as arbitration, mediation or other processes of dispute resolution</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Concerns over the Draft Telecommunication bill, 2022?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Regulatory overlaps:</strong>The broad of the definition of ‘telecommunication services’ include OTT communication platforms such as WhatsApp, Telegram, Signal among others, may potentially lead to regulatory or jurisdictional overlaps.</li>
<li><strong>Unchecked use of State powers:</strong>The Bill gives broad powers to the central government in prescribed situations without any accompanying checks and balances. The Bill empowers the central and state government to intercept messages in the interest of public safety and emergency without the providing clearly defined guardrails for it.</li>
<li><strong>Undefined National security: </strong>The term, national security is left undefined and does not match constitutional precedent or text which instead uses the phrase,in the interests of the security of state</li>
<li><strong>Users Less choice in the privacy and security of their digital footprint:</strong></li>
<li>Power to prescribe standards under Clause 23, which may result in regulations as recently issued by the Computer Emergency Response Team (CERT-In) that have resulted in the closure of servers or services by leading, global VPN providers such as Proton and TunnelBear.</li>
<li>All of this practically means that users will have less choice in the privacy and security of their digital footprint, as these powers will lead to requirements to locally register and host data, and comply with requirements to identify users (KYC requirements).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There should be some reasonable basis or some tangible evidence to initiate or seek approval for interception by State authorities. Any digression from the ethical and legal parameters set by law would be tantamount to a deliberate invasion of citizens.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Any deviation from the moral and legal parameters set by the law would amount to a deliberate attack on citizens. In this context discuss the data privacy of citizens in the era of massive expansion of internet and mobile usage.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/draft-telecommunications-bill/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Transboundary Flood Disasters</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/transboundary-flood-disasters/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Transboundary Rivers</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Disaster Management</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Transboundary Flood Disasters" class="alignnone wp-image-641871 size-full" height="444" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 828px) 100vw, 828px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fld.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fld.jpg 828w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fld-300x161.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/fld-768x412.jpg 768w" width="828"/></strong></h4>
<h4><strong>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Pakistan experiencing devastation, with a spread of diseases and severe shortage of potable water after intense flooding. In June this year Assam experienced one of its worst floods in which it affected over 30 districts. Assam and Bihar frequently suffer from transboundary flood disasters.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-recurring-floods-in-india/">transboundary flood</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Floods that are originate in upper riparian state crosses the international boundary and also affects the lower riparian state. For example, river Brahmaputra causes flood both in China and India simultaneously.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Transboundary Flood Disasters" class="alignnone wp-image-641877 size-full" height="463" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.59.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.59.jpeg 800w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.59-300x174.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.59-768x444.jpeg 768w" width="800"/>How the transboundary floods are difficult to manage than <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/floods/">normal floods</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Flooding is still considered to be a natural phenomenon that cannot be entirely prevented. But it is compounded by the lack of transparency in the sharing of hydrological information and also information relating to activities (such as by one riparian state) that are transboundary in their effect (affecting other riparian states), thus serving as an obstacle in understanding the magnitude of flooding<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Transboundary Flood Disasters" class="alignnone wp-image-641552" height="370" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 654px) 100vw, 654px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1.jpeg 1085w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1-1024x579.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-06.25.44-1-768x434.jpeg 768w" width="654"/>What is a riparian state?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A riparian state is state (or country) located alongside a river.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the International laws governing transboundary waters?</strong></h4>
<p>There are at two international treaties that governs the transboundary water</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>UNWC:</strong></li>
<li>United Nations Convention on the Law of the Non-Navigational Use of International Watercourses (UNWC) 1997.UNWC contains a direct reference to floods, which covers harmful conditions and the emergency situations.</li>
<li>Article 27 of the Convention says, Watercourse States shall individually and, where appropriate, jointly, take all appropriate measures to prevent or mitigate conditions that may be harmful to other watercourse States, whether resulting from natural causes or human conduct or desertification.</li>
<li><strong>Environmental Impact Assessment: </strong></li>
<li>The International Court of Justice (ICJ), in the Pulp Mills on the River Uruguay (Argentina vs Uruguay) case of 2010, upheld that conducting a transboundary environmental impact assessment (TEIA) of a planned measure or projects on the shared water course is part of customary international law.</li>
<li>In fact, the ICJ noted that the acting state must notify the affected party of the results of TEIA for assessment of its own damages that are likely to occur.</li>
<li><strong>UNECE: </strong>United Nations Economic Commission for Europe (UNECE) on the Protection and Use of Transboundary Watercourses and International Lakes 1992 (Water Convention).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Transboundary Flood Disasters" class="alignnone wp-image-641881" height="908" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 586px) 100vw, 586px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31.jpeg 720w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31-194x300.jpeg 194w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31-661x1024.jpeg 661w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.59.31-581x900.jpeg 581w" width="586"/>How India manages transboundary flood?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Note:</strong>Neither India nor China are signatory to UNWC or UNCEC.</li>
<li><strong>River Brahmaputra:</strong> India has signed the memorandum of understanding (MoU) with China in 2013 with a view to sharing hydrological information during the flood season (June to September). The MoU does not allow India access to urbanisation and deforestation activities on the Chinese side of the river basin.</li>
<li><strong>Rivers Gandak and kosi</strong>: Floods are also a recurrent problem in the Kosi and Gandak river basins that are shared by India and Nepal.</li>
<li><strong>The India-Nepal Kosi agreement 1954: </strong>Agreement aimed at reducing devastating flooding in the river basin. The treaty-based joint bodies have also tried to refine the early warning systems for flood forecasting.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the suggestions?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Signing the treaty: </strong>Expert suggests, India by becoming a party to either the UNWC and the Water Convention could lay the groundwork for a bilateral treaty on the Brahmaputra but subject to the reservation that it should not insist on the insertion of a dispute settlement mechanism provision<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Information exchange: </strong>In contravention of procedural customary international law obligation, India considers data on transboundary rivers as classified information, which is one of the key challenges in developing cross-border flood warning systems. India needs to share the hydrological and river information for its own sake.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Climate change has accelerated the frequency and intensity of floods across the world. with Changing climate India should also change its strategy to protect its people, to preserve the soil and to save its resources from the scourge of floods.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Questions</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Climate change has created a more difficult challenge in flood management. In this context, what measures can be taken to deal with frequent transboundary floods in India. Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/transboundary-flood-disasters/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Stressed ecology of Bay of Bengal</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bay-of-bengal/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Location,BIMSTEC,Centre for Bay of Bengal Studies</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Foreign Policy,Regional Grouping</p></div></div><h4></h4>
<h4><strong><img alt="Bay of Bengal" class="alignnone wp-image-641718 size-large" height="487" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1024x487.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1024x487.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-300x143.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-768x365.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1536x731.jpeg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1200x571.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31-1980x942.jpeg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-29-at-15.05.31.jpeg 2048w" width="1024"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At the fourth BIMSTEC summit, Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced the opening of the Centre for Bay of Bengal Studies (CBS) at Nalanda University. The launch of the CBS has once again demonstrated India’s commitment to advancing constructive agendas by forging connections and setting up platforms for all those with an interest in the of Bay of Benagl.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Bay of Bengal" class="alignnone wp-image-641724" height="547" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 545px) 100vw, 545px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-3-1.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-3-1.jpg 224w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-3-1-150x150.jpg 150w" width="545"/>Why <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/opportunity-to-propel-a-bay-of-bengal-dream/">Bay of Bengal</a> is so important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Commerce hub: </strong>The Bay has long been a major commerce hub for the Indian Ocean. It created a conduit between the East and the West in terms for trade and culture.</li>
<li><strong>Emerging arena of maritime warfare: </strong>An Indo-Pacific orientation and the realignment of global economic and military power towards Asia have had a considerable impact on the Bay region.</li>
<li><strong>Communication and Energy</strong>: The key sea lanes of communication in this area are lifelines for global economic security and are crucial to the energy security that powers the economies of many countries in the region.Further, non-traditional dangers including terrorism and climate change have become more prevalent.</li>
<li><strong>Under water resources: </strong>The Bay also provides an opportunity for greater regional cooperation in the environmentally friendly exploration of marine and energy resources. The Bay has a biodiverse marine environment.</li>
<li><strong>Fresh water resources: </strong>It receives the water from some of the world’s largest rivers. It is a partially enclosed sea that has given rise to several geological characteristics.</li>
<li><strong>Ecology: </strong>It is home to many rare and endangered marine species and mangroves, which are essential to the survival of the ecology and the fishing sector.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Bay of Bengal" class="alignnone wp-image-641722" height="422" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 632px) 100vw, 632px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S2352485520306678-gr1.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S2352485520306678-gr1.jpg 565w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S2352485520306678-gr1-300x200.jpg 300w" width="632"/>Why ecology in the region is under threat?</strong></h4>
<p>The region’s maritime environment has changed as are result of major powers expanding their economic and geopolitical influence.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Competition: </strong>Political and cultural engagement, together with economic competition, have taken on new dimensions. More crucially, the Bay’s ecosystem is going through an unprecedented crisis brought on by widespread environmental exploitation and geopolitical unrest.</li>
<li><strong>Resource exploitation</strong>: Species extinction is a result of careless exploitation of the maritime environment, which has severe consequences on biodiversity. Problems such as population growth, altered land use, excessive resource exploitation, salinity, sea level rise, and climate change are exerting significant strain on the Bay’s environment.</li>
<li><strong>Water pollution</strong>: Operational discharge from small and medium feeder ships, shipping collisions, unintentional oil spills, industrial waste, pollution, and the accumulation of non- biodegradable plastic litter are all contributing to the deterioration of the Bay.</li>
<li><strong>Declining ecology</strong>: A dead-zone has formed, and the mangrove trees that protect the shore from the fury of nature are under more threat than ever.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-641728" height="472" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-s2.0-S0959652620334545-fx1-e1664446288766.jpg" width="529"/>What could be the Solutions?</strong></h4>
<p>For a better knowledge of challenges, and strategies to overcome them for the sustainable development of the region, more focused and inter-disciplinary study is required on these issues.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Centre for Bay of Bengal studies: </strong>By founding the CBS, Nalanda University has already started its journey and given the nation a unique interdisciplinary research centre devoted to Bay focused teaching, research, and capacity building. Additionally, scholars from many countries and academic streams are already participating in CBS’s first certificate programme on the Bay.</li>
<li><strong>Inter-governmental cooperation: </strong>It is essential that nautical neighbours develop a partnership and cooperate because of the maritime domain’s interrelated and interdependent nature, transnational character, and cross-jurisdictional engagement of various governments and diverse organisations and enterprises.</li>
<li><strong>Maritime connectivity: </strong>A few concerns that need immediate attention include expanding cooperation in maritime safety and security, enhancing cooperation on maritime connectivity and the ease of maritime transit, and boosting investment possibilities in the maritime connectivity sector.</li>
<li><strong>Illegal activities: </strong>The latter subject involves addressing non-traditional threats and fostering group efforts to reduce illicit, unreported, and unregulated fishing.</li>
<li><strong>Data sharing: </strong>Standardising and harmonising data reporting.</li>
<li><strong>Balanced approach: </strong>Furthermore regional marine entities should strive to balance opportunities and goals on a national, regional, and international scale.</li>
<li><strong>Investment in R&amp;D: </strong>Littoral governments need to support and promote skill-building, research, and training.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Countries in the Bay of Bengal need to mobilise investments, manage maritime affairs more effectively. Alternative lifestyle should be explored. The cooperation of all member states, for information gathering, sharing and result oriented actions is crucial in protecting the ecology of Bay of Bengal.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Countries in the Indian subcontinent are developing rapidly, putting serious stress on the environment of the Bay of Bengal.Mention the challenges and suggest solutions.</strong></p></blockquote>
<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/3AFiKuz" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2022 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/bay-of-bengal/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>All women have Right to Legal and Safe Abortion: Supreme Court</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-legal-and-safe-abortion/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>MRTP Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Abortion rights debate</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has held that all women, irrespective of their marital status, are entitled to safe and legal abortion till 24 weeks of pregnancy under the Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act.</p>
<h4><strong>A case for safe abortion<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A Bench led by Justice D.Y. Chandrachud was hearing the appeal of a woman who wanted to abort her 24-week pregnancy after her relationship failed and her partner left her.</li>
<li>The lower court had taken an “<strong><u>unduly restrictive view</u></strong>” that her plea for a safe abortion was not covered under the Medical Termination of Pregnancy Act.</li>
<li>This was since the pregnancy arose from a consensual relationship outside wedlock.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the last amendment?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The court noted that an amendment to the Act in 2021 had <strong><u>substituted the term ‘husband’ with ‘partner’</u></strong>, a clear signal that the law covered unmarried women within its ambit.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reiterating the live-in recognition</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Chastising the lower court, the Bench said live-in relationships had already been recognised by the Supreme Court.</li>
<li>There were a significant number of people in social mainstream who see no wrong in engaging in pre-marital sex.</li>
<li>The law could not be used to quench “<strong><u>notions of social morality</u></strong>” and unduly interfere in their personal autonomy and bodily integrity.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>About Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Abortion in India has been a legal right under various circumstances for the last 50 years since the introduction of the<strong> <u>Medical Termination of Pregnancy (MTP) Act in 1971</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The Act was amended in 2003 to enable women’s access to safe and legal abortion services.</li>
<li>Abortion is covered 100% by the government’s public national health insurance funds, Ayushman Bharat and Employees’ State Insurance with the package rate for surgical abortion.</li>
</ul>
<p>The idea of terminating your pregnancy cannot originate by choice and is purely circumstantial. There are four situations under which a legal abortion is performed:</p>
<ol>
<li>If continuation of the pregnancy poses any <strong><u>risks to the life of the mother</u></strong> <strong>or <u>mental health</u></strong></li>
<li>If the <strong><u>foetus has any severe abnormalities</u></strong></li>
<li>If pregnancy occurred as a result of <strong><u>failure of contraception</u></strong> (but this is only applicable to married women)</li>
<li>If pregnancy is a result of <strong><u>sexual assault or rape</u></strong></li>
</ol>
<p>The pregnancy can be terminated upto 24 weeks of gestational age after the opinion of two registered medical practitioners under these conditions —</p>
<ul>
<li>If the woman is ​​either a survivor of sexual assault or rape or incest</li>
<li>If she is a minor</li>
<li>If her marital status has changed during the ongoing pregnancy (i.e. either widowhood or divorce)</li>
<li>If she has major physical disabilities or is mentally ill</li>
<li>On the grounds of foetal malformation incompatible with life or if the child is born, it would be seriously handicapped</li>
<li>If the woman is in humanitarian settings or disaster, or emergency situations as declared by the government</li>
</ul>
<p>These are the key changes that the Medical Termination of Pregnancy (Amendment) Act, 2021, has brought in:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong><u>The gestation limit for abortions has been raised from the earlier ceiling of 20 weeks to 24 weeks</u></strong>, but only for special categories of pregnant women such as rape or incest survivors. But this termination would need the approval of two registered doctors.</li>
<li><strong><u>All pregnancies up to 20 weeks require one doctor’s approval</u></strong>. The earlier law, the MTP Act 1971, required one doctor’s approval for pregnancies upto 12 weeks and two doctors’ for pregnancies between 12 and 20 weeks.</li>
<li><strong><u>Women can now terminate unwanted pregnancies caused by contraceptive failure</u></strong>, regardless of their marital status. Earlier the law specified that only a “married woman and her husband” could do this.</li>
<li><strong><u>There is also no upper gestation limit for abortion in case of foetal disability</u></strong> if so decided by a medical board of specialist doctors, which state governments and union territories’ administrations would set up.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Criticism of Abortion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Foetuses feel the pain:</strong> If the foetus is beyond 20 weeks of gestation, gynaecs assume that there will be pain caused to the foetus.</li>
<li><strong>Abortions cause psychological damage:</strong> Young adult women who undergo abortion may be at increased risk for subsequent depression.</li>
<li><strong>Abortions reduce the number of adoptable babies:</strong> Instead of having the option to abort, women should give their unwanted babies to people who cannot conceive. Single parenthood is also gaining popularity in the US.</li>
<li><strong>Cases of selective abortion:</strong> Such cases based on physical and genetic abnormalities (eugenic termination) is overt discrimination.</li>
<li><strong>Abortion as a form of contraception:</strong> It is immoral to kill an unborn child for convenience. Many women are using abortion as a contraceptive method.</li>
<li><strong>Morality put to question:</strong> If women become pregnant, they should accept the responsibility that comes with producing a child. People need to take responsibility for their actions and accept the consequences.</li>
<li><strong>Abortion promotes throwaway culture:</strong> The legalization of abortion sends a message that human life has little value and promotes the throwaway culture.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Arguments in favour for Abortion Rights</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Upholding individual conscience and decision-making:</strong>  The US Supreme Court has declared abortion to be a fundamental right guaranteed by the US Constitution.</li>
<li><strong>Reproductive choice empowers women:</strong> The choice over when and whether to have children is central to a woman’s independence and ability to determine her future.</li>
<li><strong>Foetal viability occurs post-birth:</strong>  Personhood begins after a foetus becomes “viable” (able to survive outside the womb) or after birth, not at conception. Abortion is the termination of a pregnancy, not a baby.</li>
<li><strong>No proof of foetal pain:</strong> Most neuroscientists believe that the cortex is necessary for pain perception. The cortex does not become functional until at least the 26th week of a foetus’ development.</li>
<li><strong>Preventing illegal abortions:</strong> Access to legal, professionally-performed abortions reduces maternal injury and death caused by unsafe, illegal abortions.</li>
<li><strong>Mother’s health:</strong> Modern abortion procedures are safe and do not cause lasting health issues such as cancer and infertility.</li>
<li><strong>Child’s health:</strong> Abortion gives pregnant women the option to choose not to bring fetuses with profound abnormalities to full term.</li>
<li><strong>Prevents women’s exclusion:</strong> Women who are denied abortions are more likely to become unemployed, to be on public welfare, to be below the poverty line, and to become victims of domestic violence.</li>
<li><strong>Reproductive choice protects women from financial disadvantage:</strong> Many women who choose abortion don’t have the financial resources to support a child.</li>
<li><strong>Justified means of population control:</strong> Many defends abortion as a way to curb overpopulation. Malnutrition, starvation, poverty, lack of medical and educational services, pollution, underdevelopment, and conflict over resources are all consequences of overpopulation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Hence it is now established that the right to abortion is a legal right of all women.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/right-to-legal-and-safe-abortion/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>UNESCO Lists 50 iconic Indian Textiles</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/unesco-iconic-indian-textiles/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Textiles mentioned in the newscard</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The UNESCO has released a list of 50 exclusive and iconic heritage textile crafts of the country.</p>
<h4>About the Report</h4>
<ul>
<li>The report is titled- Handmade for the 21st Century: Safeguarding Traditional Indian Textile.</li>
<li>It lists the histories and legends behind the textiles, describes the complicated and secret processes behind their making, mentions the causes for their dwindling popularity, and provides strategies for their preservation.</li>
<li>The publication, which aims to bridge this gap, brings together years of research on the 50 selected textiles.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Key heritage textiles mentioned in the list</h4>
<ul>
<li>Toda embroidery and Sungadi from Tamil Nadu</li>
<li>Himroo from Hyderabad</li>
<li>Bandha tie and dye from Sambalpur in Odisha</li>
<li>Khes from Panipat, Haryana</li>
<li>Chamba rumals from Himachal Pradesh</li>
<li>Thigma or wool tie and dye from Ladakh</li>
<li>Awadh Jamdani from Varanasi, UP</li>
<li>Ilkal and Lambadi or Banjara embroidery from Karnataka</li>
<li>Sikalnayakanpet Kalamkari from Thanjavur, TN</li>
<li>Kunbi weaves from Goa</li>
<li>Mashru weaves and Patola from Gujarat</li>
<li>Himroo from Maharashtra and</li>
<li>Garad-Koirial from West Bengal</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: UN Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization</h4>
<ul>
<li>The UNESCO is a specialised agency of the UN aimed at promoting world peace and security through international cooperation in education, arts, sciences and culture.</li>
<li>It has 193 member states and 12 associate members, as well as partners in the non-governmental, intergovernmental and private sector.</li>
<li>UNESCO was founded in 1945 as the successor to the League of Nations’s International Committee on Intellectual Cooperation.</li>
<li>It pursues this objective through five major program areas: education, natural sciences, social/human sciences, culture and communication/information.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/unesco-iconic-indian-textiles/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Behind the ‘world’s first CNG terminal’ at Bhavnagar, Gujarat</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/behind-the-worlds-first-cng-terminal/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CNG vs LPG</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="cng" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-641985" height="469" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 869px) 100vw, 869px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cng.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cng.jpg 869w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cng-300x162.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cng-768x414.jpg 768w" width="869"/></p>
<p>Prime Minister has laid the foundation stone for the “world’s first CNG (Compressed Natural Gas) terminal” at Bhavnagar in Gujarat.</p>
<h4>Bhavnagar CNG terminal</h4>
<ul>
<li>The idea got incepted during the January 2019 Vibrant Gujarat summit when a consortium of some stakeholder signed MoU with Gujarat Maritime Board (GMB) for development of the CNG terminal.</li>
<li>The port will be built under the BOOT (Build, Own, Operate and Transfer) policy of the state government.</li>
<li>The state-run GMB will continue to operate the berths on the south side of the port.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the Bhavnagar port important?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Bhavnagar port is in close vicinity to the Dholera Special Investment Region (SIR) and is expected to serve the industries that set up base in the region.</li>
<li>It is already connected to the northern hinterland through a railway line that extends to the existing berths at the port.</li>
</ul>
<h4>When is the CNG terminal expected to commence operations?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The construction is expected to commence in the first quarter of 2023 after GMB approves the Detailed Project Report.</li>
<li>It is expected to be made operational by 2026.</li>
<li>The proposed port terminal’s capacity is 4.65 Million Tonnes Per Annum (MTPA), of which the capacity of the CNG terminal will be 0.3 MTPA.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What makes the port unique?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The project will repair and redevelop the tidal lock gate system, which will be the fourth largest such system in the world.</li>
<li>Traditionally, because of the higher tidal range of approximately 10 meters, Bhavnagar creek attracts a significant amount of sediment in the form of silt.</li>
<li>This lock gate system has been set up so that a minimal amount of sediment enters the port basin during high tide, thus bringing down the cost of dredging inside the port substantially.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Natural gas vs. LPG</h4>
<ul>
<li>LPG, or liquefied petroleum gas, is a mixture of light hydrocarbons.</li>
<li>It consists of at least 90% of propane, with the balance made up of other gases including butane.</li>
<li>Natural gas, in contrast, is almost entirely made up of methane.</li>
<li>Compressed Natural Gas, or CNG, and Liquefied Natural Gas, or LNG, are the same substance.</li>
<li>CNG is received and stored in a vehicle’s tank in gaseous form.</li>
<li>To obtain LNG, natural gas is compressed and cooled to extremely low temperatures, at which point it turns to liquid.</li>
<li>LNG can then be shipped, stored, and used to fill the tanks of LNG vehicles.</li>
<li>Much of the global natural gas trade occurs in the form of LNG.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/behind-the-worlds-first-cng-terminal/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Vande Bharat Express 2.0</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vande-bharat-express-ii/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Vande Bharat Express</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="vande" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-641981" height="362" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vande.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vande.jpg 640w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/vande-300x170.jpg 300w" width="640"/></strong></p>
<p>Prime Minister has inaugurated the new upgraded Vande Bharat Express.</p>
<h4><strong>Vande Bharat 2.0</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Vande Bharat Express is a semi-high-speed train designed, developed, and built by the Integral Coach Factory (ICF).</li>
<li>Presently there are only two Vande Bharat trains that are running — Delhi to Varanasi and Delhi to Katra.</li>
<li>The name may be the same, but this train, the third in the Vande Bharat series, is being dubbed ‘Vande Bharat 2.0’, because of certain upgrades.</li>
<li>PM had inaugurated the Vande Bharat when it was first launched in Delhi in 2019.</li>
<li>The new trainset costs around Rs 115 crore — Rs 15 crore more than the last version.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Key Features</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The current Vande Bharat trains have <strong><u>seating only in two classes</u></strong> — chair car and executive chair car. But Railways is planning to upgrade it.</li>
<li>The trains have fully <strong><u>sealed gangways for a dust-free environment</u></strong>, modular bio-vacuum toilets, rotating seats in Executive Class, personalized reading lights, automatic entry/exit doors with sliding footsteps, diffused LED lighting, mini pantry, and sensor-based interconnecting doors in each coach.</li>
<li>They are <strong><u>self-propelled trains</u></strong> that do not require an engine. This feature is called a <strong>distributed traction power system</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the major upgrades?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Ride comfort</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>For starters, this train reaches a top speed of 160 km per hour in 129 seconds, around 16 seconds faster than its predecessor.</li>
<li>This is because this train weighs around 392 tonnes, 38 tonnes lighter than the last one, and needs to run almost a km less to attain its top speed.</li>
<li>It also has a better riding index (lower the better) of 3.26 at 180 km per hour, from the earlier 3.87.</li>
<li>At a standard speed of 115 km per, its riding index is 3.26, better than 3.62 attained at the same speed by the earlier version.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em>Riding index is a global benchmark for rolling stock calculated during trials by measuring vertical/lateral acceleration. In layman’s terms, how comfortable and steady the passenger is while the train is in motion is roughly the idea behind a riding index.</em></p></blockquote>
<p><strong>(2) Safety features</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In terms of safety features, the new train comes fitted with the automatic anti-collision system Kavach, which the previous trains did not have.</li>
<li>Coaches have disaster lights and their battery backup is for three hours, increased from the last one’s one-hour battery backup.</li>
<li>The exterior has eight flatform-side cameras, up from four.</li>
<li>There is also passenger-guard communication facility in coaches, which comes with automatic voice recording feature.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Benefits of Vande Bharat Trains</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cuts Travel Time Drastically</li>
<li>Energy Efficient</li>
<li>Reduce Turnaround Time</li>
<li>Faster Acceleration and Deceleration among others.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has embarked on a mission to roll out 400 Vande Bharats.</li>
<li>By August 2023, the country is to introduce 72 more such trains, taking the total to 75.</li>
<li>The idea is that this third trainset will carry on with its commercial run and at the same time the Railway production units will keep producing more every month to reach the target.</li>
<li>In the works is the plan to introduce Vande Bharat with sleeper berths for overnight journeys.</li>
<li>Options to make these trainsets with an aluminum body is also being explored, for a lighter product.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vande-bharat-express-ii/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>India ranks 40th in the Global Innovation Index of WIPO</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-ranks-40th-global-innovation-index/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>GII</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Innovation in India</p></div></div><p><img alt="innovation" class="alignnone wp-image-641982" height="315" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii-india.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii-india.jpg 843w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii-india-300x185.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii-india-768x473.jpg 768w" width="512"/></p>
<p>India climbed six notches to 40th position in the Global Innovation Index 2022 on account of improvement in several parameters. India was at 46th position in 2021 and at 81st rank in 2015.</p>
<h4><strong>Global Innovation Index</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Global Innovation Index (GII) is an annual ranking of countries by their capacity for, and success in, innovation.</li>
<li>It is published by Cornell University, INSEAD, and the World Intellectual Property Organization, in partnership with other organizations and institutions.</li>
<li>It is based on both subjective and objective data derived from several sources, including the International Telecommunication Union, the World Bank and the World Economic Forum.</li>
<li>The index was started in 2007 by INSEAD and World Business, a British magazine. It was created by Prof. Soumitra Dutta.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Components of GII</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="innovation" class="alignnone wp-image-641983" height="308" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 543px) 100vw, 543px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii.jpg 679w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/gii-300x170.jpg 300w" width="543"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The GII is computed by taking a simple average of the scores in two sub-indices, the Innovation Input Index and Innovation Output Index, which are composed of five and two pillars respectively</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Global scenario</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Switzerland, the US, Sweden, the United Kingdom and the Netherlands are the world’s most-innovative economies.</li>
<li>China is on the threshold of the top 10.</li>
<li>Other emerging economies are also showing consistently strong performance, including India and Turkey, both of which enter the top 40 for the first time.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-ranks-40th-global-innovation-index/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What are Small Savings Instruments (SSIs)?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/small-saving-instruments/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Small Savings Instruments (SSIs)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p>The Centre has announced increases of 0.1-0.3 percentage points in interest rates payable on five small savings instruments (SSIs) marking the first increase in small savings rates since January 2019.</p>
<h4><strong>What are Small Savings Instruments (SSIs)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Small Savings Schemes or instruments are a set of savings instruments <strong><u>managed by the central government</u></strong> with an aim to encourage citizens to save regularly irrespective of their age.</li>
<li>They are popular as they provide <strong><u>returns higher than bank fixed deposits</u></strong>, <strong><u>sovereign guarantee</u></strong> and <strong><u>tax benefits</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How is it managed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Since 2016, the Finance Ministry has been <strong><u>reviewing the interest rates</u></strong> on small savings schemes on a <strong><u>quarterly basis</u></strong>.</li>
<li>All deposits received under various schemes are <strong><u>pooled in the National Small Savings Fund</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>money</u></strong> in the fund is <strong><u>used by the Centre </u></strong>to <strong><u>finance its fiscal deficit</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the different saving schemes?</strong></h4>
<p>The schemes can be grouped under three heads –</p>
<ol>
<li>Post office deposits</li>
<li>Savings certificates and</li>
<li>Social security schemes</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>(1) Post Office Deposits</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Under this we have the savings deposit, recurring deposit and time deposits with 1, 2, 3 and 5 year maturities and the monthly income account.</li>
<li>The savings account currently pays an interest of 4% per annum and can be opened individually or jointly with an initial investment of Rs 500.</li>
<li>The recurring deposit that pays 5.8% a year compounded quarterly matures after 60 months from the date of opening.</li>
<li>It allows investors to save on a monthly basis with a minimum deposit of Rs 100 per month.</li>
<li>Investments under the 5-year time deposit up to Rs 1.5 lakh further qualifies for benefit under section 80C of Income Tax Act.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Savings Certificates</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Under this, we have the National Savings Certificate and the Kisan Vikas Patra.</li>
<li>The National Savings Certificate pays interest at a rate of 6.8% per annum upon maturity after 5 years. The interest that is earned is reinvested into the scheme every year automatically.</li>
<li>The NSC also qualifies for tax saving under Section 80C of the income tax act.</li>
<li>The Kisan Vikas Patra, which is open to everyone, doubles your one-time investment at the end of 124 months signifying a return of 6.9% compounded annually.</li>
<li>The minimum investment amount is Rs 1000 while there is no upper limit.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Social security schemes</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In the third head of social security schemes, there is Public Provident Fund, Sukanya Samriddhi Account and Senior Citizens Savings Scheme.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong> Public Provident Fund</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The Public Provident Fund is a popular saving option for long term goals like retirement.</li>
<li>It pays 7.1% a year and qualifies for tax benefit under Section 80C of the Income Tax Act.</li>
<li>Upon maturity of the account after 15 years, it can be extended indefinitely in blocks of 5 years.</li>
<li>The accumulated amount and interest earned are exempt from tax at the time of withdrawal.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong> Sukanya Samriddhi Account </strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>The Sukanya Samriddhi Account was <strong><u>launched in 2015 under the Beti Bachao Beti Padhao</u></strong> campaign exclusively for a girl child.</li>
<li>The account can be opened in the name of a girl child below the age of 10 years.</li>
<li>The scheme guarantees a return of 7.6% per annum and is eligible for tax benefit under Section 80C of the Income Tax Act.</li>
<li>The tenure of the deposit is 21 years from the date of opening of the account and a maximum of Rs 1.5 lakh can be invested in a year.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong> Senior Citizen Savings Account</strong></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>And finally, the 5-year ​​Senior Citizen Savings Account can be opened by anyone who is over 60 years to age.</li>
<li>It carries an interest of 7.4% per annum payable quarterly and qualifies for Section 80C tax benefit.</li>
<li>These time-tested and safe modes of investments don’t offer quick returns, but are safer when compared to market-linked schemes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How are G-Secs and SSIs related?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>RBI had observed that the rise in yields on <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-government-securities-g-secs/">government securities</a> (G-Secs) had turned ‘the spread between the existing interest rates’ and formula-based rates ‘negative for most small saving schemes’.</li>
<li>Returns on SSIs are linked to market yields on G-Secs with a lag and are fixed on a quarterly basis.</li>
<li>The decision to raise rates on just five SSIs, will mean that returns for some of the schemes, such as the PPF, will be negative in the coming quarter in relation to the formula.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/small-saving-instruments/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Congenital Heart Disease</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/congenital-heart-disease/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Heart, and Heart Diseases</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Health</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Heart Disease" class="alignnone wp-image-641930" height="356" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 635px) 100vw, 635px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-10.00.15-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-10.00.15-1.jpeg 642w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-10.00.15-1-300x168.jpeg 300w" width="635"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Congenital Heart Disease (CHD), which the Centre for Disease Control and Prevention(CDC), Atlanta, U.S., acknowledges to be the most common congenital disorder, is responsible for 28% of all congenital birth defects, and accounts for 6%-10 % of all the infant deaths in India. 29 September is celebrated as world heart day.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-burden-of-heart-diseases/">Congenital Heart Disease (CHD)?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Congenital heart disease is a general term for a range of birth defects that affect the normal way the heart works. The term “congenital” means the condition is present from birth.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Heart Disease" class="alignnone wp-image-641931 size-large" height="947" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.55-1024x947.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.55-1024x947.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.55-300x278.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.55-768x710.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.55-973x900.jpeg 973w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.55.jpeg 1080w" width="1024"/>What is p</strong><strong>aediatric cardiac care?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Paediatric cardiologists diagnose, treat, and manage heart problems in children, including. “Congenital heart disease” (heart differences children are born with), such as holes between chambers of the heart, valve problems, and abnormal blood vessels</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Present situation of </strong><strong>Congenital <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indias-burden-of-heart-diseases/#:~:text=According%20to%20the%20Global%20Burden,a%20legacy%20of%20economic%20growth.">Heart Disease</a></strong> <strong>In India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is estimated that over 1,00,000 children keep getting added to the existing pool of children awaiting surgery.</li>
<li>According to the Paediatric Cardiac Society of India (PCSI), the prevalence of congenital cardiac anomalies is one in every 100 live births; or an estimated 2,00,000 children are born with CHD every year. Only 15,000 of them receive treatment.</li>
<li>At least 30% of infants who have complex defects require surgical intervention to survive their first birthday but only 2,500operations can be performed each year. A case in point is the premier All India Institute of Medical Sciences (AIIMS), where infants are waitlisted till 2026 for cardiac surgery.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Heart Disease" class="alignnone wp-image-641938 size-full" height="1280" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 733px) 100vw, 733px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.56.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.56.jpeg 733w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.56-172x300.jpeg 172w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.56-586x1024.jpeg 586w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-11.37.56-515x900.jpeg 515w" width="733"/>What are the Reasons behind this worrisome situation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of money: </strong>There has been more neglect and little improvement in child health care because creating a comprehensive paediatric cardiology care service is usually considered economically unviable — it is resource intensive and requires infrastructure investment that politicians and policy makers choose to evade.</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure: </strong>There are 22 hospitals and less than 50 centres in India with infant and neonatal cardiac services.</li>
<li><strong>Uneven distribution: </strong>Geographically, these centres are not well distributed either. 2018 cardiology department report of AIIMS, highlighted how South India accounted for 70% of these centres; most centres are located in regions with a lower burden of CHD. For instance, Kerala has eight centres offering neonatal cardiac surgeries for an estimated 4.5 lakh annual childbirths. Populous Uttar Pradesh and Bihar, with an estimated annual childbirth of 48 and 27 lakh births per annum, respectively (Census of India, 2012), do not have a centre capable of performing neonatal cardiac surgery.</li>
<li><strong>Non-priority: </strong>A 2018 article by the Department of Cardiothoracic Cardiology, AIIMS, states, “paediatric cardiology is not a priority area in the face of competing demands for the resources</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the problems in treating</strong><strong> congenital Heart Disease?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Doctor population ratio: </strong>For 600 districts with a 1.4 billion population, there are only 250 paediatric cardiologists available. The doctor to patient ratio is an abysmal one for half-a-crore population. According to the Annals of Paediatric Cardiology journal, the United States had 2,966 paediatric cardiologists in 2019, ratio of one per 29,196population.</li>
<li><strong>Poverty: </strong>Poverty is another barrier before treatment. Transporting sick neonates from States with little or no cardiac care facilities to faraway centres for accurate diagnosis and treatment burdens parents financially.</li>
<li><strong>Medical devices: </strong>In addition, there is the non-availability of crucial equipment that is essential for diagnosis of heart diseases in the unborn. Accentuating the problem is the general lack of awareness about early symptoms of CHD among parents.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Heart Disease" class="alignnone wp-image-641940" height="439" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 608px) 100vw, 608px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-09.58.50.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-09.58.50.jpeg 400w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-09.58.50-300x217.jpeg 300w" width="608"/>What should be approach for the treatment of Congenital Heart Disease?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Timely treatment: </strong>Paediatricians say timely medical intervention can save 75% of these children and give them normal lives.</li>
<li><strong>National policy: </strong>The lack of a national policy for the treatment of cardiovascular diseases in children keeps a huge number outside the ambit of treatment.</li>
<li><strong>Echocardiography: </strong>The Child Heart Foundation, a non-governmental organisation working in Siliguri (WestBengal), Jalandhar (Punjab) and Delhi, with underprivileged children with CHD, has been flagging the need for fatal echocardiography.</li>
<li><strong>Hridayam</strong>: There are programmes worth emulating such as Kerala’s ‘Hridayam (for little hearts)’,aimed at early detection, management and support to children with CHD or the Tamilnadu Chief Minister’s Comprehensive Health Insurance Scheme offering free specialised surgeries.</li>
<li><strong>Ayushman Bharat: </strong>The National Health Protection Scheme (Ayushman Bharat), is expected to financially assist 10 crore poor families but has still to takeoff. So far, Maharashtra, Karnataka, Gujarat and Andhra Pradesh have apparently got going.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s performance in neo natal care is very regrettable. India can drastically reduce its infant mortality by investing in paediatric cardiac care. Sooner we realize this better will be the future of India.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Infant mortality India out of congenital Heart Disease is because of negligence and non-priority. Acknowledge the problems and suggest solutions.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/congenital-heart-disease/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Fixing Falling Indian Rupee</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/falling-indian-rupee/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>weakening of Rupee,appreciation and depreciation</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Indian Economics</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Falling Indian Rupee" class="alignnone wp-image-641941 size-full" height="752" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-1.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-1.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-1-300x188.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-1-1024x642.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.50-1-768x481.jpeg 768w" width="1200"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Last week, the rupee weakened against the dollar past the 81-mark to a record low. In recent months, the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) has been intervening in the FOREX market to smoothen the decline. Indian foreign exchange reserves have fallen by about $94billion in 12 months to about $545 billion until mid-September. Falling Indian Rupee poses huge challenge in the economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the major challenges before Indian Economy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Falling rupee</strong>: A fall in the rupee against the dollar in the FOREX market means that the Indian currency is weakening. This means that while importing from the United States or any country, India will have to pay more because the payment is done in dollars, i.e., less import cost more.</li>
<li><strong>Inflation: </strong>Since May this year, RBI has largely managed to control inflation. RBI managed inflation to keep it below 7.5 % but, looking at Ukraine situation, oil prices may shoot up again and there by inflation will rise.</li>
<li><strong>Growing CAD</strong>: India’s current account deficit (CAD) in April-June was at $23.9 billion, or 2.8 per cent of gross domestic product (GDP), much higher than the $13.4 billion, or 1.5 per cent of GDP, in January-March 2022. India has faced upward pressure on its import bill in 2022 because Russia’s invasion of Ukraine in late February led to a sharp rise in prices of commodities across the globe.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Falling of Rupee" class="alignnone wp-image-641951 size-large" height="576" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-1-1024x576.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-1-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-1-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-1-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-1.jpeg 1200w" width="1024"/>What is <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rbi-and-the-rupee-to-break-a-free-fall-or-not-to/">RBI’s role in managing falling Rupee ?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Use of foreign exchange reserve: </strong>The use of FOREX reserves is appropriate at this juncture. You build your reserves during good times and spend them during bad times. Right now, reserves are being spent in trying to curb currency volatility. RBI can’t defend the rupee at a particular level, because that would be swimming against the tide, which is not possible in this environment. But RBI can make it less volatile.</li>
<li><strong>Easy dollar supply: </strong>RBI has already undertaken measures such as easing provisions for remittances, allowing short-term foreign portfolio investments in government securities, etc. We can even think of a scheme similar to the one introduced in 2014to attract NRI investments<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Interest rate: </strong>Interest rates are being raised not only to control inflation, but also to address external imbalances. But let’s also look at past episodes of sharp depreciation of the currency which we have seen during the global financial crisis, during the taper tantrum. They tell us that the currency weakens very sharply during these episodes of global shocks, but it also corrects. If you plot it over a 15-20-year period, you will see that the overshooting of the currency typically gets corrected after the event is over. So, the aim now should only be to ensure that volatility is not too high, not to steer the currency in any direction.</li>
<li><strong>Managing the CAD</strong>: According to experts, RBI can finance the CAD with capital inflows, and prevent hot money outflow with the aid of interest rates, that could be an effective long-term solution. The focus should be on how we can stem capital that is flighty. Even during the tenure of Raghuram Rajan the CAD went up to 4%. But the moment hot money became flighty, panic set in. Till then, we were comfortably financing the CAD with capital flows.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Falling Indian Rupee" class="alignnone wp-image-641954 size-full" height="1179" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.54.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.54.jpeg 1080w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.54-275x300.jpeg 275w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.54-938x1024.jpeg 938w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.54-768x838.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.54-824x900.jpeg 824w" width="1080"/>What are the Notes of caution?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>On FOREX: </strong>There is also a limit to how much you can lean on the reserves. They can burn out pretty quickly if you are aggressive in your interventions<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>On rupee fall and CAD: </strong>RBI also needs to let the rupee depreciate in an orderly manner. Some, but not too much, depreciation will partly help the export sector, as global demand is the key influencer of exports, and currencies of our competitors are also weakening. So, the vulnerability that stems from high current account deficit (CAD) can get addressed to some extent.</li>
<li><strong>On interest rate: </strong>We have to focus on the real interest rate and economic growth, for public debt management. If the Real interest rate is going to be greater than Growth, then we are in an unsustainable situation. The only way to address these concerns such as fiscal consolidation, twin deficit crisis, given that the real rate of interest is negative, given the hawkish mode of the Fed, is to raise rates.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Falling Indian Rupee" class="alignnone wp-image-641955 size-large" height="1015" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1-1024x1015.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1-1024x1015.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1-300x298.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1-150x150.jpeg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1-768x762.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1-908x900.jpeg 908w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.57-1.jpeg 1080w" width="1024"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>With rising external trade, India’s economy is integrating with world. Impact of global uncertainty on economy is natural outcome. Ukraine episode, slowing Europe and unclear USA is going give Indian policy maker a tough time in coming months.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Recent global events and future uncertainties pose challenges to microeconomic stability. Discuss what measures India can take to keep inflation low.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/falling-indian-rupee/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Competent Chief of Defence Staff</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/chief-of-defence-staff/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CDS</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Security, Role of CDS</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Chief of Defence Staff" class="alignnone wp-image-641953 size-full" height="1280" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 877px) 100vw, 877px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.52.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.52.jpeg 877w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.52-206x300.jpeg 206w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.52-702x1024.jpeg 702w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.52-768x1121.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.52-617x900.jpeg 617w" width="877"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Government on September 28, 2022, appointed former Eastern Army Commander Lt. General Anil Chauhan as the next Chief of Defence Staff (CDS). The appointment comes more than nine months after the post fell vacant following the death of General Bipin Rawat.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the role of the Office of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/back-in-news-chief-of-defence-staff-cds-2/">Chief of Defence Staff (CDS)?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Mandate is to bring convergence in the functioning of the Army, the Navy and the Air force and bolster the country’s overall military prowess.</li>
<li>The CDS is a high military office that oversees and coordinates the working of the three Services, and offers seamless tri-service views and single-point advice to the Executive.</li>
<li>On long-term it provides for defence planning and management, including manpower, equipment and strategy, and above all, “joint manship” in operations.</li>
<li>The role of the CDS becomes critical in times of conflict.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is the need of CDS?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tri-services coordination:</strong> The creation of the CDS will eventually lead to the formation of tri-service theatre commands intended to create vertical integration of the three forces.</li>
<li><strong>Single-point military advisory:</strong> The CDS will be a single-point military adviser to the government and synergise long term planning, procurements, training and logistics of the three Services.</li>
<li><strong>Efforts saving:</strong> This is expected to save money by avoiding duplication between the Services, at a time of shrinking capital expenditure within the defence budget.</li>
<li><strong>Military diplomacy:</strong> This is today supporting conventional diplomacy. That can’t be done by different Services.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Chief of Defence Staff" class="alignnone wp-image-641959 size-full" height="1280" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 853px) 100vw, 853px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56.jpeg 853w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-200x300.jpeg 200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-682x1024.jpeg 682w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-768x1152.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.56-600x900.jpeg 600w" width="853"/>All you need to know about the New Chief of Defence Staff (CDS):</strong> <strong>Lt. General Anil Chauhan</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Indian Army:</strong> Born on May 18, 1961, Lt. Gen. Chauhan was commissioned into the 11 Gorkha Rifles of the Indian Army in 1981.</li>
<li><strong>Alumnus of NDA and IMA:</strong> He is an alumnus of the National Defence Academy, Khadakwasla and Indian Military Academy, Dehradun.</li>
<li><strong>Career of 40 years:</strong> In a career spanning over nearly 40 years, Lt. Gen. Anil Chauhan had held several command, staff and instrumental appointments and had extensive experience in counter-insurgency operations in Jammu and Kashmir and North-East India.</li>
<li><strong>As Major General:</strong> In the rank of Major General, he had commanded an Infantry Division in Baramula sector in Jammu and Kashmir</li>
<li><strong>As Lt. General:</strong> As Lt. General, he commanded a Corps in the North East and subsequently became the Eastern Army Commander in September 2019 and held the charge until his retirement from service on May 31, 2021.</li>
<li><strong>As Military Advisor to the NSA</strong>: Lt. Gen. Chauhan took over as the Military Advisor in the National Security Council Secretariat (NSCS) from Lt. Gen. Vinod G. Khandare who stepped down from the post in October 2021</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Chief of Defence Staff" class="alignnone wp-image-641984 size-large" height="1024" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 932px) 100vw, 932px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-12.40.28-932x1024.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-12.40.28-932x1024.jpeg 932w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-12.40.28-273x300.jpeg 273w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-12.40.28-768x844.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-12.40.28-819x900.jpeg 819w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-12.40.28.jpeg 1165w" width="932"/>What are the challenges facing the new chief of Defence Staff?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Responsibility: </strong>In terms of prioritisation and building a bridge between a government in a hurry and an organisation that is resistant to change, shackled by tradition and plagued by continued turf battles that cannot be wished away.</li>
<li><strong>Enhancing operational capability:</strong> To build operational capability at a pace that will ensure that the military power asymmetry vis-à-vis China remains manageable.</li>
<li><strong>Integrated structure:</strong> The need to create fresh structures to support integrated training, planning and operations. India-specific requirements need to be addressed.</li>
<li><strong>Articulated strategy:</strong> The requirement is in the area of policy, doctrines and strategy. Policies and doctrines are easier to evolve under the cover of clearly articulated national and military strategies. Though the strategic establishment is divided on the pressing need for a National Security Strategy (NSS), the CDS has his task cut out to link the NSS with transformation and expedite its promulgation</li>
<li><strong>Maintaining balance:</strong> Balancing the need to retain the operational capability and the government’s push towards self-reliance in defence manufacturing. Considering that this push demands a paradigm shift in the thinking of India’s defence innovation and manufacturing ecosystem. One needs to look no further than the US, France and Israel to embrace this push. However, this again links to forcing the armed forces to step out of their comfort zone and develop diverse intellectual capital.</li>
<li><strong>Shedding infructuous colonial legacies:</strong> Shedding several infructuous colonial legacies and traditions and fostering a sense of pride in India’s martial traditions that go back to epics such as the Mahabharata and to the Maratha and Chola empires.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Chief of Defence Staff" class="alignnone wp-image-641960 size-full" height="538" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 970px) 100vw, 970px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.48.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.48.jpeg 970w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.48-300x166.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/WhatsApp-Image-2022-09-30-at-06.33.48-768x426.jpeg 768w" width="970"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>CDS should not hesitate to speak truth to power. He should be unbiased while taking tough decisions and should consider national interest above all else. In a rapidly evolving geopolitical and global security environment, in which India faces challenges across the conflict spectrum, the CDS need to undertake this task.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.In a rapidly evolving geopolitical and global security environment, India faces challenges across the conflict spectrum. Discuss the role of CDS in the joint preparations of the three forces in this context.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/chief-of-defence-staff/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Black Cocaine?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/black-cocaine-smuggling-mumbai/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Black Cocaine</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Drugs smuggling in India</p></div></div><p><img alt="cocaine" class="alignnone wp-image-642759" height="305" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 417px) 100vw, 417px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/cocaine.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/cocaine.jpg 524w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/cocaine-300x219.jpg 300w" width="417"/></p>
<p>The Narcotics Control Bureau (NCB) has arrested a Bolivian woman from Mumbai airport for allegedly carrying black cocaine.</p>
<h4>What is Black Cocaine?</h4>
<ul>
<li>“Black cocaine”, a rare drug, is a mixture of regular cocaine and other chemicals of administrated quantity.</li>
<li>It neutralises the smell of cocaine so that it can pass through checkpoints easily.</li>
<li>Black cocaine is a mixture of regular cocaine base with various substances to camouflage typical appearance (e.g. charcoal).</li>
<li>It surpasses colour-based drug tests (cobalt salts form deep red complexes in solution), to make the mixture undetectable by drug-sniffing dogs as activated carbon may sufficiently absorb trace odours.</li>
<li>The pure cocaine base is then recovered from the mixture by extraction using common organic solvents such as methylene chloride or acetone.</li>
<li>A second process is required to convert the cocaine base into powdered cocaine hydrochloride.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What has been the major source of cocaine in India?</h4>
<ul>
<li>South American countries where coca plants grow are major suppliers of cocaine to India.</li>
<li>Generally, Mumbai is one of the landing points from where it is then sent to other parts of the country, especially to metro cities and Goa.</li>
<li>Amongst narcotics, Cocaine is one of the most expensive ones and is primarily used by the upper classes of society.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/black-cocaine-smuggling-mumbai/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>RBI hikes Repo Rate by another 50 basis points to 5.9%</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rbi-hikes-repo-rate-by-50-bps/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Repo Rate</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="repo" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-642758" height="383" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 477px) 100vw, 477px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/repo.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/repo.jpg 477w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/repo-300x241.jpg 300w" width="477"/></p>
<p>The repo rate, the rate at which RBI lends money to commercial banks, has been hiked by 50 basis points again.</p>
<h4><strong>What is Repo Rate?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Repo rate is the rate at which the central bank of a country (Reserve Bank of India in case of India) lends money to commercial banks in the event of any shortfall of funds.</li>
<li>It is used by monetary authorities to control inflation.</li>
<li>In the event of inflation, central banks increase repo rate as this acts as a disincentive for banks to borrow from the central bank.</li>
<li>This ultimately reduces the money supply in the economy and thus helps in arresting inflation.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does the repo dynamics work?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When there is a shortage of funds, commercial banks borrow money from the central bank which is repaid according to the repo rate applicable.</li>
<li>The central bank provides these short terms loans against securities such as treasury bills or government bonds.</li>
<li>This monetary policy is used by the central bank to control inflation or increase the liquidity of banks.</li>
<li>The government increases the repo rate when they need to control prices and restrict borrowings.</li>
<li>An increase in repo rate means commercial banks have to pay more interest for the money lent to them and therefore, a change in repo rate eventually affects public borrowings such as home loan, EMIs, etc.</li>
<li>From interest charged by commercial banks on loans to the returns from deposits, various financial and investment instruments are indirectly dependent on the repo rate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Relationship between repo rate and interest rates</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The relationship between the repo rate paid by the bank to RBI and the interest rates paid by the borrower to the bank is directly proportional.</li>
<li>The greater the repo rate, the higher will be the cost of borrowing. Let us understand this with two examples.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Scenario #1: RBI hikes repo rate</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>As of December 2020, the repo rate was 4%. Suppose that RBI increases this to 6%.</li>
<li>This means that now, the cost of borrowing from the RBI has increased by 2% or 200 basis points for commercial banks.</li>
<li>To compensate for a high cost of borrowing, banks will, in turn, charge a higher interest rate from their borrowers.</li>
<li>As a result, loans will become expensive for citizens.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Scenario #2: RBI slashes repo rate</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Alternatively, if the RBI slashes this rate from 4% to 3.75% (say), banks will be able to afford borrowing more easily than before.</li>
<li>They will reduce the interest rates for loans and taking a loan from the bank will become cheaper for citizens.</li>
<li>In addition to affecting the interest rates on loan, the repo rate also impacts the returns on direct deposits.</li>
<li>If there is a repo rate cut, you will earn a lower interest rate and vice versa.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Try this PYQ:</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Q.If the RBI decides to adopt an expansionist monetary policy, which of the following would it not do?</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Cut and optimize the Statutory Liquidity Ratio</li>
<li>Increase the Marginal Standing Facility Rate</li>
<li>Cut the Bank Rate and Repo Rate</li>
</ol>
<p>Select the correct answer using the code given below:</p>
<p>(a) 1 and 2 only</p>
<p>(b) 2 only</p>
<p>(c) 1 and 3 only</p>
<p>(d) 1, 2 and 3</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<hr/>
<h4><strong>Back2Basics: Repo Rate vs Bank Rate</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Bank Rate is charged against loans offered by the central bank to commercial banks, whereas, Repo Rate is charged for repurchasing the securities sold by the commercial banks to the central bank.</li>
<li>No collateral is involved while charging Bank Rate but securities, bonds, agreements and collateral is involved when Repo Rate is charged.</li>
<li>Repo Rate is always lower than the Bank Rate.</li>
<li>An increase in Bank Rate directly affects the lending rates offered to the customer, restricting people to avail of loans and damages the overall economic growth, whereas an increase in Repo Rate is usually handled by the banks and doesn’t affect customers directly.</li>
<li>Comparatively, Bank Rate caters to long-term financial requirements of commercial banks whereas Repo Rate focuses on short-term financial needs.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rbi-hikes-repo-rate-by-50-bps/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What are Community Reserves?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/community-reserves/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Community Reserves</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>India’s North East has seen a mushrooming of ‘community reserves’ in the last 11 years.</p>
<h4>What are Community Reserves?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Community reserves fall under protected areas, along with marine protected areas, national parks, wildlife sanctuaries and conservation reserves, according to the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/govt-brings-bill-to-amend-wildlife-protection-act/">Wild Life (Protection) Act, 1972</a>.</li>
<li>Community Reserves were first introduced in the Wildlife (Protection) Amendment Act of 2002 − the amendment to the Wildlife Protection Act of 1972.</li>
<li>Such areas are designated as conservation areas if they are uninhabited and completely owned by the GoI but used for subsistence by communities, and community areas if part of the lands are privately owned.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why need such areas?</h4>
<ul>
<li>These categories were added because of reduced protection in and around existing or proposed protected areas due to private ownership of land, and land use.</li>
<li>A case in point was the Melghat Tiger Reserve where a large area was left unprotected due to private ownership.</li>
<li>They typically are migration corridors between established national parks, wildlife sanctuaries and reserved and protected forests of India.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who administers Community Reserves?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Once forest land has been declared as a community reserve, it goes from being governed by local village councils to coming under the forest department.</li>
<li>Administration of such reserves would be through local people and local agencies like the Gram Panchayat, as in the case of communal forests.</li>
<li>Community reserves are the first instances of private land being accorded protection under the Indian legislature.</li>
<li>It opens up the possibility of communally owned for-profit wildlife resorts, and also causes privately held areas under non-profit organizations like land trusts to be given protection.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/community-reserves/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Graded Response Action Plan (GRAP)?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/graded-response-action-plan-upsc/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Graded Response Action Plan- GRAP</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Delhi Air Pollution issue</p></div></div><p>The Delhi CM has announced a 15-point Winter Action Plan to be implemented along with the Graded Response Action Plan (GRAP).</p>
<h4><strong>Graded Response Action Plan- GRAP</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>GRAP is a set of measures to be taken to reduce Air Pollution depending on the current level of pollution.</li>
<li>It was notified by the Union Environment Ministry in 2017 to fight air pollution, based on the SC directions.</li>
<li>In 2014, when a study by the WHO found that Delhi was the most polluted city in the world, panic spread in the Centre and the state government.</li>
<li>Approved by the Supreme Court in 2016, the plan was formulated after several meetings that the Environment Pollution (Prevention and Control) Authority (EPCA) held with state government and experts.</li>
<li>The result was a plan that institutionalized measures to be taken when air quality deteriorates.</li>
<li>GRAP works only as an emergency measure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does it work?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As such, the plan does not include action by various state governments to be taken throughout the year to tackle industrial, vehicular and combustion emissions.</li>
<li>When the air quality shifts from poor to very poor, the measures listed under both sections have to be followed since the plan is incremental in nature.</li>
<li>If air quality reaches the severe+ stage, GRAP talks about shutting down schools and implementing the odd-even road-space rationing scheme.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Measures taken under GRAP</strong></h4>
<p><strong>1) Severe+ or Emergency</strong></p>
<p>(PM 2.5 over 300 µg/cubic metre or PM10 over 500 µg/cu. m. for 48+ hours)</p>
<ul>
<li>Stop entry of trucks into Delhi (except essential commodities)</li>
<li>Stop construction work</li>
<li>Introduce odd/even scheme for private vehicles and minimise exemptions</li>
<li>Task Force to decide any additional steps including shutting of schools</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2) Severe</strong></p>
<p>(PM 2.5 over 250 µg/cu. m. or PM10 over 430 µg/cu. m.)</p>
<ul>
<li>Close brick kilns, hot mix plants, stone crushers</li>
<li>Maximise power generation from natural gas to reduce generation from coal</li>
<li>Encourage public transport, with differential rates</li>
<li>More frequent mechanized cleaning of road and sprinkling of water</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>3) Very Poor</strong></p>
<p>(PM2.5 121-250 µg/cu. m. or PM10 351-430 µg/cu. m.)</p>
<ul>
<li>Stop use of diesel generator sets</li>
<li>Enhance parking fee by 3-4 times</li>
<li>Increase bus and Metro services</li>
<li>Apartment owners to discourage burning fires in winter by providing electric heaters during winter</li>
<li>Advisories to people with respiratory and cardiac conditions to restrict outdoor movement</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>4) Moderate to poor</strong></p>
<p>(PM2.5 61-120 µg/cu. m. or PM10 101-350 µg/cu. m.)</p>
<ul>
<li>Heavy fines for garbage burning</li>
<li>Close/enforce pollution control regulations in brick kilns and industries</li>
<li>Mechanized sweeping on roads with heavy traffic and water sprinkling</li>
<li>Strictly enforce a ban on firecrackers</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Has GRAP helped?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The biggest success of GRAP has been in fixing accountability and deadlines.</li>
<li>For each action to be taken under a particular air quality category, executing agencies are clearly marked.</li>
<li>In a territory like Delhi, where a multiplicity of authorities has been a long-standing impediment to effective governance, this step made a crucial difference.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/graded-response-action-plan-upsc/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>AFSPA extended in Nagaland, Arunachal</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/afspa-extended-in-nagaland-arunachal/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>AFSPA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The Ministry of Home Affairs (MHA) has extended the Armed Forces (Special Powers) Act (AFSPA) in parts of Arunachal Pradesh and Nagaland for another six months.</p>
<h4><strong>AFSPA: A Backgrounder</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The AFSPA, 1958 came into force in the context of insurgency in the North-eastern States decades ago.</li>
<li>It provides “special power” to the Armed Forces applies to the Army, the Air Force and the Central Paramilitary forces etc.</li>
<li>It has been long contested debate whether the “special powers” granted under AFSPA gives total immunity to the armed forces for any action taken by them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Armed Forces (Special Powers) Act, 1958</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Armed Forces Special Powers Act, to put it simply, gives armed forces the power to maintain public order in “disturbed areas.”</li>
<li>AFSPA gives armed forces the authority use force or even open fire after giving due warning if they feel a person is in contravention of the law.</li>
<li>The Act further provides that if “reasonable suspicion exists”, the armed forces can also arrest a person without warrant; enter or search premises without a warrant; and ban the possession of firearms.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the Special Powers?</strong></h4>
<p>The ‘special powers’ which are spelt out under Section 4 provide that:</p>
<p><strong><u>(a) Power to use force</u></strong><u>, <strong>including opening fire</strong>, <strong>even to the extent of causing death</strong></u> if prohibitory orders banning assembly of five or more persons or carrying arms and weapons, etc are in force in the disturbed area;</p>
<p><strong><u>(b) Power to destroy structures </u></strong>used as hide-outs, training camps, or as a place from which attacks are or likely to be launched, etc;</p>
<p><strong><u>(c) Power to arrest without warrant</u></strong> and to use force for the purpose;</p>
<p><strong><u>(d) Power to enter and search premises</u></strong> without a warrant to make arrest or recovery of hostages, arms and ammunition and stolen property etc.</p>
<h4><strong>What are the Disturbed Areas?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A disturbed area is one that is declared by notification under Section 3 of the AFSPA.</li>
<li>As per Section 3, it can be invoked in places where “the use of armed forces in aid of the civil power is necessary”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who can declare/notify such areas?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Central Government or the Governor of the State or administrator of the Union Territory can declare the whole or part of the State or Union Territory as a disturbed area.</li>
<li>A suitable notification would have to be made in the Official Gazette.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Presently active ‘Disturbed Areas’</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>AFSPA is currently in force in Assam, Nagaland, Manipur, 3 districts of Arunachal Pradesh, and areas falling within the jurisdiction of 8 police stations in Arunachal Pradesh bordering Assam.</li>
<li>In Jammu and Kashmir, a separate law Armed Forces (Jammu and Kashmir) Special Powers Act, 1990 has been in force.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>AFSPA: Is it a License to Kill?</strong></h4>
<p>While the operation of the Section has been controversial in itself, it has attracted much criticism when actions have resulted in the death of civilians.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Power to kill:</strong> Section 4 of the Act granted officers the authority to “take any action” even to the extent to cause the death.</li>
<li><strong>Protection against prosecution:</strong> This power is further bolstered by Section 6 which provides that legal can be instituted against the officer, except with the previous sanction of the Central Government.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Supreme Court’s Observations over AFSPA</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>These extra-judicial killings became the attention of the Supreme Court in 2016.</li>
<li>It clarified that the bar under Section 6 would not grant “total immunity” to the officers against any probe into their alleged excesses.</li>
<li>The judgment noted that if any death was unjustified, there is no blanket immunity available to the perpetrator(s) of the offense.</li>
<li>The Court further noted that if an offense is committed even by Army personnel, there is no concept of absolute immunity from trial by the criminal court constituted under the CrPC.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Constitutionality of AFSPA</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Attempts have been made to examine the constitutionality of the Act on the grounds that it is contravention to the:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Right to Life and Personal Liberty</strong> (Article 21) and</li>
<li><strong>Federal structure</strong> of the Constitution since law and order is a <strong>State subject</strong></li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Recommendations to repeal AFSPA</strong></h4>
<p><strong><u>(1) Justice B.P. Jeevan Reddy Commission</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The 2004 Committee headed by Justice B.P. Jeevan Reddy, the content of which has never officially been revealed by the Government, recommended that AFSPA be repealed.</li>
<li>Additionally, it recommended that appropriate provisions be inserted in the Unlawful Activities Prevention Act, 1967 (UAPA) instead.</li>
<li>It also recommended that the UAPA be modified to clearly specify the powers of the armed forces and paramilitary forces and grievance cells should be set up in each district where the armed forces are deployed.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(2) ARC II</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Administrative Reforms Commission in its 5th Report on ‘Public Order’ had also recommended that AFSPA be repealed.</li>
<li>It recommended adding a new chapter to be added to the Unlawful Activities Prevention Act, 1967.</li>
<li>However, the recommendation was considered first and then rejected.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other issues with AFSPA</strong></h4>
<p><strong><u>(1) Sexual Misconduct by Armed Forces</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The issue of violation of human rights by actions of armed forces came under the consideration of the Committee on Amendments to Criminal Law (popularly known as Justice Verma Committee) set up in 2012.</li>
<li>It observed that- in conflict zones, legal protection for women was neglected.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(2) Autocracy</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The reality is that there is no evidence of any action being taken against any officer of the armed forces or paramilitary forces for their excesses.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward: Caution given by the Supreme Court</strong></h4>
<p>A July 2016 judgment authored by Justice Madan B. Lokur in Extra Judicial Execution Victim Families Association quoted the “Ten Commandments” issued by the Chief of the Army Staff for operations in disturbed areas:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Definite circumstances:</strong> The “power to cause death is relatable to maintenance of public order in a disturbed area and is to be exercised under definite circumstances”.</li>
<li><strong>Declaration preconditions:</strong> These preconditions include a declaration by a high-level authority that an area is “disturbed”.</li>
<li><strong>Due warning:</strong> The officer concerned decides to use deadly force on the opinion that it is “necessary” to maintain public order. But he has to give “due warning” first.</li>
<li><strong>No arbitrary action:</strong> The persons against whom the action was taken by the armed forces should have been “acting in contravention of any law or order for the time being in force in the disturbed area”.</li>
<li><strong>Minimal use of force:</strong> The armed forces must use only the “minimal force required for effective action against the person/persons acting in contravention of the prohibitory order.”</li>
<li><strong>Empathy with perpetrators:</strong> The court said that: the people you are dealing with are your own countrymen. All your conduct must be dictated by this one significant consideration.</li>
<li><strong>People friendliness:</strong> The court underscored how the Commandments insist that “operations must be people-friendly, using minimum force and avoiding collateral damage – restrain must be the key”.</li>
<li><strong>Good intelligence:</strong> It added that “good intelligence is the key to success”.</li>
<li><strong>Compassion:</strong> It exhorted personnel to “be compassionate, help the people and win their hearts and minds. Employ all resources under your command to improve their living conditions”.</li>
<li><strong>Upholding Dharma (Duty):</strong> The judgment ended with the final Commandment to “uphold Dharma and take pride in your country and the Army”.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Despite demands by civil society groups and human rights activities, none of the recommendations have not been implemented to date.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/afspa-extended-in-nagaland-arunachal/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Swachh Bharat Mission 2.0 : A Pledge</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/swachh-bharat-mission-2-0/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Swachh Bharat Abhiyan</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Health and Sanitation</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt=" Swachh Bharat mission 2.0 " class="alignnone wp-image-642746 size-large" height="626" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.20-1024x626.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.20-1024x626.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.20-300x184.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.20-768x470.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.20.jpeg 1177w" width="1024"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As we celebrate the 75th anniversary of India’s independence, much can be said about the progress the country has made in achieving the Sustainable Development Goals (SDG) concerning sanitation. Public-private partnerships are building on successes of the first phase of the Swachh Bharat Mission and setting more ambitious goals for the next phase Swachh Bharat Mission 2.0</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Swachh Bharat Mission?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>On 2nd October 2014, Swachh Bharat Mission was launched throughout length and breadth of the country as a national movement</li>
<li>This year also Swachh Bharat Abhiyan 2.0 will be launched on 1 October 2022.</li>
<li><strong>Aim: </strong>Swachh Bharat Abhiyan aims to connect people from different regions, languages and backgrounds. Swachh Bharat 2.0 is not just a programme but it is an effort to make people realise the importance of cleanliness. It will also contribute to better the happiness index of the country.</li>
<li><strong>Objective</strong>: The objective of Swachh Bharat 2.0 is to increase awareness about cleanliness, organise people and ensure participation of the countrymen, especially the youth, in making India clean. 744 districts and six lakh villages of the country will be linked to the campaign through all youth trusts, national service scheme and other voluntary organisations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt=" Swachh Bharat mission 2.0 " class="alignnone wp-image-642755 size-full" height="474" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 714px) 100vw, 714px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.53.00.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.53.00.jpeg 714w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.53.00-300x199.jpeg 300w" width="714"/>How was the situation before Swachh Bharat Mission?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Low coverage: </strong>Till 2014, sanitation coverage in India was as low as 39 per cent. Around 55 crore people in rural areas were without a toilet facility before 2014 and this severely affected the health and dignity of our people, especially women and children.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Prevalence of diseases: </strong>The greatest and perhaps most significant impact of poor sanitation is on health. Exposure to contaminated drinking water and food with pathogen laden human waste is a major cause of diarrhoea and can cause cholera, trachoma, intestinal worms, etc, leading to the “stunting” of huge swathes of our children.</li>
<li><strong>Impact on environment: </strong>Poor hygiene and waste management practices also impact the environment with untreated sewage flowing directly into water bodies and affecting coastal and marine ecosystems, contaminating soil and air, and exposing millions to disease.</li>
<li><strong>Economy suffers: </strong>Poor sanitary practices impact the economy adversely. A study by the World Bank states that the absence of toilets and conventional sanitation costs India 6.4 per cent of its GDP in 2006. The economic impact of poor sanitation for India is at least $38.5 billion every year under health, education, access time and tourism.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt=" Swachh Bharat mission 2.0 " class="alignnone wp-image-642749 size-large" height="1024" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.29-1-1024x1024.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.29-1-1024x1024.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.29-1-300x300.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.29-1-150x150.jpeg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.29-1-768x768.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.29-1-900x900.jpeg 900w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.29-1-1200x1200.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.24.29-1.jpeg 1280w" width="1024"/>All you need to know about <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/the-jal-jeevan-and-swachh-bharat-missions-are-improving-peoples-well-being/">Swachh</a></strong><strong><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/the-jal-jeevan-and-swachh-bharat-missions-are-improving-peoples-well-being/"> Bharat Mission 1.0.</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Open defecation Free India: </strong>The launch of the Swachh Bharat Mission (SBM) by the Prime Minister on October 2, 2014, had a unique goal to achieve universal sanitation coverage and to make the country Open Defecation Free (ODF).</li>
<li><strong>Toilet construction: </strong>By offering financial incentives for building household toilets, as well as community toilets for slums and migrant populations, the government gave a huge fillip to the toilet infrastructure.</li>
<li><strong>Behaviour changes programmes</strong>: To bring changes to the age old idea that the toilets in the home were unclean, the government ran several programmes with the participation of the private sector and NGOs to educate the population on the benefits of ODF in what is acclaimed as one of the largest behaviours change programmes in the world.</li>
<li>From 2014 to 2020, more than 10 crore toilets were constructed. The country declared itself ODF on October 2, 2019.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt=" Swachh Bharat mission 2.0 " class="alignnone wp-image-642757 size-large" height="883" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.27.05-1024x883.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.27.05-1024x883.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.27.05-300x259.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.27.05-768x662.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.27.05-1043x900.jpeg 1043w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.27.05.jpeg 1200w" width="1024"/> </strong><strong>Swachh Bharat mission 2.0 </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The second phase of the project, which commenced in 2020 and is expected to run till 2025, has set even more ambitious targets.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Safe sanitation: </strong>SBM(Urban) 2.0 envisions to make all cities ‘Garbage Free’ and ensure grey and black water management in all cities other than those covered under AMRUT, make all urban local bodies as ODF+ and those with a population of less than 1 lakh as ODF++, thereby achieving the vision of safe sanitation in urban areas.</li>
<li><strong>Solid waste management: </strong>The Mission will focus on source segregation of solid waste, utilizing the principles of 3Rs (reduce, reuse, recycle), scientific processing of all types of municipal solid waste and remediation of legacy dumpsites for effective solid waste management. The outlay of SBM-U 2.0 is around Rs.1.41 lakh crore.</li>
<li><strong>The Lighthouse Initiative (LHI)</strong>:</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Commissioned by the Ministry of Drinking Water and Sanitation as part of the Azadi ka Amrit Mahotsav is to be implemented through PPP, across villages in 75-gram panchayats in 15 states in Phase1.</li>
<li>LHI is based on the principle of inclusive sanitation and leaving no one behind.</li>
<li>LHI aims to effectively implement solid and liquid waste management structures by employing a participatory and consultative approach through mobilisation of the village communities, corporate, district and block administration and gram panchayat officers. Joint ownership and accountability between local governments, communities and corporates will ensure the success of the initiative.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Public private partnership: </strong>The India Sanitation Coalition (ISC) is a multi-stakeholder platform that creates meaningful collaborations. These stakeholders include the private sector, government, financial institutions, civil society groups, media, donors, etc. Today, ISC is recognised as the official intersection between the government and the private sector for engagement in helping build solid and liquid waste management infrastructure sustainably.</li>
<li><strong>CSR Funding: </strong>The private sector will supplement this through CSR funding. Going forward, the ISC will continue to focus on the government’s position with regard to the thematic inter-linkages  between WASH and sectors such as health, education, gender, nutrition and livelihoods</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cleanliness is next to the Godliness. Sanitation is linked with health, environment and economy. Swachh Bharat mission 2.0 has noble intention. It has to become the citizen’s movement to replicate the success of phase 1 of the mission.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Questions</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Solid waste management, including e-waste, will be major sanitation issues in the coming years. Discuss the role of citizens, government and various stakeholders in society in this context.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> <a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/swachh-bharat-mission-2-0/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Indiscriminate use of chemical fertilizers</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fertilizers/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<h4><strong><img alt="chemical fertilizers" class="alignnone wp-image-642772 size-full" height="600" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.17.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.17.jpeg 800w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.17-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.17-768x576.jpeg 768w" width="800"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Given the genetic modification of the human body and the loss of biodiversity, reducing pesticide use should have long been a national priority.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Continuous and indiscriminate use of chemical fertilizers has led to several harmful effects on the soil environment, ground and surface water reducing the productivity of soil by affecting soil health in terms of physical, chemical, and biological properties.</li>
<li>The excess/indiscriminate use of pesticides has led to the harmful compounds into food chain, death of natural enemies and development of resistance to pesticides.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Fertilizer</strong>?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Fertilizers are substances that provide one or more of the chemicals required for plant growth. Fertilizers can be both organic and inorganic.</li>
<li>Mixed fertilizers contain more than one of the three major nutrients nitrogen, phosphorus, and potassium.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="chemical fertilizers" class="alignnone wp-image-642776 size-full" height="528" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.15.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.15.jpeg 1280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.15-300x124.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.15-1024x422.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.15-768x317.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.15-1200x495.jpeg 1200w" width="1280"/>What are the consequences of misuse of fertilizers?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Soil Health: </strong>Excessive use of chemical fertilizers kills all the microorganisms available in the soil, which are so essential for maintaining soil health.</li>
<li><strong>Water pollution: </strong>Water pollutionfrom fertilizer runoff, which has a sphere of impact that extends far beyond the farmer and the fields. They get washed away by water easily and cause pollution.</li>
<li><strong>Release Greenhouse gases</strong>: Leads to the release of harmful greenhouse gases into the atmosphere and the eutrophication of our waterways.</li>
<li><strong>Impact on Health:</strong> Depending on the amount of fertilizer consumed, it may cause disturbances of the kidneys, lungs and liver and even cause cancer.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the status of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/fertilizer-sector-of-india/">Fertilizer usage in India</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The main products manufactured by the fertilizer industry in India are phosphate based fertilizers nitrogenous fertilizers, and complex fertilizers.</li>
<li>The ratio of N:P:K (Nitrogen :Phosphorus: Potassium)  which is ideally should be 4:2:1,stands at 8.2:3.2:1,overuse of urea has lead to many ecological problems.</li>
<li>States like Andhra Pradesh, Tamil Nadu, Punjab and Haryana use chemical fertilizers more than 200kgs/hectare whereas North eastern states use less than 10kg/hectare.</li>
<li>A lot of urea meant for agricultural usage is diverted to industrial use in via black market.65%of farmers in Uttar Pradesh purchase urea from black market.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="chemical fertilizers" class="alignnone wp-image-642774 size-full" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 954px) 100vw, 954px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.13.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.13.jpeg 954w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.13-300x122.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-07.10.13-768x312.jpeg 768w" width="954"/>What are the reasons behind the misuse of Fertilizers in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of knowledge: </strong>Lack of knowledge leading to indiscriminate usage of fertilizers and pesticides in a hope of better yields.</li>
<li><strong>Profit oriented Business model:</strong> In India, shopkeepers sell farm chemical inputs from multiple companies, and their business model like any other business rewards shopkeepers with higher margins for increasing sales. Shopkeepers also nudge farmers to buy what they may not necessarily need.</li>
<li><strong>Not affordable Technology: </strong>Individual farmers cannot afford good quality precision spraying equipment and that leads to wrong application and excess usage.</li>
<li><strong>Becoming a more Contracted service:</strong> 10 per cent of farm chemical input sales of each seller could be in the form of services (spray on farms). Each following year, the seller would mandatorily increase the services by an additional 10 per cent, till the business model had become one of the services contracted, and not of farm chemical inputs sold.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of transparency and accountability:</strong> The lack of real-time quality data inhibits transparency and accountability, making the reduction of chemical use difficult.</li>
<li><strong>Administrative loophole:</strong> A basic principle of law states that regulators should be independent. Alarmingly, in the case of agricultural chemical inputs, the same authorities and departments that advocate their use also regulate the trade.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="chemical fertilizers" class="alignnone wp-image-642777 size-full" height="675" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.26.43.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.26.43.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.26.43-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.26.43-1024x576.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-06.26.43-768x432.jpeg 768w" width="1200"/>What can be done to stop misuse of Fertilizers?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Adopting Service oriented business model: </strong>The business model of the farm chemical input industry must transform to become a service industry<strong>. </strong>For instance A Syngenta franchise sells its brand of farm chemicals. It also served for field spraying, ensuring low input application</li>
<li><strong>Precision spraying equipment: </strong>Assistance in getting good quality precision spraying equipment as individual farmers can’t afford.</li>
<li><strong>Better advisory and awareness:</strong> Infrastructure should be developed for better targeted farm advisory and grievance redressal. In addition awareness and knowledge centers should be developed.</li>
<li><strong>Regulated sale:</strong> Shopkeepers should report each sale of farm chemicals to the government in real time</li>
<li><strong>Need to shift our focus to Bio-fertilizers: </strong>Bio-fertilizers are cheap, renewable, and eco-friendly, with great potential to supplement plant nutrients.</li>
<li><strong>Improve fertilizer efficiency:</strong> India should pay attention to improving fertilizer efficiency through need-based use rather than broadcasting fertilizer in the field. The recently developed Nano urea by IFFCO shows promising results in reducing the usage of urea.</li>
<li><strong>Example of</strong> M<strong>andatory QR code:</strong> A mandatory QR code on each farm chemical package for instance. Bayer, the world’s largest seed and pesticide company has started to print a QR code on every pesticide package which will allow each farm input package used on the farm to be traceable to the factory floor.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>During the past several decades, agricultural development mainly focused on on short term gains in productivity and profitability, which has Caused severe damage to soil fertility, health and environment ears.</li>
<li>It is the need of the hour to understand the problems and find alternatives that can sustain the environment and feed the growing population.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.While technology induction is required for feeding the surging population, the excessive use of chemical fertilizers caused environmental imbalance and causing problems to all human being on the earth .In this context Discuss the alternatives to chemical</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fertilizers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Elderly care:Treating elderly with respect</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/elderly/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<h4><strong><img alt="elderly" class="alignnone wp-image-642786 size-full" height="583" sizes="(max-width: 1026px) 100vw, 1026px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.15.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.15.jpeg 1026w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.15-300x170.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.15-1024x582.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.15-768x436.jpeg 768w" width="1026"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The United Nations marks the International Day for Older Persons(October 1), as part of the organisation’s efforts to draw attention to healthy ageing.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>International Day for Older Persons</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>On 14 December 1990, the United Nations General Assembly designated 1 October the International Day of Older Persons.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="elderly" class="alignnone wp-image-642787 size-large" height="530" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.03-1024x530.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.03-1024x530.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.03-300x155.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.03-768x398.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.03-1200x622.jpeg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.03.jpeg 1280w" width="1024"/>What are the Statistics?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>According to UNDESA: </strong>Recently, a report by the UN Department of Economic and Social Affairs (UNDESA), World Population Prospects 2022, has projected big shifts in global demographic patterns in the coming decades.</li>
<li><strong>Worldwide population: </strong>As global birth rates stabilise and shrink, 16%of the world population by 2050 is expected to be made up of people over 65 years. India will be home to the largest population in the world which would include a large elderly sub-population.</li>
<li><strong>Status in India: </strong>The report projects India’s population to be 1.7 billion by2050, having overtaken China to be the world’s most populous country. Eight countries India is among them will account for more than half o fthe world’s increasing population by 2050.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="elderly" class="alignnone wp-image-642791 size-large" height="539" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.13-1024x539.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.13-1024x539.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.13-300x158.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.13-768x404.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-10.29.13.jpeg 1154w" width="1024"/>Why the elderly are vulnerable? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Non-communicable diseases: </strong>India’s elderly population will double to be nearly 20% of the total population by 2050. The prevalence of non-communicable diseases such as diabetes, hypertension and heart disease, or disabilities related to vision, hearing or mobility is higher among the elderly.</li>
<li><strong>Crumbling public health system</strong>: The change in demographic structure will increase the pressure on public health systems that are not geared to deliver universal health care along with social security measures such as old-age and disability pensions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Eye care model for elderly?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>HOMES: </strong>The Hyderabad Ocular Morbidity in the Elderly Study (HOMES) by the L.V. Prasad Eye Institute has been producing a series of systematic reports on various aspects of health, quality of life, mental health, morbidity, and disability amongst the elderly living in homes for the aged in Hyderabad, Telangana<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Eye care service</strong>: Delivery is uniquely placed to be the first point-of-contact with the elderly and to also help with health surveillance and planning.</li>
<li><strong>First detection: </strong>Using eye care as a point of entry, the study has been measuring a variety of health and social metrics in over 1,000participants (all aged over 60), spread across a range of socio-economic circumstances.</li>
<li><strong>Co-morbidities: </strong>Over30% of the elderly in the study had distance vision loss and over 50% had near vision impairment (they needed reading glasses). Nearly half the participants had at least one disability and a third of them had multiple morbidities. About 70% of them were using at least one assistive device, spectacles being the most common.</li>
<li><strong>Mental health: </strong>The study also explored the many links between vision impairment and an elderly person’s mental health and confidence. People with impaired vision had a greater fear, and risk of falling (a major cause of disability and hospitalisation among the elderly). This reduced their movement and independence, leading to depression. Addressing their vision impairment improved lives.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="elderly" class="alignnone wp-image-642794 size-full" height="456" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1167px) 100vw, 1167px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-12.35.55.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-12.35.55.jpeg 1167w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-12.35.55-300x117.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-12.35.55-1024x400.jpeg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/WhatsApp-Image-2022-10-01-at-12.35.55-768x300.jpeg 768w" width="1167"/>What should be the approach for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/old-age/">treating the elderly</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multiple Diagnosis: </strong>The way forward can then be a package of interventions, including assistive devices for sight, hearing, and mobility, or referrals to psychiatric support for depression or the mental health issues.</li>
<li><strong>Template to replicate</strong>: In this way, eye care can catalyse a model of elderly care that will help us recalibrate our approach to this changing world. Most eye conditions typically affect those who are very young or the elderly age groups that are dependent on others for health access.</li>
<li><strong>Primary health care</strong>: The Indian eye care model has always prioritised primary care ‘vision’ centres, bringing care closer to those in need. Chronic conditions such as diabetes and hypertension lead to irreversible vision loss and so, the sector has been building referral networks connecting with other health specialities.</li>
<li><strong>Portable devices</strong>: Eye care has also been at the cutting edge of imaging technologies and tele-health, creating portable devices and apps that remove access issues for those who cannot travel far. Crucially, eye health in India has many cross-subsidy models to help alleviate the financial burden on individuals.</li>
<li><strong>Long the approach:</strong>This set of experiences and expertise has put eye care in a unique position to help us navigate the transition to an ageing society. The future of elderly care needs to be long term, comprehensive, and integrated, and must be oriented towards primary care to be accessible.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Whatever model we devise for elderly care, it must account for all kinds of socio-economic realities, working to ensure that no elderly person is denied care irrespective of their financial status.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Medical treatment of non-working population with non-communicable disease (elderly), is crucial for healthy aging. Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/elderly/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>