<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 19:11:35 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>SC seeks Centre’s reply on issue of Marital Rape</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-seeks-centres-reply-on-marital-rape/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Persistence of marital rape and need for its criminalization</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has sought a response from the government on appeals to criminalize marital rape.</p>
<h4><strong>Split opinions on Marital Rape</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="rape" class="alignnone wp-image-637177" height="465" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 346px) 100vw, 346px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rape-223x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rape-223x300.jpg 223w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rape.jpg 595w" width="346"/></p>
<ul>
<li>This follows a split decision from the Delhi High Court on whether or not to prosecute husbands for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/criminalizing-marital-rape-in-india/">non-consensual </a>intercourse with their wives.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Marital Rape?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Marital rape is the act of sexual intercourse with one’s spouse without her consent.</li>
<li>It is no different manifestation of domestic violence and sexual abuse.</li>
<li>It is often a chronic form of violence for the victim which takes place within abusive relations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Status in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Historically considered as right of the spouses, this is now widely classified as rape by many societies around the world.</li>
<li>In India, marital rape is not a criminal offense (as protected under IPC section 375).</li>
<li>India is one of fifty countries that have not yet outlawed marital rape.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reasons for disapproval of this concept</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The reluctance to define non-consensual sex between married couples as a crime and to prosecute has been attributed to:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Traditional views of marriage</li>
<li>Interpretations of religious doctrines</li>
<li>Ideas about male and female sexuality</li>
<li>Cultural expectations of subordination of a wife to her husband</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>It is widely held that a husband cannot be guilty of any sexual act committed by himself upon his lawful wife their on account of their mutual matrimonial consent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why it must be a crime?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Associated physical violence:</strong> Rape by a spouse, partner or ex-partner is more often associated with physical violence.</li>
<li><strong>Mental harassment:</strong> There is research showing that marital rape can be more emotionally and physically damaging than rape by a stranger.</li>
<li><strong>Compulsive relationship:</strong> Marital rape may occur as part of an abusive relationship.</li>
<li><strong>Revengeful nature:</strong> Furthermore, marital rape is rarely a one-time event, but a repeated if not frequent occurrence.</li>
<li><strong>Obligation on women:</strong> In the case of marital rape the victim often has no choice but to continue living with their spouse.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Violation of fundamental rights</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Marital rape is considered as the violation of FR guaranteed under <u>Article 14</u> of the Indian constitution which guarantees the equal protection of laws to all persons.</li>
<li>By depriving married women of an effective penal remedy against forced sexual intercourse, it violates their right to privacy and bodily integrity, aspects of the right to life and personal liberty under <u>Article 21</u>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Problems in prosecuting marital rape</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of awareness:</strong> A lack of public awareness, as well as reluctance or outright refusal of authorities to prosecute, is common globally.</li>
<li><strong>Gender norms:</strong> Additionally, gender norms that place wives in subservient positions to their husbands, make it more difficult for women to recognize such rape.</li>
<li><strong>Acceptability of the concept:</strong> Another problem results from prevailing social norms that exist.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Present regulations in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian Penal Code criminalizes rape in most cases, although marital rape is not illegal when the woman is over the age of 18.</li>
<li>However, until 2017, men married to those between 15 and 18 could not be convicted of rape.</li>
<li>Marital rape of an adult wife, who is unofficially or officially separated, is a criminal offence punishable by 2 to 7 year in prison; it is not dealt by normal rape laws which stipulate the possibility of a death sentence.</li>
<li>According to the Protection of Women From Domestic Violence Act (2005), other married women subject to such crime by their husband may demand for financial compensation.</li>
<li>They also have the right to continue to live in their marital household if they wish, or may approach shelter or aid homes.</li>
</ul>
<p>However, marital rape is still not a criminal offence in this case and is only a misdemeanor.</p>
<h4><strong>Arguments against criminalization</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Subjective:</strong> It is very subjective and intricate to determine whether consent was acquired or not.</li>
<li><strong>Prone to Misuse</strong>: If marital rape is criminalized without adequate safeguards it could be misused like the current dowry law by the dissatisfied wives to harass and torture their Husbands.</li>
<li><strong>Burden on Judiciary</strong>: It will increase the burden of judiciary which otherwise may serve other more important causes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sanctioning marital rape is an acknowledgment of the woman’s right to self-determination (i.e., control) of all matters relating to her body.</li>
<li>In the absence of any concrete law, the judiciary always finds it difficult to decide the matter of domestic rape in the absence of solid evidence.</li>
<li>The main purpose of marriage is procreation, and sometimes divorce is sought on the ground of non-consummation of marriage.</li>
<li>Before giving a final interpretation, the judiciary must balance the rights and duties of both partners.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-seeks-centres-reply-on-marital-rape/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How lower fertility rate hampers demographic dividend in number of ways</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fertility-rate/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>human population</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="fertility rate" class="alignnone wp-image-637033" height="467" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 623px) 100vw, 623px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives.jpg 1200w" width="623"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Though the Global population, in terms of numbers, has been steadily increasing the average global fertility rate has been consistently declining over the past 70 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What Reports say?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Reports suggest that the global population could grow to around 8.5 billion in 2030.</li>
<li>According to the World Population Prospects 2022, Average number of children per woman in the reproductive age group has declined by 50%, from an average of five children per woman in 1951 to4 children in 2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Fertility?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fertility is the quality or state of being fertile<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>Fertility is the ability to reproduce through normal sexual interaction. In other words it is the natural capacity to conceive a biological child.</li>
<li>Fertilitychanges with age. Both males and females become fertile in their teens following puberty.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fertility rate" class="alignnone wp-image-637034" height="343" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 571px) 100vw, 571px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/e_440_x_264_14_2034043615--300x180.png" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/e_440_x_264_14_2034043615--300x180.png 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/e_440_x_264_14_2034043615-.png 440w" width="571"/> What is fertility rate?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The number of live births in women over a specific length of time.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/replacement-level-fertility-achieved-in-india/">Total fertility rate</a> is the average number of children born to a woman during her lifetime.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Recent findings</strong></h4>
<p>The newly released World Population Prospectus notes that the global fertility rate fell from three in 1990 to 2.3 in 2021.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Overview of fertility dynamics </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reason: </strong>Speeding up the social phenomenon of demographic transition.</li>
<li><strong>Poorer countries:</strong> speeding up the Transition a lot faster than the richer ones.</li>
<li><strong>Britain</strong>: Took 130 years to transition from a fertility rate of five per woman in 1800 to two in 1930, whereas</li>
<li><strong>South Korea: </strong>Took 20 years from 1965 to 1985 to achieve the same. South Korea reporting the lowest fertility rate, 1.05 children per woman.</li>
<li><strong>Most advanced economies</strong>: Have their fertility rate below the replacement rate of 2.1.</li>
<li><strong>Sub-Saharan African countries</strong>: Expected to contribute more than half the population growth after 2050 and grow through 2100. For example, Niger a sub Saharan country with highest fertility rate in the world, estimated to be 91 children per woman.</li>
<li><strong>What is Demographic transition</strong>: is a long-term trend of declining birth and death rate. It is shift from high birth rates to low birth rates in societies with minimal technology, education (especially of women) and economic development and from high death rates to Low death rates in societies with advanced economies and development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fertility rate" class="alignnone wp-image-637036" height="391" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 587px) 100vw, 587px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/shutterstock_-india-population-93427363-1-16577155543x2-1-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/shutterstock_-india-population-93427363-1-16577155543x2-1-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/shutterstock_-india-population-93427363-1-16577155543x2-1.jpeg 510w" width="587"/><br/>
Where India Stands</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to National Family Health Survey (NFHS), fertility rate falling below the replacement level for the first time to 2.0 in 2021.dropped from 2.2 to 2.0.</li>
<li>only five States have a fertility rate above the replacement rate: Bihar (3), Meghalaya (2.9), Uttar Pradesh (2.4), Jharkhand (2.3), and Manipur (2.2)</li>
<li>At the time of Independence, India’s fertility rate was six per woman, and it had taken 25 years to reach five, with the government launching the first ever family planning program in the world in 1952.</li>
<li>India’s fertility further declined to four in the 1990s when Kerala became the first State in India to have a fertility rate below replacement l</li>
<li>Increased use of contraception, more years of average schooling, better health care, and an increase in the mean marriage age of women are of the reasons behind the steady dip in fertility rate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Lower fertility rate as cause and consequences on the economy</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Positive impact:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Lower fertility leads to rise in women’s education.</li>
<li>Window of time where the ration of working-age population is higher than that of the dependent age groups.</li>
<li>This high proportion of people in the workforce boosts income and investment, and higher level of saving.</li>
<li>Lower pressure on land, water and other resources and would also contribute to achieving environmental goals.</li>
<li>Advanced health care and better nutrition, results in increased life expectancy and productivity of citizens.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>Negative impact:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Lower fertility impacts women’s education positively, which in turn lowers the fertility of the next generations.</li>
<li>While the income rises with better health care and better infrastructure development, Fertility drops.</li>
<li>A fall in fertility rate beyond replacement level would have a negative effect on the proportion of the working population, which in turn will affect output in an economy.</li>
<li>After the window of demographic dividend, the huge working age population moves to old age, supported by fewer workers.</li>
<li>Japan was the first country to experience the implications of falling fertility rates. Country is now facing fiscal challenges to meet rising social security costs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Experiments to deal with fertility decline</strong></h4>
<p>Countries across the globe are experimenting with policies to boost fertility.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Germany: </strong>found success in boosting births through liberal labour laws, allowing more parental leave and benefits.</li>
<li><strong>Denmark</strong>: offering state-funded IVF for women below 40 years</li>
<li><strong>Hungary</strong>: Recently nationalized IVF clinics.</li>
<li><strong>Poland</strong>: Gives out monthly cash payments to parents having more than two children</li>
<li><strong>Russia</strong>: Makes one-time payment to parents when their second child is born. Reinstituted the Soviet-era ‘Mother Heroine’ title, who bore and raised more than 10 children amounting to almost a one-time payment of 13 lakh<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Way ahead </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Need of the hour is to ensure liberal labor reforms, encourage higher female labor force participation, higher focus on nutrition and health.</li>
<li>Although India’s working age population will continue to grow for many more decades, it would need to keep an eye on fertility dips.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>What are Implications of lower fertility rate on the economy? What steps could be taken to deal with fertility decline? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><u><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></u></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fertility-rate/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>RBI’s attempt to manage currency could prove to be a costly mistake</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/currency/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Impossible trinity</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>RBI functions</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="currency" class="alignnone wp-image-637056" height="294" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 522px) 100vw, 522px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560.jpg 1600w" width="522"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A currency defence will also impose costs on the economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Legally, the Reserve Bank of India is mandated to target an inflation rate. But with the global economic environment taking a turn for the worse, the central bank has also been targeting the exchange rate. This could prove to be a costly mistake.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a simple definition for inflation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Inflation is the rate of increase in prices over a given period of time. Inflation is typically a broad measure, such as the overall increase in prices or the increase in the cost of living in a country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is exchange rate?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An exchange rate is a rate at which one currency will be exchanged for another currency. Most exchange rates are defined as floating and will rise or fall based on the supply and demand in the market. Some exchange rates are pegged or fixed to the value of a specific country’s currency.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is monetary policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Monetary policy is the control of the quantity of money available in an economy and the channels by which new money is supplied. Economic statistics such as gross domestic product (GDP), the rate of inflation, and industry and sector-specific growth rates influence monetary policy strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is fixed exchange rate in simple words?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A fixed exchange rate is a regime applied by a government or central bank that ties the country’s official currency exchange rate to another country’s currency or the price of gold. The purpose of a fixed exchange rate system is to keep a currency’s value within a narrow band.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="currency" class="alignnone wp-image-637058" height="346" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 519px) 100vw, 519px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dollar-kS6F-621x414%40LiveMint-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dollar-kS6F-621x414%40LiveMint-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dollar-kS6F-621x414%40LiveMint.jpg 621w" width="519"/>What is a simple definition of capital?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Capital is a broad term that can describe anything that confers value or benefit to its owners, such as a factory and its machinery, intellectual property like patents, or the financial assets of a business or an individual.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is meant by the impossible trinity?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Many economists think of possible policy responses to capital flows in terms of the so-called “impossible trinity,” or “policy trilemma”, according to which, with an open capital account, a central bank cannot simultaneously exercise monetary control and target the exchange rate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>A currency defence will impose costs on the economy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Little economic gain</strong>: Some may believe that a stronger currency gives the impression of economic stability and generates confidence in the economy. But there is an inherent contradiction between artificially propping up the rupee and the country’s growth prospects. Very little economic gain will accrue from turning the currency’s value into a political issue.</li>
<li><strong>Inflation should be tackled through monetary policy</strong>: Understandably, a depreciating currency leads to concerns over higher imported inflation. But inflation should be tackled through monetary policy, while exchange rate management should be linked to growth. Not the other way around.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Significance of currency defence for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-global-trade-in-rupees/">foreign exchange reserves</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Decline by 10 per cent:</strong> A large part of the current relative strength of the rupee vis-à-vis other currencies is due to the sale of dollars by the RBI  it has lost more than 10 per cent of its foreign reserves in the space of about nine months.</li>
<li><strong>Why country needs foreign exchange:</strong> A developing economy needs foreign exchange to finance its international transactions for both the current account (goods and services) and capital account (assets) transactions.</li>
<li><strong>Cost involved:</strong> The benefits of this stock are obvious, but there are also costs associated with the holding of these.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong><img alt="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-global-trade-in-rupees/" class="alignnone wp-image-637059" height="340" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 603px) 100vw, 603px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131.jpg 1600w" width="603"/>We should follow Tenfold Path to manage Exchange Rate Volatility rather monetary policy path</strong></h4>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong><u>(1) Selling dollars</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The first course of action has been selling dollars in the spot forex market.</li>
<li>This is fairly straightforward, but has limits as all crises are associated with declining reserves.</li>
<li>While this money is meant for a rainy day, they may just be less than adequate.</li>
<li>The idea of RBI selling dollars works well in the currency market, which is kept guessing how much the central bank is willing to sell at any point of time.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(2) NRI deposits</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The second tool used is aimed at garnering non-resident Indian (NRI) deposits.</li>
<li>It was done in 1998 and 2000 through Resurgent India bonds and India Millennium Deposits, when banks reached out asking NRIs to put in money with attractive interest rates.</li>
<li>The forex risk was borne by Indian banks.</li>
<li>This is always a useful way for the country to mobilize a good sum of forex, though the challenge is when the debt has to be redeemed.</li>
<li>At the time of deposits, the rates tend to be attractive, but once the crisis ends, the same rate cannot be offered on deposit renewals.</li>
<li>Therefore, the idea has limitations.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(3) Let oil importers buy dollars themselves</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The third option exercised often involves getting oil importing companies to buy dollars directly through a facility extended by a public sector bank.</li>
<li>Its advantage is that these deals are not in the open and so the market does not witness a large demand for dollars on this account.</li>
<li>It is more of a sentiment cooling exercise.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(4) Let exporters trade in dollars</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Another tool involves a directive issued for all exporters to mandatorily bring in their dollars on receipt that are needed for future imports.</li>
<li>This acts against an artificial dollar supply reduction due to exporter hold-backs for profit.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(5) Liberalized Exchange Rate</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The other weapon, once used earlier, is to curb the amount of dollars one can take under the Liberalized Exchange Rate Management System.</li>
<li>This can be for current account purposes like travel, education, healthcare, etc.</li>
<li>The amounts are not large, but it sends out a strong signal.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(6) Forward-trade marketing</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Another route used by RBI is to deal in the forward-trade market.</li>
<li>Its advantage is that a strong signal is sent while controlling volatility, as RBI conducts transactions where only the net amount gets transacted finally.</li>
<li>It has the same power as spot transactions, but without any significant withdrawal of forex from the system.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(7) Currency swaps</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The other tool in India’s armoury is the concept of swaps.</li>
<li>This became popular post 2013, when banks collected foreign currency non-resident deposits with a simultaneous swap with RBI, which in effect took on the foreign exchange risk.</li>
<li>Hence, it was different from earlier bond and deposit schemes.</li>
<li><strong>Most preferred options by the RBI</strong></li>
<li>Above discussed instruments have been largely direct in nature, with the underlying factors behind demand-supply being managed by the central bank.</li>
<li>Of late, RBI has gone in for more policy-oriented approaches and the last three measures announced are in this realm.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(8) Allowing banks to work in the NDF market</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>First was allowing banks to work in the non-deliverable forwards (NDF) market.</li>
<li>This is a largely overseas speculative market that has a high potential to influence domestic sentiment on our currency.</li>
<li>Here, forward transactions take place without real inflows or outflows, with only price differences settled in dollars.</li>
<li>This was a major pain point in the past, as banks did not have access to this segment.</li>
<li>By permitting Indian banks to operate here, the rates in this market and in domestic markets have gotten equalized.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(9) Capital account for NRI deposits</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>More recently, RBI opened up the capital account on NRI deposits (interest rates than can be offered), external commercial borrowings (amounts that can be raised) and foreign portfolio investments (allowed in lower tenure securities), which has the potential to draw in forex over time.</li>
<li>Interest in these expanded contours may be limited, but the idea is compelling.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(10) Settlement in Rupees</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>RBI’s permission for foreign trade deals to be settled in rupees is quite novel; as India is a net importer, gains can be made if we pay in rupees for imports.</li>
<li>The conditions placed on the use of surpluses could be a dampener for potential transactions.</li>
<li>But the idea is innovative and could also be a step towards taking the rupee international in such a delicate situation.</li>
<li>Clearly, RBI has constantly been exploring ways to address our forex troubles and even newer measures shouldn’t surprise us.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The RBI (which is in charge of monetary policy) should focus on containing inflation, as it is legally mandated to do.</li>
<li>The government (which is in charge of the fiscal policy) should contain its borrowings.</li>
<li>Higher borrowings (fiscal deficit) by the government eat up domestic savings and force the rest of the economic agents to borrow from abroad.</li>
<li>Policymakers (both in the government and the RBI) have to choose what their priority is containing inflation or being hung up on exchange rate and forex levels.</li>
<li>If they choose to contain inflation (that is, by raising interest rates) then it will require sacrificing economic growth. So be prepared for that.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.What do you understand by the term impossible trinity? How should RBI respond to manage currency exchange rate? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/currency/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>100 years of periyar because of whom tamil nadu became modern and progressive</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/periyar/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Vaikom satyagraha</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Social reform movement in tamil nadu</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Periyar" class="alignnone wp-image-637096" height="439" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 439px) 100vw, 439px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/71pQGUTHWKL._AC_SS450_-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/71pQGUTHWKL._AC_SS450_-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/71pQGUTHWKL._AC_SS450_-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/71pQGUTHWKL._AC_SS450_.jpg 450w" width="439"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>We celebrate Periyar E.V. Ramasamy’s birth anniversary (September 17) as Social Justice Day.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who is periyar?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Erode Venkatappa Ramasamy, revered as Periyar or Thanthai Periyar, was an Indian social activist and politician who started the Self-Respect Movement and Dravidar Kazhagam. He is known as the ‘Father of the Dravidian movement’. He rebelled against Brahminical dominance and gender and caste inequality in Tamil Nadu.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who started self-respect movement?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The self-respect movement was founded by V.Ramaswamy Naicker, commonly known as Periyar. It was a dynamic social movement aimed at destroying the contemporary Hindu social order in its totality and creating a new, rational society without caste, religion and god.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Periyar" class="alignnone wp-image-637097" height="644" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unnamed-200x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unnamed-200x300.jpg 200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unnamed.jpg 341w" width="429"/>Why Periyar is called as vaikom hero?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>V. Ramasamy Periyar led the famous <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/op-ed-snap-periyar-the-hero-of-vaikom/">Vaikom Sathya Graha</a> in 1924, where the people of down trodden community were prohibited to enter into the temple. Finally the Travancore government relaxed such segregation and allowed the people to enter into the temple. Hence periyar was given the title of ‘Vaikom Hero’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Leadership at a critical juncture</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The satyagraha began with the active support of the Kerala Pradesh Congress Committee.</li>
<li>Within a week all its leaders were behind bars. George Joseph sought directions from Gandhi and C. Rajagopalachari. He also wrote to Periyar pleading with him to lead the satyagraha.</li>
<li>Periyar was in the midst of political work. As he was then the president of the Tamil Nadu Congress Committee, Periyar handed over temporary charge to Rajaji before reaching Vaikom in 1924.</li>
<li>From that date to the day of the victory celebrations in 1925, he was in the struggle giving it leadership at a critical juncture.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Periyar" class="alignnone wp-image-637099" height="809" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 539px) 100vw, 539px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-200x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-200x300.jpg 200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-600x900.jpg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-1200x1800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-scaled.jpg 1707w" width="539"/>Periyar’s role</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Against violence</strong> – Periyar presided over the satyagraha in the face of violence and indignity inflicted by the orthodox and the repression of the police.</li>
<li><strong>Mobilising </strong>– To mobilise support, he visited villages in and around Vaikom and delivered public speeches in several towns.</li>
<li><strong>Gandhi </strong>– When the Kerala leaders asked for Gandhi’s permission to make the satyagraha an all-India affair, Gandhi refused saying that volunteers from Tamil Nadu would keep it alive.</li>
<li><strong>In reports</strong> – the British Resident said in his report to the government of Madras: “In fact, the movement would have collapsed long ago but for the support it has received from outside Travancore…”</li>
<li><strong>Historian T.K. Ravindran</strong> — observes that Periyar’s arrival gave “a new life to the movement”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>His Vision for the future</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Ideas on rationality</strong>: When he presented his thoughts, there was nuance, honesty, and an explicitness, which prompted even people practising different faiths to discuss and debate his ideas on rationality and religion.</li>
<li><strong>Freedom of expression</strong>: Periyar himself said, “Everyone has the right to refute any opinion. But no one has the right to prevent its expression.”</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Eradication of social evils</strong>: Periyar is often referred to as an iconoclast, for the rebellious nature of his ideas and the vigour with which he acted. His vision for the future was a part of all his actions. He did not merely aim at the eradication of social evils; he also wanted to put an end to activities that do not collectively raise standards of society.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-637101" height="424" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 761px) 100vw, 761px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ramasamy-periyar-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ramasamy-periyar-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ramasamy-periyar.jpg 759w" width="761"/>Foundation of rationalism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>He understood the evolution of political thought</strong>: Periyar’s vision was about inclusive growth and freedom of individuals. He was an important ideologue of his day because of the clarity in his political stand. More importantly, he understood the evolution of political thought and was able to glide through time with this.</li>
<li><strong>He presented rationalism as a solid foundation:</strong> For thinking along these lines. He said, “Wisdom lies in thinking. The spearhead of thinking is rationalism.” Periyar was way ahead of his time.</li>
<li><strong>Concern towards poor</strong>: “Whomsoever I love and hate, my principle is the same. That is, the educated, the rich and the administrators should not suck the blood of the poor.”</li>
<li><strong>Periyar proclaimed that he would always stand with the oppressed: </strong>In the fight against oppressors and that his enemy was oppression. There have been several social reformers in Tamil Nadu who shared their revolutionary thoughts with the people in the past century. In that spectrum, Periyar occupies a unique place because he made interactions of multiple worlds possible.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em>Periyar said, “Any opposition not based on rationalism or science or experience, will one day or other, reveal the fraud, selfishness, lies, and conspiracies.”</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>His works against the Bhraminical dominance, oppression of women in Tamil Nadu, caste prevalence are exemplary. Periyar promoted the principles of rationalism, self-respect, women’s rights and eradication of caste. He opposed the exploitation and marginalisation of the people of South India and the imposition of what he considered Indo-Aryan India.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Discuss the future vision of periyar by discussing his role in vaikom satyagraha. Do you think he has placed foundation of rationalism in Tamil Nadu?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><u><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></u></strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/periyar/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What are Entangled Atomic Clocks?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-entangled-atomic-clocks/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Atomic clocks</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-637687" height="233" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 376px) 100vw, 376px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atomic-clock-300x186.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atomic-clock-300x186.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atomic-clock-768x475.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atomic-clock.jpg 847w" width="376"/></strong></p>
<p>For the first time, scientists at the University of Oxford have been able to demonstrate a network of two entangled optical atomic clocks.</p>
<blockquote><p>Trending in news this year is the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-certification-of-quantum-entanglement/">Quantum Technology</a>, (As it used to be until last year were- the Internet of Things (IoT) CSP 2019, Artificial Intelligence (AI) etc.)</p>
<p>Must read all this news in a loop:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-national-mission-on-quantum-technologies-applications/">National Mission on QC</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-quantum-coin-or-qubit-and-entanglement-theory/">Quantum Coin</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-what-is-quantum-supremacy-claimed-by-google/">Quantum Supremacy</a></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The high-precision atomic clocks and quantum entanglement have been achieved altogether.</li>
<li>This means the inherent uncertainty in measuring their frequencies simultaneously is highly reduced.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Atomic Clocks?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An atomic clock is a clock that uses the resonance frequencies of atoms as its resonator.</li>
<li>Cesium is incredibly accurate at timekeeping and is used in atomic clocks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Fundamental limit of precision through entanglement<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Entanglement is a quantum phenomenon in which two or more particles become linked together so that they can no longer be described independently, even at vast distances.</li>
<li>This is the key to reaching the fundamental limit of precision that’s determined by quantum theory.</li>
<li>Previous experiments have demonstrated that entanglement between two atomic clocks in the same system can be used to improve the quality of measurements.</li>
<li>This is the first time researchers have been able to achieve this between clocks in two separate remotely entangled systems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why do we use clocks to navigate in space?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To determine a spacecraft’s distance from Earth, navigators send a signal to the spacecraft, which then returns it to Earth.</li>
<li>The time the signal requires to make that two-way journey reveals the spacecraft’s distance from Earth, because the signal travels at a known speed (the speed of light).</li>
<li>While it may sound complicated, most of us use this concept every day. The grocery store might be a 30-minute walk from your house.</li>
<li>If you know you can walk about a mile in 20 minutes, then you can calculate the distance to the store.</li>
<li>By sending multiple signals and taking many measurements over time, navigators can calculate a spacecraft’s trajectory: where it is and where it’s headed.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need atomic clocks?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To know the spacecraft’s position within a meter, navigators’ need clocks with precision time resolution — clocks that can measure billionths of a second.</li>
<li>Navigators also need clocks that are extremely stable<em>.</em></li>
<li>Stability refers to how consistently a clock measures a unit of time; its measurement of the length of a second, for example, needs to be the same (to better than a billionth of a second) over days and weeks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is an oscillator in a clock?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Most modern clocks, from wristwatches to those used on satellites, keep time using a quartz crystal oscillator.</li>
<li>These devices take advantage of the fact that quartz crystals vibrate at a precise frequency when voltage is applied to them.</li>
<li>The vibrations of the crystal act like the pendulum of a grandfather clock, ticking off how much time has passed.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What do atoms have to do with clocks?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>By space navigation standards, quartz crystal clocks aren’t very stable.</li>
<li>After only an hour, even the best-performing quartz oscillators can be off by a nanosecond (one billionth of a second).</li>
<li>After six weeks, they may be off by a full millisecond (one thousandth of a second), or a distance error of 185 miles (300 kilometers).</li>
<li>That would have a huge impact on measuring the position of a fast-moving spacecraft.</li>
<li>Atomic clocks combine a quartz crystal oscillator with an ensemble of atoms to achieve greater stability.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-entangled-atomic-clocks/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How Hyderabad became a part of India?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hyderabad-how-became-a-part-of-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Hyderabad's accession into India</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Post-independence consolidation</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-637690" height="291" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 462px) 100vw, 462px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hyd-300x189.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hyd-300x189.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hyd.jpg 741w" width="462"/></p>
<p>The Government of India began its year-long celebrations for the ‘Telangana Liberation Day’ on September 17, marking how on the same day in 1948, the state of Hyderabad got its independence from Nizam’s rule, as said in a press release.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>From 1911 to 1948, Nizam Mir Usman Ali, the last Nizam of Hyderabad, ruled the state composed of Telangana and parts of present-day Karnataka and Maharashtra (Marathwada).</li>
<li>While these states mark the Liberation Day officially, Telangana has never done so.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Hyderabad’s accession into India: A backgrounder</h4>
<p><strong>(1) Reluctance of Nizam</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>At the time of India’s independence, British India was a mix of independent kingdoms and provinces that were given the options of joining India, Pakistan, or remaining independent.</li>
<li>One among those who took a long time to make a decision was the Nizam of Hyderabad.</li>
<li>Believed to be one of the richest people in the world at the time, the Nizam was not ready to let go of his kingdom.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Sufferings for the people</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Meanwhile, the majority population of Hyderabad state was far from enjoying the same kind of wealth as the Nizam did.</li>
<li>The feudal nature of the state at the time caused the peasant population to suffer high taxes, indignities of forced labour, and various other kinds of exploitation at the hands of powerful landlords.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Lingual friction</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There was also a demand by the Andhra Jan Sangham for Telugu to be given primacy over Urdu.</li>
<li>By the mid-1930s, apart from a reduction in land revenue rates and the abolition of forced labour, introducing Telugu in local courts became another important issue.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Mass movement</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Soon after the organisation became the Andhra Mahasabha (AMS), and Communists became associated with it.</li>
<li>Together, the two groups built a peasant movement against the Nizam that found local support.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who were the Razakars and the Ittehad-ul-Muslimeen?</h4>
<ul>
<li>By October 1946, the Nizam banned the AMS.</li>
<li>A close aide of the Nizam, Qasim Razvi, leader of the Ittehad-ul-Muslimeen, became closely involved in securing the Nizam’s position.</li>
<li>The Ittehad-ul-Muslimeen was a political outfit that sought a greater role for Muslims in the early 20th century, but after Razvi took over the organisation, it became extremist in its ideology.</li>
<li>It was under him that a militia of the ‘Razakars’ was formed to suppress the peasant and communist movement, launching a brutal attack.</li>
<li>Around this time, the Standstill Agreement was also signed between the Nizam and the Indian government in November 1947, declaring a status quo.</li>
<li>This meant that until November 1948, the Nizam could let things be as they were and not finalise a decision as negotiations with the Indian union continued.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did the situation escalate to military action?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the first half of 1948, tensions grew as the razakar leaders and the government in Hyderabad began to speak of war with India and began border raids with Madras and Bombay Presidencies.</li>
<li>As a response, India stationed troops around Hyderabad and began to ready itself for military intervention.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India commences Operation Polo</h4>
<ul>
<li>With the Nizam importing more arms and the violence of the Razakars approaching dangerous proportions, India officially launched ‘Operation Polo’ on September 9 and deployed its troops in Hyderabad four days later.</li>
<li>On September 17, three days after the deployment, the Nizam surrendered and acceded to the Indian Union in November.</li>
<li>India has decided to be generous and not punish the Nizam.</li>
<li>He was retained as the official ruler of the state and given a privy purse of five million rupees.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The legacy of Operation Polo</h4>
<ul>
<li>It has also been said that the army’s march into Hyderabad did not just target the razakars and the radical extremist forces.</li>
<li>A four-member goodwill mission led by Pandit Sunderlal was constituted by the then Prime Minister.</li>
<li>At the request of then PM Nehru, a month was spent in Hyderabad in November 1948 where evidence was gathered and at the end, a report was filed.</li>
<li>Estimated thousands of people died in communal violence during the military action.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why debate now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The debate about whether the day of independence was about integration into the Indian union after months of negotiations, or liberation from an autocratic monarch has continued.</li>
<li>Hyderabad’s history continues to affect today’s politics.</li>
<li>After Qasim Rizvi left India for Pakistan, the organisation was handed over to Abdul Wahed Owaisi, the grandfather of a present day Parliamentarian.</li>
<li>And communal-sectarian politics is storming up the city of Hyderabad leading to religious tensions.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hyderabad-how-became-a-part-of-india/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>China blocks listing of Lashkar ‘commander’ Sajid Mir at UNSC</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/china-blocks-terrorist-listing-at-unsc-1267-list/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UNSC 1267</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>China's support for Pak sponsored terrorism</p></div></div><p><img alt="1267 list" class="alignnone wp-image-637686" height="274" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 419px) 100vw, 419px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-300x196.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-300x196.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc.jpg 493w" width="419"/></p>
<p>For the third time in three months, China blocked a joint India-US attempt to put a Pakistan-based terrorist on the UN Security Council’s 1267 list.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the UNSC 1267 list?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The UNSC resolution 1267 was adopted unanimously on 15 October 1999.</li>
<li>It came to force in 1999, and strengthened after the September, 2001 attacks.</li>
<li>It is now known as the Da’esh and Al Qaeda Sanctions Committee.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is UNSC 1267 committee?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It comprises all permanent and non-permanent members of the United Nations Security Council (UNSC).</li>
<li>The 1267 list of terrorists is a global list, with a UNSC stamp.</li>
<li>It is one of the most important and active UN subsidiary bodies working on efforts to combat terrorism, particularly in relation to Al Qaeda and the Islamic State group.</li>
<li>It discusses UN efforts to limit the movement of terrorists, especially those related to travel bans, the freezing of assets and arms embargoes for terrorism.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How is the listing done?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Submission of Proposal</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Any member state can submit a proposal for listing an individual, group, or entity.</li>
<li>The proposal must include acts or activities indicating the proposed individual/group/entity had participated in the financing, planning, facilitating, preparing, or perpetrating of acts or activities linked to the said organizations.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Actual decision</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Decisions on listing and de-listing are adopted by consensus.</li>
<li>The proposal is sent to all the members, and if no member objects within five working days, the proposal is adopted.</li>
<li>An “objection” means rejection for the proposal.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Putting and resolving ‘Technical Holds’</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Any member of the Committee may also put a “technical hold” on the proposal and ask for more information from the proposing member state.</li>
<li>During this time, other members may also place their own holds.</li>
<li>The matter remains on the “pending” list of the Committee.</li>
<li>Pending issues must be resolved in six months, but the member state that has placed the hold may ask for an additional three months.</li>
<li>At the end of this period, if an objection is not placed, the matter is considered approved.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is India furious this time?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Recently PM Modi and Xi Jinping attended the Shanghai Cooperation Organisation (SCO) summit in Samarkand.</li>
<li>The grouping had agreed to take strong and consolidated action against terrorism in the region.</li>
<li>Despite this, China has exposed its double standards on the issue of terrorism for consistently stopping the listing of Pakistan-based terrorists.</li>
<li>This is again very surprising movement by China by putting a ‘Technical Hold’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Here is a timeline of how China disrupts the global efforts against terrorism:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>2009:</strong> After the 26/11 Mumbai attacks, India moved an independent terror designation proposal against Masood Azhar but China blocked the move.</li>
<li><strong>2016:</strong> After seven years, India proposes listing of Masood Azhar as a global terrorist and is supported by the US, the UK and France. China blocks the move again.</li>
<li><strong>2017:</strong> The trio moves a third proposal only to be blocked by China again.</li>
<li><strong>2019:</strong> After the attacks on the CRPF personnel in J-K’s Pulwama, India calls 25 envoys of different countries to highlight the role Islamabad plays in funding, promoting and strengthening global terrorism. India moves the fourth proposal demanding Masood Azhar’s listing. <u>China lifted its technical hold.</u></li>
<li><strong>June 2022:</strong> China blocked a proposal by India and the US to list Pakistan-based terrorist Abdul Rehman Makki as a ‘Global Terrorist’</li>
<li><strong>August 2022:</strong> China blocks India-US joint proposal to list Jaish-e-Mohammad (JeM) deputy chief Abdul Rauf Azhar as UNSC designated terrorist.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>China’s actions expose its double speak and double standards when it comes to the international community’s shared battle against terrorism.</li>
<li>This clearly depicts its care for its vassal state Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: United Nations Security Council</h4>
<ul>
<li>The UNSC is one of the six principal organs of the United Nations and is charged with the maintenance of international peace and security.</li>
<li>Its powers include the establishment of peacekeeping operations, the establishment of international sanctions, and the authorization of military action through Security Council resolutions.</li>
<li>It is the only UN body with the authority to issue binding resolutions to member states.</li>
<li>The Security Council consists of fifteen members. Russia, the United Kingdom, France, China, and the United States—serve as the body’s five permanent members (P5).</li>
<li>These permanent members can veto any substantive Security Council resolution, including those on the admission of new member states or candidates for Secretary-General.</li>
<li>The Security Council also has 10 non-permanent members, elected on a regional basis to serve two-year terms. The body’s presidency rotates monthly among its members.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/china-blocks-terrorist-listing-at-unsc-1267-list/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Vacant offices, unaware office-bearers: curious case of delisted parties</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vacant-offices-unaware-office-bearers-curious-case-of-delisted-parties/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Registration and de-registration of Political Parties, RP Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The EC has been on a mission to clean up the list of registered unrecognized political parties, deleting 284 since May for either being untraceable during a physical check or not responding to communications.</p>
<h4><strong>Why de-list political parties?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The news highlights the tale of a Bharatiya xyz Party.</li>
<li>Its registered address, the ground floor of a Delhi Development Authority flat, has been home to a family since they purchased the house in 2008.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>When is a party de-registered?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The EC’s recent order has highlighted that a party must contest an election within five years of its registration, and should continue to contest thereafter.</li>
<li>If the party does not contest elections continuously for six years, the party shall be taken off the list of registered parties.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Registering a Political Party</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The registration of all political parties is governed by the provisions of the <strong>Representation of the People Act, 1951.</strong></li>
<li>According to the Election Commission (EC), any party seeking registration has to submit an application to the Commission within a <strong>period of 30 days</strong>.</li>
<li>This is done as per guidelines prescribed by the EC in exercise of the powers conferred by Article <strong>324 of the Constitution and Section 29A of the RP Act, 1951</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Note</strong>: There is no procedure available for de-registration of dormant political parties.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Process of registration</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The applicant is asked to publish a proposed party name in two national daily newspapers and two local daily newspapers, and provide two days for submitting objections, if any.</li>
<li>The notice for publication is also displayed on the website of the Election Commission.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why registering with the EC is important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is <strong><u>not mandatory to register</u></strong> with the Election Commission.</li>
<li>However, registering as a political party with the EC <strong><u>has its advantage</u></strong> in terms of intending to avail itself of the provisions of the RP Act, 1951.</li>
<li>The candidates set up by a political party registered with the EC will get <strong><u>preference in the matter of allotment of free symbols</u></strong> vis-à-vis purely independent candidates.</li>
<li>More importantly, these registered political parties, over course of time, <strong><u>can get expanded recognition</u></strong> as a ‘state party’ or a ‘national party’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How EC recognises a political party as a state or national party?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>For recognition as a <u>NATIONAL PARTY</u>, the conditions specified are:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>a 6% vote share in the last Assembly polls in each of any four states, as well as four seats in the last Lok Sabha polls; or</li>
<li>2% of all Lok Sabha seats in the last such election, with MPs elected from at least three states; or</li>
<li>recognition as a state party in at least four states.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>For recognition as a <u>STATE PARTY</u>, any one of five conditions needs to be satisfied:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>two seats plus a 6% vote share in the last Assembly election in that state; or</li>
<li>one seat plus a 6% vote share in the last Lok Sabha election from that state; or</li>
<li>3% of the total Assembly seats or 3 seats, whichever is more; or</li>
<li>one of every 25 Lok Sabha seats (or an equivalent fraction) from a state; or</li>
<li>an 8% state-wide vote share in either the last Lok Sabha or the last Assembly polls.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Benefits for recognized parties</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>This is subject to the fulfilment of the conditions prescribed by the Commission in the Election Symbols (Reservation and Allotment) Order, 1968.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(a) Reserved Sybol</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>If a party is recognised as a ‘state party’, it is entitled for exclusive allotment of its reserved symbol to the candidates set up by it in the state in which it is so recognised.</li>
<li>If a party is recognised as a ‘national party’ it is entitled for exclusive allotment of its reserved symbol to the candidates set up by it throughout India.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(b) Proposer for nomination</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Recognised ‘state’ and ‘national’ parties need only one proposer for filing the nomination.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(c) Campaigning benefits</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>They are also entitled for two sets of electoral rolls free of cost and broadcast/telecast facilities over state-owned Akashvani/Doordarshan during the general elections.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vacant-offices-unaware-office-bearers-curious-case-of-delisted-parties/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>AP approaches SC over Three Capitals Issue</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ap-three-capitals-isse/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Read the attached story</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Three Capitals Issue in AP</p></div></div><p><img alt="capitals" class="alignnone wp-image-637688" height="247" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 431px) 100vw, 431px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ap-capital-300x172.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ap-capital-300x172.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ap-capital.jpg 527w" width="431"/></p>
<p>After much discontent on the High Court (HC) verdict in the three capitals case, the Andhra Pradesh government has finally challenged it in the Supreme Court through a special leave petition (SLP).</p>
<h4><strong>AP’s move for three capitals</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>AP had introduced a ‘Three Capitals Act’ titled Andhra Pradesh Decentralisation and Inclusive Development of All Regions Act, 2020.</li>
<li>Thus, it was decided that:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Amaravati</strong> was to be the Legislative capital</li>
<li><strong>Visakhapatnam</strong> the Executive capital and</li>
<li><strong>Kurnool</strong> the Judicial capital</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>However, the Andhra Pradesh High Court <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/andhra-pradesh-government-repealed-laws-on-3-capitals/">repealed this Act</a> citing that the legislature has no competence to enact any law for shifting the three organs of the capital.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Concerns raised by AP government</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>AP contended that the judgement was in <strong><u>violation of the basic structure</u></strong> of the Constitution as the HC cannot hold that the State does not have the powers to decide on its capital.</li>
<li>The judgement was <strong><u>against the doctrine of separation of powers</u></strong> as it sought to preempt the legislature from taking up the issue (of three capitals).</li>
<li>Further, it is argued that under the <strong><u>federal structure</u></strong> of the Constitution, every State has an inherent right to determine where it should carry out its capital functions from.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reasons for AP’s consideration</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Viable option of </strong><strong>Visakhapatnam</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Vizag always had been the biggest city, after Hyderabad, even in the combined State.</li>
<li>It has all the settings to become a good living space.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Sri Krishna panel recommendations</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The advantages and qualities of Visakhapatnam to become the capital was elaborately deliberated by the Sri Krishna Committee to study the alternatives for a new capital for the State of Andhra Pradesh.</li>
<li>Coming to suggestion for the alternative capital, the Committee primarily took up three things for consideration — creation of single city or super city in greenfield location, expanding existing cities and distributed development.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Decentralisation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>This idea was elaborately described in the <strong><u>Sri Bagh pact</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The pact clearly defined decentralisation, for the benefit of all three main regions such as Coastal AP, Godavari and Krishna districts and Rayalaseema.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Major practical problems</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Continuum of work:</strong> The government argues that the Assembly meets only after gaps of several months, and government Ministers, officers, and staff can simply go to Amaravati when required.</li>
<li><strong>Logistics nightmare:</strong> coordinating between seats of legislature and executive in separate cities will be easier said than done.</li>
<li><strong>Time and costs of travel:</strong> The distances in Andhra Pradesh are not inconsiderable. Executive capital Visakhapatnam is 700 km from judicial capital Kurnool, and 400 km from legislative capital Amaravati.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Examples of multi-capital states in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Among Indian states, Maharashtra has two capitals– Mumbai and Nagpur (which holds the winter session of the state assembly).</li>
<li>Himachal Pradesh has capitals at Shimla and Dharamshala (winter).</li>
<li>The former state of Jammu &amp; Kashmir had Srinagar and Jammu (winter) as capitals where <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-durbar-move/">Darbar Move</a> is carried out.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Special Leave Petition</h4>
<ul>
<li>SLP hold a prime place in the Indian judicial system.</li>
<li>It provides the aggrieved party a special permission to be heard in Apex court in appeal against any judgment or order of any Court/tribunal in the territory of India.</li>
<li>It has been provided as a “residual power” in the hands of Supreme Court of India to be exercised only in cases when any substantial question of law is involved, or gross injustice has been done.</li>
<li>Article 136 vests the Supreme Court of India with a special power to grant special leave, to appeal against any judgment or order or decree.</li>
<li>It is <strong><u>discretionary power</u></strong> vested in the Supreme Court of India and the court may in its discretion refuse to grant leave to appeal.</li>
<li>The aggrieved party cannot claim special leave to appeal under Article 136 as a right, but it is privilege vested in the Supreme Court to grant leave to appeal or not.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ap-three-capitals-isse/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>It seems that inflation may hover around 7 percent</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/inflation-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>types of inflation</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>inflation overview</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="inflation" class="alignnone wp-image-637649" height="341" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1.jpg 1200w" width="647"/> </strong><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It seems that inflation may hover around 7 per cent despite RBI’s tightening of monetary policy in the months to come.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a simple definition for inflation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Inflation is an increase in the level of prices of the goods and services that households buy. It is measured as the rate of change of those prices. Typically, prices rise over time, but prices can also fall (a situation called deflation).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Inflation Rate</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Inflation Rate is the percentage change in the price level from the previous period. If a normal basket of goods was priced at Rupee 100 last year and the same basket of goods now cost Rupee 120, then the rate of inflation this year is 20%.</li>
<li>Inflation Rate= {(Price in year 2 – Price in year 1)/ Price in year 1} *100</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="inflation" class="alignnone wp-image-637678" height="350" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 841px) 100vw, 841px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-1-300x125.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-1-300x125.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-1-768x319.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-1.jpg 842w" width="841"/>Types of Inflation</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Creeping Inflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Creeping or mild inflation is when prices rise 3% a year or less. This kind of mild inflation makes consumers expect that prices will keep going up. That boosts demand. Consumers buy now to beat higher future prices. That’s how mild inflation drives economic expansion.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Walking Inflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>This type of strong, or pernicious, inflation is between 3-10% a year. It is harmful to the economy because it heats up economic growth too fast. People start to buy more than they need, just to avoid tomorrow’s much higher prices. This drives demand even further so that suppliers can’t keep up. More important, neither can wages. As a result, common goods and services are priced out of the reach of most people.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Galloping Inflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>When inflation rises to 10% or more, it wreaks absolute havoc on the economy. Money loses value so fast that business and employee income can’t keep up with costs and prices. Foreign investors avoid the country, depriving it of needed capital. The economy becomes unstable, and government leaders lose credibility. Galloping inflation must be prevented at all costs.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Hyperinflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Hyperinflation is when prices skyrocket more than 50% a month. It is very rare. In fact, most examples of hyperinflation have occurred only when governments printed money to pay for wars. Examples of hyperinflation include <strong>Germany</strong>in the 1920s, <strong>Zimbabwe</strong> in the 2000s, and <strong>Venezuela</strong> in the 2010s. The last time America experienced hyperinflation was during its civil war.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Core Inflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The core inflation rate measures rising prices in everything except food and energy. That’s because gas prices tend to escalate now and then. Higher gas costs increase the price of food and anything else that has large transportation costs.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Consumer Price Index</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>CPI is used to monitor changes in the cost of living over time. When the CPI rises, the average Indian family has to spend more on goods and services to maintain the same standard of living. The economic term used to define such a rising prices of goods and services is Inflation.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Whole sale Price Index</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>WPI is used to monitor the cost of goods and services bought by producer and firms rather than final consumers. The WPI inflation captures price changes at the factory/wholesale level.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>GDP Deflator</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Another important measure of calculating standard of living of people is GDP Deflator. GDP Deflator is the ratio of nominal GDP to real GDP. The nominal GDP is measured at the current prices whereas the real GDP is measured at the base year prices. Therefore, GDP Deflator reflects the current level of prices relative to prices in a base year. Example, In India the base year of calculating deflator is 2011-12.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="inflation" class="alignnone wp-image-637631" height="297" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 100vw, 527px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_Rate_0_1200x768-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_Rate_0_1200x768-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_Rate_0_1200x768-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_Rate_0_1200x768.jpeg 770w" width="527"/>Factors fuelling inflation in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Falling rupee:</strong> Inflation is here to stay because it has much to do with the decline in value of the rupee that has fallen to its lowest, which makes imports of oil and gas more expensive.</li>
<li><strong>Ukraine crisis:</strong> The war in Ukraine has the same effect and pushes the price of some food items upward.</li>
<li><strong>Poor inflation management:</strong> With inflation, as measured by the consumer price index, in August going back to 7 per cent, and the wholesale price index coming in at 12.4 per cent, one thing is clear India is not out of the woods on inflation management.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Rising inflation have these implications</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Impact on the poor:</strong> This upsurge of inflation is affecting the poor more because some of the commodities whose prices are increasing the most represent a larger fraction of the budget of the most vulnerable sections of society.</li>
<li><strong>Rising inequality:</strong> As a result, inequalities which were already on the rise are increasing further. Recently, the State of Inequality in India report showed that an Indian making Rs 3 lakh a year belonged to the top 10 per cent of the country’s wage earners.<strong> </strong></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inequality in healthcare: </strong>India’s spending on healthcare is among the lowest in the world. Decent level of healthcare is available only to the ones who can afford it because of increasing out-of-pocket expenditure the payment made directly by individuals for the health service, not covered under any financial protection scheme. Overall, these out-of-pocket expenses on healthcare are 60 per cent of the total expenditure on public health in India, which is one of the highest in the world.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong><img alt="inflation" class="alignnone wp-image-637701" height="358" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 643px) 100vw, 643px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200.jpg 1200w" width="643"/>Need for bold steps on three fronts to tackle inflation</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Unless bold and innovative steps are taken at least on three fronts, GDP growth and inflation both are likely to be in the range of 6.5 to 7.5 per cent in 2022-23.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>1] Tightening of loose<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/monetary-economics-barter-system-definition-function-and-evolution-of-money/"> monetary policy:</a></strong> The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) is mandated to keep inflation at 4 per cent, plus-minus 2 per cent.</p>
<ul>
<li>The RBI has already started the process of tightening monetary policy by raising the repo rate, albeit a bit late.</li>
<li>It is expected that by the end of 2022-3, the repo rate will be at least 5.5 per cent, if not more.</li>
<li>It will still stay below the likely inflation rate and therefore depositors will still lose the real value of their money in banks with negative real interest rates.</li>
<li>That only reflects an inbuilt bias in the system — in favour of entrepreneurs in the name of growth and against depositors, which ultimately results in increasing inequality in the system.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2] Prudent fiscal policy:</strong> Fiscal policy has been running loose in the wake of Covid-19 that saw the fiscal deficit of the Union government soar to more than 9 per cent in 2020-21 and 6.7 per cent in 2021-22, but now needs to be tightened.</p>
<ul>
<li>Government needs to reduce its fiscal deficit to less than 5 per cent, never mind the FRMB Act’s advice to bring it to 3 per cent of GDP.</li>
<li>However, it is difficult to achieve when enhanced food and fertiliser subsidies, and cuts in duties of petrol and diesel will cost the government at least Rs 3 trillion more than what was provisioned in the budget.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>3] Rational trade policy:</strong> Export restrictions/bans go beyond agri-commodities, even to iron ore and steel, etc. in the name of taming inflation.</p>
<ul>
<li>But abrupt export bans are poor trade policy and reflect only the panic-stricken face of the government.</li>
<li>A more mature approach to filter exports would be through a gradual process of minimum export prices and transparent export duties for short periods of time, rather than abrupt bans, if at all these are desperately needed to favour consumers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Though the government is opting for market-based economics, currently, India needs a mixed solution that comprises price stability via government channels and subsidies.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>What are the fuelling factors for inflation? Discuss what steps should be taken to tackle inflation.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/inflation-2/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Geopolitics follows the geoeconomics and not vice-versa</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/geoeconomics/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>international relations</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="geoeconomics" class="alignnone wp-image-637721" height="347" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 699px) 100vw, 699px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-300x149.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-300x149.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-1024x508.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-768x381.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-1200x595.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1.jpg 1269w" width="699"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Over the recent years India’s manoeuvres in indo-pacific have highlighted the India’s geopolitical and ambitions. Pandemic and Chinese incursion in Ladakh forced India to move fast to achieve its geopolitical ends. However missing link in India’s endeavour is geoeconomics.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is mean by geopolitics and geo-economics?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Geopolitics:</strong> is defined as the struggle over the control of geographical entities with an international and global dimension, and the use of such geographical entities for political advantage.</li>
<li><strong>Geo-economics:</strong> is defined as the combination of economic and geographic factors relating to international trade and a governmental policy guided by geoeconomics.</li>
<li>Geopolitics and geoeconomics are sometimes used interchangeably.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the strategy to pursue geopolitical goals in indo-pacific?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has managed to emerge as a major pivot of the global Indo-Paciﬁc grand strategic imagination.</li>
<li>Avoided the temptations to militarise/securitise the Quad (Australia, Japan, India and the United States).</li>
<li>Which has ensured that the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) states do not feel uneasy by the ever-increasing balance of power articulations in the Indo-Pacific</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="geoeconomics" class="alignnone wp-image-637722" height="323" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Geoeconomics-in-a-Globalized-World-300x166.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Geoeconomics-in-a-Globalized-World-300x166.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Geoeconomics-in-a-Globalized-World.jpg 525w" width="584"/>What is the missing link in India’s geopolitical strategy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The missing link in geoeconomics is India’s decision to take to the Indo-Paciﬁc and Quad in a big way.</li>
<li>While unwilling to join two of the region’s key multilateral trading agreements goes to show that geoeconomics and geopolitics are imagined and pursued parallelly in New Delhi, not as complimenting each other.</li>
<li>The most recent example is India’s refusal to join the trade pillar of the Indo-Paciﬁc Economic Framework (IPEF) while deciding to join the three other pillars of the IPEF supply chains, tax and anti-corruption, and clean energy.</li>
</ul>
<p>India also withdrew from <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/back-in-news-india-asean-relations/">ASEAN</a> led <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/regional-comprehensive-economic-partnership-rcep/">RCEP.</a></p>
<h4><strong>Is the lack of geoeconomic bad for foreign policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The absence of the world’s fifth largest economy from various regional trading platforms will invariably boost China’s geo-economic hegemony in Asia.</li>
<li>Staying out of IPEF is a bad idea is because for India, it would be hard to integrate itself into the regional and global supply chains without being a part of important regional multilateral trading agreements.</li>
<li>We have no option but to address some of the deeper challenges plaguing the investment and business environment in India.</li>
<li>If India is indeed serious about its maritime grand strategy, which cannot be solely military in nature, it needs to get the states in the region to create economic stakes in India (something China has done cleverly and consistently) and vice-versa.</li>
<li>Another impact of India’s hesitation about joining regional multilateral trading arrangements is its potential regional economic isolation. The less India engages with the region economically, and the more China does so, and given the Sino-Indian rivalry, India might risk getting economically isolated in the broader region.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Geo-economics: is defined as the combination of economic and geographic factors relating to international trade and a governmental policy guided by geoeconomics. Geopolitics and geoeconomics are sometimes used interchangeably." class="alignnone wp-image-637723" height="397" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 634px) 100vw, 634px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-1024x640.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-1536x960.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-2048x1280.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-1200x750.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-1980x1238.jpg 1980w" width="634"/>What can be done?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>New Delhi should: </strong>rethink its geoeconomic choices if it is serious about enhancing its geopolitical inﬂuence in the region. Given that India has not closed the door on the trade pillar of the IPEF, we have an opportunity to rethink our position.</li>
<li><strong>India should: </strong>also rethink its decision not to join the RECP and seek to join the Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Paciﬁc Partnership (CPTPP) from which the U.S. walked out and China is seeking to join.</li>
<li><strong>India should: </strong>also proactively lobby to become a part of the Minerals Security Partnership, the U.S.-led 11-member grouping to secure supply chains of critical minerals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the words of external affairs minister Dr. Jaishankar,” geopolitics follows the geoeconomics and not vice-versa”. Geoeconomics is inclusive of geoeconomics. India should integrate itself in multilateral trading platforms and leverage its big market to bargain the best deal for itself.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Indias pursuit of geopolitics is futile without inclusion of geoeconomics. Comment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/geoeconomics/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Without social justice constructive women empowerment is a futile exercise here is why</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-empowerment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Women empowerment</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637728" height="341" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609-768x447.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609.jpg 1000w" width="585"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Despite notable progress in closing the gender pay gap over time in India, the gap remains high by international standards. Asymmetries still abound in the country’s labor market stopping women empowerment .</li>
<li>Time to reassess the progress made in to close the Gender pay gap.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The third International Equal Pay Day is observed globally on September 18, 2022.</li>
<li>It is a United Nations-recognized event to highlight the issue of gender pay gap.</li>
<li>International Labor Organization’s “Global Wage Report 2020–21” which suggests the crisis inflicted massive downward pressure on wages and disproportionately affected women’s total wages compared to</li>
<li>This greater wage reduction for women means that the pre-existing gender pay gap has widened.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637732" height="325" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200.jpg 1200w" width="584"/>Covid-19 Impact</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While it is difficult to tell exactly what the economic damage from the global covid-19 pandemic has been, it is clear that its impact has been uneven, with women being among the worst affected in terms of their income security.</li>
<li>Many women reverted to full-time care of children and the elderly during the pandemic, foregoing their livelihoods to do so.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is gender pay gap?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The gender pay gap or gender wage gap measures the difference between the average earnings of women and men in the workforce.</li>
<li>In simple term it is a measure of what women are paid relative to men.</li>
<li>Women are generally found to be paid less than men.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is the gender pay gap?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Education: </strong>low investment o girl education<strong>, </strong>Girl children are kept out of schools, or made drop out of school at early age, girl is considered as burden on family in many societies.</li>
<li><strong>workforce </strong>: even if they are educated they are not allowed to work by their families, very limited or no decision making power, lack of women friendly work environment, discriminatory practices at workplaces.</li>
<li><strong>Household:</strong> early marriage , responsibilities of the household at early age , spending more times on domestic chores,</li>
<li><strong>Healthcare: </strong>malnutrition, anemia, Maternity, child care, looking after health of the elderly family members etc.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p>These are some of the reasons which affect education, skills, experience and the career prospectus of women as compared to men and contribute to widen the gender wage gap.</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637730" height="297" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 100vw, 527px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India.jpg 1919w" width="527"/>Discrimination as factor</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A part of gender pay gap attributed to education, skills or experience, a large part of the gender pay gap can still purely because of discrimination based on one’s gender or sex.</li>
<li>Gender-based discriminatory practices include: lower wages paid to women for work of equal value; undervaluation of women’s work in highly feminized occupations and enterprises, and motherhood pay gap lower wages for mothers compared to non-mother.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637734" height="466" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 837px) 100vw, 837px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1.jpg 1200w" width="837"/>Status in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The gender pay gap in India is among the widest in the world.</li>
<li>Indian women earned, on an average, 48% less compared to their male counterparts in 1993-94</li>
<li>According to labor force survey data of the National Sample Survey Office (NSSO) gap declined to 28% in 2018-19.</li>
<li>Periodic Labor Force Survey (PLFS) 2020-21 show an increase in the gap by 7% between 2018-19 and 2020-21.</li>
<li>Recently, the World Economic Forum (WEF) ranked India at 135 out of 146 countries in its Global Gender Gap (GGG) Index for 2022.</li>
<li>According to the estimates of the World Inequality Report 2022, in India, men earn 82 per cent of the labor income whereas women earn 18 per cent of it.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637731" height="392" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 696px) 100vw, 696px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8477553337_67c076bed2_o-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8477553337_67c076bed2_o-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8477553337_67c076bed2_o.jpg 639w" width="696"/>Steps taken by India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Minimum Wages Act in 1948</strong>: It is an act of parliament<strong>, </strong>aimed at statutory fixation of minimum wages that must be paid to skilled and unskilled labours. Payment of wages below the minimum wage rate amounts to forced labour.</li>
<li><strong>Equal Remuneration Act in 1976: </strong>This act of parliament provides for the payment of equal remuneration to men and women workers for the prevention of discrimination. It helps in bridging the gap between unequal remuneration faced by the women of our country.</li>
<li><strong>Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA) 2005:</strong> MGNREGA contributed to the rapid rise in overall rural and agricultural wages in the country. It benefited rural women workers and helped reduce the gender pay gap, both directly and indirectly. Directly, by raising the pay levels of women workers and indirectly to women involved in agricultural occupations through higher earnings.</li>
<li><strong>The Maternity Benefit (Amendment) Act 2017</strong>: has increased the duration of paid maternity leave available for women employees to 26 weeks from 12 weeks for all women working in establishments employing 10 or more workers. This is expected to reduce the motherhood pay gap among mothers in the median and high end wage earners working in the formal economy also it will help in women empowerment.</li>
<li><strong>Skill India Mission</strong>: To equip women with market-relevant skills to bridge the learning to-livelihood gap and the gender pay gap.</li>
<li>In 2019, India carried out comprehensive reforms in both the legislation and enacted the Code on Wages.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While the gender pay gap is slowly narrowing, acceleration and bold actions to prevent the widening of gender pay gap is the need of the hour.</li>
<li>Equal pay for work of equal value is necessary to close the gender pay gap.</li>
<li>Closing the gender pay gap is key to achieving <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/women-empowerment-issues-jobsreservation-education/">social justice for working women</a>, as well as economic growth for the nation as a whole</li>
<li>Without social justice women empowerment is a futile exercise.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Define gender equality .Equal pay for equal work is necessary to bridge the gender pay gap India .Comment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-empowerment/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the PM PRANAM Scheme?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-pm-pranam-scheme/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PM PRANAM Scheme</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India's fertilizer subsidy</p></div></div><p>In order to reduce the use of chemical fertilisers by incentivising states, the Union government plans to introduce a new scheme – PM PRANAM, which stands for PM Promotion of Alternate Nutrients for Agriculture Management Yojana.</p>
<h4>What is the PM PRANAM scheme?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The proposed scheme intends to reduce the subsidy burden on chemical fertilisers.</li>
<li>This burden if uneased, is expected to increase to Rs 2.25 lakh crore in 2022-2023, which is 39% higher than the previous year’s figure of Rs 1.62 lakh crore.</li>
<li>The scheme will not have a separate budget and will be financed by the “savings of existing fertiliser subsidy” under schemes run by the Department of fertilisers.</li>
</ul>
<p>Subsidies under the PRANAM</p>
<ul>
<li>Further, 50% subsidy savings will be passed on as a grant to the state that saves the money and that 70% of the grant provided under the scheme can be used for asset creation related to technological adoption of alternate fertilisers.</li>
<li>It would create alternate fertiliser production units at village, block and district levels.</li>
<li>The remaining 30% grant money can be used for incentivising farmers, panchayats, farmer producer organisations and self-help groups that are involved in the reduction of fertiliser use and awareness generation.</li>
<li>The government will compare a state’s increase or reduction in urea in a year, to its average consumption of urea during the last three years.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How much fertiliser does India require?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The kharif season (June-October) is critical for India’s food security, accounting for nearly half the year’s production of foodgrains, one-third of pulses and approximately two-thirds of oilseeds.</li>
<li>A sizable amount of fertiliser is required for this season.</li>
<li>The Department of Agriculture and Farmers Welfare assesses the requirement of fertilisers each year before the start of the cropping season, and informs the Ministry of Chemical and fertilisers to ensure the supply.</li>
<li>The amount of fertiliser required varies each month according to demand, which is based on the time of crop sowing, which also varies from region to region.</li>
<li>For example, the demand for urea peaks during June-August period, but is relatively low in March and April, and the government uses these two months to prepare for an adequate amount of fertiliser for the kharif season.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is the scheme being introduced?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Due to <strong><u>increased demand for fertiliser</u></strong> in the country over the past 5 years, the overall expenditure by the government on subsidy has also increased.</li>
<li>The final figure of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-enhances-subsidy-for-non-urea-fertilizers/"><strong>fertiliser subsidy</strong></a> touched Rs 1.62 lakh crore in 2021-22.</li>
<li>The total requirement of four fertilisers — Urea, DAP (Di-ammonium Phosphate), MOP (Muriate of potash), NPKS (Nitrogen, Phosphorus and Potassium) — increased by 21% between 2017-2018 and 2021-2022, from 528.86 lakh metric tonnes (LMT) to 640.27 LMT.</li>
<li>PM PRANAM, which seeks to reduce the use of chemical fertiliser, will likely <strong><u>reduce the burden on the exchequer. </u></strong></li>
<li>The proposed scheme is also in line with the government’s focus on promoting the <strong><u>balanced use of fertilisers or alternative fertilisers</u></strong> in the last few years.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4>Try this PYQ:</h4>
<p><strong>Q.What are the advantages of fertigation in agriculture? (CSP 2020)</strong></p>
<p>1.Controlling the alkalinity of irrigation water is possible.<br/>
2.Efficient application of Rock Phosphate and all other phosphatic fertilizers is possible.<br/>
3.Increased availability of nutrients to plants is possible.<br/>
4.Reduction in the leaching of chemical nutrients is possible.</p>
<p><strong>Select the correct answer using the code given below:</strong><br/>
(a) 1, 2 and 3 only</p>
<p>(b) 1,2 and 4 only</p>
<p>(c) 1,3 and 4 only</p>
<p>(d) 2, 3 and 4 only</p>
<p> </p>
Post your answers here.</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-pm-pranam-scheme/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the Plant Treaty?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-plant-treaty/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Plant treaty</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p> </p>
<p>The ninth session of the governing body of the International Treaty on Plant Genetic Resources for Food and Agriculture (ITPGRFA) has recently begun in New Delhi.</p>
<h4><strong>Theme of this years event</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The theme of the meeting is ‘Celebrating the Guardians of Crop Diversity: Towards an Inclusive Post-2020 Global Biodiversity Framework’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Plant Treaty?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The International Treaty on Plant Genetic Resources for Food and Agriculture (ITPGRFA) was adopted by the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations November 3, 2001.</li>
<li>It was signed in 2001 in Madrid, and entered into force on 29 June 2004.</li>
<li>It is the first legally-binding international instrument to formally acknowledge the enormous contribution of indigenous people and small-holder farmers as traditional custodians of the world’s food crops.</li>
<li>It also calls on nations to protect and promote their rights to save and use the seeds they have taken care of for millennia.</li>
<li>The parties to this treaty have come together after nearly three years to discuss governance of agricultural biodiversity and global food security.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Objectives of the treaty<br/>
</strong></h4>
<p>The treaty aims at:</p>
<ol>
<li>Guaranteeing food security through the conservation</li>
<li>Exchange and sustainable use of the world’s plant genetic resources for food and agriculture (PGRFA)</li>
<li>Fair and equitable benefit sharing arising from its use, as well as</li>
<li>Recognition of farmers’ rights.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Key feature: Annex 1 Crops</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The treaty has implemented a Multilateral System (MLS) of access and benefit sharing, among those countries that ratify the treaty, for a list of 64 of some of the most important food and forage crops essential for food security and interdependence.</li>
<li>The genera and species are listed in Annex 1 to the treaty. The treaty facilitates the continued open exchange of food crops and their genetic materials.</li>
<li>The list of plant genetic material included in the Multilateral System of the Treaty is made of major food crops and forages.</li>
<li>The Forages are also divided in legume forages and grass forages.</li>
<li>They were selected taking into account the criteria of food security and country interdependence</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-the-plant-treaty/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SC quota for Dalit Muslims and Christians</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-quota-for-dalit-muslims-and-christians/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Quota benefits for religious convertees</p></div></div><p>The Centre is likely to soon decide on setting up a national commission to study the social, economic and educational status of Dalits who converted to religions other than Hinduism, Buddhism and Sikhism.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Several petitions are pending before the Supreme Court seeking Scheduled Caste (SC) reservation benefits for Dalits who converted to Christianity or Islam.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Dalit Convertees and Quota Benefits<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The original rationale behind giving reservation to Scheduled Castes was that these sections had suffered from the social evil of untouchability, which was practised among Hindus.</li>
<li>Under Article 341 of the Constitution, the President may specify the castes, races or tribes or parts of or groups within castes, races or tribes which shall…be deemed to be Scheduled Castes.</li>
<li>The first order under this provision was issued in 1950, and covered only Hindus.</li>
<li>Following demands from the Sikh community, an order was issued in 1956, including Sikhs of Dalit origin among the beneficiaries of the SC quota.</li>
<li>In 1990, the government acceded to a similar demand from Buddhists of Dalit origin, and the order was revised to state: “No person who professes a religion different from the Hindu, the Sikh or the Buddhist religion shall be deemed to be a member of Scheduled Caste.”</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Does this religion-based bar apply to converted STs and OBCs as well?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It does not.</li>
<li>The Department of Personnel and Training (DoPT) website states, “The rights of a person belonging to a Scheduled Tribe are independent of his/her religious faith.”</li>
<li>Following the implementation of the Mandal Commission report, several Christian and Muslim communities have found place in the Central and state lists of OBCs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What efforts have been made to include Muslims and Christians of Dalit origin among SCs?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>After 1990, a number of Private Member’s Bills were brought in Parliament for this purpose.</li>
<li>In 1996, a government Bill called The Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Orders (Amendment) Bill was drafted, but in view of a divergence of opinions, the Bill was not introduced in Parliament.</li>
<li>Then government headed by PM Manmohan Singh set up two important panels:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Ranganath Misra Commission:</strong> The National Commission for Religious and Linguistic Minorities, popularly known as the Ranganath Misra Commission, in October 2004 and</li>
<li><strong>Sachar Committee:</strong> A seven-member high-level committee headed by former Chief Justice of Delhi High Court Rajinder Sachar to study the social, economic, and educational condition of Muslims in March 2005.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>What did they recommend?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The <strong><u>Sachar Committee Report</u></strong> observed that the social and economic situation of Dalit Muslims and Dalit Christians did not improve after conversion.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Ranganath Misra Commission</u></strong>, which submitted its report in May 2007, recommended that SC status should be completely de-linked from religion and Scheduled Castes should be made fully religion-neutral like Scheduled Tribes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reception to these recommendations</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The report was tabled in Parliament in 2009, but its recommendation was <strong><u>not accepted</u></strong> in view of inadequate field data and corroboration with the actual situation on the ground.</li>
<li>Few studies, commissioned by the National Commission for Minorities, was also <strong><u>not considered reliable due to insufficient data.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What lies ahead?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Based on the recommendations of the Ranganath Misra Commission, there are some <strong><u>petitions pending before the Supreme Cour</u></strong>t, seeking reservation benefits for Christians and Muslims of Dalit orgin.</li>
<li>In the last hearing, a three-judge Bench gave the Solicitor General of India three weeks’ time to present the stand of the Union government on the issue.</li>
<li>The next hearing is awaited.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-quota-for-dalit-muslims-and-christians/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Significance of Ethereum’s Merge for the future of cryptocurrencies</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/significance-of-ethereums-merge-for-the-future-of-cryptocurrencies/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ethereum Merge Event</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Cryptyocurrencies</p></div></div><p><img alt="merge" class="alignnone wp-image-637900" height="212" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 370px) 100vw, 370px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merge-300x172.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merge-300x172.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merge.jpg 721w" width="370"/></p>
<p>Ethereum’s shift of its consensus algorithm from proof-of-work (PoW) to environment-friendly proof-of-stake (PoS) in an event called ‘The Merge’ recently took place.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>One would wonder if the Merge Event has actually any relation to any corporate merger or acquisition!</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>What is Ethereum?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Ethereum is one of the most used platforms by developers to build decentralised apps (dApps), smart contracts, and even crypto tokens.</li>
<li>The platform’s currency, Ether is only second to Bitcoin (BTC) in terms of market capitalisation.</li>
<li>The change in the way Ethereum builds the blockchain comes with not just environmental consequences, but also major cyber and financial security implications.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a Merge?  </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Merge is an upgrade to the way transactions are validated on the Ethereum blockchain.</li>
<li>It moves the network proof-of-work (PoW) system to proof-of-stake (PoS) system, which is designed to be more environmentally sustainable and faster.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does PoS and PoW refer to?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>PoS and PoW are consensus mechanisms through which transactions on blockchains are validated.</li>
<li>PoW consumes more energy since it allows all miners on a network to try and validate a transaction.</li>
<li>As a result, more computers attack a transaction and hence consume more energy.</li>
<li>PoS removes miners from the equation, replacing them with entities called ‘validators’.</li>
<li>These validators put up a stake (at least 32ETH) in order to gain the right to validate transactions. Only the top stakeholders are rewarded for their work.</li>
<li>Their stakes are held in a central wallet, and they are penalized for mistakes or frauds.</li>
<li>Common centres for mining included China (before a near total crypto ban), the US, Russia, and Kazakhstan — countries with cheap electricity rates and colder climates.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is there a need for a new mechanism?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Power Saving</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Decentralised transactions are processed on blockchains using consensus mechanisms.</li>
<li>Ethereum’s former method, ‘proof-of-work’, which is also used by Bitcoin, needs powerful mining hardware that consumes a lot of electricity and generates enormous amounts of heat.</li>
<li>This energy is then used to process extremely difficult mathematical puzzles, the solution of which would let new transactions be added to the blockchain so as to reward the miners with crypto.</li>
<li>Many environmentalists, policy makers, and regulators have strongly criticised the impact of Bitcoin mining on local communities.</li>
<li>Ethereum’s website admitted that their crypto’s total annualised power consumption nearly matches that of Finland while its carbon footprint is comparable to Switzerland.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Global Crackdown</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>For some time, European countries even mulled a crypto mining ban, while China actually carried out a nationwide crackdown on crypto miners, sending them fleeing overseas.</li>
<li>Probably as a response to the backlash, Ethereum has decided to switch to a ‘proof-of-stake’ consensus mechanism.</li>
<li>The crypto owners will stake their own coins in order to serve as collateral and help process new blockchain transactions, in return for rewards.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Significance of the merge</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="merge" class="alignnone wp-image-637902" height="224" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 391px) 100vw, 391px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merge-ether-300x172.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merge-ether-300x172.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/merge-ether.jpg 669w" width="391"/></p>
<ul>
<li>According to the Ethereum Foundation, the Merge will reduce overall energy consumption of the Ethereum network by 99.95%.</li>
<li>Blockchains have a short history so far, but in that history, the Merge has become one of the most widely publicized and awaited events.</li>
<li>It has been in the works for six years and 15 September marked the end of that build-up.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Which other cryptocurrencies are changing to proof-of-stake now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>For now, no other top coin is planning an Ethereum-style Merge.</li>
<li>After Bitcoin, Dogecoin [DOGE] is the largest proof-of-work based cryptocurrency.</li>
<li>It was initially created as a joke by its founders. After that comes Ethereum Classic [ETC], formerly part of Ethereum before a community schism.</li>
<li>Ethereum Classic has made it clear that it is loyal to the proof-of-work mechanism.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/significance-of-ethereums-merge-for-the-future-of-cryptocurrencies/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Death Penalty: SC moots fair hearing</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/death-penalty-sc-moots-fair-hearing/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Death penalty debate</p></div></div><p><strong> <img alt="death" class="alignnone wp-image-637901" height="305" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/death-300x204.png" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/death-300x204.png 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/death.png 461w" width="449"/></strong></p>
<p>The Supreme Court has referred to a Constitution Bench the question of how to provide accused in death penalty cases a “meaningful, real and effective” hearing of their mitigating circumstances before a trial judge.</p>
<h4><strong>Death Penalty: A backgrounder</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-debate-over-capital-punishment/">Capital punishment</a>, sometimes called death penalty, is execution of an offender sentenced to death after conviction by a court of law for a criminal offense.</li>
<li>It should be distinguished from extrajudicial executions carried out without due process of law.</li>
<li>The term death penalty is sometimes used interchangeably with capital punishment, though imposition of the penalty is not always followed by execution, because of the possibility of commutation to life imprisonment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>When is it awarded?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The term “Capital Punishment” stands for most severe form of punishment.</li>
<li>It is the punishment which is to be awarded for the most heinous, grievous and detestable crimes against humanity.</li>
<li>While the definition and extent of such crimes vary, the implication of capital punishment has always been the death sentence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Special factors on the death penalty jurisprudence in India</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(a) Increase in Sexual Offences</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The report on death penalty published by NLU Delhi shows that the rate of awarding capital punishment to the offences of rape with murder is much higher than other offences.</li>
<li>There is no doubt that rape is one of the most heinous crimes.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(b) Sedition and waging War against India</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>India has seen many cases of treason, terrorism and seditious activities.</li>
<li>It is in fact the most vulnerable state for such crimes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Judicial observations related to Death Penalty</strong></h4>
<p>The Supreme Court has always said that the death sentence should be given rarely.</p>
<p><strong><u>Judgments against:</u></strong></p>
<p><strong>(a) Mithu vs State of Punjab (1983):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The Supreme Court ruled that the mandatory death penalty is unconstitutional.</li>
<li>It struck down Section 303 in the IPC, which entailed a mandatory death sentence for a person who commits murder while serving a life term in another case.</li>
<li>The Supreme Court ruled Section 303 violated Articles 14 (right to equality) and 21 (right to life) since an unreasonable distinction was sought to be made between two classes of murders.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(b) State of Punjab vs Dalbir Singh (2012):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Similarly, the Supreme Court ruled that mandatory death penalty as punishment for crimes under Section 27 (3) of the Arms Act, 1959, was unconstitutional.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(c) Channulal Verma vs State of Chhattisgarh (2018):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In Channulal, the Supreme Court, through Justice Kurian Joseph noted that the time was appropriate to review the constitutionality of the death penalty and take into consideration reformative aspects of punishment</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><u>Judgments in favour:</u></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In Jagmohan Singh vs State of UP’ (1973), then in ‘Rajendra Prasad vs State of UP’ (1979), and finally in ‘<strong><u>Bachan Singh vs State of Punjab’ (1980)</u></strong> the Supreme Court affirmed the constitutional validity of the death penalty.</li>
<li>It said that if capital punishment is provided in the law and the procedure is a fair, just and reasonable one, the death sentence can be awarded to a convict.</li>
<li>This will, however, only be in the “rarest of rare” cases, and the courts should render “special reasons” while sending a person to the gallows.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Avenues available to a Death-Row Convict</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Confirmation by HC:</strong> After a trial court awards the death penalty, the sentence must be confirmed by a High Court. The sentence cannot be executed till the time the High Court confirms it, either after deciding the appeal filed by the convict, or until the period allowed for preferring an appeal has expired.</li>
<li><strong>Review Petition:</strong> If the High Court confirms the death penalty and it is also upheld by the Supreme Court, a convict can file a review petition.</li>
<li><strong>Curative Petition:</strong> If the review petition is rejected, the convict can file a curative petition for reconsideration of the judgment.</li>
<li><strong>Mercy Petition: </strong>Under Article 72 of the Indian Constitution, the President shall have the power to grant pardons, reprieves, respites, or remissions of punishments or to suspend, remit or commute the sentence of any convicted person.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Debate over Death Penalty</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Arguments in favor:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Forfeiture of life:</strong> Supporters of the death penalty believe that those who commit murder, because they have taken the life of another, have forfeited their own right to life.</li>
<li><strong>Moral indignation of the victim:</strong> It is a just form of retribution, expressing and reinforcing the moral indignation not only of the victim’s relatives but of law-abiding citizens in general.</li>
<li><strong>Highest form of Justice:</strong> For heinous crimes such as the Nirbhaya Gangrape Case, no other punishment could have deterred the will of the convicts.</li>
<li><strong>Deterrent against crime:</strong> Capital punishment is often justified with the argument that by executing convicted murderers, we will deter would-be murderers from killing people.</li>
<li><strong>Proportional punishment:</strong> The guilty people deserve to be punished in proportion to the severity of their crime.</li>
<li><strong>Prevailing lawlessness:</strong> The crimes we are now witnessing cannot be addressed by simple punishments. We are seeing horrific attacks on women, young girls, minority communities and Dalits etc.</li>
<li><strong>Prevention of crime is non-existent:</strong> Despite of stringent regulations, it is certainly visible that some crimes can never be prevented in our society.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Arguments against</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Eye for an eye:</strong> Reformative justice is more productive, that innocent people are often killed in the search for retribution, and that “an eye for an eye makes the whole world blind.</li>
<li><strong>Deterrence is a myth:</strong> Death penalty is not a deterrent to capital crimes state that there is no evidence to support the claim that the penalty is a deterrent.</li>
<li><strong>Political tool of suppression:</strong> The authorities in some countries, for example Iran and Sudan, use the death penalty to punish political opponents.</li>
<li><strong>Reverence for life’ principle: </strong>Death penalty is an immoral punishment since humans should not kill other humans, no matter the reasons, because killing is killing.</li>
<li><strong>Stigma against killing:</strong> With the introduction of lethal injection as execution method, medical professionals participate in executions. Many professionals have now refused to administer such deaths.</li>
<li><strong>Skewed justice systems:</strong> In many cases recorded by Amnesty International, people were executed after being convicted in grossly unfair trials, on the basis of torture-tainted evidence and with inadequate legal representation.</li>
<li><strong>Discriminatory nature:</strong> The weight of the death penalty is disproportionally carried by those with less advantaged socio-economic backgrounds or belonging to a racial, ethnic or religious minority.</li>
<li><strong>Penalizing the innocents:</strong> The risk of executing the innocent precludes the use of the death penalty. Our colonial history has witnessed many such executions.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other issues with such executions</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(a) Socio-Economic Factors</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The recent statistics shows that the death row prisoners in India are more from the backward classes of the society.</li>
<li>The death row prisoners belong to backward classes and religious minorities and the majority of convicts’ families are living in adjunct poverty.</li>
<li>These people who are backward both in economic and social respects, are not in a position to here expensive lawyers and get proper representation in the Court.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(b) Delayed Execution</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The law provides for a long process before the execution of the convicts actually takes place.</li>
<li>The unexplained delay in execution can be a ground for commutation of death penalty, and an inmate, his or her kin, or even a public-spirited citizen could file a writ petition seeking such commutation.</li>
<li>Their trials are often cruelly forced to endure long periods of uncertainty about their fate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward: Law Commission recommendations on death penalty</strong></h4>
<p>The Law Commission of India in its 262<sup>nd</sup> Report (August 2015) recommended that:</p>
<ul>
<li>Death penalty be <strong><u>abolished for all crimes other than terrorism related offences and waging war</u></strong>.</li>
<li>Measures such as police reforms, witness protection scheme and victim compensation scheme should be taken up expeditiously by the government.</li>
<li>It felt that time has come for India to move towards abolition of the death penalty. However the concern is often raised that abolition of death penalty for terrorism-related offences and waging war, will affect national security.</li>
</ul>
<p>Further, the Commission sincerely hopes that the movement towards absolute abolition will be swift and irreversible</p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/death-penalty-sc-moots-fair-hearing/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why we need to build a framework for best global digital governance affirmation</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/digital-governance/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<h4><strong><img alt="digital governance" class="alignnone wp-image-637976" height="444" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/CRN_Services_Portfolio_Technology_696-300x200.jpg" width="667"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In an interview earlier this month, Telecom Minister Ashwini Vaishnaw spoke about a comprehensive policy roadmap for India’s digital economy and digital governance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is digital governance ?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Electronic governance or e-governance can be defined as the usage of Information and Communication Technology (ICT) by the government to provide and facilitate government services, exchange of information, communication transactions and integration of various standalone systems and services.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is “global digital governance”?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Global digital governance encompasses the norms, institutions, and standards that shape the regulation around the development and use of these technologies. Digital governance has long-term commercial and political implications.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is it important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The main objective of e-governance is to provide a friendly, affordable, and efficient interface between a government and its people. It is about ensuring greater transparency, accountability and objectivity, resulting in cost-effective and high-quality public service.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the three domains of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/interactions-between-main-groups-in-e-governance-action-plan-for-india/">e-governance</a>?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>E-administration</strong>: improving government processes</li>
<li><strong>E-services</strong>: connecting individual citizens with their government</li>
<li><strong>E-society</strong>: building interactions with and within civil society.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="digital governance" class="alignnone wp-image-637977" height="422" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 546px) 100vw, 546px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital-India-and-E-governance-300x232.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital-India-and-E-governance-300x232.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Digital-India-and-E-governance.jpg 529w" width="546"/>Is there a historical parallel to governing key economic sectors globally?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Digital economy is not unprecedented:</strong> Sectors critical to the global economy are subject to international cooperation frameworks and pacts. Therefore, the idea of setting up a single multilateral organization with a mandate to govern the digital economy is not unprecedented.</li>
<li><strong>The International Commission for Air Navigation (ICAN): </strong>Global aviation has been regulated since 1903 when the International Commission for Air Navigation (ICAN) first met, subsequently replaced by the International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO) in 1947.</li>
<li><strong>Bank for International Settlements (BIS): </strong>Similarly, the modern international banking system is governed by the Bank for International Settlements (BIS), an institution initially set up in the interwar period in 1930 to oversee Germany’s reparations to the Allies under the Treaty of Versailles. The BIS acquired a more global mandate beginning in the 1950s and is now partially responsible for global financial stability.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who are the key players in the global contest for digital governance</strong>?</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>China seeks to champion the concept of cyber sovereignty: </strong>An authoritarian vision drives the first model. Most notably, China is emerging as the standard-bearer for this model with its desire to “reinvent the internet.” China seeks to champion the concept of “cyber sovereignty,” allowing countries to control access to the internet, censor content, and institute data localization requirements, as a pretext to protecting individual national interests.</li>
<li><strong>European Union’s General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR): </strong>Which provides a more democratic concept for digital governance. This model primarily seeks to protect the privacy and rights of internet users and online content consumers. Adopted with the overwhelming support of the European Parliament in 2014, the GDPR came into effect in May 2018, giving firms that rely on digital technologies the opportunity to modify their data usage and privacy policies. The adoption of the GDPR has been a turning point for global internet governance as consumers gained unprecedented control over their data in a manner that preserved freedom and openness online.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="digital governance" class="alignnone wp-image-637978" height="434" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 591px) 100vw, 591px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Syn-19-1-300x220.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Syn-19-1-300x220.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Syn-19-1.jpg 662w" width="591"/>Why global digital governance is important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Minimum rights and protections for platform workers</strong>: Under the G20, the International Labour Organisation has already placed a proposal in the employment working group for digital labour platforms to develop an international governance system determining minimum rights and protections for platform workers.</li>
<li><strong>Implementation of central bank digital currency projects: </strong>Similarly, on digital money, a reincarnated Bretton Woods is being advocated to address the distrust in private currencies and to coordinate the implementation of central bank digital currency projects.</li>
<li><strong>Digital taxation:</strong> Finally, in the deeply contested area of digital taxation, the OECD facilitated Base Erosion and Profit Shifting (BEPS) negotiations and helped arrive at a global solution.</li>
<li><strong>Digital sovereignty:</strong> The internet is splintering and digital sovereignty is now commonplace; yet, there is no better time for countries to come together and build a framework for global digital governance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="digital governance" class="alignnone wp-image-637981" height="357" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 570px) 100vw, 570px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/E-Governance-Kya-Hai-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/E-Governance-Kya-Hai-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/E-Governance-Kya-Hai-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/E-Governance-Kya-Hai.jpg 1000w" width="570"/>What are the big 5 tech companies called?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Big Five tech giants—Apple, Amazon, Google (Alphabet), Meta, and Microsoft.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The rapid digitalisation of the world along with a new focus on trust in the global supply chains for digital products and services presents tremendous opportunities for India and its youth.  It is now up to all of us to engage in a collective “sabka prayas” to realise New India’s economic potential.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. The rapid digitalisation of the world along with a new focus on trust in the global supply chains for digital products and services presents tremendous opportunities for India. Comment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/digital-governance/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Supreme Court’s basic structure doctrine in a new context</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/basic-structure/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Various judgements on basic structure</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Features of constitution</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="basic structure" class="alignnone wp-image-637988" height="285" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 506px) 100vw, 506px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BASIC-STRUCURE-DOCTRINE-IN-INDIAN-CONSTITUTION-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BASIC-STRUCURE-DOCTRINE-IN-INDIAN-CONSTITUTION-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BASIC-STRUCURE-DOCTRINE-IN-INDIAN-CONSTITUTION.jpg 560w" width="506"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The basic structure doctrine constitutes a high watermark in the assertion of the Supreme Court’s judicial power in the teeth of a determined majoritarian regime.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is basic structure of Constitution?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The basic structure doctrine is one of the fundamental judicial principles connected with the Indian Constitution. The doctrine of the basic structure holds that there is a basic structure to the Indian Constitution, and the Parliament of India cannot amend the basic features.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the significance of the basic structure in the Constitution of India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The doctrine of basic structure is nothing but a judicial innovation to ensure that the power of amendment is not misused by Parliament. The idea is that the basic features of the Constitution of India should not be altered to an extent that the identity of the Constitution is lost in the process.08-Dec-2021</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Courts are empowered under our Constitution to invalidate not only executive orders, but also legislative enactments that violate any part of the Fundamental Rights guaranteed in Part III of the Constitution (Bill of Rights).</li>
<li>But as to whether they are also empowered to adjudicate on the validity of constitutional amendments passed with the requisite special majority and following the procedure prescribed in Article 368 the Constitution is silent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="basic structure" class="alignnone wp-image-637989" height="412" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 731px) 100vw, 731px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r.jpeg 770w" width="731"/>Historical developments on evolution of basic structure doctrine </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Constitution provided a mechanism for parliament to amend the constitution in the form of article 368 but the nature and scope of this amending power was questioned in Supreme Court on multiple occasions. Supreme Court gave a series of judgement which ultimately culminated in probably the most landmark judgement Basic structure doctrine judgement.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Shankari Prasad Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Sajjan Singh Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Golakh Nath Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Kesvananda Bharati Case</strong></li>
<li><strong>Minerva Mills case</strong></li>
<li><strong>I.R. Koelhi</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Constitutional Provisions</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>1st amendment and 9th schedule</strong></li>
<li><strong>24th amendment</strong></li>
<li><strong>42nd amendment</strong></li>
</ol>
<p> </p>
<p>His holiness, Kesavananda bharati, challenged before the supreme court, the validity of 29th CAA which inserted some laws in 9th schedule and affected property of his Hindu Mutt.</p>
<h4><strong>What else was at stake?</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li>Supreme Court (R. C. Cooper case) had struck down bank nationalization act of 1969 which had nationalized 14 major banks for illusory compensation though it conceded parliament’s right to nationalise banks in national interest.</li>
<li>Supreme Court had struck down abolition of privy purses which was a betrayal of solemn promise to erstwhile kings by Sardar Patel.</li>
</ol>
<p>Supreme Court could do all this as it had held in 1967 in Golaknath case that fundamental rights could not be abridged.</p>
<p>Before returning back to Kesavananda, Let’s take a look at the relevant provisions of the constitution and Supreme Court interpretation of the same.</p>
<ul>
<li>Art 13(2) – Any LAW abridging fundamental rights mentioned in part 3 shall be null and void to the extent of contravention</li>
<li>Art 368 -Procedure to amend the constitution.</li>
<li>Art 19(f) – freedom to acquire hold on and dispose off property.</li>
<li>Art 31 – right to property</li>
</ul>
<p>Both the rights were subject to reasonable restriction in public interest and restriction were subject to judicial review.</p>
<p>Soon after the coming into force of the constitution, states enacted land reform acts #Zamindars challenged them. #Patna high court declared Bihar act as unconstitutional for violating right to property #interim parliament passed 1st CAA.</p>
<ol>
<li>ART 31B created 9th schedule. Laws inserted under it by constitutional amendment were immune to judicial review.</li>
</ol>
<p>Other provisions not imp for this article but imp for exams –</p>
<ol>
<li>Reasonable restrictions against freedom of expression under art 19.</li>
<li>To nullify judgment in State of Madras v. Champakam Dorairajan and giving effect to art 46 (promoting educational and economic interests of weaker sections) amplified article 15 (3)</li>
</ol>
<p>Zamindars didn’t like it, not one bit. And here comes the 1st salvo</p>
<h4><strong>Shankari Prasad v Union of India</strong></h4>
<p>Challenged 1st CAA. What was the court’s judgment?</p>
<ol>
<li>Difference b/w constituent power and ordinary legislative power i.e. amendment not law for the purpose of article 13</li>
<li>art 13 and 368 in conflict # apply DOCTRINE OF HARMONIOUS CONSTRUCTION # ART 13 not applicable to art 368</li>
</ol>
<p>Govt 1-0 Zamindars</p>
<p>Govt passed 17th amendment and inserted more laws under 9th schedule ‘</p>
<p>Zamindars fired another salvo-</p>
<h4><strong>Sajjan Singh vs state of rajasthan</strong></h4>
<p>Supreme Court sang Shankari prasad song again</p>
<p>Govt 2-0 jamindars</p>
<p>But Justice Mudholkar was of the view that the every Constitution has certain features which are basic in nature and those features cannot be changed.</p>
<p>2 minority judgements…. utter confusion. And you can see seeds of basic structure were sown here.</p>
<p>Zamindars fired 3rd salvo</p>
<h4><strong>Golaknath v. State of Punjab</strong></h4>
<p>11 judge bench overturned earlier 2 verdicts by a slender majority of 6-5</p>
<p>Really? What was the logic given here?</p>
<ol>
<li>Nothing to suggest constituent power to be separate from legislative power and even if distinct, amending power not same as constituent power which is given only to constituent assembly i.e. amendment is law and subject to article 13</li>
<li>Fundamental rights so sacrosanct and transcendental that they cannot be abridged even if whole parliament unanimously decided to abridge them.</li>
</ol>
<p>But it validated all previous land reform acts as nullifying them would create utter confusion</p>
<p>Govt angry – Zamindars angry</p>
<p>New landlords happy.</p>
<p>Loss – loss to defendants as well as petitioner.</p>
<p>Madam Indira was in power and she did not like this. Not one bit.</p>
<p>Along came 24th amendment to neutralize GOLAKNATH JUDGEMENT</p>
<ol>
<li>Art 13 inapplicable to art 368</li>
<li>Art 368 provided powers as well as procedure to amend the constitution</li>
<li>Parliament by way of addition, variation or repeal can amend any provision of constitution</li>
<li>President shall give assent to CA bills ( VERY VERY IMP FOR PRELIMS )</li>
</ol>
<p>But madam Indira wouldn’t just stop here as Cooper judgment (Bank nationalization ) also had to be neutralized.</p>
<p>Smarting from this setback, Madam Indira (the parliament, herself) passed 24th CAA to neutralise GOLAKNATH judgement. But there was also a small matter of reversing Copper judgment in bank nationalisation case so parliament passed 25th CAA.</p>
<ol>
<li>Art 19f delinked from 31, in effect parliament deciding compensation amount payable instead of courts.</li>
<li>Art 31c  -inserted under which – art 39b and c, most socialist of DPSPs (equitable distribution and prevention of concentration of wealth respectively) precede over 7 freedoms (art 19 ), equality (14), property (31)</li>
<li>Parliament’s power to determine if policy is to give effect to 39b and c not subject to judicial review.</li>
</ol>
<p>29th CAA had put Kerala land reform act under 9th schedule and his holiness challenged the provisions and all hell broke loose.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Now the 4th salvo</p>
<h4><strong><img alt="basic structure" class="alignnone wp-image-637990" height="345" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 616px) 100vw, 616px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1-300x168.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1-300x168.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1-768x431.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Supreme-Court-new-social-image1.jpg 896w" width="616"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/kesavananda-bharati-case-1973-the-judgment-that-upheld-basic-structure-of-indias-constitution/">Kesvanada Bharati Case</a></strong></h4>
<p>A 13 judge bench is constituted and what does it do!</p>
<ol>
<li>Overturned Golaknath i.e. amendment not law, fundamental rights amendable, no implied limit under art 368 i.e. CAA 24 constitutional</li>
<li>Art 25 invalid to the extent it takes away judicial review i.e. 39 b and c above 14, 19 and 31 but subject to judicial review</li>
</ol>
<p>Most imp decision of all by slimmest of all 7-6 majority stated Parliament can amend any provision of the Constitution but the basic structure should not be destroyed, damaged or abrogated.</p>
<p>What’s the logic?</p>
<ol>
<li>Expression amendment did not encompass defacing the constitution such that it lost its identity.</li>
<li>In the garb of amendment parliament can not rewrite the constitution.</li>
</ol>
<p>Court gave relief to govt but reserved for itself power to review all amendment not just those that violate fundamental rights.</p>
<p>Aftermath</p>
<p>Indira Gandhi didn’t like the judgement one  bit. She (via the president) superseded 3 judges to appoint justice A.N. Ray as CJI.</p>
<p>Knives had been drawn and the battle was gonna be very bloody –</p>
<ul>
<li>Navnirman movement of JP (Jayprakash<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jayaprakash_Narayan" rel="noopener" target="_blank">)</a> had gathered steam, Indira was on the back foot and along came the judgement of Allahabad High Court convicting Indira of corrupt electoral practices. Election was declared null and void and  6 years ban to contest election was imposed on her.</li>
<li>Supreme Court stayed it and allowed her to remain PM but not to draw salary or speak or vote in parliament.</li>
<li>Darkest chapter in democracy’ 21 month emergency was declared on 25th June 1975 without even consulting cabinet (44th amendment made it mandatory for the president to have written advice of cabinet to declare emergency)</li>
</ul>
<p>Indira Gandhi wasn’t to sit quiet.</p>
<p>CAA 39th – election of president, VP, PM and speaker beyond judicial review</p>
<p>Clownish Rajnarayan challenged the CAA 39.</p>
<h4><strong>Indira Gandhi v/s Raj Narain Case</strong></h4>
<p>For the 1st time Supreme Court applied basic structure doctrine and considered free and fair election and rule of law to be part of basic structure. #amending act invalidated.</p>
<p>Note here that 4 of the 5 judges on the bench had given dissenting judgment in Bharati case but still applied the same doctrine for Supreme Court judgment becomes law until overruled by bigger bench (art 141).</p>
<p>Then how did Indira continue to be prime minister and contest election again and not get banned for 6 years?</p>
<p>Supreme court accepted retrospective amendment to electoral law i.e. electoral malpractice of Indira was no longer a corrupt practice.</p>
<p>Find out for fun the charges against Mrs. Gandhi for which she was convicted and what a popular British magazine had to say about the judgement.</p>
<p>Along came the mini constitution i.e 42nd amendment act TO ELIMINATE IMPEDIMENTS TO THE GROWTH OF THE CONSTITUTION –</p>
<ol>
<li>PART 4a fundamental duties</li>
<li>Socialist,secular and integrity word to preamble</li>
<li>New <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/indepth-understanding-of-the-directive-principles-of-state-policy/">DPSP</a>s were added</li>
</ol>
<p>And for the purpose of this article amendment to article 368 nullifying basic structure doctrine by adding amendments can’t be challenged in courts and parliament possessing unlimited power of amendment</p>
<ol start="4">
<li>All DPSPs to take precedence over all fundamental rights not just 39b and 39c.</li>
</ol>
<p>And Minerva Textile mills of Karnataka fired the 5th and the last salvo</p>
<h4><strong>Minerva Mills v Union of India</strong></h4>
<p>SC unanimously struck down amendment to article 368 holding limited amending power and judicial review to be part of basic structure.</p>
<p>Court held that constitution is founded on the bedrock of balance b/w FRs and DPSPs. Goals set out by DPSPs have to be achieved without abrogation of means provided by FRs.</p>
<p>What’s the logic?</p>
<p>If a donee was vested with limited power, it could not be exercised to control that very power power and convert into unlimited one.</p>
<p>Or</p>
<p>If a genie grants u 3 wishes, it is understood u can not, as one of the wish, ask for unlimited number of wishes!</p>
<p>Janta govt comes to power and 44th CAA deletes art 31 (b) right to property and 19 (f) freedom to acquire, hold and dispose of property as they were not considered part of basic structure</p>
<p>Right to property now a constitutional right under art 300A.</p>
<p>9th schedule and judicial review</p>
<h4><strong>I.R.Coelho vs state of TN</strong></h4>
<p>Supreme Court held that acts placed under 9th schedule after basic structure subject would be subject to judicial review to the extent of those acts violating basic structure of constitution.</p>
<p>Impact of basic structure doctrine.</p>
<p>It certainly saved Indian democracy from degenerating into authoritarian regime during those testing times but it has also given immense untold unbridled power to Supreme Court and made it the most powerful court in the world.</p>
<p>As we would later see in the NJAC Verdict (let’s call it 4th judges case), Supreme Court applied this doctrine, many would say for wrong reasons to strike down the act and kept for itself the power to appoint brother judges. In the original constitution only fetters on the power of parliament was art 13.</p>
<p>Relevance –  It was delivered at the time of single party rule both at the centre and most of the states. In the era of coalition politics no govt is going to wield so much power to destroy the constitution and then there is ever present danger of tyranny of unelected.</p>
<p>But only legitimate way to overturn the verdict would be a 15 judge bench so don’t hold your breath for that.</p>
<p>Now is the time for some thought questions</p>
<p>#1. Consider these 2 statements –</p>
<ol>
<li>Any LAW that is ordinary law violating provisions of constitution would be declared null and void to the extent of contravention.</li>
<li>Any LAW violating art 13 would be declared null and void</li>
</ol>
<p>Both statements are true…..If amendments were not law, what was the purpose of art 13 (2) other laws would anyway be declared unconstitutional!</p>
<p>#2. Is basic structure doctrine relevant in the present political scenario where no single party is unlikely to enjoy majority in both the houses?</p>
<p>#3. What should be the limits to amending power of parliament? Do u think for very substantial amendments instead of courts, people by way of referendum should determine whether amendment should go through or not?</p>
<p>#4. Whatever happens to original intent theory that constitutional courts have to interpret constitution in accordance with the implied intentions of founding fathers and there is enough evidence to suggest founding fathers thoughtfully kept FRs sacrosanct to prevent their abrogation or as we would see in a later article how supreme court by creative interpretation virtually changed procedure established by law in art 21 to due process of law while founding fathers deliberately kept expression as procedure established by law.</p>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>By restraining the amending powers of legislative organ of State, it provided basic Rights to Citizens which no organ of State can overrule. Being dynamic in nature, it is more progressive and open to changes in time unlike the rigid nature of earlier judgements.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong> Q. What do you understand by basic structure of constitution? Trace evolution of basic structure in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/basic-structure/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The hijab case and the doctrine of essentiality</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/doctrine-of-essentiality-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of doctrine of essentiality</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>judicial reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="doctrine of essentiality" class="alignnone wp-image-638019" height="496" sizes="(max-width: 755px) 100vw, 755px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/19hijab-1140302-1661758240-300x197.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/19hijab-1140302-1661758240-300x197.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/19hijab-1140302-1661758240-1024x671.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/19hijab-1140302-1661758240.jpg 1200w" width="755"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A two-judge Bench of the Supreme Court of India is presently hearing arguments on the correctness of a Karnataka High Court judgment that upheld the ban on the use of the hijab by students in Karnataka which raises question on doctrine of essentiality.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> </strong><strong>What is ‘doctrine of essentiality’? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A seven-judge Bench of the Supreme Court invented the doctrine of “essentiality” in the Shirur Mutt case in 1954. The court held that the term “religion” will cover all rituals and practices “integral” to a religion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Importance doctrine of essentiality</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the legal framework, the doctrine of essentiality is a doctrine that has evolved to protect the religious practices that are essential or integral and does not violate any fundamental right. India being a secular country has discrete religious beliefs and to deny any is to violate the freedom of religion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why hijab is not an essential practice?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Wearing of hijab (head scarf) by Muslim women does not form a part of essential religious practices in Islamic faith and it is not protected under the right to freedom of religion guaranteed under Article 25 of the Constitution of India, the High Court of Karnataka declared on March 15 2022.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="doctrine of essentiality" class="alignnone wp-image-638020" height="366" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 594px) 100vw, 594px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/r04jg7b8_hijab-row-protest_650x400_15_February_22-300x185.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/r04jg7b8_hijab-row-protest_650x400_15_February_22-300x185.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/r04jg7b8_hijab-row-protest_650x400_15_February_22.jpg 650w" width="594"/>Is hijab essential part of Islam?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Qur’an instructs Muslim women and men to dress modestly, and for some, the hijab is worn by Muslim girls and women to maintain modesty and privacy from unrelated males. According to the Encyclopedia of Islam and Muslim World, modesty concerns both men’s and women’s “gaze, gait, garments, and genitalia”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How do you identify essential religion practice?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Court observed that in order to determine whether or not a particular practice is an essential part of religion, the test must be whether the absence of the practice itself</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/op-ed-snap-the-warp-and-weft-of-religious-liberty/"><strong>Meaning of Article 26</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Freedom to manage religious affairs Subject to public order, morality and health, every religious denomination or any section thereof shall have the right.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="doctrine of essentiality" class="alignnone wp-image-638021" height="417" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 626px) 100vw, 626px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hijab-3-16625569443x2-1.jpg 1200w" width="626"/>Examples of the essential religious practices test</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While these issues are largely understood to be community-based, there are instances in which the court has applied the test to individual freedoms as well.</li>
<li>In a 2004 ruling, the Supreme Court held that the Ananda Marga sect had no fundamental right <strong>to <u>perform the Tandava dance in public</u></strong> streets since it did not constitute an essential religious practice of the sect.</li>
<li>For example, in 2016, the Supreme Court upheld the discharge of an airman from the Indian Air Force <strong>for <u>keeping a beard</u>.</strong></li>
<li>It distinguished the case of a Muslim airman from that of Sikhs who are allowed to keep a beard.</li>
<li>In 2015, the Supreme Court restored <strong>the<u> Jain religious practice of Santhara/Sallekhan</u>a</strong> (a ritualistic fast unto death) by staying an order of the Rajasthan HC.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="doctrine of essentiality" class="alignnone wp-image-637989" height="336" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 596px) 100vw, 596px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/SupremeCoaurtPTI1_PT12I12r.jpeg 770w" width="596"/>What is the Supreme Court’s judgement on Doctrine of Essentiality?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The doctrine of “essentiality” was invented by a seven-judge Bench of the Supreme Court in the ‘Shirur Mutt’ case in 1954.</li>
<li>It is a contentious doctrine evolved by the court to protect only such religious practices which were essential and integral to the religion.</li>
<li>The court held that the term “religion” will cover all rituals and practices “integral” to a religion, and took upon itself the responsibility of determining the essential and non-essential practices of a religion.</li>
<li>Referring to the Ayodhya case, the Constitution Bench had ruled in 1994 that A mosque is not an essential part of the practice of the religion of Islam and namaz (prayer) by Muslims can be offered anywhere, even in open.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How has the doctrine been used in subsequent years?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ‘essentiality doctrine’ of the Supreme Court has been criticised by several constitutional experts.</li>
<li>Scholars of constitutional law have argued that the essentiality/integrality doctrine has tended to lead the court into an area that is beyond its competence, and given judges the power to decide purely religious questions.</li>
<li>As a result, over the years, courts have been inconsistent on this question — in some cases they have relied on religious texts to determine essentiality.</li>
<li>In others it relied on the empirical behaviour of followers, and in yet others, based on whether the practice existed at the time the religion originated.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues over the doctrine</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the beginning, the court engaged with the question of whether untouchability, manifested in restrictions on entry into temples, was an “essential part of the Hindu religion”.</li>
<li>After examining selected Hindu texts, it came to the conclusion that untouchability was not an essential Hindu practice.</li>
<li>The idea of providing constitutional protection only to those elements of religion which the court considers “essential” is problematic as it assumes that one element or practice of religion is independent of other elements or practices.</li>
<li>So, while the essentiality test privileges certain practices over others, it is, in fact, all practices taken together that constitute a religion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does essentiality square up against religious freedom?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Freedom of religion was meant to guarantee freedom to practice one’s beliefs based on the concept of “inward association” of man with God.</li>
<li>The apex court in ‘Ratilal Panachand Gandhi vs The State of Bombay and Ors’ (March 18, 1954) acknowledged that “every person has a fundamental right to entertain such religious beliefs as may be approved by his judgment or conscience”.</li>
<li>The framers of the Constitution wanted to give this autonomy to each individual. Scholars have argued that the essentiality test impinges on this autonomy.</li>
<li>The apex court has itself emphasised autonomy and choice in its Privacy (2017), 377 (2018), and Adultery (2018) judgments.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Its effect on society</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Narrowing of safeguards to religious customs:</strong> It has allowed the Court to narrow the extent of safeguards available to religious customs by directly impinging on the autonomy of groups to decide for themselves what they deem valuable, violating, in the process, their right to ethical independence.</li>
<li><strong>Negated legislation that might otherwise enhance the cause of social</strong> <strong>justice</strong>: It has also negated legislation that might otherwise enhance the cause of social justice by holding that such laws cannot under any circumstances encroach on matters integral to the practice of a religion. For example, in 1962, the Court struck down a Bombay law that prohibited excommunications made by the Dai of the Dawoodi Bohra community when it held that the power to excommunicate is an essential facet of faith and that any measure aimed at social welfare cannot reform a religion out of its existence.</li>
<li><strong>A principle of anti-exclusion:</strong> Its application would require the Court to presume that a practice asserted by a religious group is, in fact, essential to the proponents of its faith. But regardless of such grounding, the Constitution will not offer protection to the practice if it excludes people on grounds of caste, gender, or other discriminatory criteria.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>For now, any Court hearing a matter touching upon a matter of faith has the unenviable task of acting not merely as an expert on law but also as an expert on religion.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Every person has a fundamental right to entertain such religious beliefs as may be approved by his judgment or conscience. Critically examine in context of doctrine of essentiality.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/doctrine-of-essentiality-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>