<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 08:16:30 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Domestic violence needs to stop for true women empowerment</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/domestic-violence/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>women empowerment</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="domestic violence" class="alignnone wp-image-638948" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 501px) 100vw, 501px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101-1024x681.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101-768x511.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Street_Theatre_on_Domestic_Violence_-_Bridge_Market_Plaza_-_Chandigarh_2016-08-07_9101.jpg 1200w" width="501"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Due to prevalence of patriarchy women have been discriminated not only in India but in most parts of the world. According to The United Nations, one out of every three women experience domestic violence. The same UN report suggests that the most dangerous place for women is their home. Gender equality and women’s empowerment are essential for the development and well-being of families, communities and nations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How UN women defines Violence against women and girls</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Any act of gender-based violence that results in, or is likely to result in, physical, sexual or mental harm or suffering to women and girls, including threats of such acts, coercion or arbitrary deprivation of liberty, whether occurring in public or in private life.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why Women are the victim</strong>?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Domestic violence is one of the most common forms of violence experienced by women globally.</li>
<li>Women are usually the victim of domestic violence that derives from unequal power relationships between men and women.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="domestic violence" class="alignnone wp-image-638960" height="443" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 575px) 100vw, 575px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/76064761-300x231.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/76064761-300x231.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/76064761.jpg 635w" width="575"/>Why there is recent spike in violence against women?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to UN, Violence against women and girls is one of the world’s most prevalent human rights violations, taking place every day, many times over, in every corner of the world.</li>
<li><strong>Conditions created by the pandemic</strong> – including lockdowns, reduced mobility, heightened isolation, stress and economic uncertainty have led to an alarming spike in domestic violence and have further exposed women and girls to other forms of violence, from child marriage to sexual harassment online.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Domestic violence?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Domestic violence is any pattern of behavior that is used to gain or maintain power and control over an intimate partner. It encompasses all physical, sexual, emotional, economic and psychological actions or threats of actions that influence another person.</li>
<li><strong>Domestic violence</strong> <strong>can include the following.</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Psychological violence: </strong>Psychological violence involves causing fear, threatening physical harm or forcing isolation from friends, family, school or work<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Economic violence: </strong>Making or attempting to make a person financially dependent by maintaining total control over financial resources.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Emotional violence: </strong>Undermining a person’s sense of self-worth through constant criticism; belittling one’s abilities; verbal abuse.</li>
<li><strong>Physical violence: </strong>Use of Physical force or hurting or trying to hurt a partner .it also includes denying medical care.</li>
<li><strong>Sexual violence: </strong>Forcing a partner to take part in a sex act when the partner does not consent</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the current Status in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Nearly one-third of women in India have experienced physical or sexual violence</li>
<li>The most common type of spousal violence is physical violence (28%), followed by emotional violence and sexual violence</li>
<li>While domestic violence against women has declined from 31.2% to 29.3% in the country, 30% women between the age of 18 and 49 have experienced physical violence since the age of 15 years, while 6% have experienced sexual violence in their lifetime,.</li>
<li>Only 14% of women who have experienced physical or sexual violence by anyone have brought the issue up.</li>
<li>32% of married women (18-49 years) have experienced physical, sexual, or emotional spousal violence.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Recent findings from National Family health Survey Report-5</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Status</strong>: Domestic violence against women is highest in Karnataka at 48%, followed by Bihar, Telangana, Manipur and Tamil Nadu. Lakshawdeep has the least domestic violence at 2.1%.</li>
<li><strong>Rural</strong>–<strong>urban difference</strong>: Physical violence is more common among women in rural areas (32%) as compared to their urban areas (24%).</li>
<li><strong>Impact of schooling and education: </strong>40% women with no schooling are subject to physical violence compared to 18% who completed their schooling.</li>
<li><strong>Impact of employment and wealth:</strong> The experience of physical violence ranges between 39% among women in the lowest wealth quintile and 17% in the highest wealth quintile.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong> </strong><strong>Why women left behind as compared to men in India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Patriarchal structure: </strong>Patriarchal structures and ideologies and the mindset lead to women subordination and gender inequalities</li>
<li><strong>Low sex ratio: </strong>Sex ratios for women in India Is not good comparatively. It was even bad at the time of independence.</li>
<li><strong>Life expectancy</strong>: Women’s life expectancy, health, nutritional levels are significantly lower than that of men.</li>
<li><strong>Education: </strong>low investment on girl education, Girl children are kept out of schools, or made drop out of school at early age, girl is considered as burden on family in many societies.</li>
<li><strong>Employment</strong>: even if they are educated they are not allowed to work by their families Discrimination at the workplaces, lower wages for the work of equal value<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Decision making: </strong>The have little say in the families, socio economic, legal and political rules and policy formulations. Very limited or no decision making power.</li>
<li><strong>Political participation: </strong>The participation of women in political and social decision making power is abysmally low. Their number in parliament has never exceeded more than 10%.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-empowerment/"><strong>What can be done for empowering women?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Recognition: </strong>Recognition of women as productive, vital agents of family and environment should be a precondition for addressing their social needs. We need to change the way they are perceived.</li>
<li><strong>Treatment: </strong>They must not be only treated only as objects of welfare but needed to be treated as those who are contributing to the economy.</li>
<li><strong>Health: </strong>To provide quality and affordable healthcare and must be easily accessible.</li>
<li><strong>Education: </strong>Education of women is the most important component for women’s empowerment.</li>
<li><strong>Safe and secure environment: </strong>providing safety and security is the precondition for empowerment and social justice.</li>
<li><strong>Economic Independence: </strong>Helping women to stand on their legs, become independent and also to earn for their family is necessary to empowering women and to raise their hand in decision making process of family, society and nation</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="domestic violence" class="alignnone wp-image-638986" height="349" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 537px) 100vw, 537px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Downloads2-300x195.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Downloads2-300x195.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Downloads2.jpg 620w" width="537"/>Woman as the foundation stone of every family, society and nation</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has an ancient woman worship tradition.</li>
<li>In India we see woman as a mother goddess. There are no of evidences to support this idea</li>
<li>For instance the Sanskrit text “Yatra naryastu pujyante ramante tatra Devata”which means where women are honored, there gods resides.</li>
<li>Which means there is a overall development if the women of the family is happy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="domestic violence" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-639056" height="158" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Top-10-Richest-Women-In-India.jpg 1200w" width="300"/>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Domestic violence against women is major obstacle on progress on achieving development targets. Without addressing it, anybody have little chance of meeting millennium development. Recognition of women as productive, vital agents of family and environment should be a precondition for addressing their social needs. Gender equality and women’s empowerment are essential for the development and well-being of families, communities and nations.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Empowering women on every front is the pre-condition for the overall development of the nation. Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/domestic-violence/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The problem of fly ash generation and its proper disposal and usage</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fly-ash/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>composition of fly ash</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>environmental pollution</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="fly ash" class="alignnone wp-image-639139" height="352" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 542px) 100vw, 542px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.28841000_1663768775_0-300x195.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.28841000_1663768775_0-300x195.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.28841000_1663768775_0-768x498.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/0.28841000_1663768775_0.jpg 1024w" width="542"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India depends heavily on coal for power generation. This creates the problem of fly-ash generation and its proper disposal, usage.</li>
<li>The <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/national-green-tribunal-ngt/">National Green Tribunal (NGT)</a> noted September 19, 2022 that there was an urgent need to augment the utilisation and disposal of fly ash in Chhattisgarh.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is fly ash?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fly ash is a by-product of coal combustion. It contains Aluminium Silicate, SiO2, CaO, oxides of iron, magnesium and toxic metals like lead, arsenic, cobalt, and copper.</li>
<li>It can travel to far places. India is growing to double its power generation in the next decade and with coal being the biggest source of fuel for power generation, the problem of fly ash is going to increase too.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fly ash " class="alignnone wp-image-639140" height="623" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 467px) 100vw, 467px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-225x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-225x300.jpg 225w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-1535x2048.jpg 1535w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-675x900.jpg 675w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-1200x1601.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-1980x2641.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/38631_3x4-scaled.jpg 1919w" width="467"/>Environmental Problems with fly ash </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A large quantity of fly ash dumped into poorly designed and maintained ash ponds. About a billion tonnes of this toxic ash lie dumped in these ponds, polluting land, air, and water.</li>
<li>All the heavy metals found in fly ash—nickel, cadmium, arsenic, chromium, lead, etc—are toxic in nature. They leech into the surrounding soil and can enter food-chains.</li>
<li>Fly ash gets easily ingested through respiration, which causes many diseases such as asthma, neurological disorders.</li>
<li>Suspended fly ash in the air acts as a global warming agent and heats the earth’s surface.</li>
<li>Fly ash settles on leaves and crops and reduces crop productivity.</li>
<li>It pollutes the groundwater.</li>
<li>There is a reduction in recharging of groundwater due to fly ash filled mine voids.</li>
<li>Reduces visibility by creating dense fog in the winter season.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fly ash" class="alignnone wp-image-639144" height="339" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 581px) 100vw, 581px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/flyash-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/flyash-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/flyash-768x449.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/flyash.jpg 900w" width="581"/>Issues with fly ash management</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The government mandates that all coal power plants (CPPs) reach 100% utilization of fly ash.</li>
<li>Along with it, CPPs should give a certain amount of fly ash free of cost for MSMEs to manufacture bricks, tiles and rest of the fly ash should be sold to other industries.</li>
<li>CPPs will have to maintain fly ash ponds to reduce its suspension in air.</li>
<li>But all these steps for utilization areas are problematic as they do little to mitigate these risks.</li>
<li>The pricing of fly ash is increasingly becoming a contentious issue that is hampering its gainful utilization.</li>
<li>The current approaches to evaluating risks with fly ash disposal are very limited, and they may underestimate the true risks</li>
<li>In spite of initiatives taken by the government, several nongovernmental and research and development organizations for fly ash utilization, the level of fly ash utilization in the country is quite low at only 38% which is less than the global standards.</li>
<li>Hence, rather than being utilized, fly ash is being stored despite warnings from regulators.</li>
<li>Deposition in storage places has negative influences on water and soil because of their mineral composition as well as morphology and filtration properties.</li>
<li>Ash-handling units are the biggest consumers of water in CPPs. The government advocates the designed ash-to-water ratios as approximately 1:5 for fly ash, but the observed ratios have been around 1:20.</li>
<li>Certain states have discouraged the use of blended cement and fly ash bricks in public works.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fly ash" class="alignnone wp-image-639142" height="353" loading="lazy" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/images-4.jpeg" width="630"/>The above issues can be addressed by</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Greater regulatory oversight and price control,</li>
<li>Revision of cement blending standards,</li>
<li>Research in improving fly ash quality,</li>
<li>Reducing the cost of transportation,</li>
<li>Provisions for overcoming information asymmetries,</li>
<li>Incentivising use in brick kilns for producing fly ash bricks,</li>
<li>Overall sensitization of key decision-makers on the matter.</li>
<li>Instead of dumping it on ash ponds, can be used for construction due to its reuse as pozzolan, and replacement of portland cement by hydraulic cement</li>
<li>Due to its grain size distribution, enhanced strength permeability, it can be used to construct embankments at road construction, concrete dams like GHATGHAR DAM</li>
<li>Strong penalties for those production units who do not use proper filtration devices</li>
<li>Moving to renewable energy production away from coal-based thermal production.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Utilization of Fly Ash is not only possible but also essential. In this context “Fly Ash Mission of Government of India” is a slow but steady start, the pace of which needs to be ramped up. An honest effort is required by the concerned stakeholders to improve the perceptions of fly ash-based cement or concrete; increase its use, particularly for government works; and impart scientific knowledge about fly ash, its uses, and possible impacts.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What is fly ash? Discuss the environmental challenges it poses. Suggest how to address the situation. </strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fly-ash/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Dvorak Technique of Weather Forecasting</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dvorak-technique-of-weather-forecasting/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Dvorak Technique</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Weather forecasting</p></div></div><p>Recently, the American meteorologist Vernon Dvorak passed away at the age of 100 who pioneered the widely used Dvorak Technique.</p>
<h4>Who was Vernon Dvorak?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dvorak was an American meteorologist best credited for developing the Dvorak (read as Do-rak) technique in the early 1970s.</li>
<li>The technique helps forecast the tropical storm.</li>
<li>His technique has saved the lives of millions of people across the world and will continue to do so.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the Dvorak technique?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Dvorak technique was first developed in 1969 and tested for observing storms in the northwest Pacific Ocean.</li>
<li>Forecasters used the available satellite images obtained from polar orbiting satellites to examine the features of the developing tropical storms (hurricanes, cyclones and typhoons).</li>
<li>During day time, images in the visible spectrum were used while at night, the ocean would be observed using infrared images.</li>
<li>It was a cloud pattern recognition technique based on a concept model of the development and decay of the tropical cyclone.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why is technique still widely in use?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Unlike land, ocean observations in the 1970s were sparse.</li>
<li>Today, there continues to be an improved network of land-based meteorological observations, either in the form of taking manual observations, installing automatic weather stations or automatic rain gauges.</li>
<li>On the other hand, ocean observations still remain limited.</li>
<li>There are many vast regions across the four oceans that have not been fully examined with meteorological instruments.</li>
<li>Ocean observations are mostly taken by deploying buoys or dedicated ships, but the number of observations from the seas is still not sufficient across the world.</li>
<li>That is why meteorologists have had to depend more on satellite-based imageries, and combine it with the available ocean-data at the time of forecasting the intensity and wind speed of the tropical cyclones.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dvorak-technique-of-weather-forecasting/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>NASA’s DART mission prepares for an asteroid Dimorphos collision</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dart-mission-prepares-for-an-asteroid-dimorphos-collision/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>DART Mission, Didymos, Dimorphos</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="dart" class="alignnone wp-image-639369 size-full" height="1497" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-scaled.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-scaled.jpg 2560w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-1024x599.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-768x449.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-1536x898.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-2048x1197.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-1200x702.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dart-1980x1158.jpg 1980w" width="2560"/></p>
<p>In the first-of-its kind NASA’s DART Mission is about to hit a small, harmless asteroid millions of miles away.</p>
<h4><strong>What is DART Mission?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The main aim of the mission is to test the newly developed technology that would allow a spacecraft to crash into an asteroid and change its course.</li>
<li>It is a suicide mission and the spacecraft will be completely destroyed.</li>
<li>The target of the spacecraft is a small moonlet called Dimorphos (Greek for “two forms”).</li>
<li>It is about 160-metre in diameter and the spacecraft is expected to collide when it is 11 million kilometres away from Earth.</li>
<li>Dimorphos orbits a larger asteroid named Didymos (Greek for “twin”) which has a diameter of 780 metres.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why Dimorphos?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Didymos is a perfect system for the test mission because it is an eclipsing binary which means it has a moonlet that regularly orbits the asteroid.</li>
<li>It is observable when it passes in front of the main asteroid.</li>
<li>Earth-based telescopes can study this variation in brightness to understand how long it takes Dimorphos to orbit Didymos.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Collision course</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At the time of impact, Didymos and Dimorphos will be relatively close to Earth – within 6.8 million miles (11 million kilometers).</li>
<li>The spacecraft will accelerate at about 24,140 kilometers per hour when it collides with Dimorphos.</li>
<li>It aims to crash into Dimorphos to change the asteroid’s motion in space.</li>
<li>This collision will be recorded by LICIACube, or Light Italian CubeSat for Imaging of Asteroids, a companion cube satellite provided by the Italian Space Agency.</li>
<li>Three minutes after impact, the CubeSat will fly by Dimorphos to capture images and video.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why such mission?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Dimorphos was chosen for this mission because its size is relative to asteroids that could pose a threat to Earth.</li>
<li>The spacecraft is about 100 times smaller than Dimorphos, so it won’t obliterate the asteroid.</li>
<li>The fast impact will only change Dimorphos’ speed as it orbits Didymos by 1%, which doesn’t sound like a lot — but it will change the moon’s orbital period.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/dart-mission-prepares-for-an-asteroid-dimorphos-collision/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>New Account Settlement System for Stock Trading</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/new-account-settlement-system-for-stock-trading/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Account settlement, T+1</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>NA</p></div></div><p>Beginning October 1, the new account settlement system for the stock broking industry will kick in under the new guidelines issued by the Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI).</p>
<h4><strong>What is Settlement of Accounts?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The SEBI mandates stockbrokers to settle i.e., transfer the available credit balance from trading account to bank account, at least once in a quarter (90 days) or 30 days.</li>
<li>The process of transferring the unutilised funds back into the bank account is called ‘Running Account Settlement’ or ‘Quarterly Settlement of Funds’.</li>
<li>The funds are transferred back to the primary bank account of the customer that is linked to the trading account.</li>
<li>As per the latest guidelines, the settlement will now be done on the first Friday of the quarter or the month depending upon the option selected by the customer.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are SEBI’s new settlement guidelines?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>On July 27, SEBI issued new guidelines on running accounts of client funds and securities lying with the broker.</li>
<li>As per the new guidelines, with effect from October 1, 2022, the settlement of running account of clients’ funds will be done by the trading members after considering the end of the day (EOD) obligation of funds.</li>
<li>In cases where the client has opted for a monthly settlement process, then the running account shall be settled on the first Friday of every month.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How will it impact investors and traders?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Changes in settlement brought in by SEBI over the last few years have had the aim of protecting the investor and preventing the misuse as money lying in trading accounts of investors for long periods.</li>
<li>SEBI’s move will give certainty to investors and trading members.</li>
<li>It will help brokers develop a system just like banks, which credit interest in the accounts of their customers at the end of the quarter.</li>
<li>Another advantage would be that if a customer has more than one demat account with different brokers, having one settlement date for the entire industry will make it easier for her to keep track of her funds.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4><strong>Back2Basics: Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The SEBI is the regulatory body for securities and commodity market in India under the jurisdiction of Ministry of Finance Government of India.</li>
<li>It was established on 12 April 1988 and given Statutory Powers on 30 January 1992 through the SEBI Act, 1992.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Jurisdiction of SEBI</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>SEBI has to be responsive to the needs of three groups, which constitute the market:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Issuers of securities</li>
<li>Investors</li>
<li>Market intermediaries</li>
</ol>
<p>SEBI has three powers rolled into one body: quasi-legislative, quasi-judicial and quasi-executive.</p>
<ul>
<li>It drafts regulations in its legislative capacity, it conducts investigation and enforcement action in its executive function and it passes rulings and orders in its judicial capacity.</li>
<li>Though this makes it very powerful, there is an appeal process to create accountability.</li>
<li>There is a Securities Appellate Tribunal which is a three-member tribunal and is currently headed by Justice Tarun Agarwala, former Chief Justice of the Meghalaya High Court.</li>
<li>A second appeal lies directly to the Supreme Court.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="0GTrfivoMm"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sebi-introduces-t1-settlement-system/">SEBI introduces T+1 Settlement System</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="0GTrfivoMm" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sebi-introduces-t1-settlement-system/embed/#?secret=ZkM1JNKkw9#?secret=0GTrfivoMm" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“SEBI introduces T+1 Settlement System” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/new-account-settlement-system-for-stock-trading/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Carbon Dating?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-carbon-dating/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Carbon Dating</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="carbon dating" class="alignnone wp-image-639365 size-full" height="694" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 618px) 100vw, 618px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/carbon-dating.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/carbon-dating.jpg 618w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/carbon-dating-267x300.jpg 267w" width="618"/></p>
<p>A Varanasi district court has issued notice regarding carbon-dating of the disputed structure known to have been found inside the premises of the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/gyanvapi-kashi-vishwanath-temple-complex-dispute/">Gyanvapi mosque</a>.</p>
<h4>What is Carbon Dating?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Carbon dating, also called radiocarbon dating is method of age determination that depends upon the decay to nitrogen of radiocarbon (Carbon-14).</li>
<li>This method was developed by the American physicist Willard F. Libby about 1946.</li>
<li>Carbon-14 is continually formed in nature by the interaction of neutrons with nitrogen-14 in the Earth’s atmosphere.</li>
<li>The neutrons required for this reaction are produced by cosmic rays interacting with the atmosphere.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How it works?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Radiocarbon present in molecules of atmospheric carbon dioxide enters the biological carbon cycle: it is absorbed from the air by green plants and then passed on to animals through the food chain.</li>
<li>Radiocarbon decays slowly in a living organism, and the amount lost is continually replenished as long as the organism takes in air or food.</li>
<li>Once the organism dies, however, it ceases to absorb carbon-14, so that the amount of the radiocarbon in its tissues steadily decreases.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The half-life concept</h4>
<ul>
<li>Carbon-14 has a half-life of <strong><u>5,730 ± 40 years</u></strong>—i.e., half the amount of the radioisotope present at any given time will undergo spontaneous disintegration during the succeeding 5,730 years.</li>
<li>Because carbon-14 decays at this constant rate, an estimate of the date at which an organism died can be made by measuring the amount of its <strong><u>residual radiocarbon</u></strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Its uses</h4>
<ul>
<li>It has proved to be a versatile technique of dating fossils and archaeological specimens from 500 to 50,000 years old.</li>
<li>The method is widely used by geologists, anthropologists, archaeologists, and investigators in related fields.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-carbon-dating/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is the draft Telecom Bill, and what changes it aims to bring?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/draft-telecom-bill/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Indian Telecommunication Bill, 2022</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><img alt="telecom" class="alignnone wp-image-639368 size-full" height="396" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1149px) 100vw, 1149px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/telecom.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/telecom.jpg 1149w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/telecom-300x103.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/telecom-1024x353.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/telecom-768x265.jpg 768w" width="1149"/></p>
<p>In a bid to do away with British-era laws governing the telecom sector, the Department of Telecommunications (DoT) issued the draft Indian Telecommunication Bill, 2022.</p>
<h4><strong>Indian Telecommunication Bill, 2022</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The proposed Bill aims to bring in sweeping changes to how the telecom sector is governed, primarily by giving the Centre more powers in several areas to do so.</li>
<li>The draft Bill consolidates three separate acts that govern the telecommunications sector:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Indian Telegraph Act 1885</li>
<li>Indian Wireless Telegraphy Act 1933, and</li>
<li>The Telegraph Wires, (Unlawful Protection) Act 1950</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Why has the government issued a draft Telecommunication Bill?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Through the bill, the Centre aims to consolidate and amend the existing laws governing the provision, development, expansion and operation of telecom services, networks and infrastructure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Key amendments introduced </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inclusion of messengers:</strong> One of the key changes is inclusion of new-age over-the-top communication services like WhatsApp, Signal and Telegram in the definition of telecommunication services.</li>
<li><strong>Licensing of telecom services:</strong> As per the draft law, providers of telecom services will be covered under the licensing regime, and will be subjected to similar rules as other telecom operators.</li>
<li><strong>Covering OTT services:</strong> This issue has been under contention for several years now with telecom service providers seeking a level-playing field with OTT apps over communication services such as voice calls, messages, etc. Operators had to incur high costs of licences and spectrum, while OTT players rode on their infrastructure to offer free services.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other focus areas</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Centre is also looking to amend the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act (TRAI Act) to dilute the sectoral watchdog’s function of being a recommendatory body.</li>
<li>The current TRAI Act mandates the telecom department to seek the regulator’s views before issuing a new licence to a service provider.</li>
<li>The proposed Bill does away with this provision.</li>
<li>It has also removed the provision that empowered TRAI to request the government to furnish information or documents necessary to make this recommendation.</li>
<li>Additionally, the new Bill also proposes to remove the provision where if the DoT cannot accept TRAI’s recommendations or needs modification, it had to refer back the recommendation for reconsideration by TRAI.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Addressing the concerns of telecom industry</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Insolvency of Telecoms</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The DoT has also proposed that if a telecom entity in possession of spectrum goes through bankruptcy or insolvency, the assigned spectrum will revert to the control of the Centre.</li>
<li>So far, in insolvency proceedings, there has been a lack of clarity on whether the spectrum owned by a defaulting operator belongs to the Centre, or whether banks can take control of it.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Granting relief</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The draft Bill also accords the Centre powers to defer, convert into equity, write off or grant relief to any licensee under extraordinary circumstances, including financial stress, consumer interest, and maintaining competition, among other things.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Replacing USOF</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>It also proposes to replace the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/universal-service-obligation-fund-usof/">Universal Service Obligation Fund (USOF)</a> with the Telecommunication Development Fund (TDF).</li>
<li>USOF is the pool of funds generated by the 5 per cent Universal Service Levy that is charged upon all telecom fund operators on their Adjusted Gross Revenue.</li>
<li>The USOF has largely been used to aid rural connectivity.</li>
<li>However, with the TDF, the objective is also to boost connectivity in underserved urban areas, R&amp;D, skill development, etc.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4><strong>Back2Basics: Universal Service Obligation Fund (USOF)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Universal Service Obligation Fund (USOF) was formed by an Act of Parliament, was established in April 2002 under the Indian Telegraph (Amendment) Act 2003.</li>
<li>It aims to provide financial support for the provision of telecom services in commercially unviable rural and remote areas of the country.</li>
<li>It is an attached office of the Department of Telecom, and is headed by the administrator, who is appointed by the central government.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/draft-telecom-bill/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysing the Kyrgyzstan-Tajikistan Conflict</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/the-kyrgyzstan-tajikistan-conflict/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Batken Region</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="conflict" class="alignnone wp-image-639366 size-full" height="883" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/conflict.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/conflict.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/conflict-300x221.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/conflict-1024x753.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/conflict-768x565.jpg 768w" width="1200"/></p>
<p>Nearly 100 people have been killed and scores injured in violent border clashes between Kyrgyzstan and Tajikistan over the last week.</p>
<h4>What is the Kyrgyzstan-Tajikistan Conflict?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The clashes are replaying old pre- and post-Soviet era legacies.</li>
<li>The borders of the two republics were demarcated under Joseph Stalin’s leadership.</li>
<li>Historically, the Kyrgyz and Tajik populations enjoyed common rights over natural resources.</li>
<li>The issue of the delimitation of the border is a relic of the Soviet era.</li>
<li>While regular talks have tried to resolve the issue, one of the crucial points of disagreement remains over the map which should be used for demarcation purposes.</li>
<li>Almost half of its close to a 1000 km border is disputed.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Genesis of the dispute</h4>
<ul>
<li>The creation of the Soviet Union saw the large-scale redistribution of livestock to collective and state farms, which upset the existing status quo.</li>
<li>Unfortunately, there was only so much land to go around.</li>
<li>The Tajik territory of Batken saw their livestock increase, and with scarce grazing land, agreements were signed between the two populations over the utilisation of Kyrgyz territory by the Tajiks’ livestock.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is happening now at the border?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The last few weeks have seen constant shelling, violent confrontations by local communities, and active engagement by security forces on either side.</li>
<li>The Batken region of Kyrgyzstan is seeing families being moved out and getting relocated.</li>
<li>According to Kyrgyzstan, close to 1,50,000 people out of the 5,50,000 odd population of the Batken region have either fled the area or have been relocated by the state.</li>
<li>The situation in Osh, Kyrgyzstan, is no different. The highly militarised borders also add to tensions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of Batken</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Batken region, bordering Tajikistan and Uzbekistan in the south of the country, is one of the seven regions of Kyrgyzstan with its natural underground and water resources, natural beauty, smooth transit routes and a population of around 500,000.</li>
<li>Located 750 kilometers (466.02 miles) from Bishkek, the capital of Kyrgyzstan, and in the southwest of the country, the Batken region is located on the edge of the famous Fergana Valley in Central Asia.</li>
<li>Fergana Valley includes Fergana, Namangan, Andijan in Uzbekistan, Hocand in Tajikistan, Osh, Jalalabad and Batken in Kyrgyzstan.</li>
<li>The Batken region borders the Republic of Uzbekistan in the northeast and the Republic of Tajikistan in the southwest and north.</li>
<li>Covering 8.5% of Kyrgyzstan’s land, the region has agricultural, underground, water and energy resources, as well as oil and natural gas resources, albeit small.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What led to the current flare-up?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The ideological basis of the current set of clashes is reinforced by developmental issues, thus providing a fertile ground for the entire geopolitical space to become a hotbed of multiple minor conflicts and clashes.</li>
<li>The groups from either side planted trees in disputed areas and engaged in a physical confrontation using agricultural equipment as weapons.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why are the clashes occurring now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The collapse of the Soviet Union and the subsequent dissolution of the then-existing water and land agreements saw the creation of multiple smaller independent farms.</li>
<li>This has led to a marked increase in water consumption patterns among the farmers.</li>
<li>Both countries share multiple water channels with undulating trajectories and flow, which upset equitable access to water on both sides.</li>
<li>As a result, small-scale conflicts occur practically every year during the crucial irrigation period.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is the road ahead?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The path to resolution of the conflict will require groups to agree upon a common map.</li>
<li>Russia often brokers between the two.</li>
<li>The international community will have to make efforts to solve the dispute by involving elders in the communities, as historically, elders have been used to resolve conflicts.</li>
<li>The informal small-scale governance mechanisms would also have to be further strengthened through a concerted effort by the respective countries to stabilize the geopolitical dynamics.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/the-kyrgyzstan-tajikistan-conflict/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Maoist movement declines along the Andhra-Odisha boundary</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/maoist-movement-declines-the-andhra-odisha-boundary/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Maoism, Leninism and Marxism</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>LWE in India</p></div></div><p><img alt="mao" class="alignnone wp-image-526403 size-full" height="994" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/lwe.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/lwe.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/lwe-300x249.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/lwe-1024x848.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/02/lwe-768x636.jpg 768w" width="1200"/></p>
<p>The Maoist movement is on the ebb on the Andhra Pradesh-Odisha boundary, with its cadre and militia strength heavily depleted.</p>
<h4><strong>Who are the Maoists?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Maoism is a form of <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/sansad-tv-perspective-left-wing-extremism/">communism</a> developed by Mao Zedong.</li>
<li>It is a doctrine to capture State power through a combination of armed insurgency, mass mobilization and strategic alliances.</li>
<li>The Maoists also use propaganda and disinformation against State institutions as other components of their insurgency doctrine.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Maoists and Maoism in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Communist Party of India (Maoist) is a Marxist–Leninist–Maoist banned communist political party and militant organization in India.</li>
<li>It aims to overthrow the “semi-colonial and semi-feudal Indian state” through people’s war.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Confused between Maoists and Naxalities?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Usually, people confuse themselves over Maoists and Naxalities and cannot exactly trace the difference between the two terminologies.</li>
<li>Media seems to be confused with the terms and uses Maoists and Naxalities quite inter-changeably.</li>
<li>This creates confusion in the readers’ minds over the actual meaning of individual terms.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The actual difference between the terms is as follows:</h4>
<ul>
<li>The difference between Maoists struggle and the Naxalite movement is that both trace their origin to the Naxalbari uprising of 1967.</li>
<li>But while the Naxalite movement thrives on the original spirit of Naxalbari; the Maoist struggle is an outcome of the 1967 uprising.</li>
<li>Maoists work with an agenda and use weapons to achieve their aims.</li>
<li>Naxalism focuses on mass organisations while the Maoism relies mainly on arms.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>History and evolution</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Russian Revolution:</strong> Naxalism in India, like any other leftist movement around the globe draws its ideological basis from the Russian revolution.</li>
<li><strong>Overthrowing Tsarist Regime:</strong> Lenin successfully fought against the Czarist Rule through a combination of peasant movement and an armed struggle.</li>
<li><strong>Marxian ideology of class struggle:</strong> The prime intent was to bestow power in the hands of the exploited and marginalized and enforce societal control over governance and nation building.</li>
<li><strong>Neo-Marxism:</strong> After the success of the Lenin-led revolution in Russia, the intellectual class in many countries got inspired. Prominent amongst them were Fidel Castro and Mao Zedong.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Root cause of origin in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Corporate exploitation:</strong> Since Eastern India is rich in natural resources including forests, minerals and mines, tribal face exploitation and harassment from government and corporate bodies targeting to extract those resources.</li>
<li><strong>Tribal alienation:</strong> Tribal communities have been systematically alienated from their traditional rights over natural resources after independence.</li>
<li><strong>Livelihood losses:</strong> Tribal livelihood is at stake due to depletion of natural resource base.</li>
<li><strong>Forceful displacement:</strong> Forceful displacement from their homeland destroys their traditional governance system.</li>
<li><strong>Absence of governance: </strong>In such exploited areas, the absence of governance becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy since the delivery systems are extinguished through killings and intimidation.</li>
<li><strong>Foreign provocations:</strong> Many of LWE outfits are supported by external forces inimical to India and the Maoists consider such alliances as strategic assets.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other factors:</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li>Oppression and HR violations by Security Forces e.g. AFSPA</li>
<li>Violation of Constitutional Protections under PESA and FRA</li>
<li>Prevalence of Acute Poverty</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Impact of LWE</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Romanticism without a cause:</strong> Some sections of the society, especially the younger generation, have romantic illusions about the Maoists, arising out of an incomplete understanding of their ideology of Class –Struggle.</li>
<li><strong>Extreme violence:</strong> Their doctrine glorifies violence as the primary means to overwhelm the existing socio-economic and political structures.</li>
<li><strong>Destruction of governance mechanism:</strong> LWEs aims at creating a vacuum at the grassroots level of the existing governance structures by killing lower-level government officials, police personnel of the local police stations and the people’s representatives of the PRIs.</li>
<li><strong>Radicalization of youths:</strong> After creating a political and governance vacuum, they coerce the local population to join the movement.</li>
<li><strong>Urban-Maoism:</strong> Many extremists have facilitated mass-mobilization in semi-urban and urban areas through ostensibly democratic means often led by well-educated intellectuals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Outcomes of perpetrating LWE</strong></h4>
<p>The Leftist organizations skilfully use state structures and legal processes to further the Maoist agenda and weaken the enforcement regime through:</p>
<ol>
<li>Recruitment of ‘professional revolutionaries’</li>
<li>Raising funds for the insurgency</li>
<li>Creating urban shelters for underground cadres</li>
<li>Providing legal assistance to arrested cadres and</li>
<li>Mass- mobilization by agitating over issues of relevance/ convenience</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Govt initiatives for LWE-affected areas</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Aspirational Districts:</strong> The MHA has been tasked with the monitoring of the Aspirational districts programme in 35 LWE affected districts.</li>
<li><strong>HRD measures:</strong> Building of schools under the Eklavya model.</li>
<li><strong>Road Connectivity Project for LWE affected areas (RRP-II):</strong> This aims for improving road connectivity in LWE affected States. Under this, 9279 km of roads and 392 bridges are sanctioned.</li>
<li><strong>Naxal Surrender Policy:</strong> It aims to wean away misguided youth and hardcore naxalites who have strayed into the fold of the naxal movement and cannot find a way back.</li>
<li><strong>National Policy Action Plan</strong>: To address Left Wing Extremism approved in 2015, has development as one of the most important component.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>SAMADHAN doctrine: </strong>It encompasses the entire strategy of government from short-term policy to long-term policy formulated at different levels. SAMADHAN stands for-</p>
<ul>
<li>S- Smart Leadership</li>
<li>A- Aggressive Strategy</li>
<li>M- Motivation and Training</li>
<li>A- Actionable Intelligence</li>
<li>D- Dashboard Based KPIs (Key Performance Indicators) and KRAs (Key Result Areas)</li>
<li>H- Harnessing Technology</li>
<li>A- Action plan for each Theatre</li>
<li>N- No access to Financing</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian counterinsurgency has to work with a dual objective of defeating the insurgents militarily and fully quell the insurgent impulses.</li>
<li>This will need institutional overhauls.</li>
<li>States must do more to synergize their efforts by launching coordinated operations, thereby denying Maoists any space for manoeuvrability.</li>
<li>On parallel grounds, it is also important to segregate the population from the insurgents both operationally and ideologically.</li>
<li>The conflict over the distribution of resources can be mended with economic development.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/maoist-movement-declines-the-andhra-odisha-boundary/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>A census is not just about aimless counting of sheeps</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/census/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of census data</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Population issues</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="census" class="alignnone wp-image-639439" height="379" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-300x222.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-300x222.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-1024x759.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-768x570.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-1536x1139.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-2048x1519.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-1200x890.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/000_17H0TP-1980x1468.jpg 1980w" width="512"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As there is no official reassurance that India will not skip its decadal Census, we can declare that we have a case of the missing census.</li>
<li>The census is a very important source of statistics on various indicators.</li>
<li>The ability to hold a census peacefully, and not coercively, has been the hallmark of a civilized state and state of affairs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a census?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Census is nothing but a process of collecting, compiling, analyzing, evaluating, publishing and disseminating statistical data regarding the population.</li>
<li>It covers demographic, social and economic data and is provided as of a particular date.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the purpose of the census?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To collect the information for planning and formulation policies for Central and the State Governments.</li>
<li>The census tells us who we are and where we are going as a nation.</li>
<li>It helps the government decide how to distribute funds and assistance to states and localities.</li>
<li>The census data is widely used by National and International Agencies, scholars, business people, industrialists, and many more.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="census" class="alignnone wp-image-639440" height="263" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 499px) 100vw, 499px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/136455-zzzrhagmjy-1581566412-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/136455-zzzrhagmjy-1581566412-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/136455-zzzrhagmjy-1581566412.jpg 600w" width="499"/>Why is the census important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Provides most credible source of information</strong><strong>:</strong> information on Demography (Population characteristics), Economic Activity, Literacy and Education, Housing &amp; Household Amenities, Urbanisation, Fertility and Mortality, Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes, Language, Religion, Migration, Disability and many other socio-cultural and demographic data<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><a href="https://eci.gov.in/delimitation-website/delimitation/" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>The delimitation/reservation of Constituencies</strong><strong>: </strong></a>Parliamentary/Assembly/Panchayats and other Local Bodies are also done on the basis of the demographic data thrown up by the Census.</li>
<li><strong>Administration: </strong>Census is the basis for reviewing the country’s progress in the past decade, monitoring the ongoing Schemes of the Government.</li>
<li><strong>Planning the future:</strong> It provides pathways for planning and resolving problems, and fixing deficiencies. Government goes through analysis over the census data and formulates policies for the future accordingly.</li>
<li><strong>Detailed accounts: </strong>The best of sample surveys find it impossible to beat a census as It carries the promise of counting each and every Indian. A census is when the state connects to every individual and it will find it hard to hide or duck from the data.</li>
<li><strong>Welfare schemes</strong>: Identifying the actual beneficiaries<strong>, </strong>Census is the key to creating identity and affirming it over time .Census data enable neat, inter-temporal comparability.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Censuses in India so far</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Census operations started in India long back during the period of the Maurya dynasty.</li>
<li>It was systematized during the years 1865 to 1872, though it has been conducted uninterruptedly from the year 1881 being a trustworthy resource of information.</li>
<li>India has held its decadal censuses regularly from 1881 to 2011, despite diseases, world wars, Partition and other instances of turmoil only COVID-19 as an exception.</li>
<li>Census 2011 is the 15th National Census of the Country.</li>
<li>The Census established that the Total Fertility Rate (TFR) is coming down at a very rapid pace and is well on its way to stabilization.</li>
<li>The 2011 Census also dispelled the notion of divorce rate differentials between city and rural India. The urban divorce rate (0.89%) is almost equal to the rural rate (0.82%).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="census" class="alignnone wp-image-639441" height="334" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Census-exercise_featured-image-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Census-exercise_featured-image-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Census-exercise_featured-image-1024x572.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Census-exercise_featured-image-768x429.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Census-exercise_featured-image-1200x670.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Census-exercise_featured-image.jpg 1390w" width="600"/>Why census 2021 has been postponed indefinitely?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Ministry of Home Affairs told the Lok Sabha in August, 2021 that the massive, decennial exercise came to a grinding halt due to the advent of Coid-19 pandemic.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What was the original timeline of the Census and how is it being delayed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Gazette notification: </strong>The Centre’s intent to conduct Census 2021 was notified in the Gazette of India on March 28, 2019. The exercise was to have been conducted in two phases, with the housing Census from April to September 2020 and population enumeration from February 9, 2021.but it did not take place due to the spread of COVID-19.</li>
<li><strong>Alternative timeline post-covid-19: </strong>In March 2021, the Home Ministry gave a Parliamentary panel a tentative alternative timeline. The fieldwork for the first phase, which would provide data on housing conditions, household amenities and assets possessed by households, is expected during 2021-22, while the fieldwork to count the population and provide data on demography, religion, Scheduled Castes and Tribes (SC/ST), language, literacy and education, economic activity, migration and fertility would be done in 2023-24, it said.</li>
<li><strong>Said Provisional data: </strong>The Ministry added that provisional data would be released in 2023-24 before the next general elections. Usually, more detailed tables providing village-level data on specific indicators will continue to be released for several years after the key information.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="census" class="alignnone wp-image-639443" height="266" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 505px) 100vw, 505px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/population-census-2021-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/population-census-2021-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/population-census-2021-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/population-census-2021-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/population-census-2021.jpg 1200w" width="505"/>Impact of delay in census 2021</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Public distribution system</strong>:</li>
<li>The National Food Security Act, 2013, says that 75% of the rural population and 50% of the rural population are entitled to receive subsidised food grains from the government under the targeted public distribution system (PDS).</li>
<li>Under the 2011 Census, India’s population was about 121 crore, hence PDS covered approximately 80 crore people.</li>
<li>If we apply projected population of 137crore ,current delay in Census data would continue to deprive more than 10 crore people of subsidised food entitlements, with the biggest gaps in Uttar Pradesh and Bihar, with 2.8 crore and 1.8 crore projected exclusions respectively.</li>
<li><strong>welfare schemes:</strong></li>
<li>Although the Government’s intent to use SECC data but failed at budgetary allocation for the projected expansion<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>Census data may not be used to calculate the beneficiaries of most schemes, but it is critical to policy planning, budgeting and administration<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>A number of schemes need to use the disaggregated age and fertility indicators to assess effectiveness as demographics change over time.</li>
<li><strong>Huge lag in Migration data: </strong></li>
<li>From the COVID19 lockdowns it is realized that the Numbers, causes and patterns of migration, which could not be answered using outdated 2011 Census data.</li>
<li>The D-tables on migration from the 2011 Census were only released in 2019, so it’s outdated by the time it came out.</li>
<li>Apart from the One Nation, One Ration card scheme which now allows for portability of food subsidy entitlements, the migration data is actually not used too much in broader economic policy and planning.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/the-caste-census-debate/"><strong>Why there is a demand for caste census in India?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>India’s population has since increased three-fold to 1.21 billion in 2011.</li>
<li>Experts believe the economic status of the dominant OBC castes have improved in the past 80 years and certain castes have not benefited as much.</li>
<li>So, the new caste census is required to measure the economic and social well-being of all castes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Other related information Key findings of 2011 census</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Population</strong><strong>:</strong></li>
<li>India’s population grew by 17.7 per cent during 2001-11, against 21.5 per cent in the previous decade.</li>
<li>India’s total population stands at 1.21 billion, which is 17.7 per cent more than the last decade, and growth of females was higher than that of males.</li>
<li>The growth rate of females was 18.3 per cent which is higher than males — 17.1 per cent.</li>
<li>Among the major states, highest decadal growth in population has been recorded in Bihar (25.4 per cent) while 14 states and Union Territories have recorded population growth above 20 per cent.</li>
<li><strong>Rural and urban population:</strong></li>
<li>Urban proportion has gone up from 17.3 per cent in 1951 to 31.2 per cent in 2011.</li>
<li>Highest proportion of urban population is in NCT Delhi (97.5 per cent).</li>
<li>Top five states in share of urban population are Goa (62.2 per cent), Mizoram (52.1 per cent), Tamil Nadu (48.4 per cent), Kerala (47.7 per cent) and Maharashtra (45.2 per cent).</li>
<li><strong>Literacy</strong>:</li>
<li>Literacy rate in India in 2011 has increased by 8 per cent to 73 per cent in comparison to 64.8 per cent in 2001.</li>
<li>Male literacy rate stands at 80.9 per cent, which is 5.6 per cent more than the previous census whereas the female literacy rate stands at 64.6 per cent, increase of 10.9 per cent than 2001.</li>
<li>The highest increase took place in Dadra and Nagar Haveli by 18.6 points (from 57.6 per cent to 76.2 per cent), while in Bihar by 14.8 points (from 47.0 per cent to 61.8 per cent), Tripura by 14.0 points (from 73.2 per cent to 87.2 per cent)</li>
<li><strong>Density</strong>:</li>
<li>The density of population in the country has also increased from 325 in 2001 to 382 in 2011 in per sq km.</li>
<li>Among the major states, Bihar occupies the first position with a density of 1106, surpassing West Bengal which occupied the first position during 2001.</li>
<li>Delhi (11,320) turns out to be the most densely inhabited followed by Chandigarh (9,258), among all states and UT’s, both in 2001 and 2011 Census.</li>
<li>The minimum population density works out in Arunachal Pradesh (17) for both 2001 and 2011 Census.</li>
<li><strong>Sex ratio</strong>:</li>
<li>The sex ratio of population in the country in 2011 stands at 940 female against 1000 males, which is 10 per cent more than the last census when the number female per thousand male stood at 933.</li>
<li>The number of females per 1000 males in Haryana in 2011 stands at 879 followed by Jammu and Kashmir (889 female) and Punjab (895 females).</li>
<li>The other two worst-performing states in terms of skewed sex ration are Uttar Pradesh (912 females) and Bihar (918 females).</li>
<li>Five top performing states in terms of sex ratio were Kerala (1,084 females), Tamil Nadu (996), Andhra Pradesh (993), Chhattisgarh (991),Odisha (979).</li>
<li><strong>Child population</strong>:</li>
<li>Child population in the age of 0 to 6 years has seen an increase of 0.4 per cent.</li>
<li>There has been a decline of 8 per cent in the sex ratio of 0-6 age group. In 2011, the child sex ratio (0-6) stands at 919 female against 1000 male in comparison to 927 females in 2001.</li>
<li>Male child (0-6) population has increased whereas female child population has decreased during 2001-11.</li>
<li>The worst performing states in regard to sex ration in the age group of 0 to 6 years are Haryana (834 females), Punjab (846), Jammu and Kashmir (862), Rajasthan (888) and Gujarat (890).</li>
<li>The best performing states are Chhattisgarh (969), Kerala (964), Assam (962), West Bengal (956) Jharkhand (948) and Karnataka (948).</li>
<li><strong>SC/ST data</strong>:</li>
<li>According to the Census, Scheduled Castes are notified in 31 states and UTs and Scheduled Tribes in 30 states. There are altogether 1,241 individual ethnic groups notified as SC’s .The number of individual ethnic groups, notified as ST’s is 705.</li>
<li>There have been some changes in the list of SC’s/ST’s in states and UT’s during the last decade.</li>
<li>The SC population in India now stands at 201.4 million, which is 20 per cent more than the last census. The ST population stands at 104.3 million in 2011 – 23.7 per cent more than 2001.</li>
<li><strong>Religious demographics</strong>:</li>
<li>The religious data on India Census 2011 was released by the Government of India on 25 August 2015.</li>
<li>Hindus are 79.8% (966.3 million), while Muslims are 14.23% (172.2 million) in India.</li>
<li>For the first time, a “No religion” category was added in the 2011 census. 2.87 million Were classified as people belonging to “No Religion” in India in the 2011 census. – 0.24% of India’s population of 1.21 billion.</li>
<li><strong>Median marriage age</strong>:</li>
<li>The median age increased for men – from 22.6 (2001) to 23.5 (2011) and for women – from 18.2 (2001) to 19.2 (2011).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The census is vital and precious as it is a repository of complete data about the country which is gathered openly, voluntarily, and with the use of public money, making it a social good.</li>
<li>The new Census is likely to capture the extent of the observed movement in migration trends towards smaller two-tier towns apart from the large metropolitan centre.</li>
<li>It could help answer questions of what kind of healthcare and social services are most needed and where.</li>
<li>The Census is about many things. But, fundamentally, it is a way in which the state, by knocking at all doors, displays its desire to connect with the people who ultimately comprise the nation.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Apart from being used to demarcate constituencies, updated decadal census data is vital to administration. How will the indefinite postponement of census impact the policy formation for the future? Critically Analyse.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong> Do follow this link </strong></p>
<p class="entry-title"><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/census-2011-the-basics-and-summary-of-important-findings/">Census 2011 | The basics and summary of important findings</a></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/census/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>The question is: Who will bell the alarm for CBI and ED?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cbi/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>CBI and ED</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>governance and transparency</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="CBI" class="alignnone wp-image-639467" height="477" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 445px) 100vw, 445px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cbi-280x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cbi-280x300.jpg 280w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/cbi.jpg 451w" width="445"/>Context  </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Despite several observations made by the Supreme Court of India (SC) against the inefficient functioning of the CBI nothing has happened to improve the situation.</li>
<li>The Enforcement Directorate (ED) is in the news now and often.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Central Bureau of Investigation (CBI)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The Bureau of Investigation traces its origins to the <strong>Delhi Special Police Establishment</strong>, a Central Government Police force, which was <strong>set up in 1941</strong> by the Government of India.</li>
<li>It then aimed to <strong>investigate bribery and corruption</strong> in transactions with the <u>War and Supply Department of India.</u></li>
<li>It then had its headquarters in Lahore.</li>
<li>After the end of the war, there was a continued need for a central governmental agency to investigate bribery and corruption by central-government employees.</li>
<li>The DSPE acquired its popular current name, Central Bureau of Investigation (CBI), through a Home Ministry resolution dated in 1963.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Mandate of the CBI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The CBI is the <strong>main investigating agency</strong> of the GoI.</li>
<li>It is <strong>not a statutory body</strong>; it derives its powers from the Delhi Special Police Establishment Act, 1946.</li>
<li>Its important role is to prevent corruption and maintain integrity in administration.</li>
<li>It works under the <strong>supervision of the CVC</strong> (Central Vigilance Commission) in matters pertaining to the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988.</li>
<li>The CBI is also India’s <strong>official representative with the</strong> <strong>INTERPOL</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="CBI" class="alignnone wp-image-639469" height="367" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 489px) 100vw, 489px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/government-axes-tenure-of-two-senior-cbi-officers-anish-prasad-abhay-singh-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/government-axes-tenure-of-two-senior-cbi-officers-anish-prasad-abhay-singh-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/government-axes-tenure-of-two-senior-cbi-officers-anish-prasad-abhay-singh-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/government-axes-tenure-of-two-senior-cbi-officers-anish-prasad-abhay-singh-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/government-axes-tenure-of-two-senior-cbi-officers-anish-prasad-abhay-singh.jpg 1200w" width="489"/>Cases to investigate</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Cases connected to infringement of <strong>economic and fiscal laws</strong></li>
<li>Crimes of a serious nature that have <strong>national and international ramifications</strong></li>
<li><strong>Coordination with</strong> the activities of the various state police forces and anti-corruption agencies.</li>
<li>It can also take up any <strong>case of public importance</strong> and investigate it</li>
<li><strong>Maintaining crime statistics</strong> and disseminating criminal information.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Notable cases cracked by CBI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Bhanwri Devi missing case:</strong> Jat leader and former Rajasthan minister Mahipal Maderna, Congress MLA Malkhan Singh and Bhanwari’s husband Amarchand were all part of the conspiracy to abduct and eliminate Bhanwari. Bhanwari had threatened to expose Malkhan’s relationship with her at the Bishnoi mahapanchayat.  Maderna, Malkhan, the three kidnappers and Sahiram along with Amarchand were arrested by the CBI.</li>
<li><strong>Noida double murder case:</strong> In May 2008, the nation was shocked with the sensational double murders in Noida. The victims were Arushi Talwar and Hemraj Banjade. Initially, there was no clarity about the motive or the perpetrator of this ghastly crime. After a lengthy investigation which spanned close to 6 years, the CBI based on circumstantial evidence established that the parents of Aarushi Talwar, Rajesh Talwar and Nupur Talwar were the perpetrators of this crime.</li>
<li><strong>The Satyam Case: </strong> B Ramalinga Raju, the disgraced chairman of Satyam Computers Services Ltd, along with 13 individuals and entities including Chintalapati Srinivasa Raju of iLabs, made Rs 2,000 crore in illegal wealth in the Satyam scam. The CBI constituted a Multi-Disciplinary Investigation Team (MDIT) to investigate the case. The team worked hard, burnt midnight oil and achieved success in a record time of 45 days when it filed its first chargesheet against the accused for offences of criminal conspiracy, cheating, forgery and falsification of accounts.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Issues with CBI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Caged parrot:</strong> The Supreme Court has criticized the CBI by calling it a “caged parrot speaking in its master’s voice”.</li>
<li><strong>Political interference:</strong> It has often been used by the government of the day to cover up wrongdoing, keep coalition allies in line and political opponents at bay.</li>
<li><strong>Investigation delay:</strong> It has been accused of enormous delays in concluding investigations due to political inertia.</li>
<li><strong>Loss of Credibility:</strong> CBI has been criticised for its mismanagement of several cases involving prominent politicians and mishandling of several sensitive cases like Bofors scandal, Bhopal gas tragedy.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of Accountability:</strong> CBI is exempted from the provisions of the Right to Information Act, thus, lacking public accountability.</li>
<li><strong>Acute shortage of personnel:</strong> A major cause of the shortfall is the government’s sheer mismanagement of CBI’s workforce.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-general-consent-for-cbi/"><strong>Limited Powers:</strong></a> The powers and jurisdiction of members of the CBI for investigation are subject to the consent of the State Govt., thus limiting the extent of investigation by CBI.</li>
<li><strong>Restricted Access:</strong> Prior approval of Central Government to conduct inquiry or investigation on the employees of the Central Government is a big obstacle in combating corruption at higher levels of bureaucracy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why was it called caged carrot by the Supreme Court?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Politicisation of the Central Bureau of Investigation (CBI) has been a work in progress for years.</li>
<li>Corruption and Politically biased nature, This was highlighted in Supreme Court criticism for being a caged parrot speaking in its master’s voice.</li>
<li>CBI has been accused of becoming ‘handmaiden’ to the party in power; as a result high profile cases are not treated seriously.</li>
<li>Since CBI is run by central police officials on deputation hence chances of getting influenced by government was visible in the hope of better future postings.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Suggestions for the improvement of the functioning of the CBI under the supervision of the <a href="https://cvc.gov.in/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">CVC</a></strong></h4>
<ol>
<li>One, the CVC Act should be amended, providing for a five/seven member Central Vigilance Commission, which could broadly assume the role visualised for the Lokpal. The selection process of the CVC members should be more broad based to prevent favouritism or from controversial persons being appointed.</li>
<li>Two, the CVC should constitute an advisory committee of at least 11 members drawn from criminologists and forensic science experts. This will augment the professional input in its functioning. Further, to reduce the burden on the CVC, it should be given the power to go to any expert or professional to assist it in screening complaints.</li>
<li>Three, the jurisdiction of CVC, which presently covers all employees of the central government and the CPSUs, should remain unchanged. There is already an administrative arrangement to delegate the vigilance administration over class II and lower formations to the ministries/departments concerned. However, if the lower formations are involved with the class I officers in a composite case, the CVC exercises a natural jurisdiction over all of them. To make this arrangement more effective, it would be important that the CVC exercises complete control over the selection, appointment and functioning of the CVOs.</li>
<li>Four, the CVC should have an adequately experienced team to technically examine and assess the gravity of a complaint, which can then be assigned to the CBI for investigation or can be investigated by this team. After assessing a complaint by this broad-based CVC, there should be no need to seek prior permission from the government.</li>
<li>Five, in the cases assigned to it by the CVC, the CBI should be made functionally and financially independent of the controls of any government ministry/department. The professional supervision over the investigations of the CBI should rest only with the CVC.</li>
<li>Six, the manner of the appointment of the CBI Director should be broad based as in the case of the CVC members, whereas the other inductions/appointments in the CBI should be brought under the overarching supervision of the CVC.</li>
<li>Seven, to achieve better synergy between anti-corruption laws and grievance handling, the laws relating to the whistle blowers and grievance redressal should be placed within the jurisdiction of the CVC.</li>
<li>Eight, effective administration of anti-corruption laws at the grass roots is the key to responsible governance. The state and their anti-corruption agencies would, therefore, need to be equally insulated from the state government’s interference on similar lines.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Reforming CBI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Need for autonomy:</strong>   As long as the government of the day has the power to transfer and post officials of its choice in the CBI, the investigating agency will not enjoy autonomy and will be unable to investigate cases freely.</li>
<li><strong>Selection of director/ Officers:</strong> To ensure that the CBI is a robust, independent and credible investigation agency, there is an urgent need to work out a much more transparent mechanism for selection and induction of officers on deputation.</li>
<li><strong>Lokpal scrutiny:</strong> The Lokpal Act already calls for a three-member committee made up of the PM, the leader of the opposition and the CJI to select the director.</li>
<li><strong>Bifurcation of Cadre:</strong> CBI should be bifurcated into an Anti-Corruption Body and a National Crime Bureau.</li>
<li><strong>Develop own cadre</strong>: One of the demands that have been before Supreme Court, and in line with international best practices, is for the CBI to develop its own dedicated cadre of officers.</li>
<li><strong>Annual social audit</strong> should be carried out by ten reputed, knowledgeable persons with background of law, justice, public affairs and administration and the audit report should be placed before the parliament.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>About Enforcement Directorate (ED)</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It goes back to May 1, 1956, when an ‘<strong><u>Enforcement Unit</u>’</strong> was formed in the Department of Economic Affairs.</li>
<li>It then aimed for handling Exchange Control Laws violations under the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act (FERA).</li>
<li>The ED today is a <strong><u>multi-dimensional organisation</u></strong> investigating economic offences under the Prevention of Money Laundering Act (PMLA), Fugitive Economic Offenders Act, Foreign Exchange Management Act and FERA.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="CBI" class="alignnone wp-image-639470" height="273" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 485px) 100vw, 485px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Enforcement-Directorate-Powers-and-Functions-of-ED-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Enforcement-Directorate-Powers-and-Functions-of-ED-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Enforcement-Directorate-Powers-and-Functions-of-ED-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Enforcement-Directorate-Powers-and-Functions-of-ED-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Enforcement-Directorate-Powers-and-Functions-of-ED.jpg 1200w" width="485"/>From where does the ED get its powers?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>When proceeds of crime (property/money) are generated, the best way to save that money is by parking it somewhere, so one is not answerable to anyone in the country.</li>
<li>Therefore, there was a need to control and prevent the laundering of money.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>PMLA</u></strong> was brought in for this exact reason in 2002, but was enacted only in 2005.</li>
<li>The objective was to prevent parking of the money outside India and to trace out the layering and the trail of money.</li>
<li>So as per the Act, the ED got its power to investigate under Sections 48 (authorities under act) and 49 (appointment and powers of authorities and other officers).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>At what stage does the ED step in when a crime is committed?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Whenever any offence is registered by a local police station, which has generated proceeds of crime <strong><u>over and above ₹1 crore</u></strong>, the investigating police officer forwards the details to the ED.</li>
<li>Alternately, <strong><u>if the offence comes under the knowledge of the Central agency</u></strong>, they can then call for the First Information Report (FIR) or the chargesheet if it has been filed directly by police officials.</li>
<li>This will be done to find out if any laundering has taken place.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="CBI" class="alignnone wp-image-639474" height="380" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 507px) 100vw, 507px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/aryan-khan-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/aryan-khan-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/aryan-khan-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/aryan-khan-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/aryan-khan.jpg 1200w" width="507"/>What differentiates the probe between the local police and officers of the ED?</strong></h4>
<p>Case study:</p>
<ul>
<li>If a theft has been committed in a nationalised bank, the local police station will first investigate the crime.</li>
<li>If it is learnt that the founder of the bank took all the money and kept it in his house, without being spent or used, then the crime is only theft and the ED won’t interfere because the amount has already been seized.</li>
<li>But if the amount which has been stolen is used after four years to purchase some properties, then the ill-gotten money is brought back in the market.</li>
<li>Or if the money is given to someone else to buy properties in different parts of the country, then there is ‘laundering’ of money.</li>
<li>Hence the ED will need to step in and look into the layering and attachment of properties to recover the money.</li>
<li>If jewellery costing ₹1 crore is stolen, police officers will investigate the theft. The ED, however, will attach assets of the accused to recover the amount of ₹1 crore.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="CBI" class="alignnone wp-image-639473" height="273" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 485px) 100vw, 485px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ezgif-sixteen_nine_157-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ezgif-sixteen_nine_157-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ezgif-sixteen_nine_157-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ezgif-sixteen_nine_157.jpg 948w" width="485"/>What are the other roles and functions of the ED?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ED carries out <strong><u>search (property) and seizure (money/documents)</u></strong> after it has decided that the money has been laundered, under Section 16 (power of survey) and Section 17 (search and seizure) of the PMLA.</li>
<li>On the basis of that, the <strong><u>authorities will decide if arrest is needed</u></strong> as per Section 19 (power of arrest).</li>
<li>Under Section 50, the ED can also <strong><u>directly carry out search and seizure without calling the person for questioning</u></strong>.</li>
<li>It is <strong><u>not necessary to summon the person first </u></strong>and then start with the search and seizure.</li>
<li><strong><u>If the person is arrested, the ED gets 60 days to file the prosecution</u></strong> <strong><u>complaint</u></strong> (chargesheet) as the punishment under PMLA doesn’t go beyond seven years.</li>
<li>If no one is arrested and only the <strong><u>property is attached</u></strong>, then the prosecution complaint along with attachment order is to be submitted before the adjudicating authority within 60 days.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Can the ED investigate cases of money laundering retrospectively?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>If an ill-gotten property is acquired before the year 2005 (when the law was brought in) and disposed off, then there is no case under PMLA.</li>
<li>But if proceeds of the crime were possessed before 2005, kept in storage, and used after 2005 by buying properties, the <strong><u>colour of the money is still black and the person is liable to be prosecuted under PMLA.</u></strong></li>
<li>Under Section 3 of PMLA, a person shall be guilty of money-laundering, if such person is found to have directly or indirectly attempted to indulge or knowingly assist a party involved in one or more of the following activities:</li>
<li>Concealment; possession; acquisition; use; or projecting as untainted property; or claiming as untainted property in any manner etc.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Allegations against ED</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Huge discretions:</strong> The ED is the only Central agency in the country that does not require permission from the government to summon or prosecute politicians or government functionaries for committing economic offences like money laundering.</li>
<li><strong>Used for petty crimes:</strong> PMLA is pulled into the investigation of even “ordinary” crimes and assets of genuine victims have been attached.</li>
<li><strong>Actual purpose denigrated: </strong>PMLA was a comprehensive penal statute to counter the threat of money laundering, specifically stemming from the trade in narcotics.</li>
<li><strong>Violations of Rights:</strong> PMLA was enacted in response to India’s global commitment to combat the menace of money laundering. Instead, rights have been “cribbed, cabined and confined”.</li>
<li><strong>Functional opacity:</strong> There is also a lack of clarity about ED’s selection of cases to investigate. We often see ED raiding houses of opposition parties suddenly.</li>
<li><strong>Poor rate of conviction:</strong> We have hardly read the conclusion of cases by ED. Meantime media-trial tears off the accused person’s credibility which is the most desired intent.</li>
<li><strong>Under-trials and slower prosecution</strong>: ED has been focusing on keeping the accused in custody rather than actually proving the charges against them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Challenges to ED</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>ED being dragged to court:</strong> The petitions against the ED had the effect of slowing down the investigations, as officers have to defend themselves in court.</li>
<li><strong>Foul crying politicians:</strong> There are attempts to cover up unexplained, high-value transactions that fall within the PMLA’s ambit</li>
<li><strong>Investigation of foreign transactions:</strong> Getting information on accounts and money stashed abroad to establish a trail is the biggest challenge they face.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The fight against corruption is intimately linked with the reform of the investigations.</li>
<li>Therefore the adjudicating authorities must work in cooperation and ensure the highest standards of transparency and fairness.</li>
<li>ED has been walking a tightrope to safeguard its integrity by speeding up investigations and court procedures.</li>
<li>The need of the hour could be systemic fixes—and not shrill calls to throw the baby out with the bathwater.</li>
<li>It is unlikely that corruption can be substantially reduced without modifying the way government agencies operate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is for the nation to demand that the country’s premier investigating agencies like the CBI, income tax authorities and the ED are not used as instruments of blackmail and intimidation by the government of the day. Rather they should work with complete objectivity and in the interest of the nation.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. CBI and ED was called caged carrot by the Supreme Court. Do you agree with this? What issues are being faced by these premier agencies? Suggest some dynamic solutions to overcome these issues.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p>Do follow</p>
<p class="entry-title"><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-enforcement-directorate-ed-dreaded-nightmare-of-indian-politicians-businessmen/">[Burning Issue] Enforcement Directorate (ED): Dreaded nightmare of Indian Politicians &amp; Businessmen</a></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/cbi/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Intra party elections are essential feature of healthy democracy</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/intra-party-election/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>election commission of india</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>electoral reforms</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Intra party election" class="alignnone wp-image-639482" height="310" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 554px) 100vw, 554px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dc-Cover-kkgjvu4o81kb5ie8sdon8gp990-20200805205510.Medi_-300x168.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dc-Cover-kkgjvu4o81kb5ie8sdon8gp990-20200805205510.Medi_-300x168.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dc-Cover-kkgjvu4o81kb5ie8sdon8gp990-20200805205510.Medi_-768x430.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dc-Cover-kkgjvu4o81kb5ie8sdon8gp990-20200805205510.Medi_.jpeg 800w" width="554"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Congress party has issued a notification for the party’s presidential election hinting towards intra party election.</li>
<li>As per the official notification, party leaders can file nominations from 24 September to 30 September. The voting will be held on 17 October and the results will be declared on 19 October.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the elections?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An election is a way people can choose their representatives of their preferences in a representative democracy. Elections enable people to judge the performance of the government.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why they are important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Elections give people a chance to evaluate their leaders, chance to change the government.</li>
<li>Elections help the people in the selection of their representatives and it provides law making power directly to the people.</li>
<li>Elections make a fundamental contribution to democratic governance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Intra party election" class="alignnone wp-image-639483" height="320" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 568px) 100vw, 568px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BJP-1-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BJP-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BJP-1-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BJP-1-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BJP-1.jpg 1200w" width="568"/>What is mean by Intra party elections?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is a mechanism to choose the candidates for various posts of the political through a democratic process, it’s a mandate given by the members of the party itself.</li>
<li>The intra-party election is a fundamental indicator to explore the authenticity of democratization and decentralization of political parties.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why elections are necessary within the political parties?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Internal debates: </strong>During intra party elections there would be contests between leaders. There will be debate, discussions some criticism, and differences of opinion. There should be a dialogue between the leaders, members and volunteers</li>
<li><strong>Democratic culture: </strong>Political parties don’t have to be homogeneous in terms of both ideas and leadership. Political parties are aggregations of interests yet Party workers should not feel they are being ignored, that their efforts are not appreciated or not going in vain under the shadow of a leader came from the family lines.</li>
<li><strong>Political career: </strong>Having these internal elections, meetings and contests of ideas is important.  Internal election is a key for upward mobility. It gives better understanding of the party’s idea, culture and the work process.</li>
<li><strong>High command culture: </strong>High command culture is what we are witnessing today in India and South Asia is problematic for democracy, where all political parties are centralized. The few members at the helm are controlling even the smallest decisions about what party should do. Members are not able to express freely their personal views.</li>
<li><strong>Feudalism: </strong>They are family-controlled parties, and dynastic politics has become a norm. Won’t be able to name more than three or four political parties which have survived 30 years in Indian politics and are today not controlled by apolitical family.</li>
<li><strong>Favoritism: </strong>where you can only rise up the ranks in the system depending on the relationship you share with the first family of that party. Irrespective of difference of opinions with the top leaders of the party, the upward mobility majorly depends on the relationship.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Intra party election" class="alignnone wp-image-639484" height="419" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 679px) 100vw, 679px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84k755ho_maharashtra-chief-minister-eknath-shinde-pti-pic_650x400_04_July_22-300x185.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84k755ho_maharashtra-chief-minister-eknath-shinde-pti-pic_650x400_04_July_22-300x185.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/84k755ho_maharashtra-chief-minister-eknath-shinde-pti-pic_650x400_04_July_22.jpg 650w" width="679"/>What is a Legal framework for election?</strong></h4>
<p>There is no law for intra-party elections as of now.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Seshan effect: </strong>When T.N. Seshan was at the helm of the Election Commission of India (ECI); by an executive order political parties were ordered to conduct intra party elections. And because Seshan was a much respected and feared person, political parties complied with it. Since then, elections are held periodically in every recognized party.</li>
<li><strong>What Constitution says</strong>: Article 324 says free and fair elections to parliament, state assemblies, president and vice-president. It doesn’t say anything about political party or election within.</li>
<li><strong>What Courts argue: </strong>The courts have made an observation that nothing in Article 324 of the Constitution, or Section 29A of the Representation of the People Act, 1951 tells us that the ECI can actually regulate internal structures, organizations or elections of the party. Which is why parties, on the left or right, have not been conducting internal elections as we want them to conduct them</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Worldwide practice</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>USA: </strong>In the U.S. election, the selection of the candidate to be the presidential nominee is done via debate, in which the contenders condemn and criticize each other<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>UK: </strong>In the U.K. Democracy should be at every level, and political parties are an essential pillar of democracy. Intra party election happens to choose the leader of party.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is state funding of election?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is an idea where state or Government of India provides funding to political parties according to their electoral performance.</li>
<li>As of today, state does provide land at concessional rate, free air time on national television but today political parties do not come under RTI. Hence some suggest state funding of elections to regulate the behavior of political parties.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the Role of <a href="https://eci.gov.in/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Election Commission</a> in organizational election of political parties?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The ECI does insist on organizational elections, but only gently. They do go through the process.</li>
<li>Election can happen only if there are two or more candidates in the fray. Getting elected unopposed is also a valid election. It is not just within the political parties, we have</li>
</ul>
<p>Seen it in panchayat elections and sometimes even in Lok Sabha and State Assembly elections that candidates have got elected unopposed.</p>
<h4><strong><img alt="Intra party election" class="alignnone wp-image-639485" height="376" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 564px) 100vw, 564px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BJPcampaign1-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BJPcampaign1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BJPcampaign1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/BJPcampaign1.jpg 1000w" width="564"/>How to fix the accountability of the political parties?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>ECI re-interpreting the existing laws, as happened in the 1990s<strong>. </strong>ECI has to imagine its role as a regulator of these political parties and in some ways. They have to try out milder options.</li>
<li>Political parties are required to hold organizational elections regularly. The parties are required to inform the ECI about changes in their office-bearers.</li>
<li>They are required to submit a document of expenditure incurred during elections and in the non-election periods. But there is no cost attached to non-compliance.</li>
<li>Expert suggests state funding of election would ensure the accountability of parties as it will bring parties under ambit of RTI and voters can seek the expenditure report from parties. Election commission can also penalize party for non-compliance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Election for a gram panchayat or presidential it is always a booster for democracy. Intraparty elections are beneficial for party, contesting individual and country at large, it culminates into emergence of quality leadership which in turn a boon for good governance.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Intra party elections are essential feature of healthy democracy. Discuss the role of election commission, the courts and the political parties for the healthy functioning of intra party democracy.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p>Do follow</p>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/need-for-internal-democracy-in-political-parties/">Internal democracy in political parties</a></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/intra-party-election/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is Ambedkar Tourist Circuit?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ambedkar-tourist-circuit/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Ambedkar Tourist Circuit</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-639721" height="300" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 294px) 100vw, 294px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ambdedkar-294x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ambdedkar-294x300.jpg 294w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ambdedkar.jpg 423w" width="294"/></p>
<p>The Central government has announced a special tourist circuit encompassing five key sites associated with Dr. B.R. Ambedkar.</p>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Activists have urged that Mahad, located in Raigad District of Maharashtra, famous for Mahad Lake Satyagraha should also be included in the proposed circuit.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Ambedkar Circuit</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The five cities in the tourist circuit as announced are Mhow (his birthplace), London (where he resided and studied), Nagpur (also studied here), Delhi (where he passed away) and finally Mumbai (where he was cremated).</li>
<li>With a special AC train, the government is looking to trace the footsteps of Ambedkar in India by giving better connectivity to four of these spots.</li>
<li>The idea is to attract tourists beyond the Dalit community, who mostly visit these places as a pilgrimage.</li>
<li>The journey will include meals, ground transportation, and entry to the sites.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>About the sites</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li><strong>Janma Bhoomi</strong>– Ambedkar’s birthplace in Madhya Pradesh’s Mhow</li>
<li><strong>Shiksha Bhoomi</strong>– the place in London where he stayed while studying in the UK</li>
<li><strong>Deeksha Bhoomi</strong>– the place in Nagpur where he embraced Buddhism</li>
<li><strong>Mahaparinirvan Bhoomi-</strong> the place of his demise in Delhi and</li>
<li><strong>Chaitya Bhoomi-</strong> the place of his cremation in Mumbai</li>
</ol>
<hr/>
<h4><strong>Back2Basics: Tourism Circuits</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The government had identified 15 tourist circuits under the Swadesh Darshan Scheme in 2014-15.</li>
<li>Besides the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-ramayana-circuit/">Ramayana</a> and Buddhist Circuits, others include Coastal Circuit, Desert Circuit, Eco Circuit, Heritage, North East, Himalayan, Sufi, Krishna, Rural, Tribal, and Tirthankar Circuits.</li>
<li>In terms of train collaboration, the Ramayana, Buddhist, and North East Circuits are already active, while Ambedkar will be fourth.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ambedkar-tourist-circuit/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What is International Argo Program?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-international-argo-program-argo/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Argo</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><img alt="argo" class="alignnone wp-image-639718 size-full" height="1108" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 2006px) 100vw, 2006px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/argo.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/argo.jpg 2006w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/argo-300x166.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/argo-1024x566.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/argo-768x424.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/argo-1536x848.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/argo-1200x663.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/argo-1980x1094.jpg 1980w" width="2006"/></p>
<p>The International Argo Program system to observe carbon concentration in the world’s oceans is extremely inadequate to meet the growing and urgent need for information on oceanic carbon, says a report.</p>
<h4>What is Argo?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Argo is an international program that uses profiling floats to observe temperature, salinity, currents, and, recently, bio-optical properties in the Earth’s oceans; it has been operational since the early 2000s.</li>
<li>The real-time data it provides is used in climate and oceanographic research.</li>
<li>A special research interest is to quantify the ocean heat content (OHC).</li>
<li>Each instrument (float) spends almost all its life below the surface.</li>
<li>The name Argo was chosen because the array of floats works in partnership with the Jason earth observing satellites that measure the shape of the ocean surface.</li>
<li>In Greek mythology Jason sailed on his ship the Argo in search of the Golden Fleece.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are its aims?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The data that Argo collects describes the temperature and salinity of the water and some of the floats measure other properties that describe the biology/chemistry of the ocean.</li>
<li>The main reason for collecting these data is to help us understand the oceans’ role in earth’s climate.</li>
<li>For example, the changes in sea level (once the tides are averaged out) depend partly on the melting of icecaps and partly on the amount of heat stored in the oceans.</li>
<li>Argo’s temperature measurements allow us to calculate how much heat is stored and to monitor from year to year how the distribution of heat changes with depth and from area to area.</li>
<li>As ocean heat content increases, sea level rises, just like the mercury in a thermometer.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How does it work?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Each Argo float (costing between $20,000 and $150,000 depending on the individual float’s technical specification) is launched from a ship.</li>
<li>The float’s weight is carefully adjusted so that, as it sinks, it eventually stabilizes at a pre-set level, usually 1 km.</li>
<li>Ten days later, an internal battery-driven pump transfers oil between a reservoir inside the float and an external bladder.</li>
<li>This makes the float first descend to 2km and then return to the surface measuring ocean properties as it rises.</li>
<li>The data and the float position are relayed to satellites and then on to receiving stations on shore.</li>
<li>The float then sinks again to repeat the 10 day cycle until its batteries are exhausted.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-international-argo-program-argo/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>G4 countries call for UNSC reforms</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/g4-countries-call-for-unsc-reforms/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>G4, Coffee Club, UNSC</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>UNSC reforms</p></div></div><p><img alt="g4" class="alignnone wp-image-639722 size-full" height="546" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 901px) 100vw, 901px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1.jpg 901w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1-300x182.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-1-768x465.jpg 768w" width="901"/></p>
<p>The G4 nations have said that the Intergovernmental Negotiations on <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-india-at-united-nations-security-council/">UN Security Council</a> reform are constrained by a lack of openness and transparency.</p>
<h4><strong>Who are the G4 Countries?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The G4 nations, comprising <strong><u>Brazil, Germany, India, and Japan</u></strong> are four countries which support each other’s bids for permanent seats on the United Nations Security Council.</li>
<li>Their primary aim is the permanent member seats on the Security Council.</li>
<li>Each of these four countries have figured among the elected non-permanent members of the council since the UN’s establishment.</li>
<li>Their economic and political influence has grown significantly in the last decades, reaching a scope comparable to the permanent members (P5).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Deterrent in their cause</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The UK and France have backed the G4’s bid for permanent seats.</li>
<li>All the permanent members of P5 have supported India’s bids for permanent seat.</li>
<li>However, China has previously implied that it is only ready to support India if it does not associate its bid with Japan.</li>
<li>The US has sent strong indications to Brazil that it is willing to support its membership; albeit, without a veto.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What holds them back?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There has been discontent among the present permanent members regarding the inclusion of controversial nations or countries not supported by them.</li>
<li>For instance, Japan’s bid is heavily opposed by China, North Korea, Russia and South Korea who think that <strong><u>Japan</u></strong> needs to make sincere reparations for <strong><u>war crimes</u></strong> committed during World War II.</li>
<li>Under the leadership of Italy, countries that strongly oppose the G4 countries’ bids have formed the <strong><u>Uniting for Consensus movement</u></strong>, also called as <strong><u>Coffee Club</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In Asia, Pakistan opposes India’s bid.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why India deserves a permanent seat?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has been part of UN since inception.</li>
<li>It has the world’s second-largest population and is the world’s largest democracy suited to represent South Asia.</li>
<li>It has contributed maximum peacekeepers to UN so far.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why reform UNSC?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Non-representative nature:</strong> UNSC in current form is not representative of developing world and global needs, with primacy of policy being political tool in hands of P5, is well recognised globally.</li>
<li><strong>Contention over Veto and Technical Holds:</strong> <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/china-blocks-terrorist-listing-at-unsc-1267-list/">Veto power</a> with P5 enables any one of them to prevent the adoption of any “substantive” draft Council resolution, regardless of its level of international support.</li>
<li><strong>Divided institution: </strong>UNSC has become an organisation, which can pass strong resolutions against weak countries, weak resolutions against strong countries and no resolution against P5 countries.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There is a possibility that if UN doesn’t reform itself, it may lose relevance and alternate global and regional groupings may assume greater importance.</li>
<li>More global pressure from middle powers like G4 may force an expansion of UNSC as a possibility, but abolition of veto power in current set up is unlikely</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: United Nations Security Council (UNSC)</h4>
<ul>
<li>The UNSC is one of the six principal organs of the United Nations and is charged with the maintenance of international peace and security.</li>
<li>Its powers include the establishment of peacekeeping operations, the establishment of international sanctions, and the authorization of military action through Security Council resolutions.</li>
<li>It is the only UN body with the authority to issue binding resolutions to member states.</li>
<li>The Security Council consists of fifteen members. Russia, the United Kingdom, France, China, and the United States—serve as the body’s five permanent members.</li>
<li>These permanent members can veto any substantive Security Council resolution, including those on the admission of new member states or candidates for Secretary-General.</li>
<li>The Security Council also has 10 non-permanent members, elected on a regional basis to serve two-year terms. The body’s presidency rotates monthly among its members.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/g4-countries-call-for-unsc-reforms/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Adani’s global footprint and India’s infrastructure diplomacy   </title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/infrastructure-diplomacy/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Infrastructure diplomacy</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="infrastructure diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-639689" height="317" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 598px) 100vw, 598px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1602768183608-300x159.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1602768183608-300x159.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1602768183608.jpg 600w" width="598"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>From mines to ports and logistics, the Adani conglomerate has been expanding across sectors, regions. This has gone hand in hand with India’s diplomatic and strategic outreach towards infrastructure diplomacy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is infrastructure?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Infrastructure is the set of facilities and systems that serve a country, city, or other area, and encompasses the services and facilities necessary for its economy, households and firms to function.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/infrastructure-sector-in-india-definitions-growth-and-infrastructure-linkage/"><strong>What are the features of infrastructure?</strong></a></h4>
<ul>
<li>Power and the source of its production such as coal and oil;</li>
<li>Roads and road transport;</li>
<li>Railways;</li>
<li>Communication, especially telecommunication;</li>
<li>Ports and airports; and.</li>
<li>For agriculture, irrigation constitutes the important infrastructure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="infrastructure diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-639690" height="488" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 559px) 100vw, 559px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/word-image148-300x262.png" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/word-image148-300x262.png 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/word-image148-1024x895.png 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/word-image148-768x671.png 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/word-image148-1030x900.png 1030w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/word-image148.png 1046w" width="559"/>What is infrastructure diplomacy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Infrastructure diplomacy is to promote infrastructure cooperation and economic ties overseas through political means and to enhance political trust between countries via collaboration in infrastructure development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news? </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>“Several foreign governments are now approaching us to work in their geographies and help build their infrastructure. Therefore, in 2022, we also laid the foundation to seek a broader expansion beyond India’s boundaries,” chairman and founder of the Adani group Gautam Adani,<strong><a href="https://indianexpress.com/article/business/gautam-adani-second-most-richest-billionaire-forbes-list-bernard-arnault-jeff-bezos-elon-musk-8154481/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">now the world’s third-richest person</a>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="infrastructure diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-639691" height="364" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Adani-300x168.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Adani-300x168.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Adani-768x430.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Adani.jpeg 770w" width="650"/>Background </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Foreign presence much earlier</strong>: In fact, the Adani group had been scouting abroad much earlier. Since 2010, the Adani group has been in Australia, developing the Carmichael coal mine in Queensland.</li>
<li><strong>A greenfield multi-purpose port:</strong> In 2017, Adani Ports and Special Economic Zones (Ltd) signed an MoU for a greenfield multi-purpose port for handling containers at Carey Island in Selangor state, about 50 km southwest of Kuala Lumpur.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is situation now?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Company pursue international infrastructure projects aggressively</strong>: The last two years, however, have seen the company pursue international infrastructure projects aggressively. In May 2022, APSEZ made a winning bid of $1.18 billion for Israeli state-owned Haifa Port, jointly with Israeli chemicals and logistics firm Gadot.</li>
<li><strong>Strategic joint investments</strong>: In August this year, APSEZ and Abu Dhabi’s AD Ports Group signed MoU for “strategic joint investments” in Tanzania. The new ASEZ-AD MoU will look at a bouquet of infrastructure projects besides Bagamoyo in the East African Indian Ocean nation — rail, maritime services, digital services and industrial zones<strong>.</strong></li>
<li><strong>India’s strategic objectives than has been possible so far</strong>: Is it just a coincidence that Adani’s global expansion closely shadows the Chinese footprint along its Belt and Road Initiative? Or is it that as <a href="https://indianexpress.com/section/cities/delhi/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Delhi</a>competes with China for influence in the neighbourhood and beyond, the Adani group’s size, resources and capacity are seen as a key element in achieving India’s strategic objectives than has been possible so far.</li>
<li><strong>India’s infrastructure diplomacy</strong>: Is now becoming identified the world over with one company.</li>
<li><strong>Public and private investment to bridge gaps</strong>: For the Adani group, described as India’s biggest ports and logistics company, there couldn’t be a better time. As the Quad grouping of Australia, India, Japan, and the US, competes with China in the Indo-Pacific, it has committed “to catalyse infrastructure delivery” by putting more than $50 billion on the table for “assistance and investment” in the Indo-Pacific over the next five years and “drive public and private investment to bridge gaps”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="infrastructure diplomacy" class="alignnone wp-image-639692" height="484" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 859px) 100vw, 859px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gautam_adani_1663308148066_1663308148213_1663308148213.jpg 1600w" width="859"/>Implications of infrastructure diplomacy</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Win-Win deal</strong>: Adani’s new “no-hands” model of doing business with neighbours a power plant in Jharkhand, exporting all its output to Bangladesh has been seen as a “win-win” deal.</li>
<li><strong>Economic interests lie at the heart of geopolitics:</strong> The link between diplomacy and commercial interests has generated its share of debate, especially in the US, where its diplomats, intelligence agencies and military interventions abroad have actively pushed the interests of big business first the hunt for cheaper raw materials, then for markets abroad, then to shift industry where manpower was cheaper. As seen in the new age trading blocs the US-led IPEF, and the Chinese dominated RCEP economic interests lie at the heart of geopolitics.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>At a time when global rivalries are growing sharper in the shadow of the war in Europe, and as India looks out for its own interests, pushing powerful corporates to the centre-stage of its diplomacy, whether it is to build ports, buy or sell weapons or make chips, is inevitable.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Economic interests lie at the heart of geopolitics. Analyse this statement in context of India’s active push for infrastructure diplomacy by including private conglomerates like Adani in it.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/infrastructure-diplomacy/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Constitutional Breakdown in Nepal</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/constitutional-breakdown-in-nepal/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>India-Nepal Relations</p></div></div><p><img alt="nepal" class="alignnone wp-image-639720 size-full" height="379" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 724px) 100vw, 724px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nepal.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nepal.jpg 724w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nepal-300x157.jpg 300w" width="724"/></p>
<p>Nepal is in a constitutional crisis with major organs of the state confronting each other as the Chief Justice is under undeclared house arrest and the PM openly criticizing the President.</p>
<h4>Nepal polity in turmoil</h4>
<ul>
<li>Prime Minister who is backed by the chiefs of four major coalition partners, is at loggerheads with President.</li>
<li>The President might seek to rule as an extra-constitutional authority beyond the sanction and imagination of the Constitution that completed six years last week.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Genesis of the crisis: Row over Citizenship</h4>
<ul>
<li>The current crisis began after President refused to ratify Nepal’s citizenship bill, which was sent to her twice after it was passed by both Houses of Parliament over the span of a month.</li>
<li>The bill seeks to give citizenship by birth and by descent to an estimated 500,000 individuals.</li>
<li>It was also sought to provide non-voting citizenship to non-resident Nepalis living in non-SAARC countries.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Constitutional crisis in Nepal: A backgrounder</h4>
<ul>
<li>Nepal transitioned into a democracy beginning with the fall of the monarchy in 2006 and the subsequent election of the Maoist government in 2008.</li>
<li>The emergence of the multiparty system was followed by the adoption of a constitution on September 20, 2015.</li>
<li>All Nepalese citizens born before this date got naturalised citizenship.</li>
<li>But their children remained without citizenship as that was to be guided by a federal law which has not yet been framed.</li>
<li>This amendment Act was expected to pave the way to citizenship for many such stateless youth as well as their parents.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What are the issues with the Act?</h4>
<p><strong>Ans. <u>Gender bias</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The main criticism against the Citizenship Amendment Act, 2006 is that it goes against established parameters of gender justice.</li>
<li>According to Article 11(2b), a person born to a father or a mother with Nepalese citizenship can get citizenship by descent.</li>
<li>Another article says a person who is born to a Nepalese mother (who has lived in the country) and an unidentified father will also get citizenship by descent.</li>
<li>But this section appears humiliating for a mother as she has to declare that her husband is unidentified for the child to be eligible for citizenship.</li>
<li>In case of a Nepalese father, such declarations are not required.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why has the President refused to sign the Act?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Bhandari is the first female President of Nepal.</li>
<li>Her refusal to sign the Act has drawn attention to certain sections in the constitution that thrusts greater responsibility on women.</li>
<li>For example, Article 11 (5) says that a person who is born to a Nepalese mother and an unidentified father can be granted citizenship by descent.</li>
<li>Next, it says that in case the unidentified father turns out to be a foreigner, the citizenship by descent would be converted to naturalised citizenship.</li>
<li>Furthermore, it supports punitive action against the mother if the father is found later.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Indian connection to the issue</h4>
<ul>
<li>There is an unarticulated concern in the orthodox sections that Nepalese men, particularly from the Terai region, continue to marry women from northern India.</li>
<li>These people feel that Nepalese identity would be undermined.</li>
<li>Because of this “Beti-Roti” (Nepalese men marrying Indian women) issue, many women could not become citizens of Nepal.</li>
<li>They were subjected to the infamous seven-year cooling off period before they could apply for citizenship in Nepal.</li>
<li>As such women were stateless, children of such families were also often found to be without Nepalese citizenship.</li>
<li>However, the new amendments have done away with the cooling off period for these stateless women.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/constitutional-breakdown-in-nepal/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>On the trail of alarming rabies cases which is having serious apprehensions</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rabies/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>particulars of virus</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Human health</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="rabies" class="alignnone wp-image-639695" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 689px) 100vw, 689px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/p032g69z-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/p032g69z-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/p032g69z-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/p032g69z.jpg 976w" width="689"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The death of a 12-year-old girl in Pathanamthitta has sharpened the focus on the rising number of rabies cases and the growing population of stray dogs in Kerala</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is rabies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The rabies virus attacks the central nervous system of the host, and in humans, it can cause a range of debilitating symptoms including states of anxiety and confusion, partial paralysis, agitation, hallucinations, and, in its final phases, a symptom called “hydrophobia,” or a fear of water.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are rabies caused by?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Rabies is a preventable viral disease most often transmitted through the bite of a rabid animal. The rabies virus infects the central nervous system of mammals, ultimately causing disease in the brain and death.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Can rabies person survive?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Once clinical signs of rabies appear, the disease is nearly always fatal, and treatment is typically supportive. Less than 20 cases of human survival from clinical rabies have been documented.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How long can a human live with rabies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Death usually occurs 2 to 10 days after first symptoms. Survival is almost unknown once symptoms have presented, even with intensive care.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="rabies" class="alignnone wp-image-639696" height="574" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 574px) 100vw, 574px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infographic-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infographic-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infographic-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infographic-768x766.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infographic.jpg 876w" width="574"/>Facts on rabies </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>What animal has the most rabies?</strong></li>
<li><strong>Bats</strong></li>
<li><strong>Wild animals accounted for 92.7% of reported cases of rabies in 2018. Bats were the most frequently reported rabid wildlife species (33% of all animal cases during 2018), followed by raccoons (30.3%), skunks (20.3%), and foxes (7.2%).</strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="rabies" class="alignnone wp-image-639698" height="417" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 626px) 100vw, 626px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/straydogs-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/straydogs-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/straydogs.jpg 621w" width="626"/>What is the issue?                                   </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>There is a blame game over the rising rabies cases:</strong> With the rabies deaths causing panic and reports of residents killing stray dogs through poisoning and strangulation, there is a blame game over the rising canine population and rabies cases. Some legal experts blame it on conflicts in the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act, 1960 and the Animal Birth Control (Dogs) Rules, 2001; others point to the flawed implementation of birth control measures.</li>
<li><strong>Legal battle over the issue in the Supreme Court:</strong> Canine culling campaigners and advocates of animal rights are also engaged in a protracted legal battle over the issue in the Supreme Court. V.K. Biju, a lawyer of the Supreme Court, who brought the issue of the “stray dog menace” before the apex court, contends that the root cause is the enactment of the Rules, which according to him, were passed in contravention of the parent Act, the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act.</li>
<li><strong>Existence of stray dogs has adversely affected the fundamental rights of citizens</strong>: Biju says that while the Act stands for the “destruction” of stray dogs, the rules are against the “destruction” of stray dogs, including the rabies affected ones, besides providing specific protection of stray dogs. In his submission before the Supreme Court, he argues that the existence of stray dogs has adversely affected the fundamental rights of citizens, i.e. the right to life and free movement.</li>
<li><strong>The quashing of the Rules to make India free of stray dogs</strong>: In his writ petition filed before the apex court, Biju has sought orders for the strict implementation of the Act and the quashing of the Rules to make India free of stray dogs.</li>
<li><strong>Animal rights campaigners are apprehensive</strong>: In the light of this, animal rights campaigners are apprehensive over the campaign to cull dogs to check rabies.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="rabies" class="alignnone wp-image-639697" height="505" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infection-from-dog-to-human-300x261.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infection-from-dog-to-human-300x261.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rabies-infection-from-dog-to-human.jpg 500w" width="580"/>How can we prevent rabies in animals?</strong></h4>
<ol>
<li>First, visit your veterinarian with your pet on a regular basis and keep rabies vaccinations up-to-date for all cats, ferrets, and dogs.</li>
<li>Second, maintain control of your pets by keeping cats and ferrets indoors and keeping dogs under direct supervision.</li>
<li>Third, spay or neuter your pets to help reduce the number of unwanted pets that may not be properly cared for or vaccinated regularly.</li>
<li>Finally, call animal control to remove all stray animals from your neighbourhood since these animals may be unvaccinated or ill.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>How can we prevent rabies in humans?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Leave all wildlife alone.</li>
<li>Know the risk: contact with infected bats is the leading cause of rabies deaths in people followed by exposure to rabid dogs while traveling internationally.</li>
<li>Wash animal bites or scratches immediately with soap and water.</li>
<li>If you are bitten, scratched, or unsure, talk to a healthcare provider about whether you need postexposure prophylaxis. Rabies in people is 100% preventable through prompt appropriate medical care.</li>
<li>Vaccinate your pets to protect them and your family.</li>
</ul>
<h4><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/a-one-health-approach-that-targets-people-animals/"><strong>Initiatives by Government to curb Neglected Tropical Diseases</strong></a></h4>
<p><a href="https://ncdc.gov.in/index1.php?lang=1&amp;level=1&amp;sublinkid=146&amp;lid=150" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>National Rabies Control Programme</strong></a>: This programme is being restructured as Integrated National Rabies Control Programme under ‘One Health Approach’, with a aim to provide vaccination to stray dogs and free vaccines through Government hospitals.</p>
<p><strong>Way forward</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Think globally, act locally. Study and adopt global ‘best-practices’ after customising them to local needs.</li>
<li>Apply integrated approach. Follow a holistic strategy.</li>
<li>Ensure efficient and effective collaboration across various government departments.</li>
<li>Partner with Civil Society Organisations (especially with WASH – Water, Sanitation and Hygiene – sector) for ground-level implementation and monitoring.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. What is rabies? What ethical challenges are involved in culling of stray dogs? Explain the control measures for the same.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/rabies/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why our urban centres need to be better planned</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-centres/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>smart city mission</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>urban planning</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="urban centres " class="alignnone wp-image-639704" height="677" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 875px) 100vw, 875px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-300x232.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-300x232.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1024x793.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-768x595.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1536x1190.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1162x900.jpg 1162w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1200x929.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities.-1980x1534.jpg 1980w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PARKROYAL_ON_PICKERING_%E2%80%93_Image_by_%C2%AEPatrick_Bingham-Hall_for_WOHA_featured_in_Dense_Green_Cities..jpg 2000w" width="875"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian urban centres need to plan for migration, climate change. Healthcare, affordable housing, sustainability and inclusion hold the key reimagining them.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does urban planning mean?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Urban planning encompasses the preparation of plans for and the regulation and management of towns, cities, and metropolitan regions. It attempts to organize socio-spatial relations across different scales of government and governance.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are ‘Happy Cities’?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A term that follows the Green City, Sustainable City, Liveable City, in the lingo of urban planning</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="urban centres " class="alignnone wp-image-639706" height="451" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Kampung_Admiralty_by_Ramboll_Studio_Dreiseitl__WOHA_and_Storm._Image__Patrick_Bingham-Hall_1-300x209.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Kampung_Admiralty_by_Ramboll_Studio_Dreiseitl__WOHA_and_Storm._Image__Patrick_Bingham-Hall_1-300x209.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Kampung_Admiralty_by_Ramboll_Studio_Dreiseitl__WOHA_and_Storm._Image__Patrick_Bingham-Hall_1.jpg 750w" width="647"/><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/smart-cities-mission-and-the-public-health/">What is a smart city?</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A smart city is one that uses information and communication technologies to enhance citizen engagement. It is a neo-vision which seeks to improve the delivery of services in urban areas. The following story maps out the steps being taken by India to explore this concept in practice.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Fast Facts -Urbanization in India</strong></h4>
<p>Most Urbanized States: Tamil Nadu 43.9%; Maharashtra 4%; Gujarat  37.4%.</p>
<p>3 out of world’s 21 mega cities: Mumbai (19 mill); Delhi (15 mill); Kolkata (14 mill)</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Global best practices in urban planning </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garden_city_movement" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>The Garden City movement:</strong> </a>In the West, the Garden City movement (initiated by Ebenezer Howard in 1898) sought to decentralise the working environment in the city centre with a push for providing healthier living spaces for factory workers. The ideal garden city was planned on a concentric pattern with open spaces, public parks and boulevards, housing 32,000 people on 6,000 acres, linked to a central city with over 50,000 people. Once a garden city reached maximum capacity, another city would be developed nearby.</li>
<li><strong>Neighbourhood concept</strong>: In the US, the garden city movement evolved into the neighbourhood concept, where residential houses and streets were organised around a local school or community centre, with a push for lowering traffic and providing safe roads. London has a metropolitan green belt around the city, covering 5,13,860 hectares of land, to offset pollution and congestion and maintain biodiversity. Why can’t Indian cities have something similar, instead of ring roads and urban sprawls?</li>
<li><strong>La ville du quart d’heure: </strong>Paris has taken this forward with the “15-minute city” (‘la ville du quart d’heure’). The idea is rather simple, every Parisian should be able to do their shopping, work, and recreational activities and fulfil their cultural needs within a 15-minute walk or bike ride this means that the number of vehicular trips gets reduced significantly.</li>
<li><strong>Investment in pedestrian infrastructure and non-motorised transport zones</strong>: A city would then be planned for pedestrians, instead of cars and motors. This requires an extensive usage of mixed-use developments, along with investment in pedestrian infrastructure and non-motorised transport zones. Instead of widening highways, this approach would push for widening pedestrian walkways.</li>
</ul>
<p><img alt="urban centres " class="alignnone wp-image-639707" height="388" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-300x208.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-300x208.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-1024x711.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-768x533.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000-1200x833.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/UrbanPlanner1440x1000.jpg 1440w" width="560"/></p>
<h4><strong>What should be adopted for India?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Every Indian city should ideally have a Master Plan</strong>: A strategic urban planning document which would be updated every decade or two. The document would entail how a city is supposed to grow, vertically and horizontally, across zones, while offering a high quality of life in a sustainable manner. Such plans would also consider poverty mitigation, affordable housing and liveability for urban migrants.</li>
<li><strong>Urban land use needs to be better</strong>: One look at satellite map imagery will show that India’s urban growth is increasingly haphazard, with informal, unplanned and sprawling neighbourhoods developing in paddy fields and along linear infrastructure (arterial roads, open spaces). India’s hidden urbanisation, driven partly by our stringent definition of the word, along with weak enforcement of building codes, has meant that the local government is often playing catch-up, unable to provide urban services and infrastructure to keep up with growth.</li>
<li><strong>Public land availability</strong>: Meanwhile, in places where there are formally recognised towns and urban neighbourhoods, outdated planning practices have meant that land utilisation is poor. Consider the case of Mumbai, where almost 1/4th of the land is open public space while over half of it is the underutilised space around buildings, which is enclosed by walls and hived off from public access. Such open spaces, if available, would help cities like Mumbai achieve similar ratios as globally benchmarked cities (Amsterdam, Barcelona) in public land availability (typically above 40 per cent).</li>
<li><strong>India’s urban density will also need to be thought through</strong>: Dense construction on the peripheries of our major cities (for instance, dense construction in Delhi’s suburbs, like Noida and Gurugram) will inevitably mean that public services are stretched and emissions (due to transportation to the main city) remain high. Such urbanisation will unavoidably lock India into a high emissions future while making our cities prone to extreme heat and flooding.</li>
<li><strong>Then there is climate change: </strong>According to the World Bank, climate change may reduce India’s GDP by 3 per cent, while depressing the living standards of its citizens by 2050. Many urban experts cite technological solutions that may save our cities a chain of sea walls, river embankments and reclamations, for instance from such potential calamities. However, structural engineering simply may not be an economically and environmentally feasible option everywhere instead, our focus must be on conservation.</li>
<li><strong>Climate resilience perspective</strong> Bengaluru, with its network of interconnected lakes, could have considered Bangkok-style ferries instead of draining out its lakes. All ongoing and upcoming urban infrastructure projects must be reconsidered from a future climate resilience perspective does the ongoing sea reclamation for the upcoming coastal road in Mumbai make sense if sea levels are rising?</li>
<li><strong>Establishing a sense of cityhood</strong>: By making a push for a city as a co-created space will also require building up institutional capacity.</li>
<li><strong>Addressing lack of town planning education: </strong>India would ideally require 3,00,000 town and country planners by 2031 (there are just 5,000 town planners currently). Much of this problem is fundamentally due to a lack of town planning education in the country there are just 26 institutes that provide this course, producing 700 town planners each year. We already have a shortage of 1.1 million planners. More schools are needed, with a push for local IITs and NITs to have a standalone planning department. With over 8,000 towns and cities, there is a clear unmet need.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><img alt="urban centres" class="alignnone wp-image-639709" height="347" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 616px) 100vw, 616px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432-1-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432-1-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/684461-urban-city-768x432-1.jpg 768w" width="616"/>Conclusion </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Our policymakers also need to be cognisant of the historical context of our urban development a push for glass buildings or utilising granite may not always be suitable for our cities. Why can’t our cities look distinctly Indian, inspired by our historical architecture? Renewing our cities will require us to rethink various urban topics, including urban design, urban healthcare, affordable housing, sustainability and inclusion among others. Our urban future depends on getting this right.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Renewing our cities will require us to rethink various urban topics, including urban design, urban healthcare, affordable housing, sustainability and inclusion among others. Elaborate.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/urban-centres/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Nationwide Crackdown on PFI</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pfi-nationwide-crackdown-on-pfi/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PFI</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Terrorism and radicalization in India</p></div></div><p><img alt="pfi" class="alignnone wp-image-639719 size-full" height="415" sizes="(max-width: 712px) 100vw, 712px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nia.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nia.jpg 712w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nia-300x175.jpg 300w" width="712"/></p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/functioning-of-the-national-investigation-agency-nia/">National Investigation Agency (NIA)</a> has launched a massive nationwide search operation in connection with anti-terror activities linked to the Popular Front of India-PFI.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the Popular Front of India (PFI)?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PFI was created in 2007 through the merger of three radicalists organisations in southern India, the National Democratic Front in Kerala, the Karnataka Forum for Dignity, and the Manitha Neethi Pasarai in Tamil Nadu.</li>
<li>A decision to bring the three outfits together was taken in November 2006 at a meeting in Kozhikode in Kerala.</li>
<li>The formation of the PFI was formally announced at a rally in Bengaluru during what was called the “Empower India Conference” on February 16, 2007.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Agenda of the PFI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The PFI has projected itself as an organisation that fights for the rights of minorities, Dalits, and marginalised communities.</li>
<li>It has frequently targeted the alleged anti-people policies of the State even as these mainstream parties have accused one another of being in cahoots with the PFI to gather the support of Muslims at the time of elections.</li>
<li>The PFI has itself never contested elections.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Parallel organizations to PFI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2009, a political outfit named Social Democratic Party of India (SDPI) evolved out of the PFI, with the aim of taking up the political issues of Muslims, Dalits, and other marginalised communities.</li>
<li>The SDPI’s stated goal is advancement and uniform development of all the citizenry including Muslims, Dalits, Backward Classes and Adivasis and to share power fairly among all the citizens.</li>
<li>The PFI is a key provider of ground workers for the SDPI’s political activities.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is PFI under crackdown?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Links to terror outfits</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Many volunteers of PFI are allegedly involved in terror funding, organising training camps, and radicalising people to join proscribed organisations.</li>
<li>It has been involved in carrying out social and Islamic religious work among Muslims on the lines of the work done by right-wing groups.</li>
<li>The PFI does not maintain records of its members, and it has been difficult for law enforcement agencies to pin crimes on the organisation after making arrests.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Promoting Radicalization</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The outfit is hostile to the consolidation across the country and the rise of a single non-secular party as the nation’s pre-eminent political and ideological force.</li>
<li>The post-2014 political landscape and the self-alienation of minorities has further pushed sections of the community towards groups like the PFI.</li>
<li>The outfit is also said to have a large number of supporters in Gulf countries who contribute handsomely to its kitty, something which is under the scanner of investigating agencies.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Hostility against state mechanism</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Starting out as an organisation primarily rooted in Kerala, Karnataka and Tamil Nadu, the PFI has spread its wings far and wide, with a presence in at least 18 states.</li>
<li>It has found particularly fertile ground in parts of Uttar Pradesh and Assam.</li>
<li>Authorities have accused the outfit of instigating and funding protests against the CAA and the National Register of Citizens.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Barbarism in the name of religion</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The PFI has had the most visible presence in Kerala, where it has been repeatedly accused of murder, rioting, intimidation, and having links with terrorist organisations.</li>
<li>The Kerala government affidavit said PFI activists were involved in 27 cases of MURDER, mostly of CPM and RSS cadres, and that the motives were highly communal.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pfi-nationwide-crackdown-on-pfi/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>