<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0"><channel><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link><description>This is generated feed from main website.</description><atom:link href="http://larskiesow.de/test.atom" rel="self"/><docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs><generator>python-feedgen</generator><image><url>http://ex.com/logo.jpg</url><title>CivilsDaily Feeds</title><link>http://larskiesow.de/test.atom</link></image><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 13:42:39 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Tamil Nadu’s new Breakfast Scheme in Schools</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tamil-nadus-breakfast-scheme-in-schools/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Meal schemes for students</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="breakfast" class="alignnone wp-image-636711" height="230" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 408px) 100vw, 408px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/food-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/food-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/food.jpg 700w" width="408"/></strong></p>
<p>Tamil Nadu CM has launched the Chief Minister’s Breakfast Scheme for students of Class I to V in government schools.</p>
<h4><strong>CM’s Breakfast Scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme covers around 1.14 lakh students in 1,545 schools which include 417 municipal corporation schools, 163 municipality schools and 728 taluk and village panchayat-level schools.</li>
<li>The inauguration of the scheme marks an important milestone in the State’s history of providing <strong><u>free meals to school students.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>How has the idea evolved?</h4>
<p><strong>(a) Pre-independence</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>In November 1920, the Madras Corporation Council approved a proposal for providing tiffin to the students of a Corporation School at Thousand Lights at a cost not exceeding one anna per student per day.</li>
<li>Theagaraya Chetty, the then President of the Corporation and one of the stalwarts of the Justice Party, said the boys studying at the school were poor, which affected the strength of the institution ‘greatly’.</li>
<li>The scheme, which was extended to four more schools and facilitated higher enrollment of students.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(b) Post-independence</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The concept saw a <strong><u>Statewide application in 1956</u></strong> when the then CM K. Kamaraj decided to provide free noon meal to poor children in all primary schools across the State.</li>
<li>The Budget for 1956-57 contained a provision for supplying mid-day meals to schoolchildren for 200 days a year, initially covering 65,000 students in 1,300 feeding centres.</li>
<li>In July 1982, it was left to the then CM MG Ramachandran to extend the programme to children in the 2-5 age group in Anganwadis and those in 5-9 age group in primary schools in rural areas.</li>
<li>Subsequently, the scheme now called <strong><u>Puratchi Thalaivar MGR Nutritious Meal Programme</u></strong> — was extended to urban areas as well.</li>
<li>Since September 1984, students of standards VI to X have been covered under the scheme.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Beneficiaries of the programme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As of now, there are nearly <strong><u>7 lakh beneficiaries</u></strong> spread over 43,190 nutritious meal centres.</li>
<li>This includes around 3,500 students of <strong><u>National Child Labour Project (NCLP)</u></strong> special schools.</li>
<li>Besides, as a consequence of the collaborative implementation of the <strong><u>Integrated Child Development Scheme (ICDS)</u></strong> and the nutritious meal programme, around 15.8 lakh children in the age group of 2+ to 5+ years receive nutritious meals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Impact on school education</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Rise in enrolment:</strong> After the improved version of the mid-day meal scheme in 1982, the Gross Enrollment Ratio (GER) at primary level (standards I to V) went up by 10% during July-September, 1982 as compared to the corresponding period in 1981.</li>
<li><strong>Girls’ enrolment:</strong> The rise in boys’ enrollment was 12% and in the case of girls, 7%, according to a publication brought out by the Tamil Nadu government on the occasion of the launch of the Scheme.</li>
<li><strong>Increase in attendance:</strong> Likewise, attendance during July-September 1982 rose by 33% over the previous year’s figure.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Focus areas programme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Anaemia</u></strong> is a major health problem in Tamil Nadu, especially among women and children, says the 2019-21 National Family Health Survey (NFHS)-5’s report.</li>
<li>From 50% during the period of the 2015-16 NFHS-4, the prevalence of anaemia in children now went up to 57%.</li>
<li>This and many other health issues can be addressed through the combined efforts of the departments of School Education, Public Health and Social Welfare and Women Empowerment.</li>
<li>Besides, a continuous and rigorous review of the progress of the scheme and nutritious meal programme should be carried out in a sustained manner.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/tamil-nadus-breakfast-scheme-in-schools/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Centre cites law to deny medical seats to Ukraine-returnees</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-deny-medical-seat-ukraine-returns/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Medical education pursuance in foreign and issues</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="medical" class="alignnone wp-image-636747" height="241" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 402px) 100vw, 402px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ukr-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ukr-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ukr-768x461.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ukr.jpg 917w" width="402"/></strong></p>
<p>The Centre has told the Supreme Court that the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/national-medical-commission-replaces-the-mci/">law</a> does not allow undergraduate medical students, who fled the “war-like situation” in Ukraine, to be accommodated in Indian medical colleges.</p>
<h4><strong>Which laws is the govt talking about?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>There are no provisions either under the <strong><u>Indian Medical Council Act, 1956</u></strong>, or the <strong><u>National Medical Commission Act, 2019</u></strong> to accommodate or transfer medical students.</li>
<li>Till now, no permission has been given by the National Medical Commission to transfer or accommodate any foreign medical students in any Indian medical institute/university.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why foreign undergraduates are not permitted?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Absence of law:</strong> The extant regulations in India do not permit migration of students from foreign universities to India.</li>
<li><strong>No backdoor entry:</strong> The public notice cannot be used as a back door entry into Indian colleges offering undergraduate courses.</li>
<li><strong>Merit issue:</strong> The students had left for foreign universities for two reasons, poor marks in the National Eligibility cum Entrance Test (NEET) and affordability of medical education in foreign countries.</li>
<li><strong>High cost:</strong> Besides, these students, if admitted in Indian colleges, would again face the problem of affordability.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why do Indians go abroad for medical studies?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to estimates from Ukraine, reported in the media, around 18,000 Indian students are in Ukraine (before Operation Ganga).</li>
<li>Most of them are pursuing medicine.</li>
<li>This war has turned the spotlight on something that has been the trend for about three decades now.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Preferred countries for a medical degree</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>For about three decades now, Indian students have been heading out to Russia, China, Ukraine, Kyrgyzstan, Kazakhstan, and Philippines to pursue a medical degree.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Hype of becoming a Doctor</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Prestige:</strong> The desire to study medicine still holds a lot of value in the Indian community (the other is becoming an IAS officer).</li>
<li><strong>Shortages of Doctor:</strong> In many rural areas, people still look at doctors as god’s incarnate.</li>
<li><strong>Rarity of opportunity:</strong> The lack of equal opportunities exacerbated by the caste factor in the Indian context, has a great deal of impact on the prestige still associated with being a doctor.</li>
<li><strong>Social upliftment ladder:</strong> For years, certain communities were denied the opportunities, and finally they do have a chance at achieving significant educational status.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why do Indians prefer going abroad?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>No language barrier:</strong> The medium of education for these students is English, a language they are comfortable with.</li>
<li><strong>Affordability:</strong> The amount spent on living and the medical degree are far more affordable than paying for an MBBS seat in private medical colleges in India.</li>
<li><strong>Aesthetics and foreign culture:</strong> People are willing to leave their home to study far away in much colder places and with completely alien cultures and food habits.</li>
<li><strong>Practice and OPD exposure:</strong> It broadens students’ mind and thinking, expose them to a whole range of experiences, and their approach to issues and crises is likely to be far better.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Doesn’t India have enough colleges?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(a) More aspirants than seats</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There are certainly far more MBBS aspirants than there are MBBS seats in India.</li>
<li>In NEET 2021, as per a National Testing Agency press release, 16.1 lakh students registered for the exam, 15.4 lakh students appeared for the test, and 8.7 lakh students qualified.</li>
<li>As per data from the National Medical Commission (NMC), in 2021-22, there were 596 medical colleges in the country with a total of 88,120 MBBS seats.</li>
<li>While the skew is in favour of Government colleges, it is not greatly so, with the number of private medical institutions nearly neck-to-neck with the state-run ones.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(b) Fees structure</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>That means over 50% of the total seats are available at affordable fees in Government colleges.</li>
<li>Add the 50% seats in the private sector that the NMC has mandated must charge only the government college fees.</li>
<li>In fully private colleges, the full course fees range from several lakhs to crores.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(c) Uneven distribution of colleges</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>These colleges are also not distributed evenly across the country, with States such as Maharashtra, Karnataka, Tamil Nadu and Kerala having many more colleges.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What about costs?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The cost factor on both sides of an MBBS degree is significant.</li>
<li>The costs of an MBBS degree in a Government college tot up to a few lakhs of rupees for the full course, but in a private medical college, <strong><u>it can go up to ₹1 crore</u></strong> <strong><u>for the five-year course</u></strong>.</li>
<li>In case it is a management seat, capitation fees can inflate the cost by several lakhs again.</li>
<li>Whereas, an MBBS course at any foreign medical university in the east and Eastern Europe costs far less (upto ₹30lakh-₹40 lakh).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While PM Modi emphasised that more private medical colleges must be set up in the country to aid more people to take up MBBS, medical education experts have called for pause on the aspect.</li>
<li>If the aim is to make medicine more accessible to students of the country, the path ahead is not in the private sector, but in the public sector, with the Central and State governments’ involvement.</li>
<li>Starting private medical colleges by reducing the strict standards set for establishing institutes may not actually be the solution to this problem, if we think this is a concern.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Creating more medical colleges will be beneficial for the country, if access and availability can be ensured.</li>
<li>This will not be possible by resorting to private enterprise only.</li>
<li>The State and Central governments can start more medical colleges, as recommended by NITI Aayog, by utilising district headquarters hospitals, and expanding the infrastructure.</li>
<li>This way, students from the lower and middle socio-economic rung, who are otherwise not able to access medical seats, will also benefit.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/centre-deny-medical-seat-ukraine-returns/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Eastern Economic Forum (EEF) and India’s Balancing Act</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/eastern-economic-forum-eef/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>EEF</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="eef" class="alignnone wp-image-636707" height="229" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 409px) 100vw, 409px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/eef--300x168.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/eef--300x168.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/eef-.jpg 610w" width="409"/></strong></p>
<p>Russia hosted the seventh Eastern Economic Forum- EEF Vladivostok from September 5 to 8. The four-day forum is a platform for entrepreneurs to expand their businesses into Russia’s Far East (RFE).</p>
<h4><strong>What is the Eastern Economic Forum-EEF?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The EEF was <strong><u>established in 2015</u></strong> aiming <strong><u>to encourage foreign investments</u></strong> in the RFE to display:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Economic potential</li>
<li>Suitable business conditions and</li>
<li>Investment opportunities in the region</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>Focus areas: </strong>The agreements focus on infrastructure, transportation projects, mineral excavations, construction, industry and agriculture.</li>
<li>With EEF, Russia is trying to attract the Asian economies in investing and developing the Far East.</li>
<li>This year, the Forum aimed at <strong><u>connecting the Far East with the Asia-Pacific</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What does the EEF aim for?</strong></h4>
<p><strong><img alt="eef" class="alignnone wp-image-635634" height="237" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 439px) 100vw, 439px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/far-east-300x162.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/far-east-300x162.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/far-east.jpg 750w" width="439"/></strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>FDI inflows:</strong> The primary objective of the EEF is to increase the Foreign Direct Investments in the RFE.</li>
<li><strong>Natural resource exploitation:</strong> The region encompasses one-third of Russia’s territory and is rich with natural resources such as fish, oil, natural gas, wood, diamonds and other minerals.</li>
<li><strong>Demographic revamp:</strong> The sparse population living in the region is another factor for encouraging people to move and work in the Far East.</li>
<li><strong>Unleashing economic potential:</strong> The region’s riches and resources contribute to five percent of Russia’s GDP.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Success of EEF</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-636708" height="434" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 418px) 100vw, 418px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/eef-289x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/eef-289x300.jpg 289w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/eef.jpg 505w" width="418"/></p>
<ul>
<li>Agreements signed at the EEF increased from 217 in 2017 to 380 agreements in 2021, worth 3.6 trillion roubles.</li>
<li>As of 2022, almost 2,729 investment projects are being planned in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h5><strong>Who are the major actors in the EEF? </strong></h5>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>China is the biggest investor</u></strong> in the region as it sees potential in promoting the Chinese Belt and Road Initiative and the Polar Sea Route in the RFE.</li>
<li>China’s investments in the region account for <strong><u>90% of the total investments</u></strong>.</li>
<li><strong><u>South Korea</u></strong> has invested in shipbuilding projects, manufacturing of electrical equipment, gas-liquefying plants, agricultural production and fisheries.</li>
<li><strong><u>Japan</u></strong> is another key trading partner. In 2017, its investments through 21 projects amounted to $16 billion.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How does Russia see Chinese investment in EEF?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong><u>Russia has been welcoming</u></strong> Chinese investments since 2015; more now than ever due to the economic pressures caused by the war in Ukraine.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>Trans-Siberian Railway</u></strong> has further helped Russia and China in advancing trade ties.</li>
<li>The <strong><u>countries share a 4000-km-long border</u></strong>, which enables them to tap into each other’s resources with some infrastructural assistance.</li>
<li>China is also looking to develop its <strong><u>Heilongjiang Province</u></strong> which connects with the RFE.</li>
<li>Both nations have invested in a fund to develop <strong><u>connectivity between the cities of</u></strong><u> <strong>Blagoveshchensk and Heihe</strong></u>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>India and Russia’s Far East</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India seeks to expand its influence in the RFE.</li>
<li>In 2019, India also offered a <strong><u>$1 billion line of credit</u></strong> to develop infrastructure in the region.</li>
<li>During the forum, PM Modi expressed the country’s readiness in expanding trade, connectivity and investments in Russia.</li>
<li>India is keen to deepen its cooperation in energy, pharmaceuticals, maritime connectivity, healthcare, tourism, the diamond industry and the Arctic.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Strategic significance of EEF for Russia</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Gateway to Asia:</strong> The RFE is geographically placed at a strategic location; acting as a gateway into Asia.</li>
<li><strong>Negating the Ukrainian war impact:</strong> The Ukraine war is a worrying issue as it affects the economic growth of the country.</li>
<li><strong>Surviving sanctions:</strong> Although, the EEF is an annual gathering, the forum comes at an opportune time for Russia who is dealing with the impact of the sanctions.</li>
<li><strong>Supply chain resilience:</strong> The IPEF will also play a key role in building resilient supply chains.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Will India be able to strike a balance between the EEF and IPEF?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Both are incomparable:</strong> The US-led <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/indo-pacific-economic-framework-for-prosperity-ipef/">Indo-Pacific Economic Framework for Prosperity (IPEF)</a> and the EEF are incomparable based on its geographic coverage and the partnership with the host-countries.</li>
<li><strong>India values both:</strong> India has not shied away from investing in the Russia-initiated EEF despite the current international conditions.</li>
<li><strong>India is firm for its purpose:</strong> At the same time, India has given its confirmation and acceptance to three of the four pillars in the IPEF.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India understands the benefits of being involved in the development in the RFE but it also perceives the IPEF as a vital platform to strengthen its presence in the Indo-Pacific region.</li>
<li>India’s participation in the forum will help in disengaging from supply chains that are dependent on China and will also make it a part of the global supply chain network.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4>Also read:</h4>
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="0hZLajNAi5"><p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/russia-far-east/">[Sansad TV] Perspective: Russia’s Far East- Opportunities for India</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="0hZLajNAi5" frameborder="0" height="327" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" sandbox="allow-scripts" scrolling="no" security="restricted" src="https://www.civilsdaily.com/russia-far-east/embed/#?secret=GSQYzFWcUp#?secret=0hZLajNAi5" style="position: absolute; clip: rect(1px, 1px, 1px, 1px);" title="“[Sansad TV] Perspective: Russia’s Far East- Opportunities for India” — Civilsdaily" width="580"></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/eastern-economic-forum-eef/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Should India choose manufacturing over services? Here is because</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/manufacturing/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>PLI scheme</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>sectors of economy</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Manufacturing" class="alignnone wp-image-636754" height="430" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 648px) 100vw, 648px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/43b07911-7d31-47db-b3dd-2c230924a198-300x199.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/43b07911-7d31-47db-b3dd-2c230924a198-300x199.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/43b07911-7d31-47db-b3dd-2c230924a198-768x510.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/43b07911-7d31-47db-b3dd-2c230924a198.jpg 1000w" width="648"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Manufacturing can create higher productivity jobs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is service sector?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The service sector, also known as the tertiary sector, is <strong>the third tier in the three-sector economy</strong>. Instead of product production, this sector produces services maintenance and repairs, training, or consulting. Examples of service sector jobs include housekeeping, tours, nursing, and teaching.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is called manufacturing sector?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Manufacturing is the making of goods by hand or by machine that upon completion the business sells to a customer. Items used in manufacture may be raw materials or component parts of a larger product. The manufacturing usually happens on a large-scale production line of machinery and skilled labor.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong style="letter-spacing: -0.0415625em;"><img alt="Manufacturing" class="alignnone wp-image-636756" height="404" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 673px) 100vw, 673px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector-300x180.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector-300x180.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector-1024x614.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector-768x461.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector-1536x922.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector-1200x720.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1600x960_1050775-manufacturing-sector.jpg 1600w" width="673"/>Should India focus on manufacturing over services?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Services sector failed to create more jobs</strong>: So far, in services, we have certainly developed some advantage and we are doing rather well. Services’ share of the economy has gone up to over 50% of the GDP. However, this sector has not been able to create enough jobs in a commensurate manner. The result is that agriculture still continues to sustain nearly half of India’s workforce, which means that 15% of GDP is supporting some 45% of the workforce.</li>
<li><strong>Manufacturing can provide productive jobs</strong>: We need more productive job opportunities for the workforce to shift away from agriculture. We need to focus attention on the manufacturing sector because of the direct and indirect jobs that it can create.</li>
<li><strong>Empirical fact</strong>: It is an empirical fact that manufacturing of all productive sectors has the highest backward and forward linkages.</li>
<li><strong>Significant potential:</strong> So, all together, there is significant potential for the manufacturing sector to create higher productivity jobs for people stuck in agricultural activities. That is the future for India.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Manufacturing" class="alignnone wp-image-636757" height="400" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 710px) 100vw, 710px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sectors-of-Indian-Economy-backup-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sectors-of-Indian-Economy-backup-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sectors-of-Indian-Economy-backup-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sectors-of-Indian-Economy-backup-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sectors-of-Indian-Economy-backup-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Sectors-of-Indian-Economy-backup.jpg 1280w" width="710"/>What is<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pli-scheme-will-help-india-nurture-manufacturing-giants/"> PLI</a> Scheme?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>As the name suggests, the scheme provides incentives to companies for enhancing their domestic manufacturing apart from focusing on reducing import bills and improving the cost competitiveness of local goods.</li>
<li>PLI scheme offers incentives on incremental sales for products manufactured in India.</li>
<li>The scheme for respective sectors has to be implemented by the concerned ministries and departments.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Criteria laid for the scheme</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Eligibility criteria for businesses under the PLI scheme vary based on the sector approved under the scheme.</li>
<li>For instance, the eligibility for telecom units is subject to the achievement of a minimum threshold of cumulative incremental investment and incremental sales of manufactured goods.</li>
<li>The minimum investment threshold for MSME is Rs 10 crore and Rs 100 crores for others.</li>
<li>Under food processing, SMEs and others must hold over 50 per cent of the stock of their subsidiaries, if any.</li>
<li>On the other hand, for businesses under pharmaceuticals, the project has to be a green-field project while the net worth of the company should not be less than 30 per cent of the total committed investment.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are the incentives offered?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An incentive of 4-6 per cent was offered last year on mobile and electronic components manufacturers such as resistors, transistors, diodes, etc.</li>
<li>Similarly, 10 percent incentives were offered for six years (FY22-27) of the scheme for the food processing industry.</li>
<li>For white goods too, the incentive of 4-6 per cent on incremental sales of goods manufactured in India for a period of five years was offered to companies engaged in the manufacturing of air conditioners and LED lights.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Benefits of PLI</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The scheme has a direct employment generation potential of over 2,00,000 jobs over 5 years.</li>
<li>It would lead to large scale electronics manufacturing in the country and open tremendous employment opportunities. Indirect employment will be about 3 times of direct employment as per industry estimates.</li>
<li>Thus, the total employment potential of the scheme is approximately 8,00,000.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In order to integrate India as a pivotal part of this modern economy, there is a strong need to step up our manufacturing capabilities.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>Should India focus on manufacturing over services for job creation? Discuss the role Production Linked Incentive Scheme could play in boosting manufacturing in India.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/manufacturing/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Highlights of India Discrimination Report, 2022</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-discrimination-report/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>India Discrimination Report, 2022</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Economic and social discrimination in India</p></div></div><p>Oxfam India’s latest ‘India Discrimination Report 2022’ finds women in India despite their same educational qualifications and work experience as men will be discriminated in the labour market due to societal and employers’ prejudices.</p>
<h4>About the report</h4>
<ul>
<li>The Oxfam India report refers to unit-level data from:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>61st round National Sample Survey (NSS) data on employment-unemployment (2004-05)</li>
<li>Periodic Labour Force Survey in 2018-19 and 2019-20 and</li>
<li>All India Debt and Investment Survey by the government</li>
</ol>
<h4>Key highlights</h4>
<p><strong>(1) Decline of women in workforce</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>As per the Union Ministry of Statistics &amp; Programme Implementation (MoSPI), LFPR for women in India was only 25.1 percent in 2020-21 for urban and rural women.</li>
<li>This is considerably lower than Brazil, Russia, China and South Africa as per the latest World Bank estimates.</li>
<li>The LFPR for women in India has rapidly declined from 42.7 percent in 2004-05 to mere 25.1 percent in 2021 showing the withdrawal of women from the workforce.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Earning Gap</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There is also a significant gap in the earnings between men and women in the case of regular and self-employment in urban areas.</li>
<li>The average earning is INR 15,996 for men and merely INR 6,626 for women in urban areas in self-employment.</li>
<li>The men’s average earning is nearly 2.5 times that of the earnings of women</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Communal aspects of discrimination</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Oppressed communities such as Dalits and Adivasis along with religious minorities such as Muslims also continue to face discrimination in accessing jobs, livelihoods, and agricultural credit.</li>
<li>The mean income for SCs or STs persons in urban areas who are regular employed is INR 15,312 as against INR 20,346 for persons belonging to the General Category.</li>
<li>The rural SC and ST communities are facing increase in discrimination in casual employment, the report shows.</li>
<li>The data shows that the unequal income among urban SC and ST casual wage work is because of 79 percent discrimination in 2019-20.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Muslims and economic backwardness</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Muslims continue to face multidimensional challenges in accessing salaried jobs and income through self-employment as compared to non-Muslims.</li>
<li>In rural areas, the sharpest increase of 17 percent in unemployment was for Muslims as compared to non-Muslims during the first quarter of the COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
<li>6 percent of the urban Muslims population aged 15 and above were engaged in regular salaried jobs whereas 23.3 percent of non-Muslims are in regular salaried jobs in 2019-20.</li>
<li>The lower employment for urban Muslims attributes 68.3 percent to discrimination in 2019-20.</li>
<li>The report shows that the discrimination faced by Muslims in 2004-05 was 59.3 percent, indicating an increase in discrimination by 09 percent over the last 16 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Recommendations from the report</h4>
<ul>
<li>Actively<strong><u> enforce effective measures</u></strong> for the implementation of the right to equal wages and work for all women.</li>
<li>Work to actively<strong><u> incentivise the participation of women</u></strong> in workforce including enhancements in pay, upskilling, job reservations and easy return-to-work options after maternity.</li>
<li>Work to actively <strong><u>challenge and change societal and caste/religion-based norms</u></strong>, around women’s’ participation in labour markets.</li>
<li>Strengthen <strong><u>civil society’s engagement</u></strong> in ensuring a more equitable distribution of household work and childcare duties between women and men and facilitating higher participation of women in labour market</li>
<li>Implement “<strong><u>living wages” as opposed to minimum wages</u></strong>, particularly for all informal workers and formalise contractual, temporary and casual labour as much as possible.</li>
<li>Extend <strong><u>priority lending and credit access</u></strong> to all farmers, regardless of social groups and penalize biased lending.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Labour Force Participation Rate (LFPR)</h4>
<ul>
<li>It is the percentage of the population which is either working (employed) or seeking for work (unemployed).</li>
<li>According to the International Labour Organisation (ILO), the LFPR is a ‘measure of the proportion of a country’s working-age population that engages actively in the labour market, either by working or looking for work’.</li>
<li>The breakdown of the labour force (formerly known as economically active population) by sex and age group gives a profile of the distribution of the labour force within a country.</li>
<li>As per the ministry of statistics and programme implementation, LFPR for women in India was only 25.1% in 2020-21.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/india-discrimination-report/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Eklavya Schools get short shrift in teacher recruitments</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/eklavya-schools-get-short-in-teachers/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>EMRS</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Schooling for Tribal students</p></div></div><p>The Ministry of Tribal Affairs has so far been unable to fix the teacher shortage faced across 378 of Eklavya model residential schools (EMRS) that are currently functional.</p>
<h4>Eklavya Model Residential Schools (EMRS)</h4>
<ul>
<li>EMRS started in the year 1997-98 to impart quality education to <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/tribes-protecting-the-tribes-india-ias/">Scheduled Tribes (ST)</a> children in remote areas in order.</li>
<li>It aims to enable them to avail of opportunities in high and professional educational courses and get employment in various sectors.</li>
<li>The schools focus not only on academic education but on the all-round development of the students.</li>
<li>Each school has a capacity of 480 students, catering to students from Class VI to XII.</li>
<li>Hitherto, grants were given for construction of schools and recurring expenses to the State Governments under Grants under Article 275 (1) of the Constitution.</li>
<li>Eklavya schools are on par with Navodaya Vidyalaya and have special facilities for preserving local art and culture besides providing training in sports and skill development.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Features of Eklavya Schools</h4>
<ul>
<li>Admission to these schools will be through selection/competition with suitable provision for preference to children belonging to Primitive Tribal Groups, first-generation students, etc.</li>
<li>Sufficient land would be given by the State Government for the school, playgrounds, hostels, residential quarters, etc., free of cost.</li>
<li>The number of seats for boys and girls will be equal.</li>
<li>In these schools, education will be entirely free.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Where are the Eklavya schools located?</h4>
<ul>
<li>It has been decided that by the year 2022, every block with more than 50% ST population and at least 20,000 tribal persons, will have an EMRS.</li>
<li>Wherever density of ST population is higher in identified Sub-Districts (90% or more), it is proposed to set up Eklavya Model Day Boarding School (EMDBS) on an experimental basis.</li>
<li>They aim for providing additional scope for ST Students seeking to avail school education without residential facility.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/eklavya-schools-get-short-in-teachers/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>PM Modi pitches for ‘Full Transit Right’ among SCO members</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pm-modi-pitches-for-full-transit-right-among-sco-members/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>International North–South Transport Corridor (INSTC)</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>With Pakistan PM listening, Prime Minister Modi urged <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/iran-belarus-to-be-newest-sco-members/">Shanghai Cooperation Organisation</a> member states to “give each other full right to transit”.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>PM Modi framed the <strong><u>right to transit in the context of connectivity</u></strong> and how it could help establish reliable and resilient supply chains in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why did PM pitch this?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Lack of <strong><u>transit across Pakistan’s territory has been a challenge for India</u></strong> to access Central Asian markets.</li>
<li>Iran’s President also said that despite the impressive potential, infrastructural connections in the <strong><u>field of transit between members of the SCO are not so extensive.</u></strong></li>
<li>Iran already provides special priority to the development of the North-South Corridor and has made huge investments.</li>
</ul>
<h4>What is International North-South Transport Corridor (INSTC)?</h4>
<p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-637170" height="259" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 411px) 100vw, 411px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/instc--300x189.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/instc--300x189.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/instc-.jpg 580w" width="411"/></p>
<ul>
<li>The INSTC is a <strong><u>7,200 km-long multimodal transportation network</u></strong> encompassing <strong><u>sea, road, and rail routes</u></strong> to offer the shortest route of connectivity.</li>
<li>It was <strong><u>established on 12th September 2000 in St. Petersburg</u></strong>, <strong><u>by Iran, Russia and India</u></strong> for the purpose of promoting transportation cooperation among the Member States.</li>
<li>It links the <strong><u>Indian Ocean to the Caspian Sea via the Persian Gulf</u></strong> onwards into Russia and Northern Europe.</li>
<li>It will move freight between India, Iran, Afghanistan, Armenia, Azerbaijan, Russia, Central Asia and Europe.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Significance of INSTC</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Trade facilitation:</strong> INSTC is aimed at reducing the carriage cost between India and Russia by about 30 percent and bringing down the transit time by more than half.</li>
<li><strong>New corridor in making:</strong> It has the potential to transform the economies of countries along the corridor into specialized manufacturing, logistics, and transit hubs by facilitating access to newer markets.</li>
<li><strong>Multimodal transit:</strong> The recent Suez Canal blockade, which cost the global economy hefty damage amounting to US$9 billion, has amplified the optimistic outlook towards the INSTC as a cheaper and faster alternative multimodal transit corridor.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Benefits offered to India</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Export promotion:</strong> The INSTC connects India with Central Asia, and Russia, and has the potential to expand up to the Baltic, Nordic, and Arctic regions, increasing the scope of trade multifold.</li>
<li><strong>Ease of trade:</strong> For India, it provides a shorter trade route with Iran, Russia, and beyond to Europe, creating scope for increased economic engagement.</li>
<li><strong>Alternative Route to Central Asia:</strong> It opens up a permanent alternative route for India to trade with Afghanistan and Central Asia, given the hurdles in the direct route through Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pm-modi-pitches-for-full-transit-right-among-sco-members/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Complex issue of Assisted Suicide</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/complex-issue-of-assisted-suicide/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Assisted Suicide</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Assisted Suicide and issues involved</p></div></div><p><img alt="suicide" class="alignnone wp-image-637178" height="273" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 371px) 100vw, 371px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/suicide-300x221.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/suicide-300x221.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/suicide.jpg 718w" width="371"/></p>
<p>A renowned French filmmaker died earlier this week by assisted suicide at the age of 91.</p>
<h4>What is Assisted Suicide?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Assisted suicide and euthanasia are practices under which a person intentionally ends their life with active assistance from others.</li>
<li>These have long been contentious topics of debate as they involve a complex set of moral, ethical and in some cases, religious questions.</li>
<li>Several European nations, some states in Australia and Colombia in South America allow assisted suicide and euthanasia under certain circumstances.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Difference between assisted suicide and euthanasia</h4>
<ul>
<li>Euthanasia is the act of <strong><u>intentionally ending a life to relieve suffering</u></strong> – for example a lethal injection administered by a doctor.</li>
<li><strong><u>Intentionally helping another person</u></strong> to kill themselves is known as assisted suicide.</li>
<li>This can include providing someone with strong sedatives with which to end their life or buying them a ticket to Switzerland (where assisted suicide is legal) to end their life</li>
<li>Euthanasia can further be divided into active and passive.</li>
<li>The practice of passive euthanasia involves simply stopping lifesaving treatment or medical intervention with the consent of the patient or a family member or a close friend representing the patient.</li>
<li>Active euthanasia, which is legal in only a few countries, entails the use of substances to end the life of the patient.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India and Assisted suicide/ Euthanasia</h4>
<ul>
<li>In a landmark judgment, the Supreme Court of <strong><u>India legalised passive euthanasia in 2018</u></strong>, stating that it was a matter of ‘living will’.</li>
<li>According to the judgment, an adult in his conscious mind is permitted to refuse medical treatment or voluntarily decide not to take medical treatment to embrace death in a natural way, under certain conditions.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Consideration for ‘living will’</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the 538-page judgment, the court laid down a set of guidelines for ‘living will’ and defined passive euthanasia and euthanasia as well.</li>
<li>It also laid down guidelines for ‘living will’ made by <strong><u>terminally ill patients who beforehand know about their chances of slipping into a permanent vegetative state.</u></strong></li>
<li>The court specifically stated that the rights of a patient, in such cases, w<strong><u>ould not fall out of the purview of Article 21</u></strong> (right to life and liberty) of the Indian Constitution.</li>
<li>The SC’s judgment was in accordance with its <strong><u>verdict in March 2011</u></strong> on a separate plea.</li>
<li>While ruling on a petition on behalf of <strong><u>Aruna Shanbaug Case</u></strong>, the court had <strong><u>allowed passive euthanasia</u></strong> for the nurse who had spent decades in a vegetative state.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who was Aruna Shanbaug?</h4>
<ul>
<li>Shanbaug had become central to debates on the legality of right to die and euthanasia in India.</li>
<li>Shanbaug died of pneumonia in March 2015 at the age of 66, 42 years of which she had spent in a room at KEM Hospital in Mumbai, after a brutal rape left her in a permanent vegetative state.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Recent cases in India</h4>
<ul>
<li>In 2018, an old couple from Mumbai wrote to then President Kovind, seeking permission for active euthanasia or assisted suicide.</li>
<li>Neither of them suffered from a life-threatening ailment.</li>
<li>The couple stated in their plea that they had lived a happy life and <strong><u>didn’t want to depend on hospitals for old age ailments.</u></strong></li>
</ul>
<h4>Justification for Euthanasia/Assisted Suicide</h4>
<ul>
<li>It provides a way to relieve extreme pain.</li>
<li>Euthanasia can save  life  of  many  other  people  by  donation  of  vital organs.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Issues with such killings</h4>
<ul>
<li>Euthanasia can be misused. Many psychiatrists are of the opinion that a terminally ill person or someone who is old and suffering from an incurable disease is often not in the right frame of mind to take a call.</li>
<li>Family members deciding on behalf of the patient can also lead to abuse of the law legalizing euthanasia as it can be due to some personal interest.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/complex-issue-of-assisted-suicide/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>SC seeks Centre’s reply on issue of Marital Rape</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-seeks-centres-reply-on-marital-rape/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Persistence of marital rape and need for its criminalization</p></div></div><p>The Supreme Court has sought a response from the government on appeals to criminalize marital rape.</p>
<h4><strong>Split opinions on Marital Rape</strong></h4>
<p><img alt="rape" class="alignnone wp-image-637177" height="465" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 346px) 100vw, 346px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rape-223x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rape-223x300.jpg 223w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/rape.jpg 595w" width="346"/></p>
<ul>
<li>This follows a split decision from the Delhi High Court on whether or not to prosecute husbands for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/criminalizing-marital-rape-in-india/">non-consensual </a>intercourse with their wives.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Marital Rape?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Marital rape is the act of sexual intercourse with one’s spouse without her consent.</li>
<li>It is no different manifestation of domestic violence and sexual abuse.</li>
<li>It is often a chronic form of violence for the victim which takes place within abusive relations.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Status in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Historically considered as right of the spouses, this is now widely classified as rape by many societies around the world.</li>
<li>In India, marital rape is not a criminal offense (as protected under IPC section 375).</li>
<li>India is one of fifty countries that have not yet outlawed marital rape.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reasons for disapproval of this concept</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The reluctance to define non-consensual sex between married couples as a crime and to prosecute has been attributed to:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Traditional views of marriage</li>
<li>Interpretations of religious doctrines</li>
<li>Ideas about male and female sexuality</li>
<li>Cultural expectations of subordination of a wife to her husband</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>It is widely held that a husband cannot be guilty of any sexual act committed by himself upon his lawful wife their on account of their mutual matrimonial consent.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why it must be a crime?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Associated physical violence:</strong> Rape by a spouse, partner or ex-partner is more often associated with physical violence.</li>
<li><strong>Mental harassment:</strong> There is research showing that marital rape can be more emotionally and physically damaging than rape by a stranger.</li>
<li><strong>Compulsive relationship:</strong> Marital rape may occur as part of an abusive relationship.</li>
<li><strong>Revengeful nature:</strong> Furthermore, marital rape is rarely a one-time event, but a repeated if not frequent occurrence.</li>
<li><strong>Obligation on women:</strong> In the case of marital rape the victim often has no choice but to continue living with their spouse.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Violation of fundamental rights</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Marital rape is considered as the violation of FR guaranteed under <u>Article 14</u> of the Indian constitution which guarantees the equal protection of laws to all persons.</li>
<li>By depriving married women of an effective penal remedy against forced sexual intercourse, it violates their right to privacy and bodily integrity, aspects of the right to life and personal liberty under <u>Article 21</u>.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Problems in prosecuting marital rape</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of awareness:</strong> A lack of public awareness, as well as reluctance or outright refusal of authorities to prosecute, is common globally.</li>
<li><strong>Gender norms:</strong> Additionally, gender norms that place wives in subservient positions to their husbands, make it more difficult for women to recognize such rape.</li>
<li><strong>Acceptability of the concept:</strong> Another problem results from prevailing social norms that exist.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Present regulations in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Indian Penal Code criminalizes rape in most cases, although marital rape is not illegal when the woman is over the age of 18.</li>
<li>However, until 2017, men married to those between 15 and 18 could not be convicted of rape.</li>
<li>Marital rape of an adult wife, who is unofficially or officially separated, is a criminal offence punishable by 2 to 7 year in prison; it is not dealt by normal rape laws which stipulate the possibility of a death sentence.</li>
<li>According to the Protection of Women From Domestic Violence Act (2005), other married women subject to such crime by their husband may demand for financial compensation.</li>
<li>They also have the right to continue to live in their marital household if they wish, or may approach shelter or aid homes.</li>
</ul>
<p>However, marital rape is still not a criminal offence in this case and is only a misdemeanor.</p>
<h4><strong>Arguments against criminalization</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Subjective:</strong> It is very subjective and intricate to determine whether consent was acquired or not.</li>
<li><strong>Prone to Misuse</strong>: If marital rape is criminalized without adequate safeguards it could be misused like the current dowry law by the dissatisfied wives to harass and torture their Husbands.</li>
<li><strong>Burden on Judiciary</strong>: It will increase the burden of judiciary which otherwise may serve other more important causes.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way forward</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Sanctioning marital rape is an acknowledgment of the woman’s right to self-determination (i.e., control) of all matters relating to her body.</li>
<li>In the absence of any concrete law, the judiciary always finds it difficult to decide the matter of domestic rape in the absence of solid evidence.</li>
<li>The main purpose of marriage is procreation, and sometimes divorce is sought on the ground of non-consummation of marriage.</li>
<li>Before giving a final interpretation, the judiciary must balance the rights and duties of both partners.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/sc-seeks-centres-reply-on-marital-rape/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How lower fertility rate hampers demographic dividend in number of ways</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fertility-rate/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>human population</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="fertility rate" class="alignnone wp-image-637033" height="467" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 623px) 100vw, 623px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives-300x225.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives-300x225.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives-768x576.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/child-policies-across-the-world-from-restrictions-to-incentives.jpg 1200w" width="623"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Though the Global population, in terms of numbers, has been steadily increasing the average global fertility rate has been consistently declining over the past 70 years.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What Reports say?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Reports suggest that the global population could grow to around 8.5 billion in 2030.</li>
<li>According to the World Population Prospects 2022, Average number of children per woman in the reproductive age group has declined by 50%, from an average of five children per woman in 1951 to4 children in 2020.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is Fertility?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Fertility is the quality or state of being fertile<strong>.</strong></li>
<li>Fertility is the ability to reproduce through normal sexual interaction. In other words it is the natural capacity to conceive a biological child.</li>
<li>Fertilitychanges with age. Both males and females become fertile in their teens following puberty.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fertility rate" class="alignnone wp-image-637034" height="343" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 571px) 100vw, 571px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/e_440_x_264_14_2034043615--300x180.png" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/e_440_x_264_14_2034043615--300x180.png 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/e_440_x_264_14_2034043615-.png 440w" width="571"/> What is fertility rate?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The number of live births in women over a specific length of time.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/replacement-level-fertility-achieved-in-india/">Total fertility rate</a> is the average number of children born to a woman during her lifetime.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h4><strong>Recent findings</strong></h4>
<p>The newly released World Population Prospectus notes that the global fertility rate fell from three in 1990 to 2.3 in 2021.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Overview of fertility dynamics </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reason: </strong>Speeding up the social phenomenon of demographic transition.</li>
<li><strong>Poorer countries:</strong> speeding up the Transition a lot faster than the richer ones.</li>
<li><strong>Britain</strong>: Took 130 years to transition from a fertility rate of five per woman in 1800 to two in 1930, whereas</li>
<li><strong>South Korea: </strong>Took 20 years from 1965 to 1985 to achieve the same. South Korea reporting the lowest fertility rate, 1.05 children per woman.</li>
<li><strong>Most advanced economies</strong>: Have their fertility rate below the replacement rate of 2.1.</li>
<li><strong>Sub-Saharan African countries</strong>: Expected to contribute more than half the population growth after 2050 and grow through 2100. For example, Niger a sub Saharan country with highest fertility rate in the world, estimated to be 91 children per woman.</li>
<li><strong>What is Demographic transition</strong>: is a long-term trend of declining birth and death rate. It is shift from high birth rates to low birth rates in societies with minimal technology, education (especially of women) and economic development and from high death rates to Low death rates in societies with advanced economies and development.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="fertility rate" class="alignnone wp-image-637036" height="391" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 587px) 100vw, 587px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/shutterstock_-india-population-93427363-1-16577155543x2-1-300x200.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/shutterstock_-india-population-93427363-1-16577155543x2-1-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/shutterstock_-india-population-93427363-1-16577155543x2-1.jpeg 510w" width="587"/><br/>
Where India Stands</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>According to National Family Health Survey (NFHS), fertility rate falling below the replacement level for the first time to 2.0 in 2021.dropped from 2.2 to 2.0.</li>
<li>only five States have a fertility rate above the replacement rate: Bihar (3), Meghalaya (2.9), Uttar Pradesh (2.4), Jharkhand (2.3), and Manipur (2.2)</li>
<li>At the time of Independence, India’s fertility rate was six per woman, and it had taken 25 years to reach five, with the government launching the first ever family planning program in the world in 1952.</li>
<li>India’s fertility further declined to four in the 1990s when Kerala became the first State in India to have a fertility rate below replacement l</li>
<li>Increased use of contraception, more years of average schooling, better health care, and an increase in the mean marriage age of women are of the reasons behind the steady dip in fertility rate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Lower fertility rate as cause and consequences on the economy</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Positive impact:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Lower fertility leads to rise in women’s education.</li>
<li>Window of time where the ration of working-age population is higher than that of the dependent age groups.</li>
<li>This high proportion of people in the workforce boosts income and investment, and higher level of saving.</li>
<li>Lower pressure on land, water and other resources and would also contribute to achieving environmental goals.</li>
<li>Advanced health care and better nutrition, results in increased life expectancy and productivity of citizens.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>Negative impact:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Lower fertility impacts women’s education positively, which in turn lowers the fertility of the next generations.</li>
<li>While the income rises with better health care and better infrastructure development, Fertility drops.</li>
<li>A fall in fertility rate beyond replacement level would have a negative effect on the proportion of the working population, which in turn will affect output in an economy.</li>
<li>After the window of demographic dividend, the huge working age population moves to old age, supported by fewer workers.</li>
<li>Japan was the first country to experience the implications of falling fertility rates. Country is now facing fiscal challenges to meet rising social security costs.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Experiments to deal with fertility decline</strong></h4>
<p>Countries across the globe are experimenting with policies to boost fertility.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Germany: </strong>found success in boosting births through liberal labour laws, allowing more parental leave and benefits.</li>
<li><strong>Denmark</strong>: offering state-funded IVF for women below 40 years</li>
<li><strong>Hungary</strong>: Recently nationalized IVF clinics.</li>
<li><strong>Poland</strong>: Gives out monthly cash payments to parents having more than two children</li>
<li><strong>Russia</strong>: Makes one-time payment to parents when their second child is born. Reinstituted the Soviet-era ‘Mother Heroine’ title, who bore and raised more than 10 children amounting to almost a one-time payment of 13 lakh<strong>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Way ahead </strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Need of the hour is to ensure liberal labor reforms, encourage higher female labor force participation, higher focus on nutrition and health.</li>
<li>Although India’s working age population will continue to grow for many more decades, it would need to keep an eye on fertility dips.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>What are Implications of lower fertility rate on the economy? What steps could be taken to deal with fertility decline? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><u><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></u></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/fertility-rate/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>RBI’s attempt to manage currency could prove to be a costly mistake</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/currency/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Impossible trinity</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>RBI functions</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="currency" class="alignnone wp-image-637056" height="294" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 522px) 100vw, 522px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_shutterstock_336372560.jpg 1600w" width="522"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A currency defence will also impose costs on the economy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why in news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Legally, the Reserve Bank of India is mandated to target an inflation rate. But with the global economic environment taking a turn for the worse, the central bank has also been targeting the exchange rate. This could prove to be a costly mistake.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a simple definition for inflation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Inflation is the rate of increase in prices over a given period of time. Inflation is typically a broad measure, such as the overall increase in prices or the increase in the cost of living in a country.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is exchange rate?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An exchange rate is a rate at which one currency will be exchanged for another currency. Most exchange rates are defined as floating and will rise or fall based on the supply and demand in the market. Some exchange rates are pegged or fixed to the value of a specific country’s currency.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is monetary policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Monetary policy is the control of the quantity of money available in an economy and the channels by which new money is supplied. Economic statistics such as gross domestic product (GDP), the rate of inflation, and industry and sector-specific growth rates influence monetary policy strategy.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is fixed exchange rate in simple words?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A fixed exchange rate is a regime applied by a government or central bank that ties the country’s official currency exchange rate to another country’s currency or the price of gold. The purpose of a fixed exchange rate system is to keep a currency’s value within a narrow band.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="currency" class="alignnone wp-image-637058" height="346" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 519px) 100vw, 519px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dollar-kS6F-621x414%40LiveMint-300x200.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dollar-kS6F-621x414%40LiveMint-300x200.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/dollar-kS6F-621x414%40LiveMint.jpg 621w" width="519"/>What is a simple definition of capital?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Capital is a broad term that can describe anything that confers value or benefit to its owners, such as a factory and its machinery, intellectual property like patents, or the financial assets of a business or an individual.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is meant by the impossible trinity?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Many economists think of possible policy responses to capital flows in terms of the so-called “impossible trinity,” or “policy trilemma”, according to which, with an open capital account, a central bank cannot simultaneously exercise monetary control and target the exchange rate.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>A currency defence will impose costs on the economy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Little economic gain</strong>: Some may believe that a stronger currency gives the impression of economic stability and generates confidence in the economy. But there is an inherent contradiction between artificially propping up the rupee and the country’s growth prospects. Very little economic gain will accrue from turning the currency’s value into a political issue.</li>
<li><strong>Inflation should be tackled through monetary policy</strong>: Understandably, a depreciating currency leads to concerns over higher imported inflation. But inflation should be tackled through monetary policy, while exchange rate management should be linked to growth. Not the other way around.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Significance of currency defence for <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-global-trade-in-rupees/">foreign exchange reserves</a></strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Decline by 10 per cent:</strong> A large part of the current relative strength of the rupee vis-à-vis other currencies is due to the sale of dollars by the RBI  it has lost more than 10 per cent of its foreign reserves in the space of about nine months.</li>
<li><strong>Why country needs foreign exchange:</strong> A developing economy needs foreign exchange to finance its international transactions for both the current account (goods and services) and capital account (assets) transactions.</li>
<li><strong>Cost involved:</strong> The benefits of this stock are obvious, but there are also costs associated with the holding of these.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong><img alt="https://www.civilsdaily.com/burning-issue-global-trade-in-rupees/" class="alignnone wp-image-637059" height="340" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 603px) 100vw, 603px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/47023612-9307-11eb-b10b-5920a68d5cf2_1621843452212_1623672706131.jpg 1600w" width="603"/>We should follow Tenfold Path to manage Exchange Rate Volatility rather monetary policy path</strong></h4>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong><u>(1) Selling dollars</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The first course of action has been selling dollars in the spot forex market.</li>
<li>This is fairly straightforward, but has limits as all crises are associated with declining reserves.</li>
<li>While this money is meant for a rainy day, they may just be less than adequate.</li>
<li>The idea of RBI selling dollars works well in the currency market, which is kept guessing how much the central bank is willing to sell at any point of time.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(2) NRI deposits</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The second tool used is aimed at garnering non-resident Indian (NRI) deposits.</li>
<li>It was done in 1998 and 2000 through Resurgent India bonds and India Millennium Deposits, when banks reached out asking NRIs to put in money with attractive interest rates.</li>
<li>The forex risk was borne by Indian banks.</li>
<li>This is always a useful way for the country to mobilize a good sum of forex, though the challenge is when the debt has to be redeemed.</li>
<li>At the time of deposits, the rates tend to be attractive, but once the crisis ends, the same rate cannot be offered on deposit renewals.</li>
<li>Therefore, the idea has limitations.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(3) Let oil importers buy dollars themselves</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The third option exercised often involves getting oil importing companies to buy dollars directly through a facility extended by a public sector bank.</li>
<li>Its advantage is that these deals are not in the open and so the market does not witness a large demand for dollars on this account.</li>
<li>It is more of a sentiment cooling exercise.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(4) Let exporters trade in dollars</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Another tool involves a directive issued for all exporters to mandatorily bring in their dollars on receipt that are needed for future imports.</li>
<li>This acts against an artificial dollar supply reduction due to exporter hold-backs for profit.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(5) Liberalized Exchange Rate</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The other weapon, once used earlier, is to curb the amount of dollars one can take under the Liberalized Exchange Rate Management System.</li>
<li>This can be for current account purposes like travel, education, healthcare, etc.</li>
<li>The amounts are not large, but it sends out a strong signal.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(6) Forward-trade marketing</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Another route used by RBI is to deal in the forward-trade market.</li>
<li>Its advantage is that a strong signal is sent while controlling volatility, as RBI conducts transactions where only the net amount gets transacted finally.</li>
<li>It has the same power as spot transactions, but without any significant withdrawal of forex from the system.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(7) Currency swaps</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The other tool in India’s armoury is the concept of swaps.</li>
<li>This became popular post 2013, when banks collected foreign currency non-resident deposits with a simultaneous swap with RBI, which in effect took on the foreign exchange risk.</li>
<li>Hence, it was different from earlier bond and deposit schemes.</li>
<li><strong>Most preferred options by the RBI</strong></li>
<li>Above discussed instruments have been largely direct in nature, with the underlying factors behind demand-supply being managed by the central bank.</li>
<li>Of late, RBI has gone in for more policy-oriented approaches and the last three measures announced are in this realm.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(8) Allowing banks to work in the NDF market</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>First was allowing banks to work in the non-deliverable forwards (NDF) market.</li>
<li>This is a largely overseas speculative market that has a high potential to influence domestic sentiment on our currency.</li>
<li>Here, forward transactions take place without real inflows or outflows, with only price differences settled in dollars.</li>
<li>This was a major pain point in the past, as banks did not have access to this segment.</li>
<li>By permitting Indian banks to operate here, the rates in this market and in domestic markets have gotten equalized.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(9) Capital account for NRI deposits</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>More recently, RBI opened up the capital account on NRI deposits (interest rates than can be offered), external commercial borrowings (amounts that can be raised) and foreign portfolio investments (allowed in lower tenure securities), which has the potential to draw in forex over time.</li>
<li>Interest in these expanded contours may be limited, but the idea is compelling.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><u>(10) Settlement in Rupees</u></strong></p>
<ul>
<li>RBI’s permission for foreign trade deals to be settled in rupees is quite novel; as India is a net importer, gains can be made if we pay in rupees for imports.</li>
<li>The conditions placed on the use of surpluses could be a dampener for potential transactions.</li>
<li>But the idea is innovative and could also be a step towards taking the rupee international in such a delicate situation.</li>
<li>Clearly, RBI has constantly been exploring ways to address our forex troubles and even newer measures shouldn’t surprise us.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The RBI (which is in charge of monetary policy) should focus on containing inflation, as it is legally mandated to do.</li>
<li>The government (which is in charge of the fiscal policy) should contain its borrowings.</li>
<li>Higher borrowings (fiscal deficit) by the government eat up domestic savings and force the rest of the economic agents to borrow from abroad.</li>
<li>Policymakers (both in the government and the RBI) have to choose what their priority is containing inflation or being hung up on exchange rate and forex levels.</li>
<li>If they choose to contain inflation (that is, by raising interest rates) then it will require sacrificing economic growth. So be prepared for that.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.What do you understand by the term impossible trinity? How should RBI respond to manage currency exchange rate? Discuss.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/currency/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>100 years of periyar because of whom tamil nadu became modern and progressive</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/periyar/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Vaikom satyagraha</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Social reform movement in tamil nadu</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="Periyar" class="alignnone wp-image-637096" height="439" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 439px) 100vw, 439px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/71pQGUTHWKL._AC_SS450_-300x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/71pQGUTHWKL._AC_SS450_-300x300.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/71pQGUTHWKL._AC_SS450_-150x150.jpg 150w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/71pQGUTHWKL._AC_SS450_.jpg 450w" width="439"/>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>We celebrate Periyar E.V. Ramasamy’s birth anniversary (September 17) as Social Justice Day.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who is periyar?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Erode Venkatappa Ramasamy, revered as Periyar or Thanthai Periyar, was an Indian social activist and politician who started the Self-Respect Movement and Dravidar Kazhagam. He is known as the ‘Father of the Dravidian movement’. He rebelled against Brahminical dominance and gender and caste inequality in Tamil Nadu.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Who started self-respect movement?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The self-respect movement was founded by V.Ramaswamy Naicker, commonly known as Periyar. It was a dynamic social movement aimed at destroying the contemporary Hindu social order in its totality and creating a new, rational society without caste, religion and god.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Periyar" class="alignnone wp-image-637097" height="644" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unnamed-200x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unnamed-200x300.jpg 200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unnamed.jpg 341w" width="429"/>Why Periyar is called as vaikom hero?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>V. Ramasamy Periyar led the famous <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/op-ed-snap-periyar-the-hero-of-vaikom/">Vaikom Sathya Graha</a> in 1924, where the people of down trodden community were prohibited to enter into the temple. Finally the Travancore government relaxed such segregation and allowed the people to enter into the temple. Hence periyar was given the title of ‘Vaikom Hero’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Leadership at a critical juncture</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The satyagraha began with the active support of the Kerala Pradesh Congress Committee.</li>
<li>Within a week all its leaders were behind bars. George Joseph sought directions from Gandhi and C. Rajagopalachari. He also wrote to Periyar pleading with him to lead the satyagraha.</li>
<li>Periyar was in the midst of political work. As he was then the president of the Tamil Nadu Congress Committee, Periyar handed over temporary charge to Rajaji before reaching Vaikom in 1924.</li>
<li>From that date to the day of the victory celebrations in 1925, he was in the struggle giving it leadership at a critical juncture.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Periyar" class="alignnone wp-image-637099" height="809" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 539px) 100vw, 539px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-200x300.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-200x300.jpg 200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-600x900.jpg 600w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-1200x1800.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/monak-artist-periyar-art-2-scaled.jpg 1707w" width="539"/>Periyar’s role</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Against violence</strong> – Periyar presided over the satyagraha in the face of violence and indignity inflicted by the orthodox and the repression of the police.</li>
<li><strong>Mobilising </strong>– To mobilise support, he visited villages in and around Vaikom and delivered public speeches in several towns.</li>
<li><strong>Gandhi </strong>– When the Kerala leaders asked for Gandhi’s permission to make the satyagraha an all-India affair, Gandhi refused saying that volunteers from Tamil Nadu would keep it alive.</li>
<li><strong>In reports</strong> – the British Resident said in his report to the government of Madras: “In fact, the movement would have collapsed long ago but for the support it has received from outside Travancore…”</li>
<li><strong>Historian T.K. Ravindran</strong> — observes that Periyar’s arrival gave “a new life to the movement”.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>His Vision for the future</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Ideas on rationality</strong>: When he presented his thoughts, there was nuance, honesty, and an explicitness, which prompted even people practising different faiths to discuss and debate his ideas on rationality and religion.</li>
<li><strong>Freedom of expression</strong>: Periyar himself said, “Everyone has the right to refute any opinion. But no one has the right to prevent its expression.”</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Eradication of social evils</strong>: Periyar is often referred to as an iconoclast, for the rebellious nature of his ideas and the vigour with which he acted. His vision for the future was a part of all his actions. He did not merely aim at the eradication of social evils; he also wanted to put an end to activities that do not collectively raise standards of society.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-637101" height="424" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 761px) 100vw, 761px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ramasamy-periyar-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ramasamy-periyar-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ramasamy-periyar.jpg 759w" width="761"/>Foundation of rationalism</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>He understood the evolution of political thought</strong>: Periyar’s vision was about inclusive growth and freedom of individuals. He was an important ideologue of his day because of the clarity in his political stand. More importantly, he understood the evolution of political thought and was able to glide through time with this.</li>
<li><strong>He presented rationalism as a solid foundation:</strong> For thinking along these lines. He said, “Wisdom lies in thinking. The spearhead of thinking is rationalism.” Periyar was way ahead of his time.</li>
<li><strong>Concern towards poor</strong>: “Whomsoever I love and hate, my principle is the same. That is, the educated, the rich and the administrators should not suck the blood of the poor.”</li>
<li><strong>Periyar proclaimed that he would always stand with the oppressed: </strong>In the fight against oppressors and that his enemy was oppression. There have been several social reformers in Tamil Nadu who shared their revolutionary thoughts with the people in the past century. In that spectrum, Periyar occupies a unique place because he made interactions of multiple worlds possible.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><em>Periyar said, “Any opposition not based on rationalism or science or experience, will one day or other, reveal the fraud, selfishness, lies, and conspiracies.”</em></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>His works against the Bhraminical dominance, oppression of women in Tamil Nadu, caste prevalence are exemplary. Periyar promoted the principles of rationalism, self-respect, women’s rights and eradication of caste. He opposed the exploitation and marginalisation of the people of South India and the imposition of what he considered Indo-Aryan India.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question</strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.Discuss the future vision of periyar by discussing his role in vaikom satyagraha. Do you think he has placed foundation of rationalism in Tamil Nadu?</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><u><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></u></strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/periyar/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>What are Entangled Atomic Clocks?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-entangled-atomic-clocks/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Atomic clocks</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Not Much</p></div></div><p><strong><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-637687" height="233" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 376px) 100vw, 376px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atomic-clock-300x186.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atomic-clock-300x186.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atomic-clock-768x475.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/atomic-clock.jpg 847w" width="376"/></strong></p>
<p>For the first time, scientists at the University of Oxford have been able to demonstrate a network of two entangled optical atomic clocks.</p>
<blockquote><p>Trending in news this year is the <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-certification-of-quantum-entanglement/">Quantum Technology</a>, (As it used to be until last year were- the Internet of Things (IoT) CSP 2019, Artificial Intelligence (AI) etc.)</p>
<p>Must read all this news in a loop:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-national-mission-on-quantum-technologies-applications/">National Mission on QC</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/pib-quantum-coin-or-qubit-and-entanglement-theory/">Quantum Coin</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/explained-what-is-quantum-supremacy-claimed-by-google/">Quantum Supremacy</a></p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>What is the news?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The high-precision atomic clocks and quantum entanglement have been achieved altogether.</li>
<li>This means the inherent uncertainty in measuring their frequencies simultaneously is highly reduced.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What are Atomic Clocks?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>An atomic clock is a clock that uses the resonance frequencies of atoms as its resonator.</li>
<li>Cesium is incredibly accurate at timekeeping and is used in atomic clocks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Fundamental limit of precision through entanglement<br/>
</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Entanglement is a quantum phenomenon in which two or more particles become linked together so that they can no longer be described independently, even at vast distances.</li>
<li>This is the key to reaching the fundamental limit of precision that’s determined by quantum theory.</li>
<li>Previous experiments have demonstrated that entanglement between two atomic clocks in the same system can be used to improve the quality of measurements.</li>
<li>This is the first time researchers have been able to achieve this between clocks in two separate remotely entangled systems.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why do we use clocks to navigate in space?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To determine a spacecraft’s distance from Earth, navigators send a signal to the spacecraft, which then returns it to Earth.</li>
<li>The time the signal requires to make that two-way journey reveals the spacecraft’s distance from Earth, because the signal travels at a known speed (the speed of light).</li>
<li>While it may sound complicated, most of us use this concept every day. The grocery store might be a 30-minute walk from your house.</li>
<li>If you know you can walk about a mile in 20 minutes, then you can calculate the distance to the store.</li>
<li>By sending multiple signals and taking many measurements over time, navigators can calculate a spacecraft’s trajectory: where it is and where it’s headed.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why need atomic clocks?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>To know the spacecraft’s position within a meter, navigators’ need clocks with precision time resolution — clocks that can measure billionths of a second.</li>
<li>Navigators also need clocks that are extremely stable<em>.</em></li>
<li>Stability refers to how consistently a clock measures a unit of time; its measurement of the length of a second, for example, needs to be the same (to better than a billionth of a second) over days and weeks.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is an oscillator in a clock?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Most modern clocks, from wristwatches to those used on satellites, keep time using a quartz crystal oscillator.</li>
<li>These devices take advantage of the fact that quartz crystals vibrate at a precise frequency when voltage is applied to them.</li>
<li>The vibrations of the crystal act like the pendulum of a grandfather clock, ticking off how much time has passed.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What do atoms have to do with clocks?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>By space navigation standards, quartz crystal clocks aren’t very stable.</li>
<li>After only an hour, even the best-performing quartz oscillators can be off by a nanosecond (one billionth of a second).</li>
<li>After six weeks, they may be off by a full millisecond (one thousandth of a second), or a distance error of 185 miles (300 kilometers).</li>
<li>That would have a huge impact on measuring the position of a fast-moving spacecraft.</li>
<li>Atomic clocks combine a quartz crystal oscillator with an ensemble of atoms to achieve greater stability.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-are-entangled-atomic-clocks/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>How Hyderabad became a part of India?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hyderabad-how-became-a-part-of-india/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Hyderabad's accession into India</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Post-independence consolidation</p></div></div><p><img alt="" class="alignnone wp-image-637690" height="291" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 462px) 100vw, 462px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hyd-300x189.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hyd-300x189.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/hyd.jpg 741w" width="462"/></p>
<p>The Government of India began its year-long celebrations for the ‘Telangana Liberation Day’ on September 17, marking how on the same day in 1948, the state of Hyderabad got its independence from Nizam’s rule, as said in a press release.</p>
<h4>Why in news?</h4>
<ul>
<li>From 1911 to 1948, Nizam Mir Usman Ali, the last Nizam of Hyderabad, ruled the state composed of Telangana and parts of present-day Karnataka and Maharashtra (Marathwada).</li>
<li>While these states mark the Liberation Day officially, Telangana has never done so.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Hyderabad’s accession into India: A backgrounder</h4>
<p><strong>(1) Reluctance of Nizam</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>At the time of India’s independence, British India was a mix of independent kingdoms and provinces that were given the options of joining India, Pakistan, or remaining independent.</li>
<li>One among those who took a long time to make a decision was the Nizam of Hyderabad.</li>
<li>Believed to be one of the richest people in the world at the time, the Nizam was not ready to let go of his kingdom.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Sufferings for the people</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Meanwhile, the majority population of Hyderabad state was far from enjoying the same kind of wealth as the Nizam did.</li>
<li>The feudal nature of the state at the time caused the peasant population to suffer high taxes, indignities of forced labour, and various other kinds of exploitation at the hands of powerful landlords.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Lingual friction</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>There was also a demand by the Andhra Jan Sangham for Telugu to be given primacy over Urdu.</li>
<li>By the mid-1930s, apart from a reduction in land revenue rates and the abolition of forced labour, introducing Telugu in local courts became another important issue.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(4) Mass movement</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Soon after the organisation became the Andhra Mahasabha (AMS), and Communists became associated with it.</li>
<li>Together, the two groups built a peasant movement against the Nizam that found local support.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who were the Razakars and the Ittehad-ul-Muslimeen?</h4>
<ul>
<li>By October 1946, the Nizam banned the AMS.</li>
<li>A close aide of the Nizam, Qasim Razvi, leader of the Ittehad-ul-Muslimeen, became closely involved in securing the Nizam’s position.</li>
<li>The Ittehad-ul-Muslimeen was a political outfit that sought a greater role for Muslims in the early 20th century, but after Razvi took over the organisation, it became extremist in its ideology.</li>
<li>It was under him that a militia of the ‘Razakars’ was formed to suppress the peasant and communist movement, launching a brutal attack.</li>
<li>Around this time, the Standstill Agreement was also signed between the Nizam and the Indian government in November 1947, declaring a status quo.</li>
<li>This meant that until November 1948, the Nizam could let things be as they were and not finalise a decision as negotiations with the Indian union continued.</li>
</ul>
<h4>How did the situation escalate to military action?</h4>
<ul>
<li>In the first half of 1948, tensions grew as the razakar leaders and the government in Hyderabad began to speak of war with India and began border raids with Madras and Bombay Presidencies.</li>
<li>As a response, India stationed troops around Hyderabad and began to ready itself for military intervention.</li>
</ul>
<h4>India commences Operation Polo</h4>
<ul>
<li>With the Nizam importing more arms and the violence of the Razakars approaching dangerous proportions, India officially launched ‘Operation Polo’ on September 9 and deployed its troops in Hyderabad four days later.</li>
<li>On September 17, three days after the deployment, the Nizam surrendered and acceded to the Indian Union in November.</li>
<li>India has decided to be generous and not punish the Nizam.</li>
<li>He was retained as the official ruler of the state and given a privy purse of five million rupees.</li>
</ul>
<h4>The legacy of Operation Polo</h4>
<ul>
<li>It has also been said that the army’s march into Hyderabad did not just target the razakars and the radical extremist forces.</li>
<li>A four-member goodwill mission led by Pandit Sunderlal was constituted by the then Prime Minister.</li>
<li>At the request of then PM Nehru, a month was spent in Hyderabad in November 1948 where evidence was gathered and at the end, a report was filed.</li>
<li>Estimated thousands of people died in communal violence during the military action.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Why debate now?</h4>
<ul>
<li>The debate about whether the day of independence was about integration into the Indian union after months of negotiations, or liberation from an autocratic monarch has continued.</li>
<li>Hyderabad’s history continues to affect today’s politics.</li>
<li>After Qasim Rizvi left India for Pakistan, the organisation was handed over to Abdul Wahed Owaisi, the grandfather of a present day Parliamentarian.</li>
<li>And communal-sectarian politics is storming up the city of Hyderabad leading to religious tensions.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/hyderabad-how-became-a-part-of-india/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>China blocks listing of Lashkar ‘commander’ Sajid Mir at UNSC</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/china-blocks-terrorist-listing-at-unsc-1267-list/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>UNSC 1267</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>China's support for Pak sponsored terrorism</p></div></div><p><img alt="1267 list" class="alignnone wp-image-637686" height="274" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 419px) 100vw, 419px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-300x196.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc-300x196.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/unsc.jpg 493w" width="419"/></p>
<p>For the third time in three months, China blocked a joint India-US attempt to put a Pakistan-based terrorist on the UN Security Council’s 1267 list.</p>
<h4><strong>What is the UNSC 1267 list?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The UNSC resolution 1267 was adopted unanimously on 15 October 1999.</li>
<li>It came to force in 1999, and strengthened after the September, 2001 attacks.</li>
<li>It is now known as the Da’esh and Al Qaeda Sanctions Committee.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is UNSC 1267 committee?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It comprises all permanent and non-permanent members of the United Nations Security Council (UNSC).</li>
<li>The 1267 list of terrorists is a global list, with a UNSC stamp.</li>
<li>It is one of the most important and active UN subsidiary bodies working on efforts to combat terrorism, particularly in relation to Al Qaeda and the Islamic State group.</li>
<li>It discusses UN efforts to limit the movement of terrorists, especially those related to travel bans, the freezing of assets and arms embargoes for terrorism.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How is the listing done?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Submission of Proposal</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Any member state can submit a proposal for listing an individual, group, or entity.</li>
<li>The proposal must include acts or activities indicating the proposed individual/group/entity had participated in the financing, planning, facilitating, preparing, or perpetrating of acts or activities linked to the said organizations.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Actual decision</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Decisions on listing and de-listing are adopted by consensus.</li>
<li>The proposal is sent to all the members, and if no member objects within five working days, the proposal is adopted.</li>
<li>An “objection” means rejection for the proposal.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Putting and resolving ‘Technical Holds’</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Any member of the Committee may also put a “technical hold” on the proposal and ask for more information from the proposing member state.</li>
<li>During this time, other members may also place their own holds.</li>
<li>The matter remains on the “pending” list of the Committee.</li>
<li>Pending issues must be resolved in six months, but the member state that has placed the hold may ask for an additional three months.</li>
<li>At the end of this period, if an objection is not placed, the matter is considered approved.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is India furious this time?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Recently PM Modi and Xi Jinping attended the Shanghai Cooperation Organisation (SCO) summit in Samarkand.</li>
<li>The grouping had agreed to take strong and consolidated action against terrorism in the region.</li>
<li>Despite this, China has exposed its double standards on the issue of terrorism for consistently stopping the listing of Pakistan-based terrorists.</li>
<li>This is again very surprising movement by China by putting a ‘Technical Hold’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Here is a timeline of how China disrupts the global efforts against terrorism:</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>2009:</strong> After the 26/11 Mumbai attacks, India moved an independent terror designation proposal against Masood Azhar but China blocked the move.</li>
<li><strong>2016:</strong> After seven years, India proposes listing of Masood Azhar as a global terrorist and is supported by the US, the UK and France. China blocks the move again.</li>
<li><strong>2017:</strong> The trio moves a third proposal only to be blocked by China again.</li>
<li><strong>2019:</strong> After the attacks on the CRPF personnel in J-K’s Pulwama, India calls 25 envoys of different countries to highlight the role Islamabad plays in funding, promoting and strengthening global terrorism. India moves the fourth proposal demanding Masood Azhar’s listing. <u>China lifted its technical hold.</u></li>
<li><strong>June 2022:</strong> China blocked a proposal by India and the US to list Pakistan-based terrorist Abdul Rehman Makki as a ‘Global Terrorist’</li>
<li><strong>August 2022:</strong> China blocks India-US joint proposal to list Jaish-e-Mohammad (JeM) deputy chief Abdul Rauf Azhar as UNSC designated terrorist.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>China’s actions expose its double speak and double standards when it comes to the international community’s shared battle against terrorism.</li>
<li>This clearly depicts its care for its vassal state Pakistan.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: United Nations Security Council</h4>
<ul>
<li>The UNSC is one of the six principal organs of the United Nations and is charged with the maintenance of international peace and security.</li>
<li>Its powers include the establishment of peacekeeping operations, the establishment of international sanctions, and the authorization of military action through Security Council resolutions.</li>
<li>It is the only UN body with the authority to issue binding resolutions to member states.</li>
<li>The Security Council consists of fifteen members. Russia, the United Kingdom, France, China, and the United States—serve as the body’s five permanent members (P5).</li>
<li>These permanent members can veto any substantive Security Council resolution, including those on the admission of new member states or candidates for Secretary-General.</li>
<li>The Security Council also has 10 non-permanent members, elected on a regional basis to serve two-year terms. The body’s presidency rotates monthly among its members.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/china-blocks-terrorist-listing-at-unsc-1267-list/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Vacant offices, unaware office-bearers: curious case of delisted parties</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vacant-offices-unaware-office-bearers-curious-case-of-delisted-parties/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Registration and de-registration of Political Parties, RP Act</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Read the attached story</p></div></div><p>The EC has been on a mission to clean up the list of registered unrecognized political parties, deleting 284 since May for either being untraceable during a physical check or not responding to communications.</p>
<h4><strong>Why de-list political parties?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The news highlights the tale of a Bharatiya xyz Party.</li>
<li>Its registered address, the ground floor of a Delhi Development Authority flat, has been home to a family since they purchased the house in 2008.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>When is a party de-registered?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The EC’s recent order has highlighted that a party must contest an election within five years of its registration, and should continue to contest thereafter.</li>
<li>If the party does not contest elections continuously for six years, the party shall be taken off the list of registered parties.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Registering a Political Party</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The registration of all political parties is governed by the provisions of the <strong>Representation of the People Act, 1951.</strong></li>
<li>According to the Election Commission (EC), any party seeking registration has to submit an application to the Commission within a <strong>period of 30 days</strong>.</li>
<li>This is done as per guidelines prescribed by the EC in exercise of the powers conferred by Article <strong>324 of the Constitution and Section 29A of the RP Act, 1951</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Note</strong>: There is no procedure available for de-registration of dormant political parties.</p></blockquote>
<h4><strong>Process of registration</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The applicant is asked to publish a proposed party name in two national daily newspapers and two local daily newspapers, and provide two days for submitting objections, if any.</li>
<li>The notice for publication is also displayed on the website of the Election Commission.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why registering with the EC is important?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It is <strong><u>not mandatory to register</u></strong> with the Election Commission.</li>
<li>However, registering as a political party with the EC <strong><u>has its advantage</u></strong> in terms of intending to avail itself of the provisions of the RP Act, 1951.</li>
<li>The candidates set up by a political party registered with the EC will get <strong><u>preference in the matter of allotment of free symbols</u></strong> vis-à-vis purely independent candidates.</li>
<li>More importantly, these registered political parties, over course of time, <strong><u>can get expanded recognition</u></strong> as a ‘state party’ or a ‘national party’.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>How EC recognises a political party as a state or national party?</strong></h4>
<p><strong>For recognition as a <u>NATIONAL PARTY</u>, the conditions specified are:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>a 6% vote share in the last Assembly polls in each of any four states, as well as four seats in the last Lok Sabha polls; or</li>
<li>2% of all Lok Sabha seats in the last such election, with MPs elected from at least three states; or</li>
<li>recognition as a state party in at least four states.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>For recognition as a <u>STATE PARTY</u>, any one of five conditions needs to be satisfied:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>two seats plus a 6% vote share in the last Assembly election in that state; or</li>
<li>one seat plus a 6% vote share in the last Lok Sabha election from that state; or</li>
<li>3% of the total Assembly seats or 3 seats, whichever is more; or</li>
<li>one of every 25 Lok Sabha seats (or an equivalent fraction) from a state; or</li>
<li>an 8% state-wide vote share in either the last Lok Sabha or the last Assembly polls.</li>
</ol>
<h4><strong>Benefits for recognized parties</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>This is subject to the fulfilment of the conditions prescribed by the Commission in the Election Symbols (Reservation and Allotment) Order, 1968.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(a) Reserved Sybol</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>If a party is recognised as a ‘state party’, it is entitled for exclusive allotment of its reserved symbol to the candidates set up by it in the state in which it is so recognised.</li>
<li>If a party is recognised as a ‘national party’ it is entitled for exclusive allotment of its reserved symbol to the candidates set up by it throughout India.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(b) Proposer for nomination</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Recognised ‘state’ and ‘national’ parties need only one proposer for filing the nomination.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(c) Campaigning benefits</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>They are also entitled for two sets of electoral rolls free of cost and broadcast/telecast facilities over state-owned Akashvani/Doordarshan during the general elections.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/vacant-offices-unaware-office-bearers-curious-case-of-delisted-parties/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>AP approaches SC over Three Capitals Issue</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ap-three-capitals-isse/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>Read the attached story</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Three Capitals Issue in AP</p></div></div><p><img alt="capitals" class="alignnone wp-image-637688" height="247" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 431px) 100vw, 431px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ap-capital-300x172.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ap-capital-300x172.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/ap-capital.jpg 527w" width="431"/></p>
<p>After much discontent on the High Court (HC) verdict in the three capitals case, the Andhra Pradesh government has finally challenged it in the Supreme Court through a special leave petition (SLP).</p>
<h4><strong>AP’s move for three capitals</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>AP had introduced a ‘Three Capitals Act’ titled Andhra Pradesh Decentralisation and Inclusive Development of All Regions Act, 2020.</li>
<li>Thus, it was decided that:</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><strong>Amaravati</strong> was to be the Legislative capital</li>
<li><strong>Visakhapatnam</strong> the Executive capital and</li>
<li><strong>Kurnool</strong> the Judicial capital</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>However, the Andhra Pradesh High Court <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/andhra-pradesh-government-repealed-laws-on-3-capitals/">repealed this Act</a> citing that the legislature has no competence to enact any law for shifting the three organs of the capital.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Concerns raised by AP government</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>AP contended that the judgement was in <strong><u>violation of the basic structure</u></strong> of the Constitution as the HC cannot hold that the State does not have the powers to decide on its capital.</li>
<li>The judgement was <strong><u>against the doctrine of separation of powers</u></strong> as it sought to preempt the legislature from taking up the issue (of three capitals).</li>
<li>Further, it is argued that under the <strong><u>federal structure</u></strong> of the Constitution, every State has an inherent right to determine where it should carry out its capital functions from.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Reasons for AP’s consideration</strong></h4>
<p><strong>(1) Viable option of </strong><strong>Visakhapatnam</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Vizag always had been the biggest city, after Hyderabad, even in the combined State.</li>
<li>It has all the settings to become a good living space.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(2) Sri Krishna panel recommendations</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The advantages and qualities of Visakhapatnam to become the capital was elaborately deliberated by the Sri Krishna Committee to study the alternatives for a new capital for the State of Andhra Pradesh.</li>
<li>Coming to suggestion for the alternative capital, the Committee primarily took up three things for consideration — creation of single city or super city in greenfield location, expanding existing cities and distributed development.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>(3) Decentralisation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>This idea was elaborately described in the <strong><u>Sri Bagh pact</u></strong>.</li>
<li>The pact clearly defined decentralisation, for the benefit of all three main regions such as Coastal AP, Godavari and Krishna districts and Rayalaseema.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Major practical problems</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Continuum of work:</strong> The government argues that the Assembly meets only after gaps of several months, and government Ministers, officers, and staff can simply go to Amaravati when required.</li>
<li><strong>Logistics nightmare:</strong> coordinating between seats of legislature and executive in separate cities will be easier said than done.</li>
<li><strong>Time and costs of travel:</strong> The distances in Andhra Pradesh are not inconsiderable. Executive capital Visakhapatnam is 700 km from judicial capital Kurnool, and 400 km from legislative capital Amaravati.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Examples of multi-capital states in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Among Indian states, Maharashtra has two capitals– Mumbai and Nagpur (which holds the winter session of the state assembly).</li>
<li>Himachal Pradesh has capitals at Shimla and Dharamshala (winter).</li>
<li>The former state of Jammu &amp; Kashmir had Srinagar and Jammu (winter) as capitals where <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/what-is-durbar-move/">Darbar Move</a> is carried out.</li>
</ul>
<hr/>
<h4>Back2Basics: Special Leave Petition</h4>
<ul>
<li>SLP hold a prime place in the Indian judicial system.</li>
<li>It provides the aggrieved party a special permission to be heard in Apex court in appeal against any judgment or order of any Court/tribunal in the territory of India.</li>
<li>It has been provided as a “residual power” in the hands of Supreme Court of India to be exercised only in cases when any substantial question of law is involved, or gross injustice has been done.</li>
<li>Article 136 vests the Supreme Court of India with a special power to grant special leave, to appeal against any judgment or order or decree.</li>
<li>It is <strong><u>discretionary power</u></strong> vested in the Supreme Court of India and the court may in its discretion refuse to grant leave to appeal.</li>
<li>The aggrieved party cannot claim special leave to appeal under Article 136 as a right, but it is privilege vested in the Supreme Court to grant leave to appeal or not.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/ap-three-capitals-isse/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>It seems that inflation may hover around 7 percent</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/inflation-2/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>types of inflation</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>inflation overview</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="inflation" class="alignnone wp-image-637649" height="341" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 647px) 100vw, 647px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1-300x158.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1-300x158.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1-1024x538.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1-768x403.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/174708-wqudprofvf-1653207399-1.jpg 1200w" width="647"/> </strong><strong>Context </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>It seems that inflation may hover around 7 per cent despite RBI’s tightening of monetary policy in the months to come.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is a simple definition for inflation?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Inflation is an increase in the level of prices of the goods and services that households buy. It is measured as the rate of change of those prices. Typically, prices rise over time, but prices can also fall (a situation called deflation).</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Inflation Rate</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Inflation Rate is the percentage change in the price level from the previous period. If a normal basket of goods was priced at Rupee 100 last year and the same basket of goods now cost Rupee 120, then the rate of inflation this year is 20%.</li>
<li>Inflation Rate= {(Price in year 2 – Price in year 1)/ Price in year 1} *100</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="inflation" class="alignnone wp-image-637678" height="350" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 841px) 100vw, 841px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-1-300x125.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-1-300x125.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-1-768x319.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-1.jpg 842w" width="841"/>Types of Inflation</strong></h4>
<p><strong>Creeping Inflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Creeping or mild inflation is when prices rise 3% a year or less. This kind of mild inflation makes consumers expect that prices will keep going up. That boosts demand. Consumers buy now to beat higher future prices. That’s how mild inflation drives economic expansion.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Walking Inflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>This type of strong, or pernicious, inflation is between 3-10% a year. It is harmful to the economy because it heats up economic growth too fast. People start to buy more than they need, just to avoid tomorrow’s much higher prices. This drives demand even further so that suppliers can’t keep up. More important, neither can wages. As a result, common goods and services are priced out of the reach of most people.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Galloping Inflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>When inflation rises to 10% or more, it wreaks absolute havoc on the economy. Money loses value so fast that business and employee income can’t keep up with costs and prices. Foreign investors avoid the country, depriving it of needed capital. The economy becomes unstable, and government leaders lose credibility. Galloping inflation must be prevented at all costs.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Hyperinflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Hyperinflation is when prices skyrocket more than 50% a month. It is very rare. In fact, most examples of hyperinflation have occurred only when governments printed money to pay for wars. Examples of hyperinflation include <strong>Germany</strong>in the 1920s, <strong>Zimbabwe</strong> in the 2000s, and <strong>Venezuela</strong> in the 2010s. The last time America experienced hyperinflation was during its civil war.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Core Inflation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The core inflation rate measures rising prices in everything except food and energy. That’s because gas prices tend to escalate now and then. Higher gas costs increase the price of food and anything else that has large transportation costs.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Consumer Price Index</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>CPI is used to monitor changes in the cost of living over time. When the CPI rises, the average Indian family has to spend more on goods and services to maintain the same standard of living. The economic term used to define such a rising prices of goods and services is Inflation.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Whole sale Price Index</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>WPI is used to monitor the cost of goods and services bought by producer and firms rather than final consumers. The WPI inflation captures price changes at the factory/wholesale level.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>GDP Deflator</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Another important measure of calculating standard of living of people is GDP Deflator. GDP Deflator is the ratio of nominal GDP to real GDP. The nominal GDP is measured at the current prices whereas the real GDP is measured at the base year prices. Therefore, GDP Deflator reflects the current level of prices relative to prices in a base year. Example, In India the base year of calculating deflator is 2011-12.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="inflation" class="alignnone wp-image-637631" height="297" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 100vw, 527px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_Rate_0_1200x768-300x169.jpeg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_Rate_0_1200x768-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_Rate_0_1200x768-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Inflation_Rate_0_1200x768.jpeg 770w" width="527"/>Factors fuelling inflation in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Falling rupee:</strong> Inflation is here to stay because it has much to do with the decline in value of the rupee that has fallen to its lowest, which makes imports of oil and gas more expensive.</li>
<li><strong>Ukraine crisis:</strong> The war in Ukraine has the same effect and pushes the price of some food items upward.</li>
<li><strong>Poor inflation management:</strong> With inflation, as measured by the consumer price index, in August going back to 7 per cent, and the wholesale price index coming in at 12.4 per cent, one thing is clear India is not out of the woods on inflation management.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Rising inflation have these implications</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Impact on the poor:</strong> This upsurge of inflation is affecting the poor more because some of the commodities whose prices are increasing the most represent a larger fraction of the budget of the most vulnerable sections of society.</li>
<li><strong>Rising inequality:</strong> As a result, inequalities which were already on the rise are increasing further. Recently, the State of Inequality in India report showed that an Indian making Rs 3 lakh a year belonged to the top 10 per cent of the country’s wage earners.<strong> </strong></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li><strong>Inequality in healthcare: </strong>India’s spending on healthcare is among the lowest in the world. Decent level of healthcare is available only to the ones who can afford it because of increasing out-of-pocket expenditure the payment made directly by individuals for the health service, not covered under any financial protection scheme. Overall, these out-of-pocket expenses on healthcare are 60 per cent of the total expenditure on public health in India, which is one of the highest in the world.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h4><strong><img alt="inflation" class="alignnone wp-image-637701" height="358" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 643px) 100vw, 643px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200.jpg 1200w" width="643"/>Need for bold steps on three fronts to tackle inflation</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Unless bold and innovative steps are taken at least on three fronts, GDP growth and inflation both are likely to be in the range of 6.5 to 7.5 per cent in 2022-23.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>1] Tightening of loose<a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/monetary-economics-barter-system-definition-function-and-evolution-of-money/"> monetary policy:</a></strong> The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) is mandated to keep inflation at 4 per cent, plus-minus 2 per cent.</p>
<ul>
<li>The RBI has already started the process of tightening monetary policy by raising the repo rate, albeit a bit late.</li>
<li>It is expected that by the end of 2022-3, the repo rate will be at least 5.5 per cent, if not more.</li>
<li>It will still stay below the likely inflation rate and therefore depositors will still lose the real value of their money in banks with negative real interest rates.</li>
<li>That only reflects an inbuilt bias in the system — in favour of entrepreneurs in the name of growth and against depositors, which ultimately results in increasing inequality in the system.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2] Prudent fiscal policy:</strong> Fiscal policy has been running loose in the wake of Covid-19 that saw the fiscal deficit of the Union government soar to more than 9 per cent in 2020-21 and 6.7 per cent in 2021-22, but now needs to be tightened.</p>
<ul>
<li>Government needs to reduce its fiscal deficit to less than 5 per cent, never mind the FRMB Act’s advice to bring it to 3 per cent of GDP.</li>
<li>However, it is difficult to achieve when enhanced food and fertiliser subsidies, and cuts in duties of petrol and diesel will cost the government at least Rs 3 trillion more than what was provisioned in the budget.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>3] Rational trade policy:</strong> Export restrictions/bans go beyond agri-commodities, even to iron ore and steel, etc. in the name of taming inflation.</p>
<ul>
<li>But abrupt export bans are poor trade policy and reflect only the panic-stricken face of the government.</li>
<li>A more mature approach to filter exports would be through a gradual process of minimum export prices and transparent export duties for short periods of time, rather than abrupt bans, if at all these are desperately needed to favour consumers.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Though the government is opting for market-based economics, currently, India needs a mixed solution that comprises price stability via government channels and subsidies.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q.</strong><strong>What are the fuelling factors for inflation? Discuss what steps should be taken to tackle inflation.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://bit.ly/cd_regular" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><strong>UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</strong></a></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/inflation-2/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Geopolitics follows the geoeconomics and not vice-versa</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/geoeconomics/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>international relations</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="geoeconomics" class="alignnone wp-image-637721" height="347" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 699px) 100vw, 699px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-300x149.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-300x149.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-1024x508.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-768x381.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1-1200x595.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1-800x445-1.jpg 1269w" width="699"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Over the recent years India’s manoeuvres in indo-pacific have highlighted the India’s geopolitical and ambitions. Pandemic and Chinese incursion in Ladakh forced India to move fast to achieve its geopolitical ends. However missing link in India’s endeavour is geoeconomics.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is mean by geopolitics and geo-economics?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Geopolitics:</strong> is defined as the struggle over the control of geographical entities with an international and global dimension, and the use of such geographical entities for political advantage.</li>
<li><strong>Geo-economics:</strong> is defined as the combination of economic and geographic factors relating to international trade and a governmental policy guided by geoeconomics.</li>
<li>Geopolitics and geoeconomics are sometimes used interchangeably.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is the strategy to pursue geopolitical goals in indo-pacific?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>India has managed to emerge as a major pivot of the global Indo-Paciﬁc grand strategic imagination.</li>
<li>Avoided the temptations to militarise/securitise the Quad (Australia, Japan, India and the United States).</li>
<li>Which has ensured that the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN) states do not feel uneasy by the ever-increasing balance of power articulations in the Indo-Pacific</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="geoeconomics" class="alignnone wp-image-637722" height="323" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Geoeconomics-in-a-Globalized-World-300x166.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Geoeconomics-in-a-Globalized-World-300x166.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Geoeconomics-in-a-Globalized-World.jpg 525w" width="584"/>What is the missing link in India’s geopolitical strategy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The missing link in geoeconomics is India’s decision to take to the Indo-Paciﬁc and Quad in a big way.</li>
<li>While unwilling to join two of the region’s key multilateral trading agreements goes to show that geoeconomics and geopolitics are imagined and pursued parallelly in New Delhi, not as complimenting each other.</li>
<li>The most recent example is India’s refusal to join the trade pillar of the Indo-Paciﬁc Economic Framework (IPEF) while deciding to join the three other pillars of the IPEF supply chains, tax and anti-corruption, and clean energy.</li>
</ul>
<p>India also withdrew from <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/back-in-news-india-asean-relations/">ASEAN</a> led <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/regional-comprehensive-economic-partnership-rcep/">RCEP.</a></p>
<h4><strong>Is the lack of geoeconomic bad for foreign policy?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The absence of the world’s fifth largest economy from various regional trading platforms will invariably boost China’s geo-economic hegemony in Asia.</li>
<li>Staying out of IPEF is a bad idea is because for India, it would be hard to integrate itself into the regional and global supply chains without being a part of important regional multilateral trading agreements.</li>
<li>We have no option but to address some of the deeper challenges plaguing the investment and business environment in India.</li>
<li>If India is indeed serious about its maritime grand strategy, which cannot be solely military in nature, it needs to get the states in the region to create economic stakes in India (something China has done cleverly and consistently) and vice-versa.</li>
<li>Another impact of India’s hesitation about joining regional multilateral trading arrangements is its potential regional economic isolation. The less India engages with the region economically, and the more China does so, and given the Sino-Indian rivalry, India might risk getting economically isolated in the broader region.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="Geo-economics: is defined as the combination of economic and geographic factors relating to international trade and a governmental policy guided by geoeconomics. Geopolitics and geoeconomics are sometimes used interchangeably." class="alignnone wp-image-637723" height="397" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 634px) 100vw, 634px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-300x188.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-300x188.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-1024x640.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-768x480.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-1536x960.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-2048x1280.jpg 2048w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-1200x750.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/nord-stream-ukraine-russia-germany-pj78t0bbf3ufk4uv8iaf36ienfqv3spmrm61lo0as8-1980x1238.jpg 1980w" width="634"/>What can be done?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>New Delhi should: </strong>rethink its geoeconomic choices if it is serious about enhancing its geopolitical inﬂuence in the region. Given that India has not closed the door on the trade pillar of the IPEF, we have an opportunity to rethink our position.</li>
<li><strong>India should: </strong>also rethink its decision not to join the RECP and seek to join the Comprehensive and Progressive Agreement for Trans-Paciﬁc Partnership (CPTPP) from which the U.S. walked out and China is seeking to join.</li>
<li><strong>India should: </strong>also proactively lobby to become a part of the Minerals Security Partnership, the U.S.-led 11-member grouping to secure supply chains of critical minerals.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Conclusion</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>In the words of external affairs minister Dr. Jaishankar,” geopolitics follows the geoeconomics and not vice-versa”. Geoeconomics is inclusive of geoeconomics. India should integrate itself in multilateral trading platforms and leverage its big market to bargain the best deal for itself.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Indias pursuit of geopolitics is futile without inclusion of geoeconomics. Comment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/geoeconomics/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item><item><title>Without social justice women empowerment is a futile exercise. here is why?</title><link>https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-empowerment/</link><description><![CDATA[<div class="post-inner thin">
<div class="entry-content">
<div class="n4s"><div class="heading">Note4Students</div><div class="content"><p>From UPSC perspective, the following things are important : </p><p><strong>Prelims level : </strong>NA</p><p><strong>Mains level : </strong>Women empowerment</p></div></div><h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637728" height="341" sizes="(max-width: 585px) 100vw, 585px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609-300x175.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609-300x175.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609-768x447.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/2022_3largeimg_2007581609.jpg 1000w" width="585"/>Context</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>Despite notable progress in closing the gender pay gap over time in India, the gap remains high by international standards. Asymmetries still abound in the country’s labor market stopping women empowerment .</li>
<li>Time to reassess the progress made in to close the Gender pay gap.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Background</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The third International Equal Pay Day is observed globally on September 18, 2022.</li>
<li>It is a United Nations-recognized event to highlight the issue of gender pay gap.</li>
<li>International Labor Organization’s “Global Wage Report 2020–21” which suggests the crisis inflicted massive downward pressure on wages and disproportionately affected women’s total wages compared to</li>
<li>This greater wage reduction for women means that the pre-existing gender pay gap has widened.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637732" height="325" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 584px) 100vw, 584px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/PTI-retail-market-food-inflation-1200.jpg 1200w" width="584"/>Covid-19 Impact</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While it is difficult to tell exactly what the economic damage from the global covid-19 pandemic has been, it is clear that its impact has been uneven, with women being among the worst affected in terms of their income security.</li>
<li>Many women reverted to full-time care of children and the elderly during the pandemic, foregoing their livelihoods to do so.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>What is gender pay gap?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The gender pay gap or gender wage gap measures the difference between the average earnings of women and men in the workforce.</li>
<li>In simple term it is a measure of what women are paid relative to men.</li>
<li>Women are generally found to be paid less than men.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Why is the gender pay gap?</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Education: </strong>low investment o girl education<strong>, </strong>Girl children are kept out of schools, or made drop out of school at early age, girl is considered as burden on family in many societies.</li>
<li><strong>workforce </strong>: even if they are educated they are not allowed to work by their families, very limited or no decision making power, lack of women friendly work environment, discriminatory practices at workplaces.</li>
<li><strong>Household:</strong> early marriage , responsibilities of the household at early age , spending more times on domestic chores,</li>
<li><strong>Healthcare: </strong>malnutrition, anemia, Maternity, child care, looking after health of the elderly family members etc.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p>These are some of the reasons which affect education, skills, experience and the career prospectus of women as compared to men and contribute to widen the gender wage gap.</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637730" height="297" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 100vw, 527px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-768x432.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India-1200x675.jpg 1200w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Gender-Inequality-in-India.jpg 1919w" width="527"/>Discrimination as factor</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>A part of gender pay gap attributed to education, skills or experience, a large part of the gender pay gap can still purely because of discrimination based on one’s gender or sex.</li>
<li>Gender-based discriminatory practices include: lower wages paid to women for work of equal value; undervaluation of women’s work in highly feminized occupations and enterprises, and motherhood pay gap lower wages for mothers compared to non-mother.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637734" height="466" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 837px) 100vw, 837px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-300x167.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-300x167.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-1024x569.jpg 1024w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1-768x427.jpg 768w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/inflation-cpi-express-archieve-1200-1.jpg 1200w" width="837"/>Status in India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>The gender pay gap in India is among the widest in the world.</li>
<li>Indian women earned, on an average, 48% less compared to their male counterparts in 1993-94</li>
<li>According to labor force survey data of the National Sample Survey Office (NSSO) gap declined to 28% in 2018-19.</li>
<li>Periodic Labor Force Survey (PLFS) 2020-21 show an increase in the gap by 7% between 2018-19 and 2020-21.</li>
<li>Recently, the World Economic Forum (WEF) ranked India at 135 out of 146 countries in its Global Gender Gap (GGG) Index for 2022.</li>
<li>According to the estimates of the World Inequality Report 2022, in India, men earn 82 per cent of the labor income whereas women earn 18 per cent of it.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong><img alt="women empowerment" class="alignnone wp-image-637731" height="392" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 696px) 100vw, 696px" src="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8477553337_67c076bed2_o-300x169.jpg" srcset="https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8477553337_67c076bed2_o-300x169.jpg 300w, https://d18x2uyjeekruj.cloudfront.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/8477553337_67c076bed2_o.jpg 639w" width="696"/>Steps taken by India</strong></h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Minimum Wages Act in 1948</strong>: It is an act of parliament<strong>, </strong>aimed at statutory fixation of minimum wages that must be paid to skilled and unskilled labours. Payment of wages below the minimum wage rate amounts to forced labour.</li>
<li><strong>Equal Remuneration Act in 1976: </strong>This act of parliament provides for the payment of equal remuneration to men and women workers for the prevention of discrimination. It helps in bridging the gap between unequal remuneration faced by the women of our country.</li>
<li><strong>Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA) 2005:</strong> MGNREGA contributed to the rapid rise in overall rural and agricultural wages in the country. It benefited rural women workers and helped reduce the gender pay gap, both directly and indirectly. Directly, by raising the pay levels of women workers and indirectly to women involved in agricultural occupations through higher earnings.</li>
<li><strong>The Maternity Benefit (Amendment) Act 2017</strong>: has increased the duration of paid maternity leave available for women employees to 26 weeks from 12 weeks for all women working in establishments employing 10 or more workers. This is expected to reduce the motherhood pay gap among mothers in the median and high end wage earners working in the formal economy also it will help in women empowerment.</li>
<li><strong>Skill India Mission</strong>: To equip women with market-relevant skills to bridge the learning to-livelihood gap and the gender pay gap.</li>
<li>In 2019, India carried out comprehensive reforms in both the legislation and enacted the Code on Wages.</li>
</ul>
<h4><strong>Way ahead </strong></h4>
<ul>
<li>While the gender pay gap is slowly narrowing, acceleration and bold actions to prevent the widening of gender pay gap is the need of the hour.</li>
<li>Equal pay for work of equal value is necessary to close the gender pay gap.</li>
<li>Closing the gender pay gap is key to achieving <a href="https://www.civilsdaily.com/story/women-empowerment-issues-jobsreservation-education/">social justice for working women</a>, as well as economic growth for the nation as a whole</li>
<li>Without social justice women empowerment is a futile exercise.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<blockquote><p><strong>Mains Question </strong></p>
<p><strong>Q. Define gender equality .Equal pay for equal work is necessary to bridge the gender pay gap India .Comment.</strong></p></blockquote>
<p><strong><a href="https://civilsdaily3.freshworks.com/crm/sales/web_forms/3d94588692757bc7fa91a20e163e1993124789e67302006fe3783f0984276181/form.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">UPSC 2023 countdown has begun! Get your personal guidance plan now! (Click here)</a></strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
</div><!-- .entry-content -->
</div>]]></description><guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.civilsdaily.com/news/women-empowerment/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0553</pubDate></item></channel></rss>